<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="dpennington.327.2" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.0 eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><shortName>NIES99_A2a_TMAX_2080.dif</shortName><title>IPCC Climate Change Data: NIES99 A2a Model: 2080 Maximum Temperature</title><creator id="1086641977078" scope="document"><organizationName>Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC)</organizationName><onlineUrl>http://www.ipcc.ch/index.html</onlineUrl></creator><associatedParty id="1086642101765" scope="document"><organizationName>SEEK</organizationName><onlineUrl>http://seek.ecoinformatics.org/</onlineUrl><role>Content Provider</role></associatedParty><abstract><para>The model used here is a coupled ocean-atmosphere model that
        consists of the CCSR/NIES atmospheric GCM, the CCSR ocean GCM, a
        thermodynamic sea-ice model, and a river routing model
        (Abe-Ouchi et al., 1996). The spatial resolution is T21 spectral
        truncation (roughly 5.6 degrees  latitude/longitude) and 20
        vertical levels for the atmospheric part, and roughly 2.8
        degrees  horizontal grid and 17 vertical levels for the oceanic
        part. Flux adjustment for atmosphere-ocean heat and water
        exchange is applied to prevent a drift of the modelled climate.
        The atmospheric model adopts a radiation scheme based on the
        k-distribution, two-stream discrete ordinate method (DOM)
        (Nakajima and Tanaka, 1986). This scheme can deal with
        absorption, emission and scattering by gases, clouds and aerosol
        particles in a consistent manner. In the calculation of sulphate
        aerosol optical properties, the volumetric mode radius of the
        sulphate particle in dry environment is assumed to be 0.2
        micron. The hygroscopic growth of the sulphate is considered by
        an empirical fit of d'Almeida et al. (1991). The vertical
        distribution of the sulphate aerosol is assumed to be constant
        in the lowest 2 km of the atmosphere. The concentrations of
        greenhouse gases are represented by equivalent-CO2.  Three
        integrations are made for 200 model years (1890-2090). In the
        control experiment (CTL), the globally uniform concentration of
        greenhouse gases is kept constant at 345 ppmv CO2-equivalent and
        the concentration of sulphate is set to zero. In the experiment
        GG, the concentration of greenhouse gases is gradually
        increased, while that of sulphate is set to zero. In the
        experiments GS, the increase in anthropogenic sulphate as well
        as that in greenhouse gases is given and the aerosol scattering
        (the direct effect of aerosol) is explicitly represented in the
        way described above. The indirect effect of aerosol is not
        included in any experiment.  The scenario of atmospheric
        concentrations of greenhouse gases and sulphate aerosols is
        given in accordance with Mitchell and Johns (1997). The increase
        in greenhouse gases is based on the historical record from 1890
        to 1990 and is increased by 1 percent / yr (compound) after
        1990. For sulphate aerosols, geographical distributions of
        sulphate loading for 1986 and 2050, which are estimated by a
        sulphur cycle model (Langer and Rodhe, 1991), are used as basic
        patterns. Based on global and annual mean sulphur emission
        rates, the 1986 pattern is scaled for years before 1990; the
        2050 pattern is scaled for years after 2050; and the pattern is
        interpolated from the two basic ones for intermediate years to
        give the time series of the distribution. The sulphur emission
        rate in the future is based on the IPCC IS92a scenario. The
        sulphate concentration is offset in our run so that it starts
        from zero at 1890. The seasonal variation of sulphate
        concentration is ignored.  Discussion on the results of the
        experiments will be found in Emori et al. (1999). Climate
        sensitivity of the CCSR/NIES model derived by equilibrium runs
        is estimated to be 3.5 degrees Celsius. Global-Mean Temperature,
        Precipitation and CO2 Changes (w.r.t. 1961-90) for the CCSR/NIES model.</para><para>For the A2 emissions scenario the main emphasis is on a
        strengthening of regional and local culture, with a "return
        to family values" in many regions. The A2 world
        "consolidates" into a series of roughly continental
        economic regions, emphasizing local cultural roots. In some
        regions, increased religious participation leads many to reject
        a materialist path and to focus attention on contributing to the
        local community. Elsewhere, the trend is towards increased
        investment in education and science and growth in economic
        productivity. Social and political structures diversify, with
        some regions moving towards stronger welfare systems and reduced
        income inequality, while others move towards "lean"
        government. Environmental concerns are relatively weak, although
        some attention is paid to bringing local pollution under control
        and maintaining local environmental amenities.  The A2 world
        sees more international tensions and less cooperation than in A1
        or B1. People, ideas and capital are less mobile so that
        technology diffuses slowly. International disparities in
        productivity, and hence income per capita, are maintained or
        increased. With the emphasis on family and community life,
        fertility rates decline only slowly, although they vary among
        regions. Hence, this scenario family has high population growth
        (to 15 billion by 2100) with comparatively low incomes per
        capita relative to the A1 and B1 worlds, at US$7,200 in 2050 and
        US$16,000 in 2100.  Technological change is rapid in some
        regions and slow in others as industry adjusts to local resource
        endowments, culture, and education levels. Regions with abundant
        energy and mineral resources evolve more resource intensive
        economies, while those poor in resources place very high
        priority on minimizing import dependence through technological
        innovation to improve resource efficiency and make use of
        substitute inputs. The fuel mix in different regions is
        determined primarily by resource availability. And divisions
        among regions persist in terms of their mix of technologies,
        with high-income but resource-poor regions shifting toward
        advanced post fossil technologies (renewables in regions of
        large land availability, nuclear in densely populated, resource
        poor regions) and low-income resource-rich regions generally
        relying on older fossil technologies.  With substantial food
        requirements, agricultural productivity is one of the main focus
        areas for innovation and RD efforts in this future. Initially
        high levels of soil erosion and water pollution are eventually
        eased through the local development of more sustainable
        high-yield agriculture.  Although attention is given to
        potential local and regional environmental damage, it is not
        uniform across regions. For example, sulfur and particulate
        emissions are reduced in Asia due to impacts on human health and
        agricultural production but increase in Africa as a result of
        the intensified exploitation of coal and other mineral
        resources. The A2 world sees high energy and carbon intensity,
        and correspondingly high GHG emissions. Its CO2 emissions are
        the highest of all four scenario families.</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>climate</keyword><keyword>global climate change</keyword><keyword>temperature</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><para>1. The IPCC Data Distribution Centre permits the research
        results from seven climate modelling centres (Hadley Centre for
        Climate Prediction and Research, Deutsches Klimarechenzentrum,
        Canadian Centre for Climate Modelling and Analysis, Geophysical
        Fluids Dynamics Laboratory, the Commonwealth and Scientific
        Industrial Research Organisation, the National centre for
        Atmospheric Research and the Centre for Climate System Research)
        to be used freely for the purposes of bona fide research. (Bona
        fide research is deemed to be research which generates results
        that are freely and universally accessible to any interested
        party, i.e., if people use DDC data they must agree to publish
        results openly or respond willingly to requests from others for
        copies of the results.)  2. The climate modelling centres'
        research results should not be used for commercial exploitation,
        business use, resale or transfer to any third party.  3. No
        warranty is given as to the suitability of the climate modelling
        centres' research results for particular purposes.  4. No
        liability is accepted by the IPCC Data Distribution Centre
        and/or the climate modelling centres for any errors or omissions
        in the climate modelling centres' research results, associated
        information and/or documentation.  5. Please acknowledge the use
        of the corresponding climate modelling centres' research results
        in any publication.  6. The intellectual property rights on the
        climate modelling centres' research results remains the property
        of each of the climate modelling centres.  7. By registering
        with the DDC you agree to abide by this Data Statement.</para></intellectualRights><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Worldwide</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-180.0</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>180.0</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>90.0</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>-90.0</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2080-01-01</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2080-12-31</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><contact id="1086642088609" scope="document"><organizationName>IPCC</organizationName></contact><methods><methodStep><description><para>Format (ASCII)  There is a six line header for each
            month, the codes for the header fields in italics (e.g.
            Model Name) are given below. The following is an example of
            the structure of the scenario data files:  IPCC Data
            Distribution Centre Results from model ModelName Date Grid
            is xxx*yyy    Month is Jan   Mean change values for yyyy -
            yyyy with respect to 1960 - 1990 Experiment name Code
            Variable-Name-(Units) DataItems-----Format is 10f8.2 Missing
            value is 9999.99  NOTE: For the period 1961-1990 the data
            are the actual values, for the 2010-2039, 2040-2069 and
            2070-2099 the data are the changes with respect to the
            1961-1990 period.Forcing Details - GG = Greenhouse Gas: GS =
            Greenhouse Gas and Sulphate Aerosols; A = 1% per annum
            (IS92a); D= 0.5% per annum (IS92d); 1, 2, 3 or 4 represents
            the ensemble member or X = Ensemble mean.Experiment Code
            -Refers to the first six characters of the file name (i.e.,
            AACCD1)Data Items - The product of xxx*yyy (e.g. 7008)</para></description></methodStep></methods><access authSystem="knb" order="denyFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><spatialRaster scope="document"><entityName>NIES99_A2a_TMAX_2080.dif</entityName><physical scope="document"><objectName>NIES99_A2a_TMAX_2080.dif</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>6</numHeaderLines><numPhysicalLinesPerRecord>1</numPhysicalLinesPerRecord><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>space</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">ecogrid://knb/IPCC.20080211731093.1</url></online></distribution></physical><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>TMAX</attributeName><attributeLabel>TemperatureMax</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Maximum Temperature (C)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>integer</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">1000</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList><spatialReference scope="document"><horizCoordSysName>GCS_WGS_1984</horizCoordSysName></spatialReference><horizontalAccuracy><accuracyReport>Unknown</accuracyReport></horizontalAccuracy><verticalAccuracy><accuracyReport>Unknown</accuracyReport></verticalAccuracy><cellSizeXDirection>0.5</cellSizeXDirection><cellSizeYDirection>0.5</cellSizeYDirection><numberOfBands>1</numberOfBands><rasterOrigin>Upper Left</rasterOrigin><rows>48</rows><columns>96</columns><verticals>12</verticals><cellGeometry>pixel</cellGeometry></spatialRaster></dataset></ns0:eml>