<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="dpennington.193.2" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.0 eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><shortName>HADCM3_A1F_TMIN_2050.dif</shortName><title>IPCC Climate Change Data: HADCM3 A1F Model: 2050 Minimum Temperature</title><creator id="1086641977078" scope="document"><organizationName>Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC)</organizationName><onlineUrl>http://www.ipcc.ch/index.html</onlineUrl></creator><associatedParty id="1086642101765" scope="document"><organizationName>SEEK</organizationName><onlineUrl>http://seek.ecoinformatics.org/</onlineUrl><role>Content Provider</role></associatedParty><abstract><para>The recent experiments performed at the Hadley Centre have
        used the new Unified Model (Cullen, 1993). These experiments
        represent a large step forward in the way climate change is
        modelled by GCMs and raises new possibilities for scenario
        construction. This experiment has overcome some of the major
        difficulties that were associated with the previous generations
        of equilibrium (circa IPCC 1990) and cold-start transient (circa
        IPCC 1992) climate change experiments.  HadCM2 has a spatial
        resolution of 2.5 degrees x 3.75 degrees (latitude by longitude)
        and the representation produces a grid box resolution of 96 x 73
        grid cells. This produces a surface spatial resolution of about
        417km x 278 km reducing to 295 x 278km at 45 degrees North and
        South (comparable to a spectral resolution of T42).  The
        equilibrium climate sensitivity (DT2x) of HadCM2, that is the
        global-mean temperature response to a doubling of effective CO2
        concentration, is approximately 2.5 degrees C, although, this
        quantity varies with the time-scale considered. This is somewhat
        lower than most other GCMs (IPCC, 1992). In order to undertake a
        'warm-start' experiment it is necessary to perturb the model
        with a forcing from an early historical era, when the radiative
        forcing was relatively small compared to the present. The Hadley
        Centre started their experiments performed with HadCM2 with
        forcing from the middle industrial era, about 1860 Mitchell et
        al., 1995 and Johns et al., 1995.  The greenhouse gas only
        integrations, HadCM2GG, used the combined forcing of all the
        greenhouse gases as an equivalent CO2 concentration. A further
        series of integrations, HadCM2GS, used the combined equivalent
        CO2 concentration plus the negative forcing from sulphate
        aerosols. The HadCM2GG integrations simulated the change in
        forcing of the climate system by greenhouse gases since the
        early industrial period (taken by HadCM2 to be 1860). The
        addition of the negative forcing effects of sulphate aerosols
        represents the direct radiative forcing due to anthropogenic
        sulphate aerosols by means of an increase in clear-sky surface
        albedo proportional to the local sulphate loading (refer to
        Mitchell et al., 1995 for details of this method). The indirect
        effects of aerosols were not simulated.  The modelled control
        climate shows a negligible long term trend in surface air
        temperature over the first 400 years. The trend is about +0.04
        degrees C per century, which is comparable to other such
        experiments.  HadCM2CON represents an improvement over previous
        generations of GCMs that have been used at the Hadley Centre
        (Johns et al., 1995 and Airey et al., 1995).  The experiments
        performed have simulated the observed climate system using
        estimated forcing perturbations since 1860. Johns et al., (1995)
        and Mitchell et al., (1995) have established that HadCM2's
        sensitivity is consistent with the real climate system. The
        agreement between the observed global-mean temperature record
        and that produced in these experiments is better for HadCM2GS
        than for HadCM2GG. This implies that HadCM2Gs has captured the
        observed signal of global-mean temperature changes better than
        HadCM2GG for the recent 100-year record.  The climate
        sensitivity of HadCM2 is about 2.5 degrees C</para><para>From the IPCC website:  The A1 Family storyline is a case of
        rapid and successful economic development, in which regional
        averages of income per capita converge - current distinctions
        between poor and rich countries eventually dissolve. In this
        scenario family, demographic and economic trends are closely
        linked, as affluence is correlated with long life and small
        families (low mortality and low fertility). Global population
        grows to some nine billion by 2050 and declines to about seven
        billion by 2100. Average age increases, with the needs of
        retired people met mainly through their accumulated savings in
        private pension systems.  The global economy expands at an
        average annual rate of about three percent to 2100. This is
        approximately the same as average global growth since 1850,
        although the conditions that lead to a global economic in
        productivity and per capita incomes are unparalleled in history.
        Income per capita reaches about US$21,000 by 2050. While the
        high average level of income per capita contributes to a great
        improvement in the overall health and social conditions of the
        majority of people, this world is not without its problems. In
        particular, many communities could face some of the problems of
        social exclusion encountered by the wealthiest countries in the
        20th century and in many places income growth could come with
        increased pressure on the global commons.  Energy and mineral
        resources are abundant in this scenario family because of rapid
        technical progress, which both reduce the resources need to
        produce a given level of output and increases the economically
        recoverable reserves. Final energy intensity (energy use per
        unit of GDP) decreases at an average annual rate of 1.3 percent.
        With the rapid increase in income, dietary patterns shift
        initially significantly towards increased consumption of meat
        and dairy products, but may decrease subsequently with
        increasing emphasis on health of an aging society. High incomes
        also translate into high car ownership, sprawling
        suburbanization and dense transport networks, nationally and
        internationally. Land prices increase faster than income per
        capita. These factors along with high wages result in a
        considerable intensification of agriculture.  Three scenario
        groups are considered in A1 scenario family reflecting the
        uncertainty in development of energy sources and conversion
        technologies in this rapidly changing world.  Near-term
        investment decisions may introduce long-term irreversibilities
        into the market, with lock-in to one technological configuration
        or another. The A1B scenario group is based on a balanced mix of
        energy sources and has an intermediate level of CO2 emissions,
        but depending on the energy sources developed, emissions in the
        variants cover a very wide range. In the fossil-fuel intensive
        scenario group A1FI, emissions approach those of the A2
        scenarios; conversely in scenario group A1T with low labor
        productivity or of rapid progress in "post-fossil"
        energy technologies, emissions are intermediate between those of
        B1 and B2.  These scenario variants have been introduced into
        the A1 storyline because of its "high growth with high
        tech" nature, where differences in alternative technology
        developments translate into large differences in future GHG
        emission levels Ecological resilience is assumed to be high in
        this storyline. Environmental amenities are viewed in a
        utilitarian way, based on their influence on the formal economy.
        The concept of environmental quality might change in thisstoryline from"conservation" of nature to active
        "management" - and marketing - of natural and
        environmental services.  Data are available for the following
        periods:  1961-1990, 2010-2039; 2040-2069; and 2090-2099 Mean
        monthly and change fields.</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>climate</keyword><keyword>global climate change</keyword><keyword>temperature</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><para>1. The IPCC Data Distribution Centre permits the research
        results from seven climate modelling centres (Hadley Centre for
        Climate Prediction and Research, Deutsches Klimarechenzentrum,
        Canadian Centre for Climate Modelling and Analysis, Geophysical
        Fluids Dynamics Laboratory, the Commonwealth and Scientific
        Industrial Research Organisation, the National centre for
        Atmospheric Research and the Centre for Climate System Research)
        to be used freely for the purposes of bona fide research. (Bona
        fide research is deemed to be research which generates results
        that are freely and universally accessible to any interested
        party, i.e., if people use DDC data they must agree to publish
        results openly or respond willingly to requests from others for
        copies of the results.)  2. The climate modelling centres'
        research results should not be used for commercial exploitation,
        business use, resale or transfer to any third party.  3. No
        warranty is given as to the suitability of the climate modelling
        centres' research results for particular purposes.  4. No
        liability is accepted by the IPCC Data Distribution Centre
        and/or the climate modelling centres for any errors or omissions
        in the climate modelling centres' research results, associated
        information and/or documentation.  5. Please acknowledge the use
        of the corresponding climate modelling centres' research results
        in any publication.  6. The intellectual property rights on the
        climate modelling centres' research results remains the property
        of each of the climate modelling centres.  7. By registering
        with the DDC you agree to abide by this Data Statement.</para></intellectualRights><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Worldwide</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-180.0</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>180.0</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>90.0</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>-90.0</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2050-01-01</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2050-12-31</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><contact id="1086642088609" scope="document"><organizationName>IPCC</organizationName></contact><methods><methodStep><description><para>Format (ASCII)  There is a six line header for each
            month, the codes for the header fields in italics (e.g.
            Model Name) are given below. The following is an example of
            the structure of the scenario data files:  IPCC Data
            Distribution Centre Results from model ModelName Date Grid
            is xxx*yyy    Month is Jan   Mean change values for yyyy -
            yyyy with respect to 1960 - 1990 Experiment name Code
            Variable-Name-(Units) DataItems-----Format is 10f8.2 Missing
            value is 9999.99  NOTE: For the period 1961-1990 the data
            are the actual values, for the 2010-2039, 2040-2069 and
            2070-2099 the data are the changes with respect to the
            1961-1990 period.Forcing Details - GG = Greenhouse Gas: GS =
            Greenhouse Gas and Sulphate Aerosols; A = 1% per annum
            (IS92a); D= 0.5% per annum (IS92d); 1, 2, 3 or 4 represents
            the ensemble member or X = Ensemble mean.Experiment Code
            -Refers to the first six characters of the file name (i.e.,
            AACCD1)Data Items - The product of xxx*yyy (e.g. 7008)</para></description></methodStep></methods><access authSystem="knb" order="denyFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><spatialRaster scope="document"><entityName>HADCM3_A1F_TMIN_2050.dif</entityName><physical scope="document"><objectName>HADCM3_A1F_TMIN_2050.dif</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>6</numHeaderLines><numPhysicalLinesPerRecord>1</numPhysicalLinesPerRecord><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>space</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">ecogrid://knb/IPCC.200802106503089.1</url></online></distribution></physical><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>TMIN</attributeName><attributeLabel>TemperatureMin</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Minimum Temperature (C)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>integer</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">1000</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList><spatialReference scope="document"><horizCoordSysName>GCS_WGS_1984</horizCoordSysName></spatialReference><horizontalAccuracy><accuracyReport>Unknown</accuracyReport></horizontalAccuracy><verticalAccuracy><accuracyReport>Unknown</accuracyReport></verticalAccuracy><cellSizeXDirection>0.5</cellSizeXDirection><cellSizeYDirection>0.5</cellSizeYDirection><numberOfBands>1</numberOfBands><rasterOrigin>Upper Left</rasterOrigin><rows>48</rows><columns>96</columns><verticals>12</verticals><cellGeometry>pixel</cellGeometry></spatialRaster></dataset></ns0:eml>