<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="dpennington.213.2" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.0 eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><shortName>HADCM3_A2a_WIND_2020.dif</shortName><title>IPCC Climate Change Data: HADCM3 A2a Model: 2020 Wind Speed</title><creator id="1086641977078" scope="document"><organizationName>Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC)</organizationName><onlineUrl>http://www.ipcc.ch/index.html</onlineUrl></creator><associatedParty id="1086642101765" scope="document"><organizationName>SEEK</organizationName><onlineUrl>http://seek.ecoinformatics.org/</onlineUrl><role>Content Provider</role></associatedParty><abstract><para>The recent experiments performed at the Hadley Centre have
        used the new Unified Model (Cullen, 1993). These experiments
        represent a large step forward in the way climate change is
        modelled by GCMs and raises new possibilities for scenario
        construction. This experiment has overcome some of the major
        difficulties that were associated with the previous generations
        of equilibrium (circa IPCC 1990) and cold-start transient (circa
        IPCC 1992) climate change experiments.  HadCM2 has a spatial
        resolution of 2.5 degrees x 3.75 degrees (latitude by longitude)
        and the representation produces a grid box resolution of 96 x 73
        grid cells. This produces a surface spatial resolution of about
        417km x 278 km reducing to 295 x 278km at 45 degrees North and
        South (comparable to a spectral resolution of T42).  The
        equilibrium climate sensitivity (DT2x) of HadCM2, that is the
        global-mean temperature response to a doubling of effective CO2
        concentration, is approximately 2.5 degrees C, although, this
        quantity varies with the time-scale considered. This is somewhat
        lower than most other GCMs (IPCC, 1992). In order to undertake a
        'warm-start' experiment it is necessary to perturb the model
        with a forcing from an early historical era, when the radiative
        forcing was relatively small compared to the present. The Hadley
        Centre started their experiments performed with HadCM2 with
        forcing from the middle industrial era, about 1860 Mitchell et
        al., 1995 and Johns et al., 1995.  The greenhouse gas only
        integrations, HadCM2GG, used the combined forcing of all the
        greenhouse gases as an equivalent CO2 concentration. A further
        series of integrations, HadCM2GS, used the combined equivalent
        CO2 concentration plus the negative forcing from sulphate
        aerosols. The HadCM2GG integrations simulated the change in
        forcing of the climate system by greenhouse gases since the
        early industrial period (taken by HadCM2 to be 1860). The
        addition of the negative forcing effects of sulphate aerosols
        represents the direct radiative forcing due to anthropogenic
        sulphate aerosols by means of an increase in clear-sky surface
        albedo proportional to the local sulphate loading (refer to
        Mitchell et al., 1995 for details of this method). The indirect
        effects of aerosols were not simulated.  The modelled control
        climate shows a negligible long term trend in surface air
        temperature over the first 400 years. The trend is about +0.04
        degrees C per century, which is comparable to other such
        experiments.  HadCM2CON represents an improvement over previous
        generations of GCMs that have been used at the Hadley Centre
        (Johns et al., 1995 and Airey et al., 1995).  The experiments
        performed have simulated the observed climate system using
        estimated forcing perturbations since 1860. Johns et al., (1995)
        and Mitchell et al., (1995) have established that HadCM2's
        sensitivity is consistent with the real climate system. The
        agreement between the observed global-mean temperature record
        and that produced in these experiments is better for HadCM2GS
        than for HadCM2GG. This implies that HadCM2Gs has captured the
        observed signal of global-mean temperature changes better than
        HadCM2GG for the recent 100-year record.  The climate
        sensitivity of HadCM2 is about 2.5 degrees C</para><para>For the A2 emissions scenario the main emphasis is on a
        strengthening of regional and local culture, with a return to
        family values in many regions. The A2 world consolidates into a
        series of roughly continental economic regions, emphasizing
        local cultural roots. In some regions, increased religious
        participation leads many to reject a materialist path and to
        focus attention on contributing to the local community.
        Elsewhere, the trend is towards increased investment in
        education and science and growth in economic productivity.
        Social and political structures diversify, with some regions
        moving towards stronger welfare systems and reduced income
        inequality, while others move towards "lean"
        government. Environmental concerns are relatively weak, although
        some attention is paid to bringing local pollution under control
        and maintaining local environmental amenities. The A2 world sees
        more international tensions and less cooperation than in A1 or
        B1. People, ideas and capital are less mobile so that technology
        diffuses slowly. International disparities in productivity, and
        hence income per capita, are maintained or increased. With the
        emphasis on family and community life, fertility rates decline
        only slowly, although they vary among regions. Hence, this
        scenario family has high population growth (to 15 billion by
        2100) with comparatively low incomes per capita relative to the
        A1 and B1 worlds, at US$7,200 in 2050 and US$16,000 in
        2100.Technological change is rapid in some regions and slow in
        others as industry adjusts to local resource endowments,
        culture, and education levels. Regions with abundant energy and
        mineral resources evolve more resource intensive economies,
        while those poor in resources place very high priority on
        minimizing import dependence through technological innovation to
        improve resource efficiency and make use of substitute inputs.
        The fuel mix in different regions is determined primarily by
        resource availability. And divisions among regions persist in
        terms of their mix of technologies, with high-income but
        resource-poor regions shifting toward advanced post fossil
        technologies (renewables in regions of large land availability,
        nuclear in densely populated, resource poor regions) and
        low-income resource-rich regions generally relying on older
        fossil technologies.With substantial food requirements,
        agricultural productivity is one of the main focus areas for
        innovation and RD efforts in this future. Initially high levels
        of soil erosion and water pollution are eventually eased through
        the local development of more sustainable high-yield
        agriculture.Although attention is given to potential local and
        regional environmental damage, it is not uniform across regions.
        For example, sulfur and particulate emissions are reduced in
        Asia due to impacts on human health and agricultural production
        but increase in Africa as a result of the intensified
        exploitation of coal and other mineral resources. The A2 world
        sees high energy and carbon intensity, and correspondingly high
        GHG emissions. Its CO2 emissions are the highest of all four
        scenario families.  Data are available for the following
        periods:  1961-1990, 2010-2039; 2040-2069; and 2090-2099 Mean
        monthly and change fields.</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>climate</keyword><keyword>global climate change</keyword><keyword>wind</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><para>1. The IPCC Data Distribution Centre permits the research
        results from seven climate modelling centres (Hadley Centre for
        Climate Prediction and Research, Deutsches Klimarechenzentrum,
        Canadian Centre for Climate Modelling and Analysis, Geophysical
        Fluids Dynamics Laboratory, the Commonwealth and Scientific
        Industrial Research Organisation, the National centre for
        Atmospheric Research and the Centre for Climate System Research)
        to be used freely for the purposes of bona fide research. (Bona
        fide research is deemed to be research which generates results
        that are freely and universally accessible to any interested
        party, i.e., if people use DDC data they must agree to publish
        results openly or respond willingly to requests from others for
        copies of the results.)  2. The climate modelling centres'
        research results should not be used for commercial exploitation,
        business use, resale or transfer to any third party.  3. No
        warranty is given as to the suitability of the climate modelling
        centres' research results for particular purposes.  4. No
        liability is accepted by the IPCC Data Distribution Centre
        and/or the climate modelling centres for any errors or omissions
        in the climate modelling centres' research results, associated
        information and/or documentation.  5. Please acknowledge the use
        of the corresponding climate modelling centres' research results
        in any publication.  6. The intellectual property rights on the
        climate modelling centres' research results remains the property
        of each of the climate modelling centres.  7. By registering
        with the DDC you agree to abide by this Data Statement.</para></intellectualRights><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Worldwide</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-180.0</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>180.0</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>90.0</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>-90.0</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2020-01-01</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2020-12-31</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><contact id="1086642088609" scope="document"><organizationName>IPCC</organizationName></contact><methods><methodStep><description><para>Format (ASCII)  There is a six line header for each
            month, the codes for the header fields in italics (e.g.
            Model Name) are given below. The following is an example of
            the structure of the scenario data files:  IPCC Data
            Distribution Centre Results from model ModelName Date Grid
            is xxx*yyy    Month is Jan   Mean change values for yyyy -
            yyyy with respect to 1960 - 1990 Experiment name Code
            Variable-Name-(Units) DataItems-----Format is 10f8.2 Missing
            value is 9999.99  NOTE: For the period 1961-1990 the data
            are the actual values, for the 2010-2039, 2040-2069 and
            2070-2099 the data are the changes with respect to the
            1961-1990 period.Forcing Details - GG = Greenhouse Gas: GS =
            Greenhouse Gas and Sulphate Aerosols; A = 1% per annum
            (IS92a); D= 0.5% per annum (IS92d); 1, 2, 3 or 4 represents
            the ensemble member or X = Ensemble mean.Experiment Code
            -Refers to the first six characters of the file name (i.e.,
            AACCD1)Data Items - The product of xxx*yyy (e.g. 7008)</para></description></methodStep></methods><access authSystem="knb" order="denyFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><spatialRaster scope="document"><entityName>HADCM3_A2a_WIND_2020.dif</entityName><physical scope="document"><objectName>HADCM3_A2a_WIND_2020.dif</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>6</numHeaderLines><numPhysicalLinesPerRecord>1</numPhysicalLinesPerRecord><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>space</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">ecogrid://knb/IPCC.200802109303345.1</url></online></distribution></physical><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>WIND</attributeName><attributeLabel>WindSpeed</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Mean Scalar Wind Speed (m/s)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>metersPerSecond</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">1000</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList><spatialReference scope="document"><horizCoordSysName>GCS_WGS_1984</horizCoordSysName></spatialReference><horizontalAccuracy><accuracyReport>Unknown</accuracyReport></horizontalAccuracy><verticalAccuracy><accuracyReport>Unknown</accuracyReport></verticalAccuracy><cellSizeXDirection>0.5</cellSizeXDirection><cellSizeYDirection>0.5</cellSizeYDirection><numberOfBands>1</numberOfBands><rasterOrigin>Upper Left</rasterOrigin><rows>48</rows><columns>96</columns><verticals>12</verticals><cellGeometry>pixel</cellGeometry></spatialRaster></dataset></ns0:eml>