<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="esa.101.2" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 eml.xsd">


<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst">
<allow>
  <principal>uid=esaadmin,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
  <principal>cn=knb-prod,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
  <principal>cn=esa-moderators,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
  <principal>uid=regetz,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>read</permission>
<permission>write</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
  <principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission>
</allow>
</access>
<dataset>
<alternateIdentifier system="National Marine Fisheries Service, Fisheries Ecology Division, Santa Cruz">Map Data avaliable at the California Seafloor Mapping Project website</alternateIdentifier>
<title>Presence -absense data of macro benthic invertebrates within the Santa Barbara Channel, California</title>
<creator>
<organizationName>National Marine Fisheries Service, Fisheries Ecology Division, Santa Cruz</organizationName>
</creator>
<creator>
<organizationName>Ecological Society of America</organizationName>
</creator>
<creator>
<individualName>
<givenName>Lisa</givenName>
<surName>Krigsman</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>National Marine Fisheries Service, Fisheries Ecology Division, Santa Cruz</organizationName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>110 Shaffer Road,
</deliveryPoint>
<city>Santa Cruz</city>
<administrativeArea>California</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>95060</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
<phone>831-420-3971</phone>
<phone phonetype="Fax">831-420-3980</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>lisa.krigsman@noaa.gov</electronicMailAddress>
</creator>
<metadataProvider><individualName>
<givenName>Lisa</givenName>
<surName>Krigsman</surName>
</individualName>
</metadataProvider>
<associatedParty><individualName>
<givenName>Lisa</givenName>
<surName>Krigsman</surName>
</individualName>
<role>associatedParty</role>
</associatedParty>
<pubDate>2011-12-08</pubDate>
<abstract>
<para>Data was collected from within the Santa Barbara Channel from Refugio State Beach to Hueneme Canyon.  Visual surveys of the seafloor were conducted 29 September to 8 October 2008 and 10 to 20 August 2009 using a camera sled towed from the R/V Shearwater. The camera sled was towed one meter above the seafloor at approximately one knot along transects roughly one nautical mile in length.  Ten second observations were made on benthic macro-organisms to lowest possible taxa, primary (&gt;50% coverage within the viewed area during the 10-second sample) and secondary (&gt;20% coverage within the viewed area during the 10-second sample) substratum type (e.g., rock, sand, etc.), and abiotic complexity (measured as low, medium, and high) based on small-scale variations in height of the seafloor surface. Numeric habitat classes of 1, 2, or 3 was assigned to each 10-second sample by combining observations of primary and secondary substrata with abiotic complexity. We developed generalized linear models (GLMs) to predict the probability of occurrence for the most frequently observed macro-invertebrate taxa. Presence-absence data from the 10-second samples were fit to binomial GLMs with logit link functions (multiple logistic regression) using alternative combinations of three covariates (block, also known as location, depth, and habitat class) and all possible 2-way interaction terms. Models were validated and using a program called MGET maps were created showing predicted probabilities of occurrence within the Santa Barbara Channel.  </para>
</abstract>
<keywordSet>
<keyword>deep-sea coral</keyword>
<keyword>Generalized Linear Models</keyword>
<keyword>Predictive species distribution maps</keyword>
<keyword>California Seafloor Mapping Project</keyword>
<keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
</keywordSet>
<additionalInfo>
<para>All map data, including bathymetry, backscatter, and seafloor character type are available at California Seafloor Mapping Project website.</para>
</additionalInfo>
<intellectualRights>
<para>no restrictions</para>
</intellectualRights>
<distribution>
<online>
<url>http://walrus.wr.usgs.gov/mapping/csmp/progress.html</url>
</online>
</distribution>
<distribution>
<offline>
<mediumName>digital </mediumName>
</offline>
</distribution>
<coverage>
<temporalCoverage>
<rangeOfDates>
<beginDate>
<calendarDate>2008-09-29</calendarDate>
</beginDate>
<endDate>
<calendarDate>2009-08-20</calendarDate>
</endDate>
</rangeOfDates>
</temporalCoverage>
<geographicCoverage>
<geographicDescription>Santa Barbara Channel</geographicDescription>
<boundingCoordinates>
<westBoundingCoordinate>-120.1694</westBoundingCoordinate>
<eastBoundingCoordinate>-119.1753</eastBoundingCoordinate>
<northBoundingCoordinate>34.4436</northBoundingCoordinate>
<southBoundingCoordinate>34.0794</southBoundingCoordinate>
</boundingCoordinates>
</geographicCoverage>
<taxonomicCoverage>
<generalTaxonomicCoverage>Gotshall, D. W. 2005. Guide to marine invertebrates: Alaska to Baja California, 2nd Edition (Revised). Sea Challengers, Monterey, California, USA.</generalTaxonomicCoverage>
<taxonomicClassification>
  <taxonRankName>Order</taxonRankName>
  <taxonRankValue>Pennatulacea</taxonRankValue>
</taxonomicClassification>
<taxonomicClassification>
  <taxonRankName>Class</taxonRankName>
  <taxonRankValue>Ophiuroidea</taxonRankValue>
</taxonomicClassification>
<taxonomicClassification>
  <taxonRankName>Order</taxonRankName>
  <taxonRankValue>Scleractinia </taxonRankValue>
</taxonomicClassification>
<taxonomicClassification>
  <taxonRankName>Class</taxonRankName>
  <taxonRankValue>Hydrozoa </taxonRankValue>
</taxonomicClassification>
</taxonomicCoverage>
</coverage>
<contact>
<individualName>
<givenName>Lisa</givenName>
<surName>Krigsman</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>National Marine Fisheries Service, Fisheries Ecology Division, Santa Cruz</organizationName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>110 Shaffer Road,
</deliveryPoint>
<city>Santa Cruz</city>
<administrativeArea>California</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>95060</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
<phone>831-420-3971</phone>
<phone phonetype="Fax">831-420-3980</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>lisa.krigsman@noaa.gov</electronicMailAddress>
</contact>
<methods><methodStep><description><section>
<title>Video analysis to record presence-absence data on benthic macro-invertebrates</title>
<para>Geo-referenced video and still images were reviewed in the laboratory using MediaMapper (Red Hen Systems, Inc., Fort Collins, Colorado, USA) to assign a numeric habitat class of 1, 2, or 3 to a 10-second samples by combining observations of primary and secondary substrata with abiotic complexity (Cochrane and Lafferty 2002, Cochrane 2008). Habitat class 1 included less complex, unconsolidated sediments (e.g., soft sand or mud); habitat class 2 comprised moderately complex, mixed sediments (e.g., flat rock outcrops or cobbles); and habitat class 3 included highly complex rugose rock.</para>
<para>Presence-absence data for benthic, non-mobile macro-organisms was also collected while in the field and back in the laboratory. Organisms were identified to the lowest possible taxonomic category or they were identified based on descriptive characteristics. </para>
</section></description></methodStep>
<sampling><studyExtent><description>
<para>Our study was located in the Santa Barbara Channel from Refugio State Beach to Hueneme Canyon. (i.e., Refugio, Coal Oil Point, Santa Barbara, Ventura, and Hueneme Canyon); no data were collected from the area offshore of Carpinteria due to poor sea conditions.</para>
</description></studyExtent>
<samplingDescription>
<para>The camera sled was towed one meter above the seafloor at approximately one knot along transects roughly one nautical mile in length. Water depths ranged from 9 to 150 m. Real-time observations were made by a biologist and a geologist during 10-second intervals at the top of every minute. These observations were recorded using a pre-programmed key pad interfaced with the navigation data.</para>
</samplingDescription>
</sampling>
</methods>
</dataset></ns0:eml>