<metadata><Source>http://www1.usgs.gov/metadata/mdata/vip/metapinnspatial.xml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Aerial Information Systems, PINN, NatureServe, California Native Plant Society</origin>
<origin>USGS/CSS/Core Science Analytics and Synthesis</origin>
<pubdate>20090101</pubdate>
<title>Pinnacles National Monument Vegetation Mapping Project - Spatial Vegetation Data</title>
<geoform>map: vector digital data</geoform>
<onlink>http://www1.usgs.gov/vip/pinn/pinngeodata.zip</onlink>
<onlink>doi:10.5066/F7S46PZ7</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>Between 2003 - 2008, the vegetation within a study area of 18,210 hectares (44,997 acres) that encompasses the Pinnacles National Monument (PINN), a quarter-mile buffer and several additional parcels of interest adjacent to the Park was mapped. The map was produced from photo interpretation of 2003 and 2005 natural color and 2002 color infrared digital 1 meter NAIP imagery orthophotos. In 2003 and 2004 Park staff collected vegetation and environmental data from 591 relev&#233;s to support the map and classification. Assessment of map accuracy entailed sampling of 766 additional data points in 2008. Multivariate analysis of the 2003-2004 plot data revealed 67 National Vegetation Classification (NVC) plant associations, alliances or Park special vegetation types within the Monument and environs. Of these, 45 are described at the plant association level; seven others are described at the alliance level. The remaining 22 are described as 'Park specials' because they occur only in small stands and appear to be unique to the Monument. The vegetation of the mapping project area is relatively diverse, including 50 NVC alliances. Chaparral, oak woodlands and dry herbaceous areas dominate the vegetation, accounting for ~35 associations. A total of 6,141 map polygons representing 34 vegetation map classes (including tree and shrub cover attributes), fourteen land use map classes and 7 miscellaneous classes were developed for the PINN vegetation mapping project. Of the 6,141 mapped polygons, 115 were assigned both a land use class and a vegetation class. The average polygon size across all map classes is 3 ha (7.3 acres). Natural and semi-natural vegetation classes cover 17,953 ha (44,362 acres), or 98.6% of the project area. Land use polygons, including ranch developments, agriculture and Park facilities cover 250 ha (617 acres), or 1.4 % of the project area. Final overall map Producer accuracy is 84.4% (Kappa correction = 83.1%). Final overall map User accuracy is 78.0% (Kappa correction = 75.6%).</abstract>
<purpose>The purpose of this project was to describe and map existing vegetation on 18,210 hectares (44,997 acres), within PINN and its environs, and to provide this information in written, tabular, digital and spatial formats useful to Monument resource managers, the California Native Plant Society, Department of Fish and Game and others. The basic project components consist of a classification and description of the Monument's vegetation and a spatial database encompassing an interpretation of the vegetation from aerial imagery.</purpose>
<supplinf>
Introduction

AIS was contracted by NPS to photo interpret and map a vegetation database for Pinnacles National Monument (PINN) using the National Vegetation Classification System (NVCS). The mapping project was initiated in 2007 and was completed in 2009. For the complete description of the project please refer to the Vegetation Classification and Mapping Project Report, Pinnacles National Monument (Kittel, et. al., 2009).

The study area for the project covers 44,997 acres and consists of two tiers. The first tier (park and buffer area) includes lands within the park boundary as well as a quarter-mile buffer around the park. The second tier (extended study area) includes several areas of interest, of varying sizes, adjacent to the park and buffer.

The base imagery for the mapping was the 2005 NAIP natural color (leaf-on) digital orthophotos, with supplementary 2003 natural color digital orthophotos (leaf-on) and 2002 color infrared digital orthophotos (leaf-on).

The Original mapping was done using an on-screen photo interpretation and digitizing method. Field reconnaissance was conducted before the mapping, and an in-field map and vegetion key validation was conducted, with resulting field revisions incorporated.

The original mapping classification contained mainly alliance and association level classes, as well as group and macrogroup categories such as xeric chaparral, mesic chaparral, riparian trees, riparian shrubs, wet herbaceous, and dry herbaceous. There were also mapping unit classes such as rock outcrop, post burn chaparral, built-up, agriculture, and planted trees and shrubs. Land use was a second layer in the database, which included park facilities. Refer to Vegetation Classification and Mapping Project Report, Pinnacles National Monument, (Kittel, et. al.,2009) for the full original mapping classification.
An accuracy assessment (AA) was conducted on the original vegetation map database. The AA had a criterium of 80% accuracy at the 90% confidence level for all classes. As a result of the AA, classes that were below the 80% threshold were bumped up the classification hierarchy until they attained a category where they met the 80% criterium. The result was a Post AA vegetation database.

During the AA process it was recognized that many of the mapped polygons, although they did not reach the 80% threshold, still held valid information that could be of importance to the park or end users. NPS on a national level also recognizes that AA discrepancies may be the result of PI, key, classification, and in-field factors such as:

" 	vegetation descriptions/definitions and key not accounting for all the variations in a type
" 	field vs. PI perspective of stand density and vegetation distribution
" 	GPS positional error
" 	low number of AA sites sampled where just one or two misses can put a class below 80%. For example
2 sites, 1 miss = 50%
3 sites, 2 miss = 33%, 1 miss = 66%
4 sites, 3 miss = 25 %, 2 miss = 50%, 1 miss = 75%
5 sites, 4 miss = 20%, 3 miss = 40%, 2 miss = 60%, 1 miss = 80%

which can result in classes falling below the 80% threshold, but may not necessarily be a true indication of the accuracy of a class.

Future NPS vegetation mapping efforts will include a validation step before final delivery for the AA that will accept classes of &gt;60% accuracy with the intent of incorporating changes into the map from new information gained by the validation process prior to AA (Lea, communication, August 2009). This new direction supports the mapping/field efforts that were done at PINN. However the final Post AA database that was considered the final deliverable, did not use the &gt;60% accuracy threshold. Therefore, in order to provide the park with a vegetation database that retained more detail than the Post AA database but modifying the vegetation interpretation from the knowledge gained through the AA process, a third Post AA Park-Specific database has been created. This database maintains most of the original suballiance and association classes with modifications made based new information. Misintepretation trends brought out by the AA process were also considered.

The three deliverable databases to the Park are described below:
" 	Original Database - This is the pre-AA vegetation map database that was delivered in February 2008, as an interim product. This database has no modifications as a result of AA. The original database may have some useful information that the other databases will not have. It is recommended to archive the original database, but it is available when needed. There is no documentation to accompany the original database.
" 	Post AA Database - This database represents the modifications to the vegetation database as a result of AA. Changes are in the form of global recoding reflecting bumping up to higher hierarchical categories for most types that were &lt;80% producer accuracy. The purpose is to have a database with as many types &gt;80% producer accuracy as possible. Some types with accuracy 70-80% were left in as agreed to by the Park. This is the peer reviewed official database. The documentation in Vegetation Classification and Mapping Project Report, Pinnacles National Monument (Kittel, et. al., 2009) is for the Post AA Database, delivered in July 2009. Note that AA only applied to land within the park boundary and quarter mile buffer.
" 	Post AA Park-Specific Database - This can be considered a final working vegetation database in which polygons for selected types that are &lt;80% producer accuracy have been revisited and reviewed for linework and/or coding in order to improve the interpretations of the type based on information gained from the AA process. In order to assess the accuracy of this database a new AA effort would need to be conducted. In theory accuracy is improved, though not assessed, by applying information learned through the AA process. This document is provided to accompany the Post AA Park-Specific database. Descriptions have been modified in some cases to better reflect the mapping as a result of accuracy assessment information. Types above 60% were kept. If the total polygon count for a type was &lt;30 then all polygons were revisited and recoded as needed. If the polygon count was &gt;30 then a limited criteria such as low conifer density or low tree density were used for revisiting and recoding. In other cases a description modification was necessary. Refer to the Classification Modification Summary for the Post AA Park-Specific Vegetation Database (below) for a list of the changes made for each type.

Vegetation Classification vs. Mapping Classification

It is important for the user to understand the difference between the vegetation classification and the mapping classification. Vegetation classification is based on analylsis of detailed field information from Releve and Rapid Assessment Plots (RA) that describe types based not only on the overstory, but on understory and vegetation species composition and cover, as well as environmental factors. The sampling effort is constrained by accessibility, logistics, and budget. Types may be missed, over sampled, undersampled, or auto correlated. Many of the components describing the vegetation type are not visible from above and therefore cannot be ascertained through photo interpretation or remote sensing techniques.

The mapping classification, although attempting to mimic the vegetation classification, can only take into account visible parameters. Visible factors include overstory vegetation, understory vegetation where the overstory is open to sparse allowing a visible understory, environmental setting (aspect, elevation, slope shape, slope position, slope steepness, local geomorphology, moisture, and proximity to water). Some vegetation classes are not mappable due to consistently small size less than the minimum mapping unit, and some due to limitations in the imagery. In mapping the mapper has to put a boundary around each vegetation stand and classify each stand as a type based on the definitions and descriptions from the vegetation classification. In the process, the mapper may encounter gaps in the vegetation classification, or wide variations in the expression of a type, and gradations or transitions of one type to another. Therefore, the mapping classification description describes the vegetation or mapping classes from a photo interpretation and mapping perspective.

Mapping classes that do not correlate directly to the macrogroup, group, alliance, or association of the vegetation classification are called suballiance or superalliance "Mapping Units". The mapping unit is a mapping class that is a mappable type as viewed on the imagery that maintains consistent floristic and/or ecological relationships. If not for the mapping unit, the type would be backed off to an alliance, group, or even macrogroup level.

Chronology

The following section is a short outline, listed in chronological order, of the vegetation mapping effort at Pinnacles National Monument (PINN).
2003 -- 256 relev&#233; plots were collected within the Monument following California Native Plant Society protocols
2004 -- an additional 335 relev&#233;s were collected on portions of the 2,000 acres of land that previously comprised the Kingman Ranch and is now held by The Nature Conservancy for NPS purchase. Additional relev&#233; data were collected to capture vegetation types not sampled in 2003. University of Montana conducted mapping with Landsat imagery.
2005 -- University of Montana, Wildlife Spatial Analysis Lab completed a vegetation
map with 11 classes
2006 -- Park acquires more funding to complete vegetation association classification and a more detailed map. California Native Plant Society (CNPS) and NatureServe are contracted to conduct vegetation classification and plant association descriptions. AIS is contracted to produce a more detailed map of the current vegetation. Fall 2006, winter 2007 Vegetation analysis and classification gets under way.
2007
March-- Initial Meeting and Park Tour, Preliminary photo interpretation mapping classification compiled.
May-- First photo interpretation field reconnaissance
June-- Second photo interpretation field reconnaissance
August-- Begin photo interpretation, mapping and quality control of vegetation delineations and attribution.
October-- First field verification
November --Second field verification. Field meeting with CNPS and NatureServe, key to association's field tested.
2008
January-June Final mapping classification for photo interpretation. Completion of photo interpretation, mapping and quality control of vegetation delineations and attribution.
July -September Field crew training by CNPS, NatureServe and AIS, and field work conducted to collect AA points.
September -December AA data entered into database.
2009
January-February AA data analyzed, map validation, AA statistics generated and final map production.
March-June-- Final report production and map printing

Post AA Park-Specific Mapping Classification
1000 - 2000 FORESTS &amp; WOODLANDS

1200 - California Evergreen Coniferous Forests and Woodlands Group
1210 - Foothill Pine Woodland Alliance
1211 - Foothill Pine/Chaparral Woodland Mapping Unit [park/buffer]
1212 - Foothill Pine/California Wild Buckwheat Alluvial Woodland Mapping Unit [park/buffer]
1213 - Foothill Pine/California Wild Buckwheat Thin Substrate Woodland Mapping Unit [park/buffer]
1220 - California Juniper Woodland Alliance

1300 - Southwestern North American Riparian Evergreen and Deciduous Forest Group
1310 - California Sycamore Temporarily Flooded Woodland Alliance
1311 - California Sycamore-Coast Live Oak Woodland Association [park/buffer]

2100 - California Broadleaf Forest and Woodland Group [non-deciduous]
2110 - Coast Live Oak Woodland Alliance
2112 - Coast Live Oak/Annual Grass-Herb Woodland Association [park/buffer]
2114 - Coast Live Oak Alluvial Woodland Mapping Unit [park/buffer]
2120 - Interior Live Oak Woodland Alliance

2200 - California Broadleaf Forest and Woodland Group [deciduous]
2210 - Blue Oak Woodland Alliance
2211 - Blue Oak/Chaparral/Grass Woodland Mapping Unit [park/buffer]
2212 - Blue Oak/Mixed Herbaceous Woodland Association [park/buffer]
2213 - Blue Oak-California Juniper Woodland Association [park/buffer]
2216 - Blue Oak-California Buckeye Woodland Mapping Unit [park/buffer]
2217 - Blue Oak-Foothill Pine Woodland Mapping Unit [park/buffer]
2218 - Blue Oak/Coastal Sage Scrub Woodland Mapping Unit [park/buffer]
2220 - California Buckeye Woodland Alliance
2230 - Valley Oak Woodland Alliance
2231 - Valley Oak-Coast Live Oak/Grass Woodland Association [park/buffer]
2232 - Valley Oak-Coast Live Oak/Mesic Grass Woodland Mapping Unit [park/buffer]

3000 - SHRUBLANDS

3100 - Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup [extended area]
3101 - Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Group
3110 - Chamise Shrubland Alliance [park/buffer]
3114 - Chamise-Coastal Sage Scrub Shrubland Mapping Unit [park/buffer]
3115 - Chamise-California Wild Buckwheat Shrubland Mapping Unit [park/buffer]
3150 - Hollyleaf Cherry Shrubland Alliance [park/buffer]
3160 - California Scrub Oak Shrubland Alliance

3200 - Evergreen Coastal Scrub Shrubland Group
3210 - Coyote Brush Shrubland Alliance [park/buffer]

3300 - California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup
3330 - California Wild Buckwheat Shrubland Alliance [park/buffer]
3331 - California Wild Buckwheat Alluvial Shrubland Mapping Unit [park/buffer]
3332 - California Wild Buckwheat Thin Substrate Shrubland Mapping Unit [park/buffer]
3350 - Silver Lupine Shrubland Alliance [park/buffer]
3360 - Black Sage Alliance [park/buffer]
3370 - California Sagebrush-California Wild Buckwheat Shrubland Alliance [park/buffer]

3400 - Southwestern North American Riparian/Wash Scrub Shrubland Group
3410 - California Rose Shrubland Alliance

4000 - HERBACEOUS

4003 - Open to Sparse Grass on Thin Substrate Herbaceous Vegetation Mapping Unit

4404 - Alluvial Herb and Shrub Vegetation Mapping Unit

4100 - Western North American Freshwater Marsh Herbaceous Vegetation Macrogroup
4101 - Bulrush-Cattails Herbaceous Vegetation Mapping Unit

4300 - Mediterranean California Naturalized Annual and Perennial Grassland and Herbaceous Vegetation Macrogroup

4500 - Western North American Wet Meadow and Low Shrub Carr Herbaceous Vegetation Macrogroup
4510 - Deergrass Herbaceous Vegetation Alliance

9000 - MISCELLANEOUS CLASSES

9100 - Built-up Mapping Unit

9200 - Agriculture Mapping Unit

9400 - Sparsely Vegetated to Non-vegetated Mapping Units
9420 - Cliffs, Rock Outcrops, and Steep Eroded Slopes Mapping Unit

9500 - Water Mapping Unit

9600 - Planted Trees and Shrubs Mapping Unit

9700 - Post Burn and Post Disturbance Undifferentiated Shrub and Grass-Herb Regeneration Mapping Unit
9710 - Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit
9720 - Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit

COVER CLASS DENSITY VALUES - Conifer, Hardwood, Shrub
1 = &gt;60%
2 = 40-60%
3 = 25-40%
4 = 10-25%
5 = 2-10%
9 = None

LAND USE MAP UNITS

100 - Urban - Non-park facilities and private in-holdings
110 - Residential (includes farmsteads [residences with associated farm buildings] along Hwy 25, Regan Ranch, Schmidt Ranch, McCabe Canyon, and the West side)
200 - Agriculture
210 - Cropland
220 - Orchards and Vineyards
230 - Other Agriculture
400 - National Park/Monument Facilities
401 - Bear Gulch Facilities (Headquarters, Visitor Center, Employee Residence, Parking, Restroom)
402 - Chalone Creek Facilities (Maintenance, Employee Residence)
403 - Bear Gulch Parking (Parking, Restroom)
404 - Pinnacles Campground Facilities
405 - Chaparral Facilities (Visitor Center, Parking, Picnic Area, Employee Residence)
408 - Eastern Addition Former Farmsteads
409 - Eastern Addition Airport Buildings
410 - North Chalone Peak Lookout/Restroom
800 - Water
900 - Vacant

Classification Modification Summary for the Post AA Park-Specific Vegetation Database

1210 - PiSa strongly dominant trees
" 	Including polygons coded as 1210,1211, 1212, 1213
" 	Pre and Post AA producer accuracy of 71%
" 	No modifications from alliance level point of view.
1211 - PiSa strongly dominant trees over chaparral dominant or co-dominant shrub layer
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	kept 1211 in the Park-Specific Database
o 	revisited and reviewed polygons with assigned conifer density cover code of 5 (2-10%) and recoded attributes to appropriate veg type/cover code
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy of 59% with 27 AA sites
o 	Tree density at borderline threshold 8-10% between trees vs. shrub alliance
o 	Field vs. PI perspective of cover density within polygon
o 	Field vs. PI perspective of shrub and tree distribution within polygon
" 	Post AA database bumped up to 1210 alliance
1212 - PiSa strongly dominant trees in alluvial setting
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	kept 1212 in Park-Specific Database
o 	revisited and reviewed all 23 polygons and recoded map code to appropriate veg type code
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy of 43% with 7 AA sites
o 	Crew and PI both called as PiSa alliance class
o 	Polygons are in alluvial setting
o 	Riparian shrubs as inclusional
" 	Post AA bumped up to 1210 alliance
1213 - PiSa strongly dominant trees in rocky setting
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	kept 1213
o 	revisited and reviewed all 15 polygons and recode to map code to appropriate veg type code
o 	Reviewed for rockiness (including context) and tree vs. shrub density threshold for alliance
o 	Potential indicator of SeBi presence
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy 0% with 4 AA sites
o 	Tree density at borderline threshold 8-10% between trees vs. shrub alliance
o 	Field vs. PI perspective of cover density within polygon
o 	Field vs. PI perspective of shrub and tree distribution within polygon
" 	Post AA bumped up to 1210 alliance
1220 - JuCa dominant trees
" 	Including polygons coded as 1220 and 1221
" 	Pre AA and Post AA producer accuracy of 83%
" 	No action required
1221 - JuCa dominant with PrIl in understory
" 	Deleted from Park-Specific Database mapping classification
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy of 25%
o 	Very low PrIl component, but correct at the alliance level
o 	Only one association in the alliance
" 	Post AA and Park-Specific Database recoded all 5 polygons as 1220
1300=1301 (original) - Mixed riparian trees with PoFr, SalLas, and PlRa dominating or co-dominating
" 	Including polygons coded as 1300, 1310, 1311
" 	Post AA producer accuracyof 73%
o 	Tree density at borderline threshold 8-10% between riparian trees vs. riparian shrubs
o 	Field view density vs. PI view density
o 	Field view of shrub and tree distribution vs. PI view of distribution
o 	Code changed from original 1301 to 1300 reflecting clarification in NVCS hierarchy
" 	Post AA database kept as is
o 	Riparian areas significant
o 	Producer accuracy in 70s is worth keeping for Post AA database
" 	No action required.
1301 - See 1300
" 	Code changed from original 1301 (original) to 1300 reflecting clarification in NVCS hierarchy
1310 - PlRa dominant or co-dominant tree
" 	Including polygons coded as 1310 and 1311
" 	Pre AA and Post AA producer accuracy of 80%
" 	Park-Specific Database revisited and reviewed 1 missed AA polygon of the 2 polygons originally coded as 1310 and split into 1310 (RA point here) and 2114 (AA site here).
1311 - PlRa-QuAg co-dominant trees
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	recoded 1310 original codes back as 1310, bringing 1311 back to 100%
" 	Pre AA 100%, Post AA 80% producer accuracy
o 	Post AA called all 1310s as 1311, thus lowering the accuracy to 80%
2101=2110 - Live Oak dominant hardwood tree (QuAg, QuWi)
" 	Deleted from Park-Specific mapping classification
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy of 80%
" 	Most (80%) AA site calls were QuAg types, so Post AA decision was to globally recode all polygons to 2110 alliance.
" 	Note that there are a few RA sites classed as QuWi alliance in some polygons originally coded as 2101, none of these were selected as AA sites; these may also have QuAg in them.
2110 - QuAg dominant hardwood tree
" 	including polygons coded as 2110, 2112, 2114, and 2117
" 	Post AA producer accuracy of 86%
" 	No action required.
2112 - QuAg dominant hardwood tree over grass understory
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	kept 2112 in the Park-Specific Database
o 	revisited and reviewed all 20 polygons and recoded the map code as appropriate for veg type code
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy of 20% with 5 AA sites
o 	QuAg dominant tree over grass with low to very low cover of shrubs.
o 	Shrub cover hovered at threshold of 8-10% shrubs in understory.
o 	AA call went with alliance, while CNPS supervisor during PI field verification independently went with 2112 on two of the AA sites and other similar polygons.
" 	Post AA bumped up to 2110 alliance.
2114 - QuAg dominant hardwood tree in alluvial setting
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	kept the 2114 code in the Park-Specific Database
o 	documentation changed to reflect "Alluvial" rather than "Riparian" in type name and description.
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy of 66% with 28 AA sites
o 	Original name of class was QuAg Riparian. This caused most of the AA calls to go with alliance rather than 2114 since field crew determined that not really riparian. Post AA discussion concluded that QuAg Alluvial would have been a better name.
" 	Post AA bumped up to 2110 alliance.
2117 - QuAg-QuDo co-dominant trees
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	revisited and reviewed all 8 polygons and recoded map code as appropriate veg type code, eliminating 2117
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy of 33% with 3 AA sites
o 	QuDo-QuAg may be inclusional or ecotonal in general in the PINN area. QuAg tends to be in bottoms and concavities while QuDo is usually on side slopes.
" 	Post AA bumped up to 2110 alliance.
" 	Deleted from classification
2120 - QuWi dominant tree
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	kept as 2120 in Park-Specific Database since there is one known location.
o 	Mt. Defiance location is not likely for QuAg
" 	No AA conducted
" 	Only one site mapped, off Mt. Defiance, and was visited during field verification.
" 	Post AA recoded as 2110 alliance.
" 	See also code 2101 above
2210 - QuDo dominant or co-dominant tree
" 	Including polygons coded as 2210, 2211, 2212, 2213, 2216, 2217, and 2218
" 	Pre and Post AA producer accuracy of 87%
" 	No action required.
2211 - QuDo dominant over chaparral dominant to co-dominant shrubs, very little or no PiSa
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	kept 2211 in the Park-Specific Database
o 	revisited and reviewed polygons with conifer cover density 2-10% (code 5) and recoded map code appropriately for veg type code and conifer cover code
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy of 63% with 37 AA sites
o 	Sparse chaparral and grass in understory
o 	Field vs. PI perspective of chaparral distribution
o 	Tree density at borderline threshold 8-10% between trees vs. shrub alliance
o 	Many AA sites were calls within the QuDo alliance
" 	Post AA bumped up to the alliance
2212 - QuDo dominant over grass, very little or no chaparral, and very little or no PiSa
" 	Pre and Post AA producer accuracy of 89%
" 	No action required.
2213 - QuDo dominant or co-dominant with JuCa
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	kept 2213 in the Park-Specific Database
o 	revisited and reviewed all 53 polygons for JuCa vs. QuDo cover and recoded map code as appropriate for veg type/cover codes
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy of 61% with 23 AA sites o Some AA sites had low JuCa cover
" 	Post AA bumped up to 2210 alliance
2216 - QuDo dominant or co-dominant with AeCa
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	keep 2216 in the Park-Specific Database
o 	revisited and reviewed all 23 polygons for QuDo-AeCa co-dominance and recoded map code as appropriate for veg type code.
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy of 67% with 6 AA sites
o 	AeCa and QuDo present, with QuAg or QuBe also present
" 	Post AA bumped up to 2210 alliance
2217 - QuDo co-dominant with PiSa
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	kept 2217 in the Park-Specific Database
o 	revisited and reviewed polygons with conifer cover density 2-10% (code 5) and recoded map code as appropriate for veg type code
o 	Renamed class as QuDo-PiSa Woodland Mapping Unit
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy of 66% with 35 AA sites
o 	Conifer cover density borderline at 5-10% between 2217 and 2212
o 	Tree density at borderline threshold 8-10% between trees vs. shrub alliance
" 	Post AA bumped up to 2210 alliance
2218 - QuDo dominant over coastal sage scrub
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	keep 2218 in the Park-Specific Database since Pre AA producer accuracy is 80%
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy of 80%
" 	Post AA bumped up to 2210 alliance
2220 - AeCa dominant tree
" 	Pre and Post AA producer accuracy is 81%
" 	No action required.
2230 - QuLo dominant tree or co-dominant with QuAg
" 	Including all polygons coded as 2230, 2231 and 2232
" 	Pre AA and Post AA producer accuracy 100%
" 	No action required
2231 - QuLo and QuAg co-dominant trees over grass
" 	including all polygons coded as 2231 and 2232
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	revisited and reviewed all 19 original polygons and recoded map code as appropriate veg type code
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy 71% with 7 AA sites
" 	Post AA producer accuracy is 100%
o 	All original 2231 polygons recoded to 2230 and all original 2232 polygons recoded to 2231
2232 - QuLo and QuAg co-dominant trees over mesic grass
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	Kept 2232 in Park-Specific Database since it was at 100% accuracy for pre AA
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy 100%
" 	Post AA all polygons recoded to 2231
3100 - Chaparral in the Extended Study Area
" 	Park-Specific Database represents chaparral in the extended study area
" 	Original database represents chaparral in the extended study area o No AA conducted
" 	Post AA database represents chaparral within the entire study area, including dry-mesic chaparral within the park/buffer (see 3102 below)
3101 - Xeric chaparral in the park/buffer (see 3110)
" 	Park-Specific Database recoded to 3110 (see 3110 below)
" 	Original and Post AA database coded as 3101.
3102=3100 (Post AA) - Dry-mesic chaparral (AdFa-CeCu, CeCu, with mesic shrub [PrIl, HeAr, CeBe, RhIl, ArPu, ArGl, ClLa] component) in the park/buffer
" 	 Park-Specific Database
o 	kept 3102 code in Park-Specific Database
o 	recoded polygons back to 3102 and renamed class to Dry-Mesic Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit.
o 	AA site polygons were revisited, reviewed and map code recoded as appropriate for veg type code
" 	 Original and Park-Specific Database database coded as 3102, Post AA database included in 3100.
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy is 71% o Original database included polygons coded as 3102, 3150 and 3160.
o 	Many AA sites show either AdFa -CeCu co-dominance with mesic shrub presence
o 	A few sites show AdFa-SaMe co-dominance with presence of mesic shrubs
o 	Many sites show CeCu dominance with presence of mesic shrubs
" 	Post AA database bumped up to 3100 chaparral macrogroup for producer accuracy of 76%
3103 - Post burn dry-mesic chaparral (original and Post AA) (see 9710)
" 	Park-Specific Database code changed to 9710 to better reflect post burn hierarchy
" 	No AA conducted
3104 - Post burn xeric chaparral (original and Post AA) (see 9720)
" 	Park-Specific Database code changed to 9720 to better reflect post burn hierarchy
" 	No AA conducted
3110=3101 (original/post AA) - AdFa dominant or AdFa-SaMe co-dominant chaparral
" 	Including polygons coded as 3110, 3113, 3114, and 3115
" 	Park-Specific Database recoded 3101 as 3110
o 	A majority of the AA points showed AdFa dominant or were called as AdFa alliance
" 	Original and Post AA database coded as 3101
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy as 3101 is 85%
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy as 3110 is 80%
3113=3110 - AdFa-SaMe co-dominant chaparral
" 	Park-Specific Database recoded 3113 as 3110
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy is 28%
o 	Many AA sites did not have SaMe or enough SaMe for co-dominance, but did have AdFa
o 	Some sites had other CSS shrubs in addition to or instead of SaMe
o 	Some AA sites had AdFa with CeCu and SaMe
" 	Post AA bumped 3113 up to 3101
" 	Deleted from classification
3114 - AdFa-Coastal sage scrub co-dominant chaparral
" 	including polygons coded as 3114 and 3115
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	Kept 3114 in Park-Specific Database
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy is 62%
o 	Tree density at borderline threshold 8-10% between trees vs. shrub alliance
o 	Shrub density at borderline threshold 8-10% between chaparral vs. CSS
o 	Field vs. PI perspective of cover density
o 	Field vs. PI perspective of shrub and tree distribution
o 	Field vs. PI perspecive of chaparral/CSS distribution
" 	Some AA sites show dominance of CSS (SaMe or ErFa or both)
" 	Post AA bumped 3114 up to 3101
3115 - AdFa-ErFa co-dominant chaparral
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	Kept 3115 in Park-Specific Database
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy is 65%
o 	Shrub density at borderline threshold 8-10% between chaparral vs. CSS
o 	Field vs. PI perspective of cover density
o 	Field vs. PI perspective of chaparral/CSS distribution
" 	Some AA sites show mix of CSS with the AdFa
" 	Post AA bumped 3115 up to 3101
3150 - PrIl dominant chaparral
" 	Pre AA and Post AA producer accuracy is 85%
" 	No action required
3160 - QuBe dominant chaparral
" 	Pre AA and Post AA producer accuracy is 80%
" 	No action required
3210 - BaPi dominant shrubs
" 	Pre and Post AA producer accuracy is 100%
" 	No action required
3300=3301 (original) - Coastal sage scrub dominant
" 	Including polygons coded as 3300, 3310, 3330, 3331, 3332, 3350, 3360, and 3370
" 	Park-Specific Database original database 3301 map code recoded as 3300
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy is 95%
o 	Original database 3300 code only used in extended study area
o 	Original database 3301 code only used in park/buffer
" 	Post AA producer accuracy is 94%
o 	Original database code of 3301 changed to Post AA database code of 3300
3310 - ArCa dominant CSS, no or very little chaparral
" 	Not mappable, no AA conducted
" 	Deleted from mapping classification
" 	Post AA and Park-Specific Database
o 	one polygon, code changed to 3330 (Field site information contained dominant ErFa with &lt;MMU inclusion of ArCa)
3330 - ErFa dominant CSS, no or very little chaparral
" 	Including polygons coded as 3331 and 3332
" 	Pre and Post AA producer accuracy is 96%
" 	No action required.
3331 - ErFa dominant CSS in alluvial setting
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	kept 3331 in Park-Specific Database
o 	revisited and reviewed all 11 polygons and recoded map code as appropriate for veg type code
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy is 60% with 5 AA sites
o 	Tree density at borderline threshold 8-10% between trees vs. shrub alliance
o 	Field vs. PI perspective of cover density
o 	Sites are in alluvial setting with ErFa
" 	Post AA bumped up to 3330 alliance
3332 - ErFa dominant CSS in rocky setting, no or very little chaparral
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	kept 3332 in Park-Specific Database
o 	revisited and reviewed all 29 polygons for rockiness vs. soil and recoded map code as appropriate for veg type code
o 	Post AA and Park-Specific Database descriptions modified to account for high SeBi cover.
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy is 40% for 5 AA sites
o 	A few AA sites had too much herb (not SeBi) and not enough rockiness
o 	Descriptions did not account for high SeBi cover.
" 	Post AA bumped up to 3330 alliance
3350 - LuAl dominant to co-dominant with alluvial CSS in alluvial setting, east side of park
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	kept 3350 in Park-Specific Database
o 	revisited and reviewed all 13 polygons and coded map code as appropriate for veg type code
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy is 60% with 5 AA sites
o 	Possible locational problem
o 	LuAl and ErFa in sparse stand co-dominate in alluvial setting
" 	Post AA bumped up to 3300
3360 - SaMe dominant CSS, no or very little chaparral
" 	Pre AA and Post AA producer accuracy is 100%
" 	No action required
3370 - ArCa-SaMe co-dominant shrubs, no or very little chaparral
" 	Pre AA and Post AA producer accuracy is 100%
" 	No action required
3400=3401 - Mixed riparian shrubs
" 	Includes polygons coded as 3400 and 3410
" 	Post AA and Park-Specific Database recoded original 3401 to 3400 reflecting clarification in NVCS hierarchy
" 	Pre AA and Post AA producer accuracy is 85%
" 	No action required
3410=3510 - RoCa dominant shrubs
" 	Post AA and Park-Specific Database recoded original 3510 to 3410 reflecting clarification in NVCS hierarchy
" 	Pre AA and Post AA producer accuracy is 100%
" 	No action required
4001 - Wet herbaceous (original) (see 4500)
" 	Only mapped in extended area in original database
" 	Post AA and Park-Specific Database recoded to 4001 to 4500 reflecting clarification in NVCS hierarchy
4002 - Dry herbaceous (original) (see 4300)
" 	Only mapped in extended area in original database
" 	Post AA and Park-Specific Database recoded 4002 to 4300 reflecting clarificationin NVCS hierarchy
4003 - Open to sparse grass on thin substrate (rocky, herbaceous, ErFa)
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	kept 4003 in Park-Specific Database
o 	descriptions modified to reflect possible moderate to high cover of SeBi
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy is 62%
o 	Tree density at borderline threshold 8-10% between trees vs. sparse/unvegetated alliance
o 	Field vs. PI perspective of cover density
o 	Field vs. PI perspective of sparse/unvegetated and tree distribution
o 	Shrub density at borderline threshold 8-10% between shrubs vs. sparse/unvegetated alliance
o 	Field vs. PI perspective of shrub and sparse/unvegetated distribution
o 	Descriptions did not have SeBi of moderate to high cover
" 	Post AA combined 4003 into 9420
4004=4401/9430 (original) - Very sparse alluvial herb and shrub on braided interfluves and bars
" 	Post AA and Park Specific Database
o 	kept and recoded from original 4401 to 4004
o 	combined 9430 into 4004 because they are very similar. Temporal in nature located in floodplain.
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy is 50%
o 	Sparse to very sparse stands with diverse alluvial shrubs and herbs, riparian shrubs may be present or adjacent as narrow linear inclusions
4101 - Bulrush-Cattails, inundated vegetation
" 	Only mappable areas are in Extended study area, no AA conducted
4201 - Wet herbaceous (park and buffer) (original) (see 4500)
" 	Post AA and Park-Specific Database
o 	recoded from original 4201 and 4001 (extended area) to 4500 to reflect clarification in the NVCS hierarchy
4300=4310/4002 (original) Dry herbaceous, annual and perennial dry grasses and forbs
" 	Post AA and Park-Specific Database
o 	recoded from original 4310 and 4002 (extended area) to 4300 to reflect clarification in NVCS hierarchy
" 	Pre AA and Post AA producer accuracy is 78%
o 	A couple sites on-ground vegetation modified since date of image
o 	Tree density at borderline threshold 8-10% between trees vs. herb alliance
o 	Field vs. PI perspective of cover density
o 	Field vs. PI perspective of herb and tree distribution
o 	Shrub density at borderline threshold 8-10% between shrubs vs. herb alliance
o 	Field vs. PI perspective of shrub and herb distribution
4310 - Dry herbaceous (park and buffer) (original) (see 4300)
" 	Post AA and Park-Specific Database
o 	kept and recoded from original 4310 and 4002 (extended area) to 4300 to reflect clarification in NVCS hierarchy
4500/4201/4001 (original) - Wet herbaceous, meadow grasses and forbs
" 	Includes polygons coded as 4500 and 4510
" 	Post AA and Park-Specific Database code change from original 4201 (park and buffer) and 4001 (extended area) to 4500 to reflect clarification in the NVCS hierarchy
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	kept and recoded original 4201 as 4500 in Park Specific Database
o 	revisited and reviewed, and recoded map code as appropriate for veg type code
" 	Post AA recoded 5 of the 7 polygons to 3400.
o 	The two largest polygons in the park/buffer were good examples of 4500 and were kept
o 	Most other larger polygons coded 4500 are in the extended study area.
o 	Presence of riparian shrubs as inclusion or adjacent.
o 	Temporal in nature
o 	Shrub density at borderline threshold 8-10% between shrubs vs. herb alliance
o 	Field vs. PI perspective of cover density o Field vs. PI perspective of shrub and herb distribution
o 	Most polygons were about &#189; ha in size
4510 - MuRi dominant herb
" 	Pre AA and Post AA producer accuracy is 100%
" 	No action required
9100 - Built Up
" 	No AA conducted
9200 - Agriculture
" 	No AA conducted
9420 - Cliffs, bluffs rock outcrops, steep eroded slopes
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	kept original 9420
o 	kept Post AA name
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy is 80%
" 	Post AA producer accuracy is 86%
o 	Post AA combined 4003 into 9420 and renamed without "Sparsely vegetated to non-vegetated".
" 	Post AA and Park-Specific Database description modified to include moderate to high cover of SeBi
9430=4004 - Sparsely vegetated to non vegetated stream beds and flats
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	Recoded 9430 as 4004
" 	Pre AA producer accuracy is 25% with 4 AA sites
o 	Sparse cover of diverse alluvial shrubs and herbs
o 	Temporal in nature
o 	Presence of riparian shrubs as inclusion or adjacent
o 	Very similar to 4004
" 	Post AA combine 9430 into 4004.
" 	Deleted from mapping classification
9500 - Water
" 	No AA conducted
9600 - Planted trees and shrubs
" 	No AA conducted
9700 - Post burn/post disturbance undifferentiated shrubs and grasses/herbs
" 	No AA conducted
9710=3103 - Post burn/post disturbance dry-mesic chaparral
" 	Park-Specific Database
o 	code changed to 9710 to better reflect post burn hierarchy
" 	No AA conducted
" 	Original and Post AA database coded as 3103.
9720=3104 - Post burn/post disturbance xeric chaparral
" 	 Park-Specific Database
o 	code changed to 9720 to better reflect post burn hierarchy
" 	No AA conducted
" 	Original and Post AA database coded as 3104.

Post AA Park-Specific Database Mapping Descriptions

The mapping descriptions characterize the mapping classes used in the Pinnacles National Monument vegetation map that was compiled in 2007-08. The descriptions are based on field reconnaissance, releve field samples, and 2005 NAIP natural color imagery. Other supplemental imagery may be applicable where noted.

Each mapped class is presented with the following format:
" 	The top of each page lists the Map Code with the Common Name of the map class, followed by the Scientific Name of the map class.
" 	Any vegetation classification associations that nest hierarchically into the map class are listed next.
" 	A snapshot of the vegetation map showing an example mapped polygon of the map class draped over the NAIP aerial imagery.
" 	A map showing the distribution of the map class in the original database over the study area. The inner boundary shown is the park boundary.
" 	A brief description of the map class describing general structure, cover, species, and ecology. Also noted is whether the map class is mapped within the park and buffer, expanded study area, or both.
" 	A brief description of the photo signature for the map class.
" 	A list of other map classes which are similar in signature to the map class being described.

Dominance and percent cover terms used in these descriptions are represented as follows (values are approximate):

Overall Structural Density  	 	    Individual Species
&gt;60%    Dense or continuous           &gt;60%    Extremely High
40-60%  Intermittent or slightly open 40-60%  Very High
25-40%  Open      25-40%   High
10-25%  Sparse    10-25%   Moderate
&lt;10%    Very sparse    5-10%          Low, for trees this can be emergent
&lt;5%     Very Low, or can be present

1210 - Foothill Pine Woodland Alliance
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Pinus sabiniana Woodland Alliance
Pinus sabiniana/Ceanothus cuneatus-Rhamnus ilicifolia Woodland Association
Pinus sabiniana/Eriogonum fasciculatum Woodland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Pinus sabiniana Woodland Alliance is mapped as intermittent to sparse stands of trees over an understory of intermittent to sparse chaparral, coastal sage scrub, grass, and/or rock. Pinus sabiniana is the dominant tree at high to low cover. This alliance can be found on floodplain terraces, canyon bottoms, and lower to upper side slopes. It can occupy northerly or southerly exposures. Quercus douglasii or Quercus agrifolia may be present at low to very low cover. Juniperus californica may be present at very low cover. Typical chaparral shrubs may include Ceanothus cuneatus, Adenostoma fasciculatum, Cercocarpus betuloides, and Rhamnus ilicifolia. In alluvial floodplains and terraces typical short shrubs may include Eriogonum fasciculatum, Lupinus albifrons, Lotus scoparius, and Eriodictyon tomentosum. Riparian shrubs including Salix lasiolepis, Salix exigua, and Baccharis salicifolia may be present at very low to moderate cover, usually as narrow channel inclusions. On steep rocky upper slopes sparse Pinus sabiniana may contain an understory of open to sparse chaparral and/or Eriogonum fasciculatum. Here Selaginella bigelovii may also be present at very low to high cover. This alliance is mapped within the park, buffer, and expanded study area. The alliance also represents the hierarchical class into which all Pinus sabiniana types are nested.

Photo Signature:
Pinus sabiniana appears on the imagery as rounded- to irregularly-crowned trees emergent over other shorter trees, chaparral, and grass. It has a light blue-green color with a soft to wispy texture. The chaparral is shorter with a rounded to irregular crown. Some shrubs appear as individuals, others as clusters with no distinctive crown. The chaparral can have a dull green, brownish-green, bluish-green, grayish-green, or brown color. Eriogonum fasciculatum is a low shrub with a gray, tan, or brown to rust color. It appears as small rounded individuals or in small clusters.

Types with Similar Signature:
Quercus agrifolia Woodland Alliance - 2110
Quercus douglasii Woodland Alliance - 2210
Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup - 3100
Adenostoma fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3110
California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup - 3300 (original 3301)
Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3330
Open to Sparse Grass on Rocky Thin Substrate Herbaceous Vegetation Mapping Unit - 4003
Alluvial Herb and Shrub Vegetation Mapping Unit - 4004 (original 4404)
Cliffs, Rock Outcrops, and Steep Eroded Slopes Mapping Unit - 9420

1211 - Foothill Pine/Chaparral Woodland Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original, and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Pinus sabiniana/Chaparral Woodland Mapping Unit
Pinus sabiniana/Ceanothus cuneatus-Rhamnus ilicifolia Woodland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Pinus sabiniana/Chaparral Woodland Mapping Unit is mapped as intermittent to sparse stands of trees over an understory of intermittent to sparse chaparral. Pinus sabiniana is the strongly dominant tree at high to low cover. Juniperus californica, Quercus douglasii, or Quercus agrifolia may be present at low to very low cover. Chaparral shrubs may include Ceanothus cuneatus, Adenostoma fasciculatum, Cercocarpus betuloides, and Rhamnus ilicifolia. This mapping unit favors northerly slopes, and is occasionally found on lower southerly slopes and canyon bottoms. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. In the expanded study area it is mapped as Pinus sabiniana Woodland Alliance (1210).

Photo Signature:
Pinus sabiniana appears on the imagery as rounded- to irregularly-crowned trees emergent over other shorter trees, chaparral, and grass. It has a light blue-green to blue-gray color with a soft to wispy texture. The chaparral is shorter with a rounded to irregular crown. Some shrubs appear as individuals, others as clusters with no distinctive crown. The chaparral can have a dull green, brownish-green, bluish-green, grayish-green, or brown color.

Types with Similar Signature:
Quercus douglasii Woodland Alliance - 2210
Quercus douglasii-Pinus sabiniana Woodland Mapping Unit - 2217
Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup - 3100
Adenostoma fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3110

1212 - Foothill Pine/California Wild Buckwheat Alluvial Woodland Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Pinus sabiniana/Eriogonum fasciculatum Alluvial Woodland Mapping Unit

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Pinus sabiniana/Eriogonum fasciculatum Alluvial Woodland Mapping Unit is mapped as open to sparse stands of trees over an understory of herbs and intermittent to sparse low shrubs. Pinus sabiniana is the dominant tree at moderate to low cover. Eriogonum fasciculatum is present at high to very low cover. Other low alluvial shrubs, including Lupinus albifrons, Lotus scoparius, and Eriodictyon tomentosum, may be present at very low cover. Quercus douglasii, Quercus agrifolia, Salix laevigata, Populus fremontii or Platanus racemosa may be present at very low cover. Riparian shrubs including Salix lasiolepis, Salix exigua, and Baccharis salicifolia may be present at very low to moderate cover, usually as narrow channel inclusions. Chaparral shrubs may also be present at very low cover. This association favors flat alluvial floodplain terraces and gently sloping lower alluvial fans or toe slopes adjacent to floodplains and valley or canyon bottoms. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. In the expanded study area it is mapped as Pinus sabiniana Woodland Alliance (1210).

Photosignature:
Pinus sabiniana appears on the imagery as rounded- to irregularly-crowned trees emergent over the shorter trees, low shrubs, and herbs. It has a light blue-green to blue-gray color with a soft to wispy texture. Eriogonum fasciculatum is a low shrub with a gray, tan, or brown to rust color. It appears as small rounded individuals.

Types with Similar Signature:
Pinus sabiniana/Eriogonum fasciculatum Thin Substrate Woodland Mapping Unit - 1213
Quercus agrifolia Woodland Alliance - 2110
Quercus douglasii Woodland Alliance - 2210
Quercus douglasii/Coastal Sage Scrub Woodland Mapping Unit - 2218
Eriogonum fasciculatum Alluvial Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3331
Eriogonum fasciculatum Thin Substrate Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3332
Alluvial Herb and Shrub Vegetation Mapping Unit - 4004 (original 4404)

1213 - Foothill Pine/California Wild Buckwheat Thin Substrate Woodland Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Pinus sabiniana/Eriogonum fasciculatum Thin Substrate Woodland Mapping Unit

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Pinus sabiniana/Eriogonum fasciculatum Thin Substrate Woodland Mapping Unit is mapped as open to sparse stands of trees over an understory of open to sparse low shrubs, grass, and rock. Pinus sabiniana is the dominant tree at moderate to low cover. Eriogonum fasciculatum is present at moderate to very low cover. Juniperus californica or Quercus douglasii may be present at very low cover. Chaparral shrubs may also be present at very low cover. This mapping unit favors steep, southerly, lower to upper slopes, with convex to neutral shapes and thin to rocky soils. Due to the thin substrate and rocky nature of the environment, Selaginella bigelovii may be present at low to high cover. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. In the expanded study area it is mapped as Pinus sabiniana Woodland Alliance (1210).

Photo Signature:
Pinus sabiniana appears on the NAIP imagery as rounded- to irregularly-crowned trees emergent over the shorter trees, low shrubs, and grass. It has a light blue-green to blue-gray color with a soft to wispy texture. Eriogonum fasciculatum is a low shrub with a gray, tan, or brown to rust color. It appears as small rounded individuals or in small clusters.

Types with Similar Signature:
Pinus sabiniana/Eriogonum fasciculatum Alluvial Woodland Mapping Unit - 1212
California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup - 3300 (original 3301)
Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3330
Eriogonum fasciculatum Alluvial Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3331
Eriogonum fasciculatum Thin Substrate Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3332
Open to Sparse Grass-Herb on Thin Substrate Herbaceous Vegetation Mapping Unit - 4003
Cliffs, Rock Outcrops, and Steep Eroded Slopes Mapping Unit - 9420

1220 - California Juniper Woodland Alliance
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Juniperus californica Woodland Alliance
Juniperus californica/Prunus ilicifolia/Moss Woodland Mapping Unit

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Juniperus californica Woodland Alliance is mapped as intermittent to sparse stands of trees over an understory of open to sparse chaparral shrubs or grass. Juniperus californica is the dominant tree at moderate to low cover. Pinus sabiniana may be present at low to very low cover. Prunus ilicifolia is present at moderate to very low cover. Other chaparral shrubs, including Cercocarpus montanus, Ceanothus cuneatus and Diplacus aurantiacus, may be present at very low cover. This alliance favors northerly, gentle to moderately steep lower to upper slopes. Due to the difficulty in photo interpretation of this type, field visits and releve sites are used to identify known locations of this alliance. It is mapped within the park, buffer, and expanded study area. The alliance also represents the hierarchical class into which Juniperus californica types are nested.

Photo Signature:
Juniperus californica appears on the imagery as a dull medium green to yellow-green color with a rounded crown. Its signature is very similar to Quercus douglasii, which has a blue cast to its color. Juniperus californica, however, will have a green cast to it. Prunus ilicifolia appears as a bright medium green color with individual rounded to irregular crowns. Prunus ilicifolia has a very bright red color on the supplementary CIR imagery, which aids in its identification.
Types with Similar Signature:
Quercus douglasii Woodland Alliance - 2210
Quercus douglasii/Mixed Herbaceous Woodland Association - 2212

1221 - California Juniper/Hollyleaf Cherry/Moss Woodland Association
(Included in the Original database)

Juniperus californica/Prunus ilicifolia/Moss Woodland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Juniperus californica/Prunus ilicifolia/Moss Woodland Association is mapped as intermittent to sparse stands of trees over an understory of open to sparse chaparral shrubs or grass. Juniperus californica is the dominant tree at moderate to low cover. Pinus sabiniana may be present at low to very low cover. Prunus ilicifolia is present at moderate to very low cover. Other chaparral shrubs, including Cercocarpus montanus, Ceanothus cuneatus and Diplacus aurantiacus may be present at very low cover. This association favors northerly, gentle to moderately steep lower to upper slopes. Due to the difficulty in photo interpretation of this type, field visits and releve sites are used to identify known locations of this alliance. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. In the expanded study area it is mapped as Juniperus californica Woodland Alliance (1220).

Photo Signature:
Juniperus californica appears on the imagery as a dull medium green color with a rounded crown. It appears very similar to the signature of Quercus douglasii, which has a bluish cast to its color. Juniperus californica, however, will have a green to yellow-green cast to it. Prunus ilicifolia appears as a bright medium green color with individual rounded to irregular crowns. Prunus ilicifolia has a very bright red color on the supplementary CIR imagery, which aids in its identification.

Types with Similar Signature:
Quercus douglasii/Chaparral/Grass Woodland Mapping Unit - 2211
Quercus douglasii/Mixed Herbaceous Woodland Association - 2212
Quercus douglasii-Juniperus californica Woodland Association - 2213
Quercus douglasii-Pinus sabiniana Woodland Mapping Unit - 2217
Prunus ilicifolia Shrubland Alliance - 3150

1300/1301- Southwestern North American Riparian Evergreen and Deciduous Forest Group
(Included in the Original (1301), Post AA (1300), and Park-Specific (1300) databases)

Salix laevigata Temporarily Flooded Woodland Alliance
Salix laevigata/Artemisia douglasiana-Rubus ursinus Woodland Association
Populus fremontii Temporarily Flooded Woodland Alliance
Populus fremontii-Salix laevigata Woodland Association
Populus fremontii/Baccharis salicifolia Woodland Associaton
Platanus racemosa Temporarily Flooded Woodland Alliance
Platanus racemosa-Quercus agrifolia Woodland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Southwestern North American Riparian Evergreen And Deciduous Forest Group is mapped as dense to sparse stands of riparian trees over intermittent to sparse shrubs and herbs. Trees are typically dominated by Salix laevigata, Populus fremontii, and/or Platanus racemosa at high to low cover. Quercus agrifolia, and Quercus lobata, may be present at moderate to very low cover. Pinus sabiniana may be present at low to very low cover. Riparian or mesic shrubs, including Salix lasiolepis, Baccharis salicifolia, Baccharis pilularis, Toxicodendron diversilobum, and Rosa californica may be present, each at high to very low cover. This type favors riparian corridors along perennial streams on major flat floodplains. The trees usually occupy the stream channel edge or are within the active floodplain. Platanus racemosa is common in the Bear Gulch and South Wilderness Chalone Creek areas. Populus fremontii is common in Bear Valley and in the South Wilderness Chalone Creek areas. Quercus lobata is common in the Bear Valley area. This class is mapped within the park, buffer, and expanded study area.

Photo Signature:
The trees are usually clustered together with no clear indication of individuals. Salix laevigata and Populus fremontii both appear as dull green with a large, irregularly shaped, dense crown. Due to the similarity of signature, they are very difficult to discern from each other. Platanus racemosa also has a similar signature as Salix laevigata and Populus fremontii. However, Platanus racemosa is usually taller than the other trees in the canopy. It also has a more open crown and occurs as individuals. Quercus agrifolia is more discernible on the imagery. It is dark green in color with a coarse texture, and a rounded billowy crown. Individuals can be seen among the other riparian trees. Quercus lobata is dull to dark green with a large rounded crown containing many small openings.

Types with Similar Signature:
Platanus racemosa Temporarily Flooded Woodland Alliance - 1310
Platanus racemosa-Quercus agrifolia Woodland Association - 1311
Quercus agrifolia Woodland Alliance - 2110
Southwestern North American Riparian/Wash Scrub Shrubland Group - 3400 (original 3401)

1310 - California Sycamore Temporarily Flooded Woodland Alliance
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Park-Specific databases)

Platanus racemosa Temporarily Flooded Woodland Alliance
Platanus racemosa Temporarily Flooded Woodland Association
Platanus racemosa-Quercus agrifolia Woodland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Platanus racemosa Temporarily Flooded Woodland Alliance is mapped as dense to open stands of trees. Platanus racemosa is the dominant tree at high to moderate cover. Quercus agrifolia is present at moderate to low cover. Other trees, including Quercus agrifolia, Salix laevigata, and Populus fremontii may be present at moderate to very low cover. This alliance favors riparian areas on fairly flat perennial stream floodplains. This type is found only on the east side of the park. This alliance is mapped within the park, buffer, and expanded study area. The alliance also represents the hierarchical class into which all Platanus racemosa types are nested.

Photo Signature:
Platanus racemosa appears on the imagery as a dull to bright green color with an irregularly shaped open crown, usually taller than the other trees in the canopy.

Types with Similar Signature:
Southwestern North American Riparian Evergreen and Deciduous Forest Group - 1300 (original 1301)
Quercus agrifolia Woodland Alliance - 2110

1311 - California Sycamore-Coast Live Oak Woodland Association
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Park-Specific databases)

Platanus racemosa-Quercus agrifolia Woodland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Platanus racemosa-Quercus agrifolia Woodland Association is mapped as dense to open stands of trees. Platanus racemosa and Quercus agrifolia co-dominate, each at high to moderate cover. Populus fremontii and Salix laevigata may be present at low to very low cover. Toxicodendron diversilobum may be present in the understory at moderate to very low cover, and is usually hidden from view under the tree canopy. This association favors riparian areas on fairly level and flat perennial stream floodplains. It is only found on the east side of the park. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. In the expanded study area it is mapped as Platanus racemosa Temporarily Flooded Woodland Alliance (1310).

Photo Signature:
Platanus racemosa appears on the imagery as a dull to bright green color with an irregularly shaped open crown, usually taller than the other trees in the canopy. Quercus agrifolia is dark green in color with a coarse texture, and a rounded billowy crown.

Types with Similar Signature:
Southwestern North American Riparian Evergreen And Deciduous Forest Group - 1300 (original 1301)
Quercus agrifolia Woodland Alliance - 2110

2101 - Live Oak Woodland and Shrubland Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original database)

Quercus sp. Woodland and Shrubland Mapping Unit
Quercus agrifolia Woodland Alliance
Quercus wislizenii Woodland Alliance
Quercus berberidifolia Shrubland Alliance

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Quercus sp. Woodland and Shrubland Mapping Unit is mapped where Quercus agrifolia, Quercus wislizenii and/or Quercus berberidifolia cannot be differentiated from photo interpretation. Quercus agrifolia is typically a large tree; Quercus wislizenii can be a tree or a tall shrub; and Quercus berberidifolia is a tall shrub. Quercus sp. is present at high to moderate cover. Quercus douglasii may also be present at moderate to very low cover. Field reconnaissance and releve sites are not available for these areas. This mapping unit is found on northerly, moderately steep to steep, lower to upper slopes. Quercus wislizenii favors thin soil or rockier sites, while Quercus berberidifolia prefers deeper soils. Quercus agrifolia also prefers deeper soils and is usually found on canyon bottoms and floodplains, but can be found on slopes. This class is mapped within the park, buffer, and expanded study area.

Photo Signature:
Quercus wislizenii and Quercus berberidifolia are medium to dark green in color with a coarse texture and a rounded, billowy crown. Quercus agrifolia has a similar signature but is usually darker in color and larger in stature.

Types with Similar Signature:
Quercus agrifolia Woodland Alliance - 2110
Quercus agrifolia/Annual Grass-Herb Woodland Association - 2112
Quercus wislizenii Woodland Alliance - 2120
Quercus berberidifolia Shrubland Alliance - 3160

2110 - Coast Live Oak Woodland Alliance
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Park-Specific databases)

Quercus agrifolia Woodland Alliance
Quercus agrifolia-Aesculus californica Woodland Association
Quercus agrifolia/Toxicodendron diversilobum Intermittently Flooded Woodland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Quercus agrifolia Woodland Alliance is mapped as dense to sparse stands of trees over open to sparse chaparral, short shrubs, grasses and herbs. Quercus agrifolia dominates at high to low cover. Pinus sabiniana, Quercus douglasii, Quercus wislizenii, and Aesculus californica may be present at moderate to very low cover. Quercus lobata may be present at low to very low cover. Toxicodendron diversilobum may be present at moderate to very low cover. In riparian areas riparian or mesic shrubs, including Salix lasiolepis, Baccharis salicifolia, Baccharis pilularis, and Rosa californica may be present, each at low to very low cover. This alliance favors dry to mesic ravines, canyon bottoms, and floodplains, and lower slopes adjacent to floodplains. It may also be found on northerly, moderately steep, concave to neutral, lower to upper slopes. It also favors sites at the base of pinnacles, cliffs and large rock outcrops. This alliance is mapped within the park, buffer, and expanded study area. The alliance also represents the hierarchical class into which all Quercus agrifolia types are nested. Note that although Quercus wislizenii stands were not mapped, small stands may occur within the study area mapped as this alliance. Q. wislizenii is known to occur in the Balconies area and on the north face of Mt. Defiance.

Photo Signature:
Quercus agrifolia is dark green in color with a coarsely textured, large, rounded, billowy crown. The grass-herb understory is brown to tan in color with a smooth texture. Pinus sabiniana appears on the imagery as rounded to irregularly crowned trees emergent over other shorter trees, chaparral, and grass. It has a light blue-green to blue-gray color with a soft to wispy texture. Quercus douglasii has a large, rounded crown that is dull blue to blue-green color. Aesculus californica appears as large, round-crowned individuals with a soft texture. The signature on the supplemental natural color imagery can appear as bright green, medium green, yellow-green, or yellow-tan to light tan, depending on its stage of senescence. Quercus wislizenii is medium to dark green in color with a coarsely textured, large, rounded, billowy crown. The signature is similar to that of Quercus agrifolia, which has a darker green color and taller, larger stature. Quercus agrifolia prefers deeper soils than Quercus wislizenii.

Types with Similar Signature:
Pinus sabiniana Woodland Alliance - 1210
Southwestern North American Riparian Evergreen and Deciduous Forest Group - 1300 (original 1301)
Platanus racemosa Temporarily Flooded Woodland Alliance - 1310
Platanus racemosa-Quercus agrifolia Woodland Association - 1311
Quercus douglasii Woodland Alliance - 2210
Quercus lobata Woodland Alliance - 2230
Quercus berberidifolia Shrubland Alliance - 3160

2112 - Coast Live Oak/Annual Grass-Herb Woodland Association
(Included in the Original and Post AA Park-Specific database)

Quercus agrifolia/Annual Grass-Herb Woodland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Quercus agrifolia/Annual Grass-Herb Woodland Association is mapped as open to sparse stands of trees over grasses and herbs. Quercus agrifolia is the dominant tree at moderate to low cover. Quercus lobata may be present at low to very low cover. Quercus douglasii and Pinus sabiniana may be present at very low cover. Toxicodendron diversilobum may be present and hidden from view under the canopy. This type occurs on flat floodplain terraces or on north-facing, moderate to steep, neutral to concave, lower to upper slopes. This class is mapped within the park and buffer. Within the expanded study area it is mapped as Quercus agrifolia Woodland Alliance (2110).

Photo Signature:
Quercus agrifolia is dark green in color with a coarsely textured, large, rounded, billowy crown. The grass-herb understory is brown to tan in color with a smooth texture.

Types with Similar Signature:
Platanus racemosa-Quercus agrifolia Woodland Alliance - 1311
Quercus sp. Woodland and Shrubland Mapping Unit - 2101
Quercus agrifolia Alluvial Woodland Mapping Unit - 2114
Quercus agrifolia-Quercus douglasii Woodland Mapping Unit - 2117
Quercus lobata-Quercus agrifolia/Grass Woodland Association - 2231

2114 - Coast Live Oak Alluvial Woodland Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Quercus agrifolia Alluvial Woodland Mapping Unit

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Quercus agrifolia Alluvial Woodland Mapping Unit is mapped as dense to open stands of trees along riparian corridors. Quercus agrifolia is the dominant tree at high to low cover. Pinus sabiniana may be present at low to very low cover. Toxicodendron diversilobum may be present at high to very low cover. Other riparian or mesic shrubs, including Salix lasiolepis, Baccharis salicifolia, Baccharis pilularis, and Rosa californica may be present, each at low to very low cover. This mapping unit favors riparian corridors and edges of active floodplains. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. Within the expanded study area it is mapped as Quercus agrifolia Woodland Alliance (2110).

Photo Signature:
Quercus agrifolia is dark green in color with a coarsely textured, large, rounded, billowy crown. Pinus sabiniana appears on the imagery as rounded- to irregularly-crowned trees emergent over other shorter trees, chaparral, and grass. It has a light blue-green to blue-gray color with a soft to wispy texture.

Types with Similar Signature:
Southwestern North American Riparian Evergreen and Deciduous Forest Group - 1300 (original 1301)
Platanus racemosa-Quercus agrifolia Woodland Association - 1311
Quercus sp. Woodland and Shrubland Mapping Unit - 2101
Quercus agrifolia Woodland Alliance - 2110
Quercus agrifolia/Annual Grass-Herb Woodland Association - 2112
Quercus agrifolia-Quercus douglasii Woodland Mapping Unit - 2117

2117 - Coast Live Oak-Blue Oak Woodland Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original database)

Quercus agrifolia-Quercus douglasii Woodland Mapping Unit

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Quercus agrifolia-Quercus douglasii Woodland Mapping Unit is mapped as intermittent to open stands of trees with an understory of shrubs and/or grass. Quercus agrifolia is dominant at high to low cover. Quercus douglasii is present or co-dominates at high to low cover. Pinus sabiniana may be present at moderate to low cover. Chaparral shrubs may be present at moderate to very low cover. Grasses and herbs may also be present. It is also found on drier sites of lower to upper slopes along floodplain edges, and in side canyons and ravines of major floodplains. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. Within the expanded study area it is mapped as Quercus agrifolia Woodland Alliance (2110).

Photo Signature:
Quercus agrifolia is dark green in color with a coarsely textured, large, rounded, billowy crown. Quercus douglasii has a large, rounded crown that is dull green to blue-green in color. Pinus sabiniana appears on the imagery as rounded to irregularly crowned trees, emergent over other shorter trees, chaparral, and grass. It has a light blue-green to blue-gray color with a soft to wispy texture.

Types with Similar Signature:
Pinus sabiniana/Chaparral Woodland Mapping Unit - 1211
Quercus sp. Woodland and Shrubland Mapping Unit - 2101
Quercus agrifolia Woodland Alliance - 2110
Quercus agrifolia/Annual Grass-Herb Woodland Association - 2112
Quercus agrifolia Alluvial Woodland Mapping Unit - 2114
Quercus douglasii/Chaparral/Grass Mapping Unit - 2211
Quercus douglasii-Pinus sabiniana Woodland Mapping Unit - 2217

2120 - Interior Live Oak Woodland Alliance
(Included in the Original and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Quercus wislizenii Woodland Alliance

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Quercus wislizenii Woodland Alliance is mapped as an intermittent to sparse stand of trees over open to sparse chaparral and/or grasses and herbs. Quercus wislizenii is the dominant tree at high to low cover. In the field it has only been observed as a tall shrub. Pinus sabiniana may be present at very low cover. Chaparral shrubs, including Adenostoma fasciculatum, Ceanothus cuneatus, Prunus ilicifolia or Heteromeles arbutifolia, may be present at moderate to very low cover. This type favors northerly, moderately steep, neutral- to convex-shaped, mid to upper slopes on thin to rocky soils. It also prefers higher elevations in the park. This alliance is mapped within the park, buffer, and expanded study area.
Photo Signature:
Quercus wislizenii is medium to dark green in color with a coarsely textured, large, rounded, billowy crown. The signature is similar to that of Quercus agrifolia, which has a darker green color and taller, larger stature. Quercus agrifolia and Quercus berberidifolia both prefer deeper soils than Quercus wislizenii.

Types with Similar Signature:
Quercus sp. Woodland Mapping Unit - 2101
Quercus agrifolia Woodland Alliance - 2110
Quercus berberidifolia Shrubland Alliance - 3160

2210 - Blue Oak Woodland Alliance
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Quercus douglasii Woodland Alliance

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Quercus douglasii Woodland Alliance is mapped as a dense to sparse stand of trees over chaparral, coastal sage scrub, and/or grasses and herbs. Quercus douglasii is the dominant tree at high to low cover. Pinus sabiniana, Aesculus californica, and Juniperus californica may be present, or may co-dominate, at moderate to very low cover. Quercus agrifolia can be present at low to very low cover. Chaparral shrubs may include Cercocarpus montanus, Ceanothus cuneatus, Adenostoma fasciculatum, Prunus ilicifolia, and/or Rhamnus ilicifolia. The amount and proportions of shrubs and grasses may vary throughout the stand.In some situations Artemisia californica and/or Eriogonum fasciculatum may dominate the understory at high to low cover, with Salvia mellifera sometimes present at moderate to very low cover. This alliance favors northerly, gentle to moderately steep, lower to upper slopes. This alliance is mapped within the park, buffer, and expanded study area. The alliance also represents the hierarchical class into which all Quercus douglasii types are nested.

Photo Signature:
Quercus douglasii has a large, rounded crown that is dull green to blue-green in color. Pinus sabiniana appears on the imagery as tall, rounded to irregularly crowned trees, emergent over other shorter trees, chaparral, and grass. It has a light blue-green to blue-gray color with a soft to wispy texture. Quercus agrifolia is dark green in color with a coarsely textured, large, rounded, billowy crown. Aesculus californica appears as large, round-crowned individuals, with a soft texture. The signature on the natural color imagery can appear bright green, medium green, yellow-green, or yellow-tan to light tan, depending on its stage of senescence. Juniperus californica appears as dull medium green color with a rounded crown. Its signature is very similar to Quercus douglasii, which has a blue cast to its color. However, Juniperus californica will have a green to yellow-green cast to it. The chaparral is shorter with a rounded to irregular crown. Some shrubs appear as individuals, others as clusters with no distinctive crown. Artemisia californica is gray in color, occurring as patches or individuals, with a smooth texture. Eriogonum fasciculatum is gray, tan, or reddish brown in color, occurs as small rounded individuals. Salvia mellifera can be green, gray, or tan in color, occurring in patches or as individuals, with a smooth texture. Grasses and herbs have a brown to tan color with a smooth texture.

Types with Similar Signature:
Pinus sabiniana Woodland Alliance - 1210
Juniperus californica Woodland Alliance - 1220
Quercus agrifolia Woodland Alliance - 2110
Quercus douglasii/Mixed Herbaceous Woodland Association - 2212
Aesculus californica Woodand Alliance - 2220

2211 - Blue Oak/Chaparral/Grass Woodland Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Quercus douglasii/Chaparral/Grass Woodland Mapping Unit

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Quercus douglasii/Chaparral/Grass Woodland Mapping Unit is mapped as intermittent to sparse stands of trees over intermittent to sparse chaparral. Quercus douglasii is the dominant tree at high to moderate cover. Pinus sabiniana may be present at very low cover. Chaparral shrubs, including Cercocarpus montanus, Ceanothus cuneatus, Adenostoma fasciculatum, Prunus ilicifolia, and/or Rhamnus ilicifolia are present throughout the stand, each at high to low cover. Grasses are present at high to moderate cover. This mapping unit favors northerly, gentle to moderately steep, lower to upper slopes. The amount and proportions of shrubs and grasses may vary throughout the stand. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. Within the expanded study area it is mapped as Quercus douglasii Woodland Alliance (2210).

Photo Signature:
Quercus douglasii has a large, rounded crown that is dull green to blue-green in color. Pinus sabiniana appears on the imagery as rounded to irregularly crowned trees emergent over other shorter trees, chaparral, and grass. It has a light blue-green to blue-gray color with a soft to wispy texture. The chaparral is shorter with a rounded to irregular crown. Some shrubs appear as individuals, others as clusters with no distinctive crown. Grasses occupy the understory of the tree/shrub canopy.

Types with Similar Signature:
Pinus sabiniana/Chaparral Woodland Mapping Unit - 1211
Quercus douglasii/Mixed Herbaceous Woodland Association - 2212
Quercus douglasii-Juniperus californica Woodland Association - 2213
Quercus douglasii-Pinus sabiniana Woodland Mapping Unit - 2217

2212 - Blue Oak/Mixed Herbaceous Woodland Association
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Quercus douglasii/Mixed Herbaceous Woodland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Quercus douglasii/Mixed Herbaceous Woodland Association is mapped as an open to sparse stand of trees over grasses and herbs. Quercus douglasii is the dominant tree at high to low cover. Pinus sabiniana and/or Juniperus californica may be present at very low cover. Shrubs may also be present at low to very low cover, but are mainly inclusional or in isolated patches. This mapping unit favors northerly, gentle to moderately steep, lower to upper slopes. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. Within the expanded study area it is mapped as Quercus douglasii Woodland Alliance (2210).

Photo Signature:
Quercus douglasii has a large, rounded crown that is dull green to blue-green in color. Pinus sabiniana appears on the imagery as tall, rounded to irregularly crowned trees emergent over other shorter trees, chaparral, and grass. It has a light blue-green to blue-gray color with a soft to wispy texture. Grasses and herbs surround the trees, and have a brown to tan color with a smooth texture.

Types with Similar Signature:
Pinus sabiniana Woodland Alliance - 1210
Quercus douglasii Woodland Alliance - 2210

2213 - Blue Oak/California Juniper Woodland Association
(Included in the Original and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Quercus douglasii/Juniperus californica Woodland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Quercus douglasii/Juniperus californica Woodland Association is mapped as an intermittent to open stand of trees over shrubs and/or grasses and herbs. Quercus douglasii is dominant at high to low cover. Juniperus californica is present, but can co-dominate, at moderate to low cover. Pinus sabiniana may be present at low to very low cover. Chaparral shrubs may be present at moderate to very low cover. The amount and proportions of shrubs and grasses may vary throughout the stand. This association favors northerly, moderate to steep, mid to upper slopes. Because Juniperus californica is difficult to distinguish from Quercus douglasii, releve and reconnaissance sites assisted in the identification of possible locations. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. Within the expanded study area it is mapped as Quercus douglasii Woodland Alliance (2210).

Photo Signature:
Quercus douglasii has a large, rounded crown that is dull green to blue-green in color. Juniperus californica appears as dull medium green color with a rounded crown. Its signature is very similar to Quercus douglasii, which has a blue cast to its color. However, Juniperus californica will have a green or yellow-green cast to it. Pinus sabiniana appears on the imagery as tall, rounded to irregularly crowned trees emergent over other shorter trees, chaparral, and grass. It has a light blue-green to blue-gray color with a soft to wispy texture. The chaparral is shorter with a rounded to irregular crown. Some shrubs appear as individuals, others as clusters with no distinctive crown. Grasses and herbs surround the trees, and have a brown to tan color with a smooth texture.

Types with Similar Signature:
Quercus douglasii/Chaparral/Grass Woodland Mapping Unit - 2211
Quercus douglasii/Mixed Herbaceous Woodland Association - 2212
Quercus douglasii-Aesculus californica Woodland Mapping Unit - 2216
Quercus douglasii-Pinus sabiniana Woodland Mapping Unit - 2217

2216 - Blue Oak-California Buckeye Woodland Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Quercus douglasii-Aesculus californica Woodland Mapping Unit

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Quercus douglasii-Aesculus californica Woodland Mapping Unit is mapped as a dense to intermittent stand of trees over intermittent to sparse shrubs and/or grass and herbs. Quercus douglasii typically dominates at high to moderate cover. Aesculus californica is present, but can co-dominate at high to very low cover. Pinus sabiniana and Quercus agrifolia may be present at very low cover. Chaparral shrubs may be present at low to very low cover. This mapping unit favors northerly, gentle to moderately steep, lower to mid slopes. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. Within the expanded study area it is mapped as Quercus douglasii Woodland Alliance (2210).

Photo Signature:
Quercus douglasii has a large, rounded crown that is dull green to blue-green in color. Aesculus californica appears as large, round-crowned individuals, with a soft texture. The signature on the supplemental natural color imagery appears bright green, medium green, yellow-green, or yellow-tan to light tan, depending on its stage of senescence. Pinus sabiniana appears on the imagery as tall, rounded to irregularly crowned trees emergent over other shorter trees, chaparral, and grass. It has a light blue-green to blue-gray color with a soft to wispy texture. Quercus agrifolia is dark green in color with a coarsely textured, large, rounded, billowy crown. The chaparral is shorter with a rounded to irregular crown. Some shrubs appear as individuals, others as clusters with no distinctive crown.

Types with Similar Signature:
Quercus douglasii/Chaparral/Grass Woodland Mapping Unit - 2211
Quercus douglasii-Pinus sabiniana Woodland Mapping Unit - 2217
Aesculus californica Woodland Alliance - 2220

2217 - Blue Oak-Foothill Pine Woodland Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Quercus douglasii-Pinus sabiniana Woodland Mapping Unit

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
Quercus douglasii-Pinus sabiniana Woodland Mapping Unit is mapped as a dense to open stand of Quercus douglasii and Pinus sabiniana over intermittent to sparse shrubs and/or grass and herbs. Quercus douglasii dominates at high to low cover. Pinus sabiniana is present and frequently co-dominates at high to low cover. Chaparral shrubs may be present at moderate to low cover. Grasses are typically present. The amount and proportions of shrubs and grasses may vary throughout the stand. This mapping unit favors northerly, gentle to moderately steep, lower to middle slopes. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. Within the expanded study area it is mapped as Quercus douglasii Woodland Alliance (2210).

Photo Signature:
Quercus douglasii has a large, rounded crown that is dull green to blue-green in color. Pinus sabiniana appears on the imagery as tall, rounded to irregularly crowned trees emergent over other shorter trees, chaparral, and grass. It has a light blue-green to blue-gray color with a soft to wispy texture. The chaparral is shorter with a rounded to irregular crown. Some shrubs appear as individuals, others as clusters with no distinctive crown. Grasses and herbs surround the trees, and have a brown to tan color with a smooth texture.

Types with Similar Signature:
Pinus sabiniana/Chaparral Woodland Mapping Unit - 1211
Quercus agrifolia-Quercus douglasii Woodland Mapping Unit - 2117
Quercus douglasii/Chaparral/Grass Woodland Mapping Unit - 2211
Quercus douglasii/Mixed Herbaceous Woodland Association - 2212
Quercus douglasii-Juniperus californica Woodland Association - 2213
Quercus douglasii-Aesculus californica Woodland Mapping Unit - 2216

2218 - Blue Oak/Coastal Sage Scrub Woodland Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Quercus douglasii/Coastal Sage Scrub Woodland Mapping Unit

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
Quercus douglasii/Coastal Sage Scrub Woodland Mapping Unit is mapped as open to sparse stands of trees over intermittent to sparse shrubs, grasses and herbs. Quercus douglasii is the dominant tree at high to moderate cover. Artemisia californica and/or Eriogonum fasciculatum are typically in the understory at high to low cover. Salvia mellifera is sometimes present at moderate to very low cover. This mapping unit favors northerly, gentle to moderately steep, lower to upper slopes. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. Within the expanded study area it is mapped as Quercus douglasii Woodland Alliance (2210).

Photo Signature:
Quercus douglasii has a large, rounded crown that is dull green to blue-green in color. Artemisia californica is gray in color, occurring as patches or individuals, with a smooth texture. Eriogonum fasciculatum is gray, tan, or reddish brown in color, occurs as small rounded individuals. Salvia mellifera can be green, gray, or tan in color, occurring in patches or as individuals, with a smooth texture. Grasses and herbs have a brown to tan color with a smooth texture.

Types with Similar Signature:
Quercus douglasii/Chaparral/Grass Woodland Mapping Unit - 2211
Quercus douglasii/Mixed Herbaceous Woodland Association - 2212

2220 - California Buckeye Woodland Alliance
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Aesculus californica Woodland Alliance
Aesculus californica/Toxicodendron diversilobum/Moss Woodland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Aesculus californica Woodland Alliance is mapped as a dense to intermittent stand of trees over open to sparse shrubs. Aesculus californica is the dominant tree at high to moderate cover. Quercus douglasii and Quercus agrifolia may be present at low to very low cover. Pinus sabiniana may be present at low to very low cover. This alliance favors northerly, protected, gentle to moderately steep, lower to mid slopes. This type is mapped within the park, buffer, and expanded study area.

Photo Signature:
Aesculus californica appears as large, round-crowned individuals with a soft texture. The signature on the supplemental natural color imagery appears bright green, medium green, yellow-green, or yellow-tan to light tan, depending on its stage of senescence. Quercus douglasii has a large, rounded crown that is dull green to blue-green in color. Quercus agrifolia is dark green in color with a coarsely textured, large, rounded billowy crown. Pinus sabiniana appears on the imagery as tall, rounded to irregularly crowned trees emergent over other shorter trees, chaparral, and grass. It has a light blue-green to blue-gray color with a soft to wispy texture. The chaparral is shorter with a rounded to irregular crown. Some shrubs appear as individuals, others as clusters with no distinctive crown.

Types with Similar Signature:
Quercus agrifolia Woodland Alliance - 2110
Quercus douglasii Woodland Alliance - 2210
Quercus douglasii-Aesculus californica Woodland Mapping Unit - 2216

2230 - Valley Oak Woodland Alliance
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Quercus lobata Woodland Alliance

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Quercus lobata Woodland Alliance is mapped as dense to sparse stands of trees over grasses and herbs. Quercus lobata dominates at moderate to low cover. Quercus agrifolia may be present or co-dominate at moderate to very low cover. Dense to open grasses and herbs form the understory. This association favors flat, level floodplain terraces and valley bottoms. This class is mapped in the expanded study area only. The Quercus lobata Woodland Alliance is mapped within the park, buffer, and expanded study area. The alliance also represents the hierarchical class into which all Quercus lobata types are nested.

Photo Signature:
Quercus lobata is dull green to dark green with a large, rounded crown containing many small openings. The signature may be similar to very large Quercus douglasii, which may have a blue cast to it. Quercus agrifolia is dark green in color with a coarsely textured, large, rounded, billowy crown. Dry or moist grasses and herbs surround the trees. Dry grasses and herbs have a brown, tan, or green color with a smooth texture. Moist grasses and herbs have a green color, with a smooth texture, indicating moist situations.

Types with Similar Signature:
Quercus agrifolia Woodland Alliance - 2110
Quercus douglasii Woodland Alliance - 2210
Quercus douglasii/Mixed Herbaceous Woodland Association - 2212
Quercus lobata-Quercus agrifolia/Grass Woodland Association - 2231

2231 - Valley Oak-Coast Live Oak/Grass Woodland Association
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Quercus lobata-Quercus agrifolia/Grass Woodland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Quercus lobata-Quercus agrifolia/Grass Woodland Association is mapped as dense to sparse stands of trees over grasses and herbs. Quercus lobata and Quercus agrifolia may co-dominate at moderate to very low cover. Dense to open grasses and herbs form the understory. This association favors flat floodplain terraces and valley bottoms. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. Within the extended study area it is mapped as Quercus lobata Woodland Alliance (2230).

Photo Signature:
Quercus lobata is dull green to dark green with a large rounded crown containing many small openings. The signature may be similar to very large Quercus douglasii, which may have a blue cast to it. Quercus agrifolia is dark green in color with a coarsely textured, large, rounded, billowy crown. Grasses and herbs surrounding the trees have a brown to tan color with a smooth texture.

Types with Similar Signature:
Quercus agrifolia/Annual Grass-Herb Woodland Association - 2112
Quercus douglasii/Mixed Herbaceous Woodland Mapping Unit - 2212
Quercus lobata-Quercus agrifolia/Mesic Grass Woodland Mapping Unit - 2232

2232 - Valley Oak-Coast Live Oak/Mesic Grass Woodland Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Quercus lobata-Quercus agrifolia/Mesic Grass Woodland Mapping Unit

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Quercus lobata-Quercus agrifolia/Mesic Grass-Herb Woodland Mapping Unit is mapped as dense to sparse stands of trees over wet grass and herbs. Quercus lobata and Quercus agrifolia may co-dominate at moderate to very low cover. Dense to open wet grasses and herbs form the understory. This association favors wet sites on flat floodplain terraces and valley bottoms where seeps occur. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. Within the extended study area it is mapped as Quercus lobata Woodland Alliance (2230).

Photo Signature:
Quercus lobata is dull green to dark green with a large rounded crown containing many small openings. The signature may be similar to very large Quercus douglasii, which may have a blue cast to it. Quercus agrifolia is dark green in color with a coarsely textured, large, rounded, billowy crown. Grasses and herbs surrounding the trees have a green color, indicating moist grasses with a smooth texture.

Types with Similar Signature:
Quercus agrifolia/Annual Grass-Herb Woodland Association - 2112
Quercus douglasii/Mixed Herbaceous Woodland Association - 2212
Quercus lobata-Quercus agrifolia/Grass Woodland Association - 2231

3100 - Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Adenostoma fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance
Adenostoma fasciculatum Shrubland Association
Adenostoma fasciculatum-Arctostaphylos glauca Shrubland Association
Adenostoma fasciculatum-Arctostaphylos pungens Shrubland Association
Adenostoma fasciculatum-Ceanothus cuneatus Shrubland Association
Adenostoma fasciculatum-Salvia mellifera Shrubland Association
Adenostoma fasciculatum/Selaginella bigelovii Shrubland Association
Arctostaphylos glauca Shrubland Alliance
Arctostaphylos glauca Shrubland Association
Ceanothus cuneatus Shrubland Alliance
Ceanothus cuneatus var. cuneatus Shrubland Association
Cercocarpus montanus var. glaber Shrubland Alliance
Cercocarpus montanus var. glaber Shrubland Association
Prunus ilicifolia Shrubland Alliance
Prunus ilicifolia Shrubland Association
Prunus ilicifolia-Ceanothus cuneatus Shrubland Association
Prunus ilicifolia-Fraxinus dipetala Shrubland Association
Prunus ilicifolia-Heteromeles arbutifolia Shrubland Association
Rhamnus ilicifolia-Clematis lasiantha Shrubland Association
Quercus berberidifolia Shrubland Alliance
Quercus berberidifolia Shrubland Association
Quercus berberidifolia-Cercocarpus montanus var. glaber Shrubland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup is mapped as dense to sparse stands of dominant undifferentiated chaparral shrubs. In the expanded study area no attempt is made to differentiate between xeric and mesic chaparral types other than Prunus ilicifolia Shrubland Alliance (3150) and Quercus berberidifolia Shrubland Alliance (code 3160). Xeric chaparral shrubs present may include Adenostoma fasciculatum, Ceanothus cuneatus, Arctostaphylos glauca, and Arctostaphylos pungens. Mesic chaparral shrubs may include Prunus ilicifolia, Rhamnus ilicifolia, Clematus lasiantha, Quercus berberidifolia, and Cercocarpus montanus var. glaber. Coastal sage scrub shrubs, including Salvia mellifera or Eriogonum fasciculatum may also be present at moderate to very low cover. Selaginella bigelovii may be present at moderate to very low cover. In the extended study area this mapping unit includes xeric as well as mesic sites on all aspects, slope positions, slope steepness, and slope shapes. Within the park and buffer Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Group (3101/3110), Prunus ilicifolia Shrubland Alliance, and Quercus berberidifolia Shrubland Alliance were mapped separately from Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup (3100). Most areas of this type are mapped mainly on northerly, gentle to moderately steep, lower to mid slopes, with concave to neutral shapes, or on canyon bottoms and some sparsely vegetated floodplains. In many areas within the park and buffer Ceanothus cuneatus dominates or co-dominates with Adenostoma fasciculatum. Mesic shrubs areas include Prunus ilicifolia, Cercocarpus montanus var. glaber, Ceanothus cuneatus, Rhamnus ilicifolia, Quercus berberidifolia, Heteromeles arbutifolia, Clematis lasiantha, Dendromecon rigida, and Fraxinus dipetala. Quercus douglasii and Pinus sabiniana may be emergent at very low cover. In some instances Quercus agrifolia, Quercus wislizenii, or Juniperus californica may also be present at very low cover.

Photo Signature:
The signatures of the xeric chaparral shrub species are very difficult to distinguish from each other on the imagery. Species interpretation using environmental characteristics is sometimes employed; however, in this case, the shrubs are not consistent with the environmental characteristics and cannot be discerned by this method. The xeric shrubs range from dark green to tan or dark gray on the imagery. They have a coarse to smooth texture, and occur as dense groups or open patches. Individual crowns are usually not distinguishable. The shrubs will usually appear as a burgundy color on the supplemental CIR imagery, but sometimes will also appear as individual bright red dots within the burgundy. The signatures of the individual mesic shrubs are also very difficult to distinguish from each other on the imagery. Prunus ilicifolia will appear as bright green with a coarse texture. On the supplemental CIR imagery it will appear as a bright red color. The other mesic shrubs range from medium green to dull green to dark green. On the supplemental CIR imagery they will show as bright red to burgundy, or a mix of red shades, but not a consistent dark burgundy. The texture will tend to be coarse.

Types with Similar Signature:
Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Group - 3101
Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3103/9710
Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3104/9720
Adenostoma fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3110
California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup - 3300

3101/3110 - Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Group
(Included in the Original (3101), Post AA (3101) and Post AA Park-Specific (3110) databases)

Adenostoma fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance
Adenostoma fasciculatum Shrubland Association
Adenostoma fasciculatum-Arctostaphylos glauca Shrubland Association
Adenostoma fasciculatum-Arctostaphylos pungens Shrubland Association
Adenostoma fasciculatum-Ceanothus cuneatus Shrubland Association
Adenostoma fasciculatum-Salvia mellifera Shrubland Association
Adenostoma fasciculatum/Selaginella bigelovii Shrubland Association
Arctostaphylos glauca Shrubland Alliance
Arctostaphylos glauca Shrubland Association
Ceanothus cuneatus Shrubland Alliance
Ceanothus cuneatus var. cuneatus Shrubland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Group is mapped as a dense to sparse stand of xeric chaparral shrubs. Adenostoma fasciculatum is typically strongly dominant or dominant at low to high cover. Ceanothus cuneatus may dominate in some lower slope or gently sloping areas, and in some areas may co-dominate with Adenostoma fasciculatum. Generally Ceanothus cuneatus has a high to very low cover. Arctostaphylos glauca and A. pungens occur in some areas as scattered plants, but can occur in some patches as the dominant shrub, or co-dominant with Adenostoma fasciculatum. Arctostaphylos spp. may have high to very low cover. Salvia mellifera, Eriogonum fasciculatum, Lotus scoparius, and Selaginella bigelovii may be present at very low to moderate cover, typically on southerly slopes. Eriogonum fasciculatum and Selaginella bigelovii will occur on rockier sites. This mapping unit favors dry sites on all aspects, slope positions, slope steepness, and slope shapes. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. Within the expanded study area it is included in the Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup (3100).

Photo Signature:
The signatures of the individual xeric chaparral shrubs are very difficult to distinguish from each other on the imagery. Species interpretation using environmental characteristics is sometimes employed; however, in this case, the shrubs are not consistent with the environmental characteristics and cannot be discerned by this method. The xeric shrubs range from dark green to tan or dark gray on the imagery. They have a coarse to smooth texture and occur as dense groups or open patches. Individual crowns are usually not distinguishable unless the shrub canopy is open. They will usually appear as a burgundy color on the supplemental CIR imagery, but sometimes are mottled, with individual red dots within the burgundy, which may be Prunus ilicifolia, Heteromeles arbutifolia, Ceanothus cuneatus, or Arctostaphylos pungens.

Types with Similar Signature:
Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup - 3100
Dry-Mesic Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3102
Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3103/9710
Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3104/9720
Salvia mellifera Shrubland Alliance - 3360

3102 - Dry-Mesic Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Adenostoma fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance
Adenostoma fasciculatum-Ceanothus cuneatus Shrubland Association
Cercocarpus montanus var. glaber Shrubland Alliance
Cercocarpus montanus var. glaber Shrubland Association
Prunus ilicifolia Shrubland Alliance
Prunus ilicifolia Shrubland Association
Prunus ilicifolia-Ceanothus cuneatus Shrubland Association
Prunus ilicifolia-Fraxinus dipetala Shrubland Association
Prunus ilicifolia-Heteromeles arbutifolia Shrubland Association
Rhamnus ilicifolia-Clematis lasiantha Shrubland Association
Quercus berberidifolia Shrubland Alliance
Quercus berberidifolia Shrubland Association
Quercus berberidifolia-Cercocarpus montanus var. glaber Shrubland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Dry-Mesic Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit is mapped as a dense to sparse stand of mesic chaparral shrubs. In many stands, Ceanothus cuneatus tends to dominate or co-dominate with other mesic shrubs or with Adenostoma fasciculatum. Mesic shrubs including Prunus ilicifolia, Cercocarpus montanus var. glaber, Ceanothus cuneatus, Rhamnus ilicifolia, Quercus berberidifolia, Heteromeles arbutifolia, Clematis lasiantha, Dendromecon rigida, and Fraxinus dipetala may be present, each at high to very low cover. Adenostoma fasciculatum may be present at moderate to very low cover. Quercus douglasii and Pinus sabiniana may be emergent at very low cover. In some instances Quercus agrifolia, Quercus wislizenii, or Juniperus californica may also be present at very low cover. This mapping unit favors northerly, protected, concave to neutral shapes, lower to middle slopes, canyon bottoms, and some sparsely vegetated floodplains. It can be found on gentle to moderately steep slopes. It also occurs below rock outcrops and pinnacles. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. Within the expanded study area it is mapped as the Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit (3100).

Photo Signature:
The signatures of the individual mesic shrubs are very difficult to distinguish from each other on the imagery. Prunus ilicifolia will appear as bright medium green with a coarse texture. On the supplemental CIR imagery it will appear as a bright red color. The other mesic shrubs range from medium green to dull green to dark green. The supplemental CIR imagery will show the shrubs as bright red to burgundy, or a mix of red shades, but not a consistent dark burgundy. The texture will tend to be coarse.

Types with Similar Signature:
Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Group - 3101
Adenostoma fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3110
Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3103/9710
Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3104/9720
Prunus ilicifolia Woodland Alliance - 3150

3103/9710 - Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original (3103), Post AA (3103), and Post AA Park-Specific (9710) databases)

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit is mapped as an intermittent to sparse stand of chaparral shrubs occurring in a mesic to semi-mesic environment, usually on northerly, concave to neutral, lower to mid slooes. The shrubs are regenerating or recovering from a burn or disturbance that had occurred within the last ten years. Most shrubs are short and sparse, and are therefore difficult to identify by photo interpretation within the imagery limitations. Field visits were used in some cases to help in the identification of the shrubs present. Ceanothus cuneatus typically is dominant at high to low cover. Adenostoma fasciculatum may also be present at very low cover. Mesic shrubs, including Prunus ilicifolia, Heteromeles arbutifolia, and Clematis lasiantha may be present, each at a very low cover. In many cases, the mesic shrubs grew back slower than the Ceanothus cuneatus or Adenostoma fasciculatum. Mesic shrubs would grow beneath the taller xeric shrubs. Fire and disturbance followers, including Eriodictyon tomentosum, Lotus scoparius, and Dendromecon rigida may be present at moderate to very low cover. These species may be more prevalent in stands with open to sparse cover. Quercus agrifolia may also be present. Emergent Quercus douglasii snags may be in the stand, but are not visible on the imagery. This mapping unit favors northerly, protected, concave to neutral shapes, lower to middle slopes and canyon bottoms. It can be found on gentle to moderately steep slopes. It also occurs below rock outcrops and pinnacles. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. Within the expanded study area it is mapped as the Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup (3100).

Photo Signature:
The burned area appears as shorter shrubs than the adjacent older stands. There is usually a burn line where the fire stopped, dividing the low stature regenerating stands from the taller older unburned stands. The texture of the shrubs in the burned areas is smooth. The signatures of the individual shrubs are very difficult to distinguish from each other on the imagery. Ceanothus cuneatus and Adenostoma fasciculatum will appear as dark green on the imagery. It will appear as a light pink on the supplemental CIR imagery. Prunus ilicifolia and Heteromeles arbutifolia will usually not be distinguishable on the imagery because they may be hidden under the taller xeric shrubs.

Types with Similar Signature:
Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup - 3100
Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Group - 3101
Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3104/9720
Adenostoma fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3110
Prunus ilicifolia Shrubland Alliance - 3150
Post Burn and Post Disturbance Undifferentiated Shrub and Grass-Herb Regeneration Mapping Unit - 9700

3104/9720 - Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original (3104), Post AA (3104), and Post AA Park-Specific (9720) databases)

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Xeric Shrubland Mapping Unit is mapped as a dense to sparse stand of short xeric chaparral shrubs that are regenerating or recovering from a burn or disturbance that had occurred within the last ten years. Most shrubs are short and sparse, and therefore are difficult to identify by photo interpretation within the imagery limitations. Field visits were used in some cases to help in the identification of the shrubs present. Adenostoma fasciculatum is typically strongly dominant or dominant at high to low cover. Ceanothus cuneatus may dominate in some lower slope or gently sloping areas, and in some areas may co-dominate with Adenostoma fasciculatum. Generally Ceanothus cuneatus has a high to very low cover. Salvia mellifera, Eriogonum fasciculatum, and Selaginella bigelovii may be present at moderate to very low cover. Fire and disturbance followers, include Salvia mellifera, Eriogonum fasciculatum, Eriodictyon tomentosum, Lotus scoparius, and Dendromecon rigida, at moderate to very low cover. Malacothamnus arboriginum is a rare plant within the park and was observed in the 1998 burn area near the mouth of Grassy Canyon. These species may be more prevalent in stands with sparse cover. This mapping unit favors dry sites on all aspects, slope positions, slope steepness, and slope shapes. This type is mapped within the expanded area, park and buffer.

Photo Signature:
The burned area appears as shorter shrubs in comparison to the adjacent older stands. There is usually a burn line where the fire stopped, dividing the low stature regenerating stands from the taller older unburned stands. The texture of the unburned areas is coarse, while that of the burned areas are smoother. The signatures of the individual xeric chaparral shrubs are very difficult to distinguish from each other on the imagery. Species interpretation using environmental characteristics is sometimes employed; however, in this case, the shrubs are not consistent with the environmental characteristics and cannot be discerned by this method. The xeric shrubs are dark green, tan or dark gray on the imagery. They have a coarse texture, and occur as dense groups or open patches. Individual crowns are usually not distinguishable. They will appear as a burgundy color on the supplemental CIR imagery. Regenerating Adenostoma fasciculatum and Ceanothus cuneatus are dark green in color and appear as very small individuals. Eriodictyon tomentosum appears as white to gray or bluish gray color with a soft fuzzy texture. Eriogonum fasciculatum can be reddish brown in color, but sometimes appears tan or gray. It usually occurs as small individuals, but can appear in clumps. Salvia mellifera will appear as medium green or gray to tan. Lotus scoparius, Dendromecon rigida, and Malacothamnus arboriginum are very difficult to identify on the imagery.

Types with Similar Signature:
Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup - 3100
Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Group - 3101
Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3103/9710
Adenostoma fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3110
Post Burn and Post Disturbance Undifferentiated Shrub and Grass-Herb Regeneration Mapping Unit - 9700

3110 - Chamise Shrubland Alliance
(Included in the Original (3101), Post AA (3101), and Post AA Park-Specific (3110) databases)

Adenostoma fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance
Adenostoma fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance
Adenostoma fasciculatum Shrubland Association
Adenostoma fasciculatum-Arctostaphylos glauca Shrubland Association
Adenostoma fasciculatum-Arctostaphylos pungens Shrubland Association
Adenostoma fasciculatum-Ceanothus cuneatus Shrubland Association
Adenostoma fasciculatum-Salvia mellifera Shrubland Association
Adenostoma fasciculatum/Selaginella bigelovii Shrubland Association

A Description:
The Adenostoma fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance is mapped as dense to sparse stands of chaparral with Adenostoma fasciculatum as the dominant shrub at high to low cover. Ceanothus cuneatus, Arctostaphylos glauca, Arctostaphylos pungens, Salvia mellifera, Eriogonum fasciculatum, and Selaginella bigelovii may be present, or co-dominant, at moderate to very low cover. This alliance favors dry sites on all aspects, slope positions, slope steepness, and slope shapes. The alliance also represents the hierarchical class into which all Adenostoma fasciculatum types are nested.

Photo Signature:
The signature of Adenostoma fasciculatum is similar to those of other xeric chaparral shrubs, and which are very difficult to distinguish from each other on the NAIP imagery. Species interpretation using environmental characteristics is sometimes employed; however, in this case, the shrubs are not consistent with the environmental characteristics and cannot be discerned by this method. The xeric shrubs range from dark green to tan or dark gray on the imagery. They have a coarse texture, and occur as dense groups or open patches. Individual crowns are usually not distinguishable. They will usually appear as a burgundy color on the supplemental CIR imagery, but sometimes they can have individual red dots within the burgundy, which may be Prunus ilicifolia, Heteromeles arbutifolia, Ceanothus cuneatus, or Arctostaphylos pungens.

Types with Similar Signature:
Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Group - 3101
Dry-Mesic Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3102
Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit 3104/9720
Salvia mellifera Shrubland Alliance - 3360

3113 - Chamise-Black Sage Shrubland Association
Included in the Original database)

Adenostoma fasciculatum-Salvia mellifera Shrubland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Adenostoma fasciculatum-Salvia mellifera Shrubland Association is mapped as a dense to open stand of co-dominant Adenostoma fasciculatum and Salvia mellifera, each with a high to low cover. The association typically favors southerly, moderately steep, lower to upper slopes and ridge tops, but in some instances is located on northerly aspects. Field reconnaissance and releve sites were used to identify known positions for this type and assisted in the extrapolation to other possible locations. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. Within the expanded study area it is mapped as the Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup (3100).

Photo Signature:
The signature of Adenostoma fasciculatum is dark green, tan or dark gray on the imagery, and may have a coarse or smooth texture. The supplemental CIR imagery shows it as a dark burgundy color. Salvia mellifera is a short shrub with a medium green color on the imagery. The texture can at times appear smooth or coarse. On the imagery, Salvia mellifera is sometimes difficult to see among the taller shrubs. A light green undertone may be an indication of its presence. The supplemental CIR will show it as a lighter red color. Sometimes the Salvia mellifera signature will appear tan or gray on the imagery, and may be confused with that of Eriogonum fasciculatum or Artemisia californica. In these cases the unit will be mapped as the Adenostoma fasciculatum-Coastal Sage Scrub Shrubland Mapping Unit (3114).

Types with Similar Signature:
Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Group - 3101
Adenostoma fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3110
Adenostoma fasciculatum-Coastal Sage Scrub Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3114
Adenostoma fasciculatum-Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Mapping Uni - 3115
California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup - 3300 (original 3301)
Salvia mellifera Shrubland Alliance - 3360

3114 - Chamise-Coastal Sage Scrub Shrubland Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Adenostoma fasciculatum-Coastal Sage Scrub Shrubland Mapping Unit
Adenostoma fasciculatum-Salvia mellifera Shrubland

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Adenostoma fasciculatum-Coastal Sage Scrub Shrubland Mapping Unit is mapped as a dense to sparse stand of Adenostoma fasciculatum over coastal sage scrub. Adenostoma fasciculatum is the dominant chaparral shrub at high to low cover. Ceanothus cuneatus and Arctostaphylos glauca may be present at moderate to very low cover. Salvia mellifera and/or Eriogonum fasciculatum are present at high to very low cover. Selaginella bigelovii can be present at moderate to very low cover, especially when Eriogonum fasciculatum is also present. Lotus scoparius, Diplacus aurantiacus, and Eriodictyon tomentosum may also be present at moderate to very low cover. This mapping unit favors dry, southerly, moderately steep, lower to upper slopes. The Eriogonum fasciculatum and Selaginella bigelovii variants favor rockier and/or steeper sites. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. Within the expanded study area it is mapped as the Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup (3100).

Photo Signature:
The signature of Adenostoma fasciculatum is dark green, tan or dark gray on the imagery, with a coarse to smooth texture. The supplemental CIR imagery shows it as a dark burgundy color. Salvia mellifera is a short shrub with a medium green, tan, or gray color on the imagery. The supplemental CIR will show it as a lighter red color. The texture can appear smooth or coarse. Eriogonum fasciculatum is a low shrub with a gray, brown, or rust color. It appears as small rounded individuals or in small clusters. The coastal sage scrub shrubs are sometimes difficult to see among the taller shrubs. If the Salvia mellifera is the strongly dominant coastal sage scrub shrub and appears green within the Adenostoma fasciculatum, then it is mapped as the Adenostoma fasciculatum-Salvia mellifera Shrubland Association.

Types with Similar Signature:
Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Group - 3101
Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3104/9720
Adenostoma fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3110
Adenostoma fasciculatum-Salvia mellifera Shrubland Association - 3113
Adenostoma fasciculatum-Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3115
California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup - 3300 (original 3301)
Eriogonum fasciculatum Thin Substrate Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3332
Salvia mellifera Shrubland Alliance - 3360

3115 - Chamise-California Wild Buckwheat Shrubland Mapping Unit
(Included in the Originial and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Adenostoma fasciculatum-Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Mapping Unit

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description: The Adenostoma fasciculatum-Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Association is mapped as an open to sparse stand of Adenostoma fasciculatum and Eriogonum fasciculatum. Adenostoma fasciculatum dominates at high to low cover. Eriogonum fasciculatum is sub-dominant, but may co-dominate, at moderate to very low cover. In some instances Selaginella bigelovii may be present at moderate to very low cover. Lotus scoparius and Eriodictyon tomentosum may also be present at low to very low cover. The association typically favors thin soil, southerly, moderately steep to steep, lower to upper slopes and ridge tops. Field reconnaissance and releve sites were used to identify known positions for this type and assisted in the extrapolation to other possible locations. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. Within the expanded study area it is mapped as the Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup (3100).

Photo Signature:
The signature of Adenostoma fasciculatum is dark green, tan or dark gray on the imagery, with a coarse to smooth texture. The supplemental CIR imagery shows it as a dark burgundy color. Eriogonum fasciculatum is a short shrub with a reddish-brown to tan or gray color on the imagery. The shrubs appear as coarse small individuals. It is sometimes difficult to see among the taller shrubs. A light green undertone may be an indication of its presence. Sometimes the Salvia mellifera signature will appear tan or gray on the imagery, and may be confused with that of Eriogonum fasciculatum or Artemisia californica. In these cases the unit will be mapped as the Adenostoma fasciculatum-Coastal Sage Scrub Shrubland Mapping Unit (3114).

Types with Similar Signature:
Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Group - 3101
Adenostoma fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3110
Adenostoma fasciculatum-Salvia mellifera Shrubland Association - 3113
Adenostoma fasciculatum-Coastal Sage Scrub Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3114
California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup - 3300 (original 3301)
Salvia mellifera Shrubland Alliance - 3360

3150 - Hollyleaf Cherry Shrubland Alliance
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Prunus ilicifolia Shrubland Alliance
Prunus ilicifolia Shrubland Association
Prunus ilicifolia-Ceanothus cuneatus Shrubland Association
Prunus ilicifolia-Heteromeles arbutifolia Shrubland Association
Prunus ilicifolia-Fraxinus dipetala Shrubland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Prunus ilicifolia Shrubland Alliance is mapped as dense to open stands of strongly dominant or dominant Prunus ilicifolia at high to low cover. Mesic shrubs, including Prunus ilicifolia, Cercocarpus montanus var. glaber, Ceanothus cuneatus, Rhamnus ilicifolia, Quercus wislizenii, Heteromeles arbutifolia, Clematis lasiantha, and Fraxinus dipetala, may be present, each at high to very low cover. Prunus ilicifolia may co-dominate with Ceanothus cuneatus, Heteromeles arbutifolia or Fraxinus dipetala. Adenostoma fasciculatum may be present at low to very low cover. This Alliance favors northerly, protected, concave to neutral shapes, lower to middle slopes and canyon bottoms. It can be found on gentle to steep slopes. It also occurs below rock outcrops and pinnacles. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. Within the expanded study area it is mapped as the Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup (3100).

Photo Signature:
Prunus ilicifolia will appear as bright green with a coarse texture. On the supplemental CIR imagery it will appear as a bright red color. Since Prunus ilicifolia is the dominant shrub, its vivid signature overwhelms that of the other shrubs. The other mesic shrubs range from medium green to dull green to dark green. Therefore this type is mapped when the imagery is bright green and the supplemental CIR is bright red throughout the unit.

Types with Similar Signature:
Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup - 3100
Dry-Mesic Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3102
Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3103/9710

3160 - California Scrub Oak Shrubland Alliance
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Quercus berberidifolia Shrubland Alliance
Quercus berberidifolia Shrubland Association
Quercus berberidifolia-Cercocarpus montanus var. glaber Shrubland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Quercus berberidifolia Shrubland Alliance is mapped as dense to open stands of tall shrubs. Quercus berberidifolia is the dominant plant at high to moderate cover. Other tall shrubs, including Adenostoma fasciculatum, Cercocarpus montanus var. glaber, Prunus ilicifolia, Ceanothus cuneatus, Heteromeles arbutifolia, and Rhamnus ilicifolia may be present at low to very low cover. Pinus sabiniana may also be present at moderate to low cover. This association favors northerly, moderately steep, lower to upper slopes. This class is mapped within the park buffer and expanded study area.

Photo Signature:
Quercus berberidifolia appears on the imagery as groups of large, round-crowned individuals with a medium to dark green color and a coarse texture. The supplemental CIR imagery shows it as bright red individuals.

Types with Similar Signature:
Quercus agrifolia Woodland Alliance - 2110
Quercus douglasii Woodland Alliance - 2210
Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup - 3100
Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Group - 3101
Adenostoma fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3110
Prunus ilicifolia Shrubland Alliance - 3150

3210 - Coyote Brush Shrubland Alliance
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Baccharis pilularis Shrubland Alliance
Baccharis pilularis/Annual Grass-Herb Shrubland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Baccharis pilularis Shrubland Alliance is mapped as a dense to open stand of shrubs consisting of dominant Baccharis pilularis at moderate to high cover. Emergent trees, including Quercus lobata and Quercus agrifolia, occur at very low cover. This alliance is found on flat floodplain terraces. Survey points, including releve and reconnaissance sites, that identify known positions assisted in the extrapolation to other nearby possible locations. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. Within the expanded study area it is mapped as the California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup (3300).

Photo Signature:
Baccharis pilularis is a tall shrub and appears as dark green clumps or patches with a slightly coarse texture.

Types with Similar Signature:
Southwestern North American Riparian/Wash Scrub Shrubland Group - 3400 (original 3401)
Rosa californica Shrubland Alliance - 3410/3510
Alluvial Herb and Shrub Vegetation Mapping Unit - 4004 (original 4401)

3300 - California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup
(Included in the Original (3300/3301), Post AA (3300), and Post AA Park-Specific databases (3300)

Artemisia californica Shrubland Alliance
Artemisia californica Shrubland Association
Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance
Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Association
Salvia mellifera Shrubland Alliance
Salvia mellifera Shrubland Association
Salvia mellifera-Eriogonum fasciculatum/Bromus rubens Shrubland Association
Artemisia califorica-Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance
Artemisia californica-Eriogonum fasciculatum/Annual Grass-Herb Shrubland Association
Lupinus albifrons Shrubland Alliance
Lupinus albifrons-Senecia flaccidus var. douglasii Shrubland Association
Diplacus aurantiacus Shrubland Alliance
Diplacus aurantiacus Shrubland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup is mapped as dense to sparse stands of coastal sage scrub shrubs at high to sparse cover. This class is mapped where it is difficult to photointerpret and/or differentiate the coastal sage scrub types. Artemisia californica, Eriogonum fasciculatum, and/or Salvia mellifera may be present as dominant or co-dominant with each other. Eriogonum fasciculatum tends to favor the driest locations, Salvia mellifera not as dry, and Artemisia californica the least dry locations of the three. Adenostoma fasciculatum may be present at low to very low cover. Quercus douglasii and Pinus sabiniana may also be present at very low cover. This class also includes other low shrubs including Eriogonum fasciculatum, Lupinus albifrons, Lotus scoparius, and Eridictyon tomentosum. This mapping unit is found on gentle to moderately steep, lower to upper slopes. It is also found in alluvial washes and fans, and floodplain terraces, where Eriogonum faciculatum and Lupinus albifrons may occur. Throughout most of the park, coastal sage scrub tends to occur on southerly aspects. However, on the west side, mainly within the expanded study area, coastal sage scrub may be found on northerly as well as southerly aspects. This type is mapped within the park and buffer only where difficult to interpret to the alliance or association. In the expanded study area no attempt was made to interpret to the alliance or association.
Photo Signature:
The coastal sage scrub shrubs tend to overlap in signature, making it difficult to distinguish between them in many cases. Artemisia californica is usually gray in color with a fine texture. It can occur as small individuals or in clumps. Eriogonum fasciculatum can be reddish brown in color, but sometimes appears tan or gray. It usually occurs as small individuals, but can also appear as clumps. Salvia mellifera can be green in color, but sometimes appears tan or gray. It usually occurs as clumps with a smooth or coarse texture rather than as individuals. Eriodictyon tomentosum appears as white to gray or bluish gray in color with a soft texture. It is found as individuals or in patches. Lupinus albifrons is difficult to distinguish on the imagery, and occurs in similar situations as Eriogonum fasciculatum.

Types with Similar Signature:
Quercus douglasii Woodland Alliance - 2210
Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Group - 3100
Adenostoma fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3110
Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3330
Salvia mellifera Shrubland Alliance - 3360
Artemisia californica-Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3370
Cliffs, Rock Outcrops, and Steep Eroded Slopes Mapping Unit - 9420

3330 - California Wild Buckwheat Shrubland Alliance
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance
Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance is mapped as open to sparse stands of dominant Eriogonum fasciculatum at high to low cover. This alliance favors dry sites on southerly steep slopes, or flat alluvial floodplains, alluvial terraces, fans, and gently sloping toe slopes. On sideslopes Salvia mellifera, Lotus scoparius, and Artemisia californica may be present, or co-dominant, at moderate to very low cover. On alluvial floodplain terraces Eriodictyon tomentosum may subdominate at moderate to very low cover; Lupinus albifrons may also be present at very low cove; and Pinus sabiniana may be emergent at very low cover. Riparian shrubs, including Baccaris salicifolia, Salix lasiolepis, and Salix exigua may occur in adjacent narrow stream channels as inclusions. On moderate to very steep rocky upper slopes Eriogonum fasciculatum may dominate at moderate to very low cover. Other short shrubs, including Lotus scoparius, Eriodictyon tomentosum, and Lupinus albifrons may be present at very low cover. In rockier areas Selaginella bigelovii may be present at very low to high cover. Pinus sabiniana may be emergent at very low cover. The alliance also represents the hierarchical class into which all Eriogonum fasciculatum types are nested. In areas where the signature does not allow for distinguishing the coastal sage scrub species, then the California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Group (3300, original 3301) is used. This type is mapped within the park, buffer. In the expanded study area the California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Group (3300) is used.

Photo Signature:
Eriogonum fasciculatum can appear tan, gray, or reddish-brown on the imagery. It usually occurs as small individuals, but can also appear as clumps.

Types with Similar Signature:
Pinus sabiniana Woodland Alliance - 1210
Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Group - 3101
Adenostoma fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3110
California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup - 3300 (original 3301)
Salvia mellifera Shrubland Alliance - 3360
Artemisia californica-Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3370
Southwestern North American Riparian/Wash Scrub Shrubland Group - 3400 (original 3401)
Open to Sparse Grass on Rocky Thin Substrate Herbaceous Vegetation Mapping Unit - 4003
Alluvial Herb and Shrub Vegetation Mapping Unit - 4004 (original 4401)
Cliffs, Rock Outcrops, and Steep Eroded Slopes Mapping Unit - 9420

3331 - California Wild Buckwheat Alluvial Shrubland Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Eriogonum fasciculatum Alluvial Shrubland Mapping Unit

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Eriogonum fasciculatum Alluvial Shrubland Mapping Unit is mapped as open to sparse low shrubs. It is typically dominated by Eriogonum fasciculatum at high to low cover. Eriodictyon tomentosum sub-dominates at moderate to very low cover. Lupinus albifrons may also be present at very low cover. Pinus sabiniana may be emergent at very low cover. This mapping unit is found on alluvial terraces, flat canyon bottoms, and alluvial toeslopes. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. Within the expanded study area it is mapped as the California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup (3300). In narrow canyon bottoms, alluvial terraces or fans, it may be difficult to distinguish this type from Lupinus albifrons Shrubland Alliance.

Photo Signature:
Eriogonum fasciculatum can appear tan, gray, or reddish-brown on the imagery. It usually occurs as small individuals, but can also appear as clumps. Eriodictyon tomentosum appears light bluish gray, white or gray in color with a soft texture. It occurs in clumps or patches.

Types with Similar Signature:
Pinus sabiniana/Eriogonum fasciculatum Alluvial Woodland Mapping Unit - 1212
Pinus sabiniana/Eriogonum fasciculatum Thin Substrate Woodland Mapping Unit - 1213
California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup - 3300 (original 3301)
Artemisia californica Shrubland Alliance - 3310
Eriogonum fasciculatum Alluvial Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3332
Lupinus albifrons Shrubland Alliance - 3350
Artemisia fasciculatum-Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3370
Southwestern North American Riparian/Wash Scrub Shrubland Group - 3400 (original 3401)
Alluvial Herb and Shrub Vegetation Mapping Unit - 4004 (original 4401)

3332 - California Wild Buckwheat Thin Substrate Shrubland Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Eriogonum fasciculatum Thin Substrate Shrubland Mapping Unit

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Eriogonum fasciculatum Thin Substrate Shrubland Mapping Unit is mapped as open to sparse stands of low shrubs. Eriogonum fasciculatum is the dominant shrub at moderate to very low cover. Other short shrubs, including Lotus scoparius, Eriodictyon tomentosum, and Lupinus albifrons may be present at very low cover. Selaginella bigelovii may be present at low to very low cover. Grass may also be present. Pinus sabiniana may be emergent at very low cover. This mapping unit favors southerly, moderate to very steep, mid to upper slopes on thin to rocky soils. It can also be found on eroded slopes and escarpments. Field reconnaissance and releve sites were used to identify known positions for this type and assisted in the extrapolation to other possible locations. On slopes where Eriogonum fasciculatum dominates and site is not rocky, or it is difficult to determine substrate, then Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance (3330) is mapped. In areas where the signature does not allow for distinguishing the coastal sage scrub species, then the California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup (3300, original 3301) is used. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. Within the expanded study area it is mapped as the California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup (3300).

Photo Signature:
Eriogonum fasciculatum can appear tan, gray, or reddish-brown on the imagery. It usually occurs as small individuals, but can also appear as clumps. Rock outcrops and thin, rocky soils appear as white or gray color with smooth textures.

Types with Similar Signature:
Pinus sabiniana/Eriogonum fasciculatum Alluvial Woodland Mapping Unit - 1212
Pinus sabiniana/Eriogonum fasciculatum Thin Substrate Woodland Mapping Unit - 1213
Adenostoma fasciculatum-Salvia mellifera Shrubland Association - 3113
Adenostoma fasciculatum-Coastal Sage Scrub Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3114
Adenostoma fasciculatum-Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3115
California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup - 3300 (original 3301)
Artemisia californica Shrubland Alliance - 3310
Eriogonum fasciculatum Alluvial Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3331
Salvia mellifera Shrubland Alliance - 3360
Artemisia californica-Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3370
Open to Sparse Grass on Rocky Thin Substrate Herbaceous Vegetation Mapping Unit - 4003

3350 - Silver Lupine Shrubland Alliance
(Included in the Original and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Lupinus albifrons Shrubland Alliance
Lupinus albifrons-Senecio flaccidus var. douglasii Shrubland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Lupinus albifrons Shrubland Alliance is mapped as open to sparse stands of low shrubs. Lupinus albifrons is the dominant shrub at high to low cover. Eriogonum fasciculatum and Eriodictyon tomentosum may be present at low to very low cover. This association occurs on alluvial fans and alluvial canyon bottoms. Field reconnaissance and releve sites were used to identify known positions for this type and assisted in the extrapolation to other possible locations. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. Within the expanded study area it is mapped as the California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup (3300). On narrow canyon bottoms, these sites may be difficult to distinguish from the Eriogonum fasciculatum Alluvial Shrubland Mapping Unit (3331).

Photo Signature:
The signature for Lupinus albifrons is very difficult to distinguish from other coastal sage scrub shrubs on the imagery. Context and survey sites are used to assist in mapping this type. The alluvial fan signature is white to gray or tan with tiny dots of the open to sparse shrubs.

Types with Similar Signature:
California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup - 3300 (original 3301)
Eriogonum fasciculatum Alluvial Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3331
Alluvial Herb and Shrub Vegetation Mapping Unit - 4004 (original 4401)

3360 - Black Sage Alliance
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Salvia mellifera Shrubland Alliance
Salvia mellifera Shrubland Association
Salvia mellifera-Eriogonum fasciculatum/Bromus rubens Shrubland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Salvia mellifera Shrubland Alliance is mapped as dense to open stands of strongly dominant Salvia mellifera at high to low cover. Adenostoma fasciculatum, Eriogonum fasciculatum, or Artemisia californica may be present at very low cover. The association favors southerly, gentle to moderately steep, concave, convex, and neutral shapes on lower to upper slopes and ridgetops. Field reconnaissance and releve sites were used to identify known positions for this type and assisted in the extrapolation to other possible locations. In areas where the signature does not allow for distinguishing the coastal sage scrub species, then the California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup (3300, original 3301) is used. This type is mapped within the park, buffer. In the expanded study area the California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup (3300) is used.
Photo Signature:
Salvia mellifera is a short shrub and can be green in color, but sometimes appears tan or gray. It usually occurs as clumps with a smooth or coarse texture rather than as individuals. The lighter color is an indication of its presence. The supplemental CIR will show it as a light red color.

Types with Similar Signature:
Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup - 3100
Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Group - 3101
Adenostoma fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3110
California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup - 3300 (original 3101)
Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3330
Artemisia californica-Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3370

3370 - California Sagebrush-California Wild Buckwheat Shrubland Alliance
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Artemisia californica-Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance
Artemisia californica-Eriogonum fasciculatum/Annual Grass-Herb Shrubland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Artemisia californica-Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance is mapped as dense to sparse stands of low shrubs consisting of a co-dominance of Artemisia californica and Eriogonum fasciculatum, each at moderate to low cover. The alliance favors southerly, moderate to steep, neutral to convex lower to upper slopes. Field reconnaissance and releve sites were used to identify known positions for this type and assisted in the extrapolation to other possible locations. In areas where the signature does not allow for distinguishing the coastal sage scrub species, then the California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Group (3300, original 3301) is used. This type is mapped within the park, buffer. In the expanded study area the California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Group (3300) is used.

Photo Signature:
Artemisia californica is a short shrub with a gray color on the imagery and can appear as individuals or in patches. The texture may be smooth or coarse. Eriogonum fasciculatum will appear tan or gray, and sometimes reddish-brown. It is usually difficult to distinguish the two species when they intermix. Sometimes Salvia mellifera is in the area and appears tan or gray on the imagery. Its signature can be confused with that of Artemisia californica or Eriogonum fasciculatum.

Types with Similar Signature:
California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup - 3300 (original 3301)
Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3330
Salvia mellifera Shrubland Alliance - 3360

3400/3401 - Southwestern North American Riparian/Wash Scrub Shrubland Group
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Salix lasiolepis Temporarily Flooded Alliance
Salix lasiolepis/Baccharis salicifolia Shrubland Association
Salix lasiolepois/Rosa californica Shrubland Association
Salix (exigua, interior) Temporarily Flooded Shrubland Alliance
Salix exigua Temporarily Flooded Shrubland Association
Baccharis salicifolia Intermittently Flooded Shrubland Alliance
Baccharis salicifolia Riparian Shrubland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Southwestern North American Riparian/Wash Scrub Shrubland Group is mapped as dense to open stands of short riparian trees and saplings and riparian shrubs. The short-statured trees may include Salix laevigata, Salix lasiolepis, Populus fremontii, and Platanus racemosa at high to very low cover. Shrubs include Salix lasiolepis, Salix exigua, and Baccharis salicifolia at high to very low cover. The mapping unit is found in or at the edge of the active channel, as well as in the active floodplain. This unit may braid around small isolated sand bars, alluvial terraces, and may contain inclusions of other riparian types. This class is mapped within the park, buffer, and expanded study area.

Photo Signature:
The signatures of the individual riparian short trees and shrubs are very difficult to distinguish from each other on the imagery. Species interpretation using environmental characteristics is sometimes employed; however, in this case, the shrubs are not consistent with the environmental characteristics and cannot be discerned by this method. Therefore the riparian low-growth trees and shrubs have been mapped together as this mapping unit. The plants are bright green or dull green to gray-green on the imagery. They have a smooth texture and tend to occur as dense groups or open patches. Individual crowns are usually not distinguishable. They will appear as a bright red color on the supplemental CIR imagery. Many times they occur in a linear path along the stream channel or braids of the channel.

Types with Similar Signature:
Pinus sabiniana Woodland Alliance - 1210
Southwestern North American Riparian Evergreen and Deciduous Forest Group - 1300 (original 1301)
Quercus agrifolia Woodland Alliance - 2110
Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3330
Alluvial Herb and Shrub Vegetation Mapping Unit - 4004 (original 4401)

3410/3510 - California Wildrose Shrubland Alliance
(Included in the Original (3510), Post AA (3410), and Post AA Park-Specific (3410) databases)

Rosa californica Shrubland Alliance
Rosa californica Shrubland Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Rosa californica Shrubland Alliance is mapped as dense stands of shrub thickets consisting of very dominant Rosa californica at high cover. The thickets are usually small patches in riparian corridors and floodplains. This type is mapped within the park, buffer, and expanded study area.

Photo Signature:
Rosa californica appears as short dense thickets with a bright green color, very smooth texture, and rounded edges. The thickets may occur in small groups.

Types with Similar Signature:
Southwestern North American Riparian/Wash Scrub Shrubland Group - 3400 (original 3401)

4003 - Open to Sparse Grass on Rocky Thin Substrate Herbaceous Vegetation Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Open to Sparse Grass on Rocky Thin Substrate Herbaceous Vegetation Mapping Unit is mapped as herbs, grasses, forbs and low-profile exposed rock mixed with thin soil substrate. It occurs on steep flat neutral slopes with thin soils and rocky exposures. Scree may also be present. Eriogonum fasciculatum and/or Selaginella bigelovii may be present at low to very low cover. This class is mapped within the park, buffer, and expanded study area. Areas of large boulder, cliff and pinnacle rock outcrops are mapped as Cliffs, Rock Outcrops, and Steep Eroded Slopes Mapping Unit (9420).

Photo Signature:
The grasslands appear tan to light tan with a smooth texture. Rockier areas are mottled with white or gray. The tan of grass will mix or mosaic with the white or gray of rock. The grass signature in the rocky areas can appear flat and low in height grading into the thin-soil areas.

Types with Similar Signature:
Pinus sabiniana/Eriogonum fasciculatum Thin Substrate Shrubland Mapping Unit - 1213
California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup - 3300 (original 3301)
Eriogonum fasciculatum Thin Substrate Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3332
Mediterranean California Naturalized Annual and Perennial Grassland and Herbaceous Vegetation Macrogroup - 4300 (original 4002 and 4310)
Cliffs, Rock Outcrops, and Steep Eroded Slopes Mapping Unit - 9420

4004/4401 -Alluvial Herb and Shrub Vegetation Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original (4401), Post AA (4004), and Post AA Park-Specific (4004) databases)

(Artemisia dracunculus)-Gnaphalium canescens Herbaceous Vegetation
Artemisia dracunculus Alluvial Fan Herbaceous Vegetation

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Alluvial Herb and Shrub Vegetation Mapping Unit is mapped as open to very sparse stands of herbaceous vegetation on floodplains and flat canyon bottoms. Scattered shrubs may occur within the stand. This class may contain Artemisia dracunculus, Artemisia douglasiana, Lotus scoparius, Eriogonum fasciculatum, Escholtzia californica, and Lupinus albifrons in various combinations at very low cover. Riparian shrubs, including Salix lasiolepis and Baccharis salicifolia, and trees, including Salix laevigata, Platanus racemosa, Quercus agrifolia and Pinus sabiniana, may also be present at very low cover or occurs in immediately adjacent stream channels. This mapping unit is found on sand or gravel bars and active floodplain terraces adjacent to braided stream channels, as well as in alluvial canyon bottoms, and bare dry active stream channels. Because of frequent flooding it usually has a very sparse vegetative cover. This type is mapped within the park and buffer.

Photo Signature:
The mapping unit appears as a white signature with very sparse vegetation and a sandy to gravelly substrate. Tiny dots of vegetation are visible. In denser more moist areas an herbaceous stand may appear green in color. The units are either of very limited extent, or can run along the canyon and/or floodplain stream drainage.

Types with Similar Signature:
Pinus sabiniana Woodland Alliance - 1210
Southwestern North American Riparian Evergreen and Deciduous Forest Group - 1300 (original 1301)
California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup - 3300 (original 3301)
Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3330
Southwestern North American Riparian/Wash Scrub Shrubland Group - 3400 (original 3401)
Western North America Wet Meadow and Low Shrub Carr Macrogroup - 4500 (original 4001 and 4201)

4101 - Bulrush-Cattails Herbaceous Vegetation Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Scirpus spp.-Typha spp. Herbaceous Vegetation Mapping Unit

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Scirpus spp.-Typha spp. Herbaceous Vegetation Mapping Unit is mapped where herbaceous vegetation is situated in standing water. Scirpus spp. or Typha spp. may be present at high to low cover. It is found on the flat edges of water bodies or in shallow water. This class is mapped within the park, buffer, and expanded study area.

Photo Signature:
The signature of the plant is bright to medium green within the black or dark blue to light blue signature of the water body.

Types with Similar Signature:
Western North America Wet Meadow And Low Shrub Carr Macrogroup - 4500 (original 4001 and 4201)
Water Mapping Unit - 9500

4300/4310 - Mediterranean California Naturalized Annual and Perennial Grassland Herbaceous Vegetation Group
(Included in the Original (4002/4310), Post AA (4300), and Post AA Park-Specific (4300) databases)

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Mediterranean California Naturalized Annual and Perennial Grassland Herbaceous Vegetation Group is mapped as dense to sparse stands of grasses at high to moderate cover. There is usually a thin to deep soil layer that allows for grassy vegetation. There may be some limited rocky areas where Selaginella bigelovii and Eriogonum fasciculatum may be present at very low cover. Stands of dense to open Artemisia dracunculus on floodplains are included. The mapping unit typically occurs on level to gentle slopes in all aspects, but at times may occur on moderately steep slopes. It is usually found on canyon bottoms, floodplains, and lower slopes, but can occur on mid to upper slopes. This type is mapped within the park, buffer, and expanded study area. The rockier, thin substrate grassy areas are mapped as Cliffs, Rock Outcrops, and Steep Eroded Slopes Mapping Unit (9420).

Photo Signature:
The grasslands appear as brown, tan to light tan or yellow areas with a smooth texture. In rockier areas they may be mottled with white or gray rocky exposures and scattered shrubs.

Types with Similar Signature:
Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Group - 3101
Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3330
Western North America Wet Meadow And Low Shrub Carr Herbaceous Vegetation Macrogroup - 4500 (original 4001 and 4201)
Open to Sparse Grass on Rocky Thin Substrate Herbaceous Vegetation Mapping Unit - 4003
Cliffs, Rock Outcrops, and Steep Eroded Slopes Mapping Unit - 9420

4500 - Western North America Wet Meadow And Low Shrub Carr Herbaceous Vegetation Macrogroup
(Included in the Original (4001/4201), Post AA (4500), and Post AA Park-Specific (4500) databases)

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Western North America Wet Meadow And Low Shrub Carr Herbaceous Vegetation Macrogroup is mapped as dense herbs, grasses, and forbs in moist areas such as seeps and springs, and adjacent to wet stream channels and moist floodplains. Plants may include Carex spp., Juncus spp., Scirpus spp., Typha spp., wet graminoids, and sparse sandbar vegetation, including Artemisia dracunculus. Vegetation in standing water is mapped as Scirpus spp.-Typha spp. Herbaceous Vegetation Mapping Unit (4101). This type is mapped within the park, buffer, and expanded study area.

Photo Signature:
The moist herbaceous vegetation typically has a bright to medium green signature with a smooth texture. It may include the sand bar areas, which have a white to gray signature.

Types with Similar Signature:
Scirpus spp.-Typha spp. Herbaceous Vegetation Mapping Unit - 4101
Mediterranean California Natrualized Annual and Perennial Grassland Herbaceous Vegetation Group - 4300 (original 4002 and 4310)

4510 - Deergrass Herbaceous Vegetation Alliance
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Muhlenbergia rigens Herbaceous Vegetation Alliance
Muhlenbergia rigens Herbaceous Vegetation Association

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Muhlenbergia rigens Herbaceous Vegetation Alliance is mapped as open to sparse stands of herbaceous vegetation. Muhlenbergia rigens is dominant at high to moderate cover. Only one site was mapped, in McCabe Canyon, on the flat canyon bottom.

Photo Signature:
The site mapped as Muhlenbergia rigens is not distinguishable from wet graminoids. It appears as a medium green signature with a smooth to bumpy texture.

Types with Similar Signature:
California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup - 3300 (original 3301)
Alluvial Herb and Shrub Vegetation Mapping Unit - 4004 (original 4401)
Mediterranean California Naturalized Annual and Perennial Grassland Herbaceous Vegetation Group - 4300 (original 4002 and 4310)
Western North America Wet Meadow And Low Shrub Carr Herbaceous Vegetation Group - 4500 (original 4001 and 4201)

9100 - Built-up Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Built-up Mapping Unit is mapped in areas consisting of man-made structures that are used for residential, commercial, industrial, or utility purposes. Vegetation is very limited, sparse, or not present. If significant vegetation occurs in a land use area, then the appropriate vegetation class is used. This class is mapped within the park, buffer, and expanded study area.

Photo Signature:
The signature shows one or more building structures, usually in a cluster. Their associated grounds, landscaped areas, parking areas, or activity disturbances area are included.

9200 - Agriculture Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Agriculture Mapping Unit is mapped in areas consisting of open space agricultural uses including corrals and pens, orchards, vineyards, cropland, and nurseries. Trees may be present in open pasture or field crop areas, in which case the appropriate woodland alliance class may be used. This mapping unit is mapped within the park, buffer, and expanded study area. Farm buildings including residences, barns, and outbuildings are mapped as the Built-up Mapping Unit (9100). Fenced grasslands are mapped as California Annual Grasslands Herbaceous Vegetation Mapping Unit (4310).

Photo Signature:
Corrals and pens appear as a series of square, rectangular or straight-sided fenced enclosures covering very small areas. Vineyards are usually consecutive thin rows of green vegetation showing some relief. Orchards are an array of green trees in a consistent pattern of rows and columns. Cropland is consistent, green, smooth vegetation or thin rows of green vegetation showing very low relief. Freshly tilled fields are also included. Nurseries are thin rows of vegetation that are not in a consistent pattern of color or texture. They also include temporary greenhouse structures of white or gray.

9420 - Cliffs, Rock Outcrops, and Steep Eroded Slopes Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Cliffs, Rock Outcrops and Steep Eroded Slopes Mapping Unit is mapped as rocky exposures with no to low cover of vegetation. They can appear as steep cliffs, pinnacle rock formations, or low flat rocky areas, and herbaceous areas with thin soils. Scattered trees and shrubs, including Pinus sabiniana, Juniperus californica, Quercus agrifolia, Quercus wislizenii, Adenostoma fasciculatum, Ceanothus cuneatus, Cercocarpus montanus, Prunus ilicifolia, Heteromeles arbutifolia, Arctostaphylos glauca, and Arctostaphylos pungens may be found. Salvia mellifera and Eriogonum fasciculatum may be present at very low to low cover. Patchy stands of herbaceous vegetation, including grasses, may also be present at very low to low cover as a mosaic, especially with low profile rock outcrops. Selaginella bigelovii, however may be present at very low to high cover. Mesic shrubs and trees tend to occur at the bottom edges of the rock pinnacles and cliffs, with some also situated in narrow cracks in the outcrop. Scree or talus may be present within the cliff, outcrop, or eroded slope. Grasses and Selaginella bigelovii can occur on flatter areas with thin substrate. This mapping unit is mapped within the park, buffer, and expanded study area.

Photo Signature:
Cliffs, rock outcrops, and steep eroded slopes can appear as white, gray, or tan colors with a mottled appearance and a smooth to rough texture. Green to dark green shrubs may be visible. The grasslands appear tan to light tan with a smooth texture. Rockier areas are mottled with white or gray. The tan of grass will mix or mosaic with the white or gray of rock. The grass signature in the rocky areas can appear flat and low in height grading into the thin-soil areas.

Types with Similar Signature:
Pinus sabiniana Woodland Alliance - 1210
Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Group - 3101
Adenostoma fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3110
California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup - 3300 (original 3301)
Eriogonum fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3330
Mediterranean California Naturalized Annual and Perennial Grassland Herbaceous Vegetation Group - 4300 (original 4002 and 4310)

9430 - Sparsely Vegetated to Non-vegetated Stream Beds and Flats Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original database)

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Sparsely Vegetated to Non-vegetated Stream Beds and Flats Mapping Unit is mapped along drainages where the imagery shows very little or no vegetation. The area mapped includes the stream channel and adjacent sand bars or flats. This mapping unit is mapped within the park, buffer, and expanded study area. In the original database, if the floodplain shows braided channels with interfluvial low terraces, then the Alluvial Herb and Shrub Mapping Unit (4401) is used. In the Post AA and Post AA Park-Specific databases this class is included in the Alluvial Herb and Shrub Mapping Unit (4004)

Types with Similar Signature:
Southwestern North American Riparian Evergreen and Deciduous Forest Group - 1300 (original 1301)
Southwestern North American Riparian/Wash Scrub Shrubland Group - 3400 (original 3401)
Alluvial Herb and Shrub Vegetation Mapping Unit - 4004 (original 4401)

9500 - Water Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
Water bodies such as man-made ponds and reservoirs are included here. Water has a black or deep blue signature on the imagery. Sometimes it may have a white or silvery appearance from reflected sunlight. If the signature shows vegetation growing within the water body, then the Scirpus spp.-Typha spp. Herbaceous Vegetation Mapping Unit (4101) is mapped for that portion of the water body. This class is mapped within the park, buffer, and expanded study area.

9600 - Planted Trees &amp; Shrubs Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Planted Trees &amp; Shrubs Mapping Unit is mapped as areas consisting of exotic trees and shrubs. Trees may include Eucalyptus spp., Schinus molle, and non-native conifers. Exotic trees and shrubs are common in land use areas. Orchards and vineyards are mapped as Agriculture Mapping Unit (9200). Exotic trees are difficult to photo interpret and differentiate from native trees due to the limitations of the imagery. Proximity to land use, context, and supplemental field site visits assist in interpretation of this mapping unit. This mapping unit is mapped within the park, buffer, and expanded study area.

9700 - Post Burn and Post Disturbance Undifferentiated Shrub and Grass-Herb Regeneration Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original, Post AA, and Post AA Park-Specific databases)

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Post Burn and Post Disturbance Undifferentiated Shrub and Grass-Herb Regeneration Mapping Unit is mapped as open to very sparse stands of short regenerating shrubs, grasses, and/or herbaceous vegetation that has been disturbed by man-induced activity, grading, or fire within the last ten years. Most shrubs are short and sparse, and are therefore unidentifiable by photo interpretation within the imagery limitations. Attempts were made to identify the vegetation through alternate means. Typically there are no releve sites in the burned or disturbed areas. Field visits were used in some cases to help in the identification of the shrubs present. Shrubs present following disturbance may include Lotus scoparius, Eriodictyon tomentosum, Malacothamnus aboriginum, Dendromicon rigida, Salvia mellifera, and Eriogonum fasciculatum at moderate to very low cover. Adenostoma fasciculatum or Ceanothus cuneatus may be present at low to very low cover, regenerating from crown sprouting or seeding after disturbance. Grasses and herbs may also be present at high to very low cover. This mapping unit is mapped within the park, buffer, and expanded study area. If a burned/disturbed stand was determined to be dominant xeric shrubs, then it was mapped as Post Burn and Post Disturbed Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit (3104). If a burned/disturbed stand was determined to be in a mesic environment, usually with Ceanothus cuneatus dominant, then it was mapped as Post Burn and Post Disturnbed Mesic Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit (3103). If a burned/disturbed stand is not otherwise identifiable then it is mapped as 9700.

Photo Signature:
Sparse vegetation is very difficult to identify with the imagery, unless it occurs in denser clumps. Regenerating Adenostoma fasciculatum is dark green in color and appears as very small individuals. Eriodictyon tomentosum appears as white, gray, or bluish-gray color with a soft texture. It occurs in clumps or patches. Eriogonum fasciculatum can be reddish-brown in color, but sometimes appears tan or gray. It usually occurs as small individuals, but can also appear as clumps. Salvia mellifera will appear as medium green, gray, or tan. Lotus scoparius, Dendromecon rigida, and Malacothamnus arboriginum are very difficult to identify on the imagery.

Types with Similar Signature:
Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3103/9710
Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Xeric Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3104/9720
Mediterranean California Naturalized Annual and Perennial Grassland Herbaceous Vegetation Macrogroup - 4300 (original 4002 and 4310)

9710 - Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit
(Included in the Original (3103), Post AA (3103), and Post AA Park-Specific (9710) databases)

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit is mapped as an intermittent to sparse stand of chaparral shrubs occurring in a mesic to semi-mesic environment, usually on northerly, concave to neutral, lower to mid slooes. The shrubs are regenerating or recovering from a burn or disturbance that had occurred within the last ten years. Most shrubs are short and sparse, and are therefore difficult to identify by photo interpretation within the imagery limitations. Field visits were used in some cases to help in the identification of the shrubs present. Ceanothus cuneatus typically is dominant at high to low cover. Adenostoma fasciculatum may also be present at very low cover. Mesic shrubs, including Prunus ilicifolia, Heteromeles arbutifolia, and Clematis lasiantha may be present, each at a very low cover. In many cases, the mesic shrubs grew back slower than the Ceanothus cuneatus or Adenostoma fasciculatum. Mesic shrubs would grow beneath the taller xeric shrubs. Fire and disturbance followers, including Eriodictyon tomentosum, Lotus scoparius, and Dendromecon rigida may be present at moderate to very low cover. These species may be more prevalent in stands with open to sparse cover. Quercus agrifolia may also be present. Emergent Quercus douglasii snags may be in the stand, but are not visible on the imagery. This mapping unit favors northerly, protected, concave to neutral shapes, lower to middle slopes and canyon bottoms. It can be found on gentle to moderately steep slopes. It also occurs below rock outcrops and pinnacles. This type is mapped within the park and buffer. Within the expanded study area it is mapped as the Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup (3100).

Photo Signature:
The burned area appears as shorter shrubs than the adjacent older stands. There is usually a burn line where the fire stopped, dividing the low stature regenerating stands from the taller older unburned stands. The texture of the shrubs in the burned areas is smooth. The signatures of the individual shrubs are very difficult to distinguish from each other on the imagery. Ceanothus cuneatus and Adenostoma fasciculatum will appear as dark green on the imagery. It will appear as a light pink on the supplemental CIR imagery. Prunus ilicifolia and Heteromeles arbutifolia will usually not be distinguishable on the imagery because they may be hidden under the taller xeric shrubs.

Types with Similar Signature:
Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup - 3100
Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Group - 3101
Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3104/9720
Prunus ilicifolia Shrubland Alliance - 3150
Post Burn and Post Disturbance Undifferentiated Shrub and Grass-Herb Regeneration Mapping Unit - 9700

9720 - Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit (Rework 9720)
(Included in the Original (3104), Post AA (3104), and Post AA Park-Specific (9720) databases)

Aerial Photo Mapped Unit      Distribution

A Description:
The Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Xeric Shrubland Mapping Unit is mapped as a dense to sparse stand of short xeric chaparral shrubs that are regenerating or recovering from a burn or disturbance that had occurred within the last ten years. Most shrubs are short and sparse, and therefore are difficult to identify by photo interpretation within the imagery limitations. Field visits were used in some cases to help in the identification of the shrubs present. Adenostoma fasciculatum is typically strongly dominant or dominant at high to low cover. Ceanothus cuneatus may dominate in some lower slope or gently sloping areas, and in some areas may co-dominate with Adenostoma fasciculatum. Generally Ceanothus cuneatus has a high to very low cover. Salvia mellifera, Eriogonum fasciculatum, and Selaginella bigelovii may be present at moderate to very low cover. Fire and disturbance followers, include Salvia mellifera, Eriogonum fasciculatum, Eriodictyon tomentosum, Lotus scoparius, and Dendromecon rigida, at moderate to very low cover. Malacothamnus arboriginum is a rare plant within the park and was observed in the 1998 burn area near the mouth of Grassy Canyon. These species may be more prevalent in stands with sparse cover. This mapping unit favors dry sites on all aspects, slope positions, slope steepness, and slope shapes. This type is mapped within the expanded area, park and buffer.

Photo Signature:
The burned area appears as shorter shrubs in comparison to the adjacent older stands. There is usually a burn line where the fire stopped, dividing the low stature regenerating stands from the taller older unburned stands. The texture of the unburned areas is coarse, while that of the burned areas are smoother. The signatures of the individual xeric chaparral shrubs are very difficult to distinguish from each other on the imagery. Species interpretation using environmental characteristics is sometimes employed; however, in this case, the shrubs are not consistent with the environmental characteristics and cannot be discerned by this method. The xeric shrubs are dark green, tan or dark gray on the imagery. They have a coarse texture, and occur as dense groups or open patches. Individual crowns are usually not distinguishable. They will appear as a burgundy color on the supplemental CIR imagery. Regenerating Adenostoma fasciculatum and Ceanothus cuneatus are dark green in color and appear as very small individuals. Eriodictyon tomentosum appears as white to gray or bluish gray color with a soft fuzzy texture. Eriogonum fasciculatum can be reddish brown in color, but sometimes appears tan or gray. It usually occurs as small individuals, but can appear in clumps. Salvia mellifera will appear as medium green or gray to tan. Lotus scoparius, Dendromecon rigida, and Malacothamnus arboriginum are very difficult to identify on the imagery.

Types with Similar Signature:
Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup - 3100
Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3101
Adenostoma fasciculatum Shrubland Alliance - 3110
Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit - 3103/9710
Post Burn and Post Disturbance Undifferentiated Shrub and Grass-Herb Regeneration Mapping Unit - 9700

COVER CLASS DENSITY VALUES
Conifer, Hardwood, Shrub
1 = &gt;60%
2 = 40-60%
3 = 25-40%
4 = 10-25%
5 = 2-10%
9 = None

LAND USE MAP UNITS

100 - Urban - Non-park facilities and private in-holdings
110 - Residential (includes farmsteads [residences with associated farm buildings] along Hwy 25, Regan Ranch, Schmidt Ranch, McCabe Canyon, and the West side)
200 - Agriculture
210 - Cropland
220 - Orchards and Vineyards
230 - Other Agriculture
400 - National Park/Monument Facilities
401 - Bear Gulch Facilities (Headquarters, Visitor Center, Employee Residence, Parking, Restroom)
402 - Chalone Creek Facilities (Maintenance, Employee Residence)
403 - Bear Gulch Parking (Parking, Restroom)
404 - Pinnacles Campground Facilities
405 - Chaparral Facilities (Visitor Center, Parking, Picnic Area, Employee Residence)
408 - Eastern Addition Former Farmsteads
409 - Eastern Addition Airport Buildings
410 - North Chalone Peak Lookout/Restroom
800 - Water
900 - Vacant

Citations

Kittel, G., E. Reyes, J. Evens, J. Buck and D. Johnson. 2009. Vegetation Classification and Mapping Project, Pinnacles National Monument. Natural Resource Technical Report NPS/ SFAN/NRTR-2009/XXX. National Park Service, Fort Collins, Colorado.
Lea, Chris. August 2009. Phone conversation with E. Reyes, AIS.

The shapefile was imported into a geodatabase by the USGS/CSS/Core Science Analytics and Synthesis.
</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>2005</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>ground condition</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>As needed</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<descgeog>Pinnacles National Monument and environs</descgeog>
<bounding>
<westbc>-121.313284</westbc>
<eastbc>-121.096789</eastbc>
<northbc>36.568949</northbc>
<southbc>36.383668</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>None</themekt>
<themekey>Vegetation</themekey>
<themekey>Vegetation Map</themekey>
<themekey>Vegetation Mapping</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>None</placekt>
<placekey>Pinnacles National Monument</placekey>
<placekey>San Benito County</placekey>
<placekey>Monterey County</placekey>
<placekey>California</placekey>
<placekey>United States</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>None</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>Standardized National Vegetation Classification System</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>vegetation classification</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>alliance</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>community association</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Plantae</taxonrv>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>Please acknowledge the originators in products derived from these data. Any person using the information presented here should fully understand the data collection and compilation before beginning analysis. The burden for determining fitness for use lies entirely with the user.</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Pinnacles National Monument</cntorg>
<cntper>Brent Johnson</cntper>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Botanist</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>Pinnacles National Monument, 50000 Highway 146</address>
<city>Paicines</city>
<state>California</state>
<postal>95043</postal>
<country>U.S.A</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>831-389-4486 ext.259</cntvoice>
<cnttdd>831-389-4486 ext.259</cnttdd>
<cntfax>831-389-4489</cntfax>
<cntemail>brent_johnson@nps.gov</cntemail>
<hours>7:30 am - 4:30 pm PST</hours>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
<datacred>Vegetation classification development was conducted by PINN, NatureServe, and the California Native Plant Society. The vegetation mapping was conducted by Aerial Information Systems. Acknowledgements This project was completed through the effort and dedication of numerous individuals and organizations. Details of the role of each person mentioned here is described in more detail in the Project Overview section. Sharon Franklet, Denise Louie, Paul Johnson and Brent Johnson (Pinnacles National Monument), Julie Evens and Jennifer Buck (California Native Plant Society), Gwen Kittel and Marion Reid (NatureServe), and Debbie Johnson, Ben Johnson, Ed Reyes and Arin Glass (Aerial Information Systems). Funding for this project was provided through the USGS-NPS National Vegetation Mapping Program and administered to the Park by the kind help of the San Francisco Bay Area Inventory and Monitoring Network. Numerous individuals collected plot and accuracy assessment field data. We appreciate the hard work of Melinda Elster, Andra Forney and Betsy Harbert with oversight by Jennifer Buck, Eric Peterson, Donna Shorrock, and Kendra Sikes (CNPS). The 2003 and 2004 Park crews were Sherry Bottoms, Katie deLaveaga, Shauna Hee, Michelle Karle, Kipp Marzullo, Keir Morse, Kendra Moseley (NPS) and others not listed here. Gwen Kittel of NatureServe conducted quantitative analyses and prepared the preliminary vegetation classification; analysis results were reviewed and final association names assigned by Julie Evens (CNPS) and Gwen Kittel (NatureServe). The California Native Plant Society staff, including Ed Kentner, created the local association descriptions. Ed Reyes and Arin Glass (AIS) conducted the photo interpretation and Debbie Johnson, Ed Reyes, Mike Nelson and Ben Johnson conducted the accuracy assessment. Jennifer Buck (CNPS) assisted with accuracy assessment analysis. All parties contributed to the final report. Ben Johnson of AIS also created most of the report figures. Thanks also to John Menke (AIS) and Todd Keeler-Wolf (California Department of Fish and Game) for their guidance during the initial meeting and field reconnaissance. Special thanks to Sharon Franklet, Jason Herynk, Denise Louise, Brent Johnson, Valerie Nuttman, Paul Johnson, Eric Brunnermann, Darrell Chambers, Leticia Ruiz, Lisa Smith, and the Condor Program Team of Pinnacles National Monument, who made us welcome whenever we arrived to check the map or collect field data, and provided helpful advice, keys, access and field assistance to help us best access different parts of the Monument. For these and other contributors to the success of the project, we are grateful.</datacred>
<native>Microsoft Windows Server 2008 R2 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; ESRI ArcGIS 10.0.2.3200</native>
<crossref>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Aerial Information Systems, PINN, NatureServe, California Native Plant Society</origin>
<pubdate>20090101</pubdate>
<title>Post AA Park-Specific Vegetation Database</title>
<geoform>database</geoform>
</citeinfo>
</crossref>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<attracc>
<attraccr>
An accuracy assessment (AA) was conducted on the original vegetation map database. The AA had a criterium of 80% accuracy at the 90% confidence level for all classes. As a result of the AA, classes that were below the 80% threshold were bumped up the classification hierarchy until they attained a category where they met the 80% criterium. The result was a Post AA vegetation database.

During the AA process it was recognized that many of the mapped polygons, although they did not reach the 80% threshold, still held valid information that could be of importance to the park or end users. NPS on a national level also recognizes that AA discrepancies may be the result of PI, key, classification, and in-field factors such as:

" 	vegetation descriptions/definitions and key not accounting for all the variations in a type
" 	field vs. PI perspective of stand density and vegetation distribution " GPS positional error
" 	low number of AA sites sampled where just one or two misses can put a class below 80%. For example
2 sites, 1 miss = 50%
3 sites, 2 miss = 33%, 1 miss = 66%
4 sites, 3 miss = 25 %, 2 miss = 50%, 1 miss = 75%
5 sites, 4 miss = 20%, 3 miss = 40%, 2 miss = 60%, 1 miss = 80%

which can result in classes falling below the 80% threshold, but may not necessarily be a true indication of the accuracy of a class.

Future NPS vegetation mapping efforts will include a validation step before final delivery for the AA that will accept classes of &amp;gt;60% accuracy with the intent of incorporating changes into the map from new information gained by the validation process prior to AA (Lea, communication, August 2009). This new direction supports the mapping/field efforts that were done at PINN. However the final Post AA database that was considered the final deliverable, did not use the &amp;gt;60% accuracy threshold. Therefore, in order to provide the park with a vegetation database that retained more detail than the Post AA database but modifying the vegetation interpretation from the knowledge gained through the AA process, a third Post AA Park-Specific database has been created. This database maintains most of the original suballiance and association classes with modifications made based new information. Misintepretation trends brought out by the AA process were also considered.
</attraccr>
</attracc>
<logic>Unknown.</logic>
<complete>Unknown.</complete>
<posacc>
<horizpa>
<horizpar>Unknown</horizpar>
</horizpa>
<vertacc>
<vertaccr>Unknown</vertaccr>
</vertacc>
</posacc>
<lineage>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Vincent Matthews</origin>
<pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
<title>Geologic Map of Pinnacles Volcanic formation</title>
<geoform>Unknown</geoform>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<srcscale>24000</srcscale>
<typesrc>CD-ROM</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>Unknown</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>Unknown</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>Geologic Map of Pinnacles Volcanic formation</srccitea>
<srccontr>PINN</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Unknown</origin>
<pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
<title>PINN Vegetation Releve Plots</title>
<geoform>Unknown</geoform>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<typesrc>None</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<rngdates>
<begdate>2003</begdate>
<enddate>2004</enddate>
</rngdates>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>PINN Vegetation Releve Plots</srccitea>
<srccontr>PINN</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Unknown</origin>
<pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
<title>PINN Vegetation Accuracy Assessment Sites</title>
<geoform>Unknown</geoform>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<typesrc>electronic mail system</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>2009</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>PINN Vegetation Accuracy Assessment Sites</srccitea>
<srccontr>PINN, California Native Plant Society</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Unknown</origin>
<pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
<title>Natural color digital orthophotos</title>
<geoform>imagery</geoform>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<typesrc>CD-ROM</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>2003</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>Unknown</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>Natural color digital orthophotos</srccitea>
<srccontr>PINN</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Unknown</origin>
<pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
<title>Color infrared digital orthophotos</title>
<geoform>imagery</geoform>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<typesrc>CD-ROM</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>2002</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>Color infrared digital orthophotos</srccitea>
<srccontr>PINN</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Unknown</origin>
<pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
<title>NAIP natural color digital orthophotos</title>
<geoform>imagery</geoform>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<typesrc>CD-ROM</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>2005</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>NAIP natural color digital orthophotos</srccitea>
<srccontr>PINN</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<procstep>
<procdesc>
AIS was contracted by NPS to photo interpret and map a vegetation database for Pinnacles National Monument (PINN) using the National Vegetation Classification System (NVCS). The mapping project was initiated in 2007 and was completed in 2009. For the complete description of the project please refer to the Vegetation Classification and Mapping Project Report, Pinnacles National Monument (Kittel, et. al., 2009).

The study area for the project covers 44,997 acres and consists of two tiers. The first tier (park and buffer area) includes lands within the park boundary as well as a quarter-mile buffer around the park. The second tier (extended study area) includes several areas of interest, of varying sizes, adjacent to the park and buffer.

The base imagery for the mapping was the 2005 NAIP natural color (leaf-on) digital orthophotos, with supplementary 2003 natural color digital orthophotos (leaf-on) and 2002 color infrared digital orthophotos (leaf-on).

The Original mapping was done using an on-screen photo interpretation and digitizing method. Field reconnaissance was conducted before the mapping, and an in-field map and vegetation key validation was conducted, with resulting field revisions incorporated.

The original mapping classification contained mainly alliance and association level classes, as well as group and macrogroup categories such as xeric chaparral, mesic chaparral, riparian trees, riparian shrubs, wet herbaceous, and dry herbaceous. There were also mapping unit classes such as rock outcrop, post burn chaparral, built-up, agriculture, and planted trees and shrubs. Land use was a second layer in the database, which included park facilities. Refer to Vegetation Classification and Mapping Project Report, Pinnacles National Monument, (Kittel, et. al.,2009) for the full original mapping classification.

An accuracy assessment (AA) was conducted on the original vegetation map database. The AA had a criterium of 80% accuracy at the 90% confidence level for all classes. As a result of the AA, classes that were below the 80% threshold were bumped up the classification hierarchy until they attained a category where they met the 80% criterium. The result was a Post AA vegetation database.

During the AA process it was recognized that many of the mapped polygons, although they did not reach the 80% threshold, still held valid information that could be of importance to the park or end users. NPS on a national level also recognizes that AA discrepancies may be the result of PI, key, classification, and in-field factors such as:

" 	vegetation descriptions/definitions and key not accounting for all the variations in a type
" 	field vs. PI perspective of stand density and vegetation distribution " GPS positional error
" 	low number of AA sites sampled where just one or two misses can put a class below 80%. For example
2 sites, 1 miss = 50%
3 sites, 2 miss = 33%, 1 miss = 66%
4 sites, 3 miss = 25 %, 2 miss = 50%, 1 miss = 75%
5 sites, 4 miss = 20%, 3 miss = 40%, 2 miss = 60%, 1 miss = 80%

which can result in classes falling below the 80% threshold, but may not necessarily be a true indication of the accuracy of a class.

Future NPS vegetation mapping efforts will include a validation step before final delivery for the AA that will accept classes of &gt;60% accuracy with the intent of incorporating changes into the map from new information gained by the validation process prior to AA (Lea, communication, August 2009). This new direction supports the mapping/field efforts that were done at PINN. However the final Post AA database that was considered the final deliverable, did not use the &gt;60% accuracy threshold. Therefore, in order to provide the park with a vegetation database that retained more detail than the Post AA database but modifying the vegetation interpretation from the knowledge gained through the AA process, a third Post AA Park-Specific database has been created. This database maintains most of the original suballiance and association classes with modifications made based new information. Misintepretation trends brought out by the AA process were also considered.

The three deliverable databases to the Park are described below:
" 	Original Database - This is the pre-AA vegetation map database that was delivered in February 2008, as an interim product. This database has no modifications as a result of AA. The original database may have some useful information that the other databases will not have. It is recommended to archive the original database, but it is available when needed. There is no documentation to accompany the original database.
" 	Post AA Database - This database represents the modifications to the vegetation database as a result of AA. Changes are in the form of global recoding reflecting bumping up to higher hierarchical categories for most types that were &lt;80% producer accuracy. The purpose is to have a database with as many types &gt;80% producer accuracy as possible. Some types with accuracy 70-80% were left in as agreed to by the Park. This is the peer reviewed official database. The documentation in Vegetation Classification and Mapping Project Report, Pinnacles National Monument (Kittel, et. al., 2009) is for the Post AA Database, delivered in July 2009. Note that AA only applied to land within the park boundary and quarter mile buffer.
" 	Post AA Park-Specific Database - This can be considered a final working vegetation database in which polygons for selected types that are &lt;80% producer accuracy have been revisited and reviewed for linework and/or coding in order to improve the interpretations of the type based on information gained from the AA process. In order to assess the accuracy of this database a new AA effort would need to be conducted. In theory accuracy is improved, though not assessed, by applying information learned through the AA process. This document is provided to accompany the Post AA Park-Specific database. Descriptions have been modified in some cases to better reflect the mapping as a result of accuracy assessment information. Types above 60% were kept. If the total polygon count for a type was &lt;30 then all polygons were revisited and recoded as needed. If the polygon count was &gt;30 then a limited criteria such as low conifer density or low tree density were used for revisiting and recoding. In other cases a description modification was necessary. Refer to the Classification Modification Summary for the Post AA Park-Specific Vegetation Database (below) for a list of the changes made for each type.
</procdesc>
<procdate>20072009</procdate>
<proccont>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Edward Reyes</cntper>
<cntorg>Aerial Information Systems, Inc.</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntpos>Project Coordinator</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>physical address</addrtype>
<address>112 First Street</address>
<city>Redlands</city>
<state>California</state>
<postal>92373</postal>
<country>U.S.A</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(909) 793-9493</cntvoice>
<cntfax>(909) 798-4430</cntfax>
<cntemail>unknown</cntemail>
<hours>8:00am - 5:00pm M-F</hours>
</cntinfo>
</proccont>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>The shapefile was imported into a geodatabase by the USGS/CSS/Core Science Analytics and Synthesis.</procdesc>
<procdate>201301</procdate>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>Metadata imported.</procdesc>
<procdate>201301</procdate>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spdoinfo>
<direct>Vector</direct>
<ptvctinf>
<sdtsterm>
<sdtstype>G-Polygon</sdtstype>
<ptvctcnt>6346</ptvctcnt>
</sdtsterm>
</ptvctinf>
</spdoinfo>
<spref>
<horizsys>
<planar>
<gridsys>
<gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
<utm>
<utmzone>10</utmzone>
<transmer>
<sfctrmer>0.999600</sfctrmer>
<longcm>-123.000000</longcm>
<latprjo>0.000000</latprjo>
<feast>500000.000000</feast>
<fnorth>0.000000</fnorth>
</transmer>
</utm>
</gridsys>
<planci>
<plance>Coordinate Pair</plance>
<coordrep>
<absres>0.000100</absres>
<ordres>0.000100</ordres>
</coordrep>
<plandu>meters</plandu>
</planci>
</planar>
<geodetic>
<horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
<ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
<semiaxis>6378137.000000</semiaxis>
<denflat>298.257222</denflat>
</geodetic>
</horizsys>
</spref>
<eainfo>
<detailed>
<enttyp>
<enttypl>PINN_VegPolys</enttypl>
<enttypd>Feature class attribute table</enttypd>
<enttypds>see citation above</enttypds>
</enttyp>
<attr>
<attrlabl>OBJECTID</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Poly_ID</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Unique identifier for each polygon</attrdef>
<attrdefs>NPS</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Unique plot code.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>MapUnit_ID</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Code used to represent the Map Unit</attrdef>
<attrdefs>NPS</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Map unit code.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>MapUnit_Name</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Full Map Unit name</attrdef>
<attrdefs>NPS</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Map unit association common name.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>X_Centroid</attrlabl>
<attrdef>X Coordinate (UTM Easting) of the centroid of the polygon</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Easting coordinate.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Y_Centroid</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Y Coordinate (UTM Northing) of the centroid of the polygon</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Northing coordinate.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Acres</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Area (meters)</attrdef>
<attrdefs>XTools</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Hectares</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Perimeter (meters)</attrdef>
<attrdefs>XTools</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Shape_Length</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Length of feature in internal units.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SHAPE_Area</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Area of feature in internal units squared.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
</detailed>
<detailed>
<enttyp>
<enttypl>rc_VegPolys_tVegMapInfo</enttypl>
<enttypd>Defines relationship between Veg polygons and basic vegetation attributes</enttypd>
<enttypds>National Park Service</enttypds>
</enttyp>
</detailed>
<overview>
<eaover>
Vegetation PI codes:
1200	California Evergreen Coniferous Forest and Woodland Group
1210	Foothill Pine Woodland Alliance
1211	Foothill Pine/Chaparral Woodland Mapping Unit
1212	Foothill Pine/California Wild Buckwheat Alluvial Woodland Mapping Unit
1213	Foothill Pine/California Wild Buckwheat Thin Substrate Woodland Mapping Unit
1220	California Juniper Woodland Alliance
1221	California Juniper/Hollyleaf Cherry/Moss Woodland Association
1300	Southwestern North American Riparian Evergreen and Deciduous Forest Group
1301	Southwestern North American Riparian Evergreen and Deciduous Forest Group
1310	California Sycamore Temporarily Flooded Woodland Alliance
1311	California Sycamore-Coast Live Oak Woodland Association
2100	Californian Broadleaf Forest and Woodland Group [non-deciduous]
2101	Live Oak Woodland and Shrubland Mapping Unit
2110	Coast Live Oak Woodland Alliance
2112	Coast Live Oak/Annual Grass-Herb Woodland Association
2114	Coast Live Oak Alluvial Woodland Mapping Unit
2117	Coast Live Oak-Blue Oak Woodland Mapping Unit
2120	Interior Live Oak Woodland Alliance
2200	Californian Broadleaf Forest and Woodland Group [deciduous]
2210	Blue Oak Woodland Alliance
2211	Blue Oak/Chaparral/Grass Woodland Mapping Unit
2212	Blue Oak/Mixed Herbaceous Woodland Association
2213	Blue Oak-California Juniper Woodland Association
2216	Blue Oak-California Buckeye Woodland Mapping Unit
2217	Blue Oak-Foothill Pine Woodland Mapping Unit
2218	Blue Oak/Coastal Sage Scrub Woodland Mapping Unit
2220	California Buckeye Woodland Alliance
2230	Valley Oak Woodland Alliance
2231	Valley Oak-Coast Live Oak/Grass Woodland Association
2232	Valley Oak-Coast Live Oak/Mesic Grass Woodland Mapping Unit
3100	Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup
3101	Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Group
3102	Dry-Mesic Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit
3103	Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit
3104	Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit
3110	Chamise Shrubland Alliance
3113	Chamise-Black Sage Shrubland Association
3114	Chamise-Coastal Sage Scrub Shrubland Mapping Unit
3115	Chamise-California Wild Buckwheat Shrubland Mapping Unit
3150	Hollyleaf Cherry Shrubland Alliance
3160	California Scrub Oak Shrubland Alliance
3200	Evergreen Coastal Scrub Shrubland Group
3210	Coyote Brush Shrubland Alliance
3300	California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup [extended area]
3301	California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup
3310	California Sagebrush Shrubland Alliance
3330	California Wild Buckwheat Shrubland Alliance
3331	California Wild Buckwheat Alluvial Shrubland Mapping Unit
3332	California Wild Buckwheat Thin Substrate Shrubland Mapping Unit
3350	Silver Lupine Shrubland Alliance
3360	Black Sage Shrubland Alliance
3370	California Sagebrush-California Wild Buckwheat Shrubland Alliance
3400	Southwestern North American Riparian/Wash Scrub Shrubland Group
3401	Southwestern North American Riparian/Wash Scrub Shrubland Group
3410	California Wildrose Shrubland Alliance
3510	California Rose Shrubland Alliance
4001	Western North American Freshwater Marsh Herbaceous Vegetation Macrogroup [Extended Area]
4002	Mediterranean California Naturalized Annual and Perennial Grassland and Herbaceous Vegetation Macrogroup [Extended Area]
4003	Open to Sparse Grass on Rocky Thin Substrate Herbaceous Vegetation Mapping Unit
4004	Alluvial Herb and Shrub Vegetation Mapping Unit
4100	Western North America Freshwater Marsh Herbaceous Vegetation
4101	Bulrush-Cattails Herbaceous Vegetation Mapping Unit
4201	Western North American Wet Meadow and Low Shrub Carr Herbaceous Vegetation Macrogroup
4300	Mediterranean California Naturalized Annual and Perennial Grassland Herbaceous Vegetation Macrogroup
4310	Mediterranean California Naturalized Annual and Perennial Grassland and Herbaceous Vegetation Macrogroup
4401	Alluvial Herb and Shrub Vegetation Mapping Unit
4500	Western North America Wet Meadow and Low Shrub Carr Herbaceous Vegetation Macrogroup
4510	Deergrass Herbaceous Vegetation Alliance
9100	Built-up Mapping Unit
9200	Agriculture Mapping Unit
9420	Cliffs, Rock Outcrops, and Steep Eroded Slopes Mapping Unit
9430	Sparsely Vegetated to Non-vegetated Stream Beds and Flats Mapping Unit
9500	Water Mapping Unit
9600	Planted Trees &amp; Shrubs Mapping Unit
9700	Post Burn and Post Disturbance Undifferentiated Shrub and Grass-Herb Regeneration Mapping Unit
9710	Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit
9720	Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit
</eaover>
<eadetcit>Pinnacles National Monument Vegetation</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS/CSS/Core Science Analytics and Synthesis</cntorg>
<cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntper>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, MS 302</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>303-202-4219</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
<distliab>
The U.S. Geological Survey and the National Park Service shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.  These data and related graphics (if available) are not legal documents and are not intended to be used as such.

The information contained in these data is dynamic and may change over time.  The data are not better than the original sources from which they were derived.  It is the responsibility of the data user to use the data appropriately and consistent within the limitations of geospatial data in general and these data in particular.  Any related graphics (if available) are intended to aid the data user in acquiring relevant data; it is not approriate to use the related graphics as data.

The U.S. Geological Survey and the National Park Service gives no warranty, expressed or implied, as to the accuracy, reliability, or completeness of these data.  It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from an U.S. Geological Survey and National Park Service servers and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way.  Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the utility of the data on another system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data. Mention of trade names or commercial products in this metadata report does not constitute endorsement or recommendation for use by the U. S. Department of the Interior, U. S. Geological Survey and National Park Service.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>HTML</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://www.usgs.gov/core_science_systems/csas/vip/parks/pinn.html</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
<accinstr>Internet Access</accinstr>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20110902</metd>
<metrd>20130129</metrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS/CSS/Core Science Analytics and Synthesis</cntorg>
<cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntper>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, MS 302</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>303-202-4219</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
<metextns>
<onlink>http://www.usgs.gov/core_science_systems/csas/metadata/index.html</onlink>
</metextns>
</metainfo>
</metadata>