<metadata><Source>http://www1.usgs.gov/metadata/mdata/vip/metamorrfield.xml</Source>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Lesley Sneddon, NatureServe</origin>
        <origin>USGS/CSS/BIP/Center for Biological Informatics</origin>
        <pubdate>20071231</pubdate>
        <title>Morristown National Historical Park Vegetation Mapping Project - Field Plot and Accuracy Assessment Points</title>
        <edition>Plots V3.0</edition>
        <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
        <onlink>http://www1.usgs.gov/vip/morr/morrgeodata.zip</onlink>
        <lworkcit>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>L. Sneddon, R.E. Zaremba, E. Largay, G. Podniesinski, S. Perles, and J. Thompson</origin>
            <pubdate>200804</pubdate>
            <title>Vegetation Classification and Mapping of Morristown National Historical Park, New Jersey, Technical Report NPS/NER/NRTR--2008/116</title>
            <geoform>report</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Philadelphia, PA</pubplace>
              <publish>National Park Service</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://www.usgs.gov/core_science_systems/csas/vip/parks/morr.html</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </lworkcit>
        <onlink>doi:10.5066/F7WW7FMR</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The locations of vegetation classification sampling plots used to develop an association-level vegetation classification of Morristown National Historical Park by NatureServe for the National Park Service. Vegetation sampling was performed by NatureServe subcontractor Robert E. Zaremba.

The accuracy assessment points used to assess the association-level vegetation map of Morristown National Historical Park developed by NatureServe for the National Park Service. Accuracy assesement was performed by Stephanie Perles and Greg Podniesinski.</abstract>
      <purpose>The geodatabase shows point locations for vegetation classification sampling points and locations for accuracy assessment observation points. Locations were determined using a Garmin76C or Garmin GPS Map 76 gps unit.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Data were reformatted to match Plots V3.0 by the USGS/CSS/BIP/Center for Biological Informatics.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>200408</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>None planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Morristown National Historical Park and environs</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-74.563729</westbc>
        <eastbc>-74.511231</eastbc>
        <northbc>40.781278</northbc>
        <southbc>40.741432</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>National Park Service Theme Category Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>Vegetation</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
        <themekey>biota</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>vegetation</themekey>
        <themekey>vegetation map</themekey>
        <themekey>vegetation association</themekey>
        <themekey>vegetation alliance</themekey>
        <themekey>vegetation formation</themekey>
        <themekey>vegetation classification</themekey>
        <themekey>accuracy assessment</themekey>
        <themekey>observation point</themekey>
        <themekey>plot point</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>National Park System Unit Name Thesaurus</placekt>
        <placekey>Morristown National Historical Park</placekey>
      </place>
      <place>
        <placekt>National Park System Unit Code Thesaurus</placekt>
        <placekey>MORR</placekey>
      </place>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>Morristown National Historical Park</placekey>
      </place>
      <temporal>
        <tempkt>None</tempkt>
        <tempkey>2004</tempkey>
      </temporal>
    </keywords>
    <taxonomy>
      <keywtax>
        <taxonkt>None</taxonkt>
        <taxonkey>Standardized National Vegetation Classification System</taxonkey>
        <taxonkey>vegetation classification</taxonkey>
        <taxonkey>alliance</taxonkey>
        <taxonkey>community association</taxonkey>
      </keywtax>
      <taxoncl>
        <taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
        <taxonrv>Plantae</taxonrv>
      </taxoncl>
    </taxonomy>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Brian R. Mitchell</cntper>
          <cntorg>National Park Service</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Inventory and Monitoring Coordinator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
          <address>Northeast Temperate Network</address>
          <address>National Park Service</address>
          <address>54 Elm Street</address>
          <city>Woodstock</city>
          <state>VT</state>
          <postal>05091</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>802-457-3368 x37</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>802-457-3405</cntfax>
        <cntemail>brian_r_mitchell@nps.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <browse>
      <browsen>http://www1.usgs.gov/vip/morr/morrplots.pdf</browsen>
      <browsed>Locations of vegetation plots; low resolution for web browsing.</browsed>
      <browset>PDF</browset>
    </browse>
    <native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.1.3500</native>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <logic>ESRI point geometry</logic>
    <complete>Point locations for all 22 plots and 73 accuracy assessment are included</complete>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Within each polygon selected for sampling, a plot was established in an area that was most representative of the existing vegetation association (Mueller-Dombois and Ellenberg 1974).  All vegetation data were collected following NatureServe's accepted natural heritage sampling protocols (Strakosch-Walz 2000), with 20-m x 20-m plots in forests and woodlands, 10-m x 10-m plots in shrublands, and 5-m x 5-m plots in herbaceous vegetation.  In some cases, where the polygons were too narrow to reasonably accommodate standard plot sizes, the plots were adjusted accordingly, e.g., rectangular plots rather than square plots were used to accommodate linear stands.

Plot forms used in this project are shown in the technical report (Appendix B) cited above (see Larger Work Citation).  Abbreviated instructions for completing this form and definitions of the fields can be found in the NBS/NPS Vegetation Mapping Program: Field Methods for Vegetation Mapping manual (The Nature Conservancy and Environmental Systems Research Institute 1994b).  The vegetation was visually divided into eight strata: emergent trees (variable height), tree canopy (variable height), tree subcanopy (&gt;5m in height), tall shrub (2-5m), short shrub (&lt;2m), herbaceous, non-vascular, and vines.  The percent cover was estimated for each species in each stratum using modified Braun - Blanquet cover classes (Strakosch-Walz 2000).  Specimens of species that were not identifiable in the field were collected for later identification.  In addition to floristic information, the following environmental variables were recorded at each plot: slope, aspect, topographic position, hydrologic regime, soil stoniness, average soil texture, and soil drainage.  Any unvegetated area of the plot was characterized by the exposed substrate.  Notes were taken on the plot representativeness of the surrounding vegetation and any other significant environmental information, such as landscape context, herbivory, stand health, recent disturbance, or evidence of historic disturbance.  The vegetation profile and topographic position were sketched in cross-section to represent the location and setting of the plot.  A digital photograph of each plot was also taken.  The location of each plot was recorded with a global positioning system (GPS) unit, with the datum set to North American 1983 (Conus) and the coordinate system set to Universal Trans-Mercator (UTM) zone 18.

Plot sampling was conducted in the summers of 2003 and 2004 by NatureServe subcontractor ecologist, Robert Zaremba.  In total, 22 plots were sampled throughout Morristown National Historical Park.  All vegetation types were sampled over a range of environmental variables. Vegetation sampling was limited to the Jockey Hollow portion of the park. Plot forms were crosswalked to the National Vegetation Classification System by NatureServe's Senior Regional Ecologist, Lesley Sneddon.</procdesc>
        <procdate>2003-2004</procdate>
        <proccont>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntper>Lesley Sneddon</cntper>
              <cntorg>NatureServe</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Senior Regional Ecologist, East</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
              <address>11 Avenue de Lafayette, 5th floor</address>
              <city>Boston</city>
              <state>MA</state>
              <postal>02111</postal>
              <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>617-542-1908 x 245</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>617-542-1620</cntfax>
            <cntemail>lesley_sneddon@natureserve.org</cntemail>
          </cntinfo>
        </proccont>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Thematic accuracy of the association-level vegetation map for Morristown National Historical Park was assessed following the USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program protocols (TNC and ESRI 1994). Sampling was restricted to Jockey Hollow and New Jersey Brigade units. Accuracy assessment was not conducted in either the Fort Nonsense or Washington's Headquarters units due to their small size, homogeneity, and similarity to the two larger units. A stratified random sampling approach was used, distributing the sampling effort across 13 mapped associations. Polygons attributed with land use codes were not included in the accuracy assessment sampling design. In total, 73 thematic accuracy assessment sampling points were placed throughout the association-level map

During August 2005, each accuracy assessment point was located in the field using either a Garmin 76C or Garmin GPS map 76 unit. The datum on the GPS units was set to North American 1983 (Conus) and the coordinate system was set to Universal Trans-Mercator (UTM) zone 18. The vegetation association at the point was then determined using the dichotomous key and the detailed vegetation descriptions.  The minimum area of observation around the sampling point was a circle with a radius of 50 m. The dominant plant species in each stratum, environmental attributes, surrounding vegetation associations, rationale for classification and other comments were noted on a field form.  After field work was completed, data from the 73 accuracy assessment points were entered into the NatureServe PLOTS 2.0 Database System on a Microsoft Access platform.  Vegetation associations were identified using the vegetation key developed for the park. AA results were analyzed using a sample misclassification matrix. Overall accuracy, Kappa index and 90% confidence intervals were calculated according to the Accuracy Assessment Procedures-USGS-NPS Vegetation Mappiong Program manual (The Nature Conservancy 1994).</procdesc>
        <procdate>2005</procdate>
        <proccont>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntper>Greg Podneisinski</cntper>
              <cntorg>Pennsylvania Natural Heritage Program</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Inventory and Assessment Manager</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
              <address>Western Pennsylvania Conservancy 208 Airport Drive</address>
              <city>Middletown</city>
              <state>PA</state>
              <postal>17057</postal>
              <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>(717) 948-3959</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>(717) 948-3957</cntfax>
            <cntemail>gpodniesinski@paconserve.org</cntemail>
          </cntinfo>
        </proccont>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Data were reformatted using Plots V3.0, and then the shapefiles and the data was imported into a geodatabase by the USGS/CSS/BIP/Center for Biological Informatics.</procdesc>
        <procdate>201102</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Metadata imported.</procdesc>
        <procdate>201102</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Vector</direct>
    <ptvctinf>
      <sdtsterm>
        <sdtstype>Entity point</sdtstype>
        <ptvctcnt>95</ptvctcnt>
      </sdtsterm>
    </ptvctinf>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>18</utmzone>
            <transmer>
              <sfctrmer>0.999600</sfctrmer>
              <longcm>-75.000000</longcm>
              <latprjo>0.000000</latprjo>
              <feast>500000.000000</feast>
              <fnorth>0.000000</fnorth>
            </transmer>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
          <coordrep>
            <absres>0.000100</absres>
            <ordres>0.000100</ordres>
          </coordrep>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
        <ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.000000</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257222</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>MORR_VegPoints</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Feature class attribute table</enttypd>
        <enttypds>National Park Service</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>OBJECTID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Plot_Code</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Unique identifier for this Accuracy Assessment, Observation or Plot point</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Plots V3.0</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Unique plot number.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Pnts_Type</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Point type (accuracy assessment point, observation point or plot point)</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Plots V3.0</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Accuracy Assessment Point</edomv>
            <edomvd>AA Point</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Plots V3.0</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Observation Point</edomv>
            <edomvd>Observation Point</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Plots V3.0</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Plot Point</edomv>
            <edomvd>Plot Point</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Plots V3.0</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>X_Coord</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>X Coordinate (UTM Easting)</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Plots V3.0</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Easting coordinate.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Y_Coord</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Y Coordinate (UTM Northing)</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Plots v3.0</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Northing coordinate.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>rc_VegPoints_tAA_tPlots</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Relationship Class</enttypd>
        <enttypds>National Park Service</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>USGS/CSS/Core Science Analytics and Synthesis</cntorg>
          <cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Characterization Program Coordinator</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, MS 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>Colorado</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>(303) 202-4219</cntfax>
        <cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc>Downloadable data</resdesc>
    <distliab>The U.S. Geological Survey and the National Park Service shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.  These data and related graphics (if available) are not legal documents and are not intended to be used as such.

The information contained in these data is dynamic and may change over time.  The data are not better than the original sources from which they were derived.  It is the responsibility of the data user to use the data appropriately and consistent within the limitations of geospatial data in general and these data in particular.  Any related graphics (if available) are intended to aid the data user in acquiring relevant data; it is not approriate to use the related graphics as data.

The U.S. Geological Survey and the National Park Service gives no warranty, expressed or implied, as to the accuracy, reliability, or completeness of these data.  It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from an U.S. Geological Survey and National Park Service servers and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way.  Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the utility of the data on another system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data. Mention of trade names or commercial products in this metadata report does not constitute endorsement or recommendation for use by the U. S. Department of the Interior, U. S. Geological Survey and National Park Service.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>HTML</formname>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://www.usgs.gov/core_science_systems/csas/vip/parks/morr.html</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
            <accinstr>Internet Access</accinstr>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20080604</metd>
    <metrd>20110225</metrd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>USGS/CSS/Core Science Analytics and Synthesis</cntorg>
          <cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Characterization Program Coordinator</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, MS 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>Colorado</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>303-202-4219</cntfax>
        <cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.usgs.gov/core_science_systems/csas/metadata/index.html</onlink>
    </metextns>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>