<metadata><Source>http://www1.usgs.gov/metadata/mdata/vip/metasagafield.xml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Sue Gawler, NatureServe</origin>
<origin>USGS/CSS/Core Science Analytics and Synthesis</origin>
<pubdate>200412</pubdate>
<title>Saint-Gaudens National Historic Site Vegetation Mapping Project - Field Plots and Accuracy Assessment Points</title>
<edition>Plots V3.2</edition>
<geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
<onlink>http://www1.usgs.gov/vip/saga/sagageodata.zip</onlink>
<onlink>doi:10.5066/F75D8PSX</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>This geodatabase includes the locations of vegetation classification sampling plots and accuracy assessment points used to develop an association-level Vegetation classification of Saint-Gaudens National Historic Site for the National Park Service. Vegetation sampling was performed by Peter Bowman. Accuracy assesement was performed by Sue Gawler from NatureServe.</abstract>
<purpose>The shapefile depicts point locations of vegetation classification sampling points  and point locations for accuracy assessment observation points. Plot locations were recorded with a WAAS-enabled GPS unit. A GPSMap60CSX unit was programmed with coordinates of the selected accuracy assessment sampling locations.</purpose>
<supplinf>Data were reformatted to match Plots V3.2 by the USGS/CSS/Core Science Analytics and Synthesis.</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>200409</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>ground condition</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>None planned</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<descgeog>Saint-Gaudens National Historic Site and environs</descgeog>
<bounding>
<westbc>-72.380129</westbc>
<eastbc>-72.365661</eastbc>
<northbc>43.502717</northbc>
<southbc>43.490721</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>National Park Service Theme Category Thesaurus</themekt>
<themekey>Vegetation</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
<themekey>biota</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>none</themekt>
<themekey>Vegetation Map</themekey>
<themekey>Association level</themekey>
<themekey>Vegetation Classification</themekey>
<themekey>vegetation plots</themekey>
<themekey>thematic accuracy assessment</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>National Park System Unit Name Thesaurus</placekt>
<placekey>Saint-Gaudens National Historic Site</placekey>
</place>
<place>
<placekt>National Park System Unit Code Thesaurus</placekt>
<placekey>SAGA</placekey>
</place>
<place>
<placekt>none</placekt>
<placekey>Saint-Gaudens National Historic Site</placekey>
<placekey>Cornish</placekey>
<placekey>New Hampshire</placekey>
</place>
<temporal>
<tempkt>none</tempkt>
<tempkey>2004</tempkey>
</temporal>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>None</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>Standardized National Vegetation Classification System</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>vegetation classification</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>alliance</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>community association</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Plantae</taxonrv>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>None</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Sue Gawler</cntper>
<cntorg>NatureServe</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntpos>Regional Ecologist</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
<address>256 Gupthill Road</address>
<city>Belgrade</city>
<state>ME</state>
<postal>04917</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>207.495.3513</cntvoice>
<cntfax>207.495.3444</cntfax>
<cntemail>sue_gawler@natureserve.org</cntemail>
<hours>9am-5pm</hours>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
<browse>
<browsen>http://www1.usgs.gov/vip/saga/sagaplots.pdf</browsen>
<browsed>Locations of vegetation plots; low resolution for web browsing.</browsed>
<browset>PDF</browset>
</browse>
<browse>
<browsen>http://www1.usgs.gov/vip/saga/sagaaa.pdf</browsen>
<browsed>Locations of thematic accuracy assessment sites; low resolution for web browsing.</browsed>
<browset>PDF</browset>
</browse>
<crossref>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Susan C. Gawler, NatureServe</origin>
<origin>Peter S. Bowman, New Hampshire Natural Heritage Bureau</origin>
<pubdate>201205</pubdate>
<title>Vegetation Classification and Mapping of Saint-Gaudens National Historic Site, New Hampshire</title>
<geoform>Report</geoform>
<othercit>Natural Resource Technical Report NPS/NER/NRTR--2012/584.1</othercit>
<onlink>http://www.usgs.gov/core_science_systems/csas/vip/parks/saga.html</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</crossref>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<logic>Dataset contains no duplicate features.</logic>
<complete>Point locations for all 25 plots and 17 accuracy assessments are included. Each accuracy assessment point is representaed by one point in the shapefile. All points fall within vegetation association polygons.</complete>
<lineage>
<procstep>
<procdesc>
Twenty-five vegetation plots were sampled for this vegetation project during August and September of 2004. Field survey methodology followed the standards of the USGS/NPS Vegetation Mapping Program (http://biology.usgs.gov/npsveg/), using NatureServe field forms adapted for the project.  At least three vegetation plots were placed in each type identified in the reconnaissance, except where limited spatial extent prevented it. Areas classified as Anderson Level II (modified) categories were not sampled. The plot data collection was carried out by Pete Bowman. Vegetation structure is documented as total cover, stratum height, and characteristic species for each stratum. Then, segregated by stratum, each species' cover was recorded in the applicable cover class, as the class midpoint. A seven-class cover scale was used. Data also included diameter at breast height (dbh) measurements for trees in the plot. Additional data were collected on landscape position, adjacent vegetation types, presence and abundance of non-native invasive species, and disturbance types. Because of archaeological restrictions within the park, soil disturbances are not permitted, and information collected on soils was limited to what was visible at the surface. Digital photographs were taken of most vegetation associations. The location of each plot was recorded with a global positioning system (GPS) unit, with the datum set to North American 1983 (Conus) and the coordinate system set to Universal Trans-Mercator (UTM) zone 18. The GPS unit was WAAS (Wide-Area Augmentation System) enabled and provided real-time differential correction.

Vegetation association-level data recorded in the plot forms were crosswalked to the US National Vegetaiton Classification System by NatureServe'sRegional Ecologist, Sue Gawler in 2004.
</procdesc>
<procdate>2004</procdate>
<proccont>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Peter Bowman</cntper>
<cntorg>New Hampshire Natural Heritage Bureau</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntpos>Ecologist</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
<address>P.O. Box 1856</address>
<city>Concord</city>
<state>NH</state>
<postal>03301</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(603) 271-3623 x427</cntvoice>
<cntemail>pbowman@dred.state.nh.us</cntemail>
<hours>9-5</hours>
</cntinfo>
</proccont>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>
Thematic accuracy has several objectives including to asssess the data's suitability for a particular application, to inform the map producers to learn more about data errors and improve the mapping process, and conform to production standards.

Accuracy assessment (AA) sampling design followed the guidelines provided in the NPS Vegetation Mapping Program (The Nature Conservancy 1994) manuals with respect to the number of AA points sampled and their distribution across park polygons. The sampling design called for  20 points during the 2006 field season. AA sampling coordinates were selected by generating random points within the minimum and maximum easting and northing UTM coordinates of the park's extent.  During October 2006, 17 accuracy assessment point was located in the field using a GPSMap60CSX unit. Points were then buffered at a distance of 10 meters from the polygon border to exclude ecotonal areas that may be of ambiguous classification.The datum on the GPS units was set to North American 1983 (Conus) and the coordinate system was set to Universal Trans-Mercator (UTM) zone 18. The vegetation association at the point was then determined using the dichotomous key and the detailed vegetation descriptions.  The dominant plant species in each stratum, environmental attributes, surrounding vegetation associations, rationale for classification and other comments were noted on a field form.  After field work was completed, data from the 17 accuracy assessment points were entered into the NatureServe PLOTS 2.0 Database System on a Microsoft Access platform.  Vegetation associations were identified using the vegetation key developed for the park. AA results were analyzed using a sample missclassification matrix. Overall accuracy and Kappa index were calculated following the Accuracy Assessment Procedures-USGS/NPS Vegetation Mappiong Program manual (The Nature Conservancy 1994).
</procdesc>
<procdate>2006</procdate>
<proccont>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Sue Gawler</cntper>
<cntorg>NatureServe</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntpos>Regional Vegetation Ecologist</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>256 Gupthill Road</address>
<city>Belgrade</city>
<state>ME</state>
<postal>04917</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>207.495.3513</cntvoice>
<cntfax>207.495.3444</cntfax>
<cntemail>sue_gawler@natureserve.org</cntemail>
<hours>9-5</hours>
</cntinfo>
</proccont>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>Data were reformatted using Plots V3.2, and then the Shapefiles and the data was imported into a geodatabase by the USGS/CSS/Core Science Analytics and Synthesis.</procdesc>
<procdate>201212</procdate>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>Metadata imported.</procdesc>
<procdate>201212</procdate>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spdoinfo>
<direct>Vector</direct>
<ptvctinf>
<sdtsterm>
<sdtstype>Entity point</sdtstype>
<ptvctcnt>42</ptvctcnt>
</sdtsterm>
</ptvctinf>
</spdoinfo>
<spref>
<horizsys>
<planar>
<gridsys>
<gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
<utm>
<utmzone>18</utmzone>
<transmer>
<sfctrmer>0.999600</sfctrmer>
<longcm>-75.000000</longcm>
<latprjo>0.000000</latprjo>
<feast>500000.000000</feast>
<fnorth>0.000000</fnorth>
</transmer>
</utm>
</gridsys>
<planci>
<plance>coordinate pair</plance>
<coordrep>
<absres>0.000001</absres>
<ordres>0.000001</ordres>
</coordrep>
<plandu>meters</plandu>
</planci>
</planar>
<geodetic>
<horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
<ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
<semiaxis>6378137.000000</semiaxis>
<denflat>298.257222</denflat>
</geodetic>
</horizsys>
</spref>
<eainfo>
<detailed>
<enttyp>
<enttypl>SAGA_VegPoints</enttypl>
<enttypd>Attribute table for shapefile of vegetation classification sample plot locations for Saint-Gaudens National Historic Site</enttypd>
<enttypds>NatureServe</enttypds>
</enttyp>
<attr>
<attrlabl>OBJECTID</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Plot_Code</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Unique identifier for this Accuracy Assessment, Observation or Plot point</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Plots V3.2</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Unique plot number.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Pnts_Type</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Point type (accuracy assessment point, observation point or plot point)</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Plots V3.2</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Accuracy Assessment Point</edomv>
<edomvd>AA Point</edomvd>
<edomvds>Plots V3.2</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Observation Point</edomv>
<edomvd>Observation Point</edomvd>
<edomvds>Plots V3.2</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Plot Point</edomv>
<edomvd>Plot Point</edomvd>
<edomvds>Plots V3.2</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>X_Coord</attrlabl>
<attrdef>X Coordinate (UTM Easting)</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Plots V3.2</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Easting coordinate.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Y_Coord</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Y Coordinate (UTM Northing)</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Plots V3.0</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Northing coordinate.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
</detailed>
<detailed>
<enttyp>
<enttypl>rc_VegPoints_tAA_tPlots</enttypl>
<enttypd>Defines relationship between Veg points and basic AA/plot attributes</enttypd>
<enttypds>National Park Service</enttypds>
</enttyp>
</detailed>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS/CSS/Core Science Analytics and Synthesis</cntorg>
<cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntper>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, MS 302</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>303-202-4219</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
<distliab>
The U.S. Geological Survey and the National Park Service shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.  These data and related graphics (if available) are not legal documents and are not intended to be used as such.

The information contained in these data is dynamic and may change over time.  The data are not better than the original sources from which they were derived.  It is the responsibility of the data user to use the data appropriately and consistent within the limitations of geospatial data in general and these data in particular.  Any related graphics (if available) are intended to aid the data user in acquiring relevant data; it is not approriate to use the related graphics as data.

The U.S. Geological Survey and the National Park Service gives no warranty, expressed or implied, as to the accuracy, reliability, or completeness of these data.  It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from an U.S. Geological Survey and National Park Service servers and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way.  Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the utility of the data on another system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data. Mention of trade names or commercial products in this metadata report does not constitute endorsement or recommendation for use by the U. S. Department of the Interior, U. S. Geological Survey and National Park Service.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>HTML</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://www.usgs.gov/core_science_systems/csas/vip/parks/saga.html</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
<accinstr>Internet Access</accinstr>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20090904</metd>
<metrd>20121217</metrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS/CSS/Core Science Analytics and Synthesis</cntorg>
<cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntper>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, MS 302</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>303-202-4219</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
<metextns>
<onlink>http://www.usgs.gov/core_science_systems/csas/metadata/index.html</onlink>
</metextns>
</metainfo>
</metadata>