<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>U.S. Geological Survey, Core Science Analytics and Synthesis, Gap Analysis Program, Kevin Gergely</origin>
        <pubdate>201305</pubdate>
        <title>U.S. Geological Survey Gap Analysis Program</title>
        <geoform>Maps and Data</geoform>
        <onlink>http://gapanalysis.usgs.gov/</onlink>
        <onlink>http://gapanalysis.usgs.gov/padus/</onlink>
        <onlink>http://gapanalysis.usgs.gov/gaplandcover/</onlink>
        <onlink>http://gapanalysis.usgs.gov/species/</onlink>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F76971K8</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The Gap Analysis Program (GAP) is an element of the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). GAP helps to implement the Department of Interior?s goals of inventory, monitoring, research, and information transfer. GAP has three primary goals:

1	Identify conservation gaps that help keep common species common;

2	Provide conservation information to the public so that informed resource management decisions can be made; and

3	Facilitate the application of GAP data and analysis to specific resource management activities.


To implement these goals, GAP carries out the following objectives:

--Map the land cover of the United States

--Map predicted distributions of vertebrate species for the U.S.

--Map the location, ownership and stewardship of protected areas

--Document the representation of vertebrate species and land cover types in areas managed for the long-term maintenance of biodiversity

--Provide this information to the public and those entities charged with land use research, policy, planning, and management

--Build institutional cooperation in the application of this information to state and regional management activities.

GAP provides the following data and web services:

The Protected Areas Database of the United States (PAD-US) is a geodatabase that illustrates and describes public land ownership, management and other conservation lands, including voluntarily provided privately protected areas. The PADUS GAP Status Layer web service can be found at http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/gap/PADUS_Status/MapServer .

The Land Cover Data creates a seamless data set for the contiguous United States from the four regional Gap Analysis Projects and the LANDFIRE project. The Raster data in both ArcGIS Grid and ERDAS Imagine format is available for download at http://gis1.usgs.gov/csas/gap/viewer/land_cover/Map.aspx . In addition to the raster datasets the data is available in Web Mapping Services (WMS) format for each of the six NVC classification levels (Class, Subclass, Formation, Division, Macrogroup, Ecological System) at the following links. http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/gap/GAP_Land_Cover_NVC_Class_Landuse/MapServer http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/gap/GAP_Land_Cover_NVC_Subclass_Landuse/MapServer http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/gap/GAP_Land_Cover_NVC_Formation_Landuse/MapServer http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/gap/GAP_Land_Cover_NVC_Division_Landuse/MapServer http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/gap/GAP_Land_Cover_NVC_Macrogroup_Landuse/MapServer http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/gap/GAP_Land_Cover_Ecological_Systems_Landuse/MapServer 

The GAP species range data show a coarse representation of the total areal extent of a species or the geographic limits within which a species can be found (Morrison and Hall 2002). The GAP species distribution models represent the areas where species are predicted to occur based on habitat associations. A full report documenting the parameters used in each species model can be found via: http://gis1.usgs.gov/csas/gap/viewer/species/Map.aspx Web map services for species distribution models can be accessed from: http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/NAT_Species_Birds http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/NAT_Species_Mammals http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/NAT_Species_Amphibians http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/NAT_Species_Reptiles A table listing all of GAP's available web map services can be found here: http://gapanalysis.usgs.gov/species/data/web-map-services/</abstract>
      <purpose>The USGS Gap Analysis Program (GAP) grew out of biologists? response to the need to complement species-by-species management in dealing with widespread habitat loss. A new approach was needed that could provide clear, geographically-explicit information on the distribution of native vertebrate species, their habitat preferences, and their management status, in order to determine ?gaps? in biodiversity protection.</purpose>
      <supplinf>1. Protected Areas Database citation:  
US Geological Survey, Gap Analysis Program (GAP). November 2012. Protected Areas Database of the United States (PADUS), version 1.3 Combined Feature Class.  http://gapanalysis.usgs.gov/padus/data/ 

2. Land Cover Data citation:  
U.S. Geological Survey, Gap Analysis Program (GAP). May 2011. National Land Cover, Version 2.  http://gapanalysis.usgs.gov/gaplandcover/data/ 

3. Species Data citation - Range Maps: U.S. Geological Survey, Gap Analysis Program
(GAP). 2011. National GAP vertebrate species range data.
http://gapanalysis.usgs.gov/species

4. Species Data citation - Distribution models: U.S. Geological Survey, Gap Analysis Program (GAP). 2011.
National GAP vertebrate species distribution model.
http://gapanalysis.usgs.gov/species</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>1989</begdate>
          <enddate>2013</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>In work</progress>
      <update>As needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>continental United States, Alaska &amp; Hawaii</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-178</westbc>
        <eastbc>-66</eastbc>
        <northbc>70</northbc>
        <southbc>17</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>biodiversity</themekey>
        <themekey>conservation</themekey>
        <themekey>Gap Analysis</themekey>
        <themekey>land cover</themekey>
        <themekey>vegetation</themekey>
        <themekey>species</themekey>
        <themekey>species range</themekey>
        <themekey>species distribution model</themekey>
        <themekey>predicted distribution</themekey>
        <themekey>predicted habitat</themekey>
        <themekey>habitat modeling</themekey>
        <themekey>protected areas</themekey>
        <themekey>protection status</themekey>
        <themekey>land stewardship</themekey>
        <themekey>land ownership</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>United States</placekey>
        <placekey>Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Hawaii</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from the U.S. Geological Survey Gap Analysis Program server, and not indirectly through other sources, which may have changed the data in some way. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the individual metadata files associated with these data. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein. All information is created with a specific end use or uses in mind. This is especially true for GIS data, which is expensive to produce and must be directed to meet the immediate program needs.

Appropriate uses of the data: primarily as a coarse map for a large area such as a county or to provide context for finer-level maps.

The digital land cover dataset may be used for various purposes with user?s discretion. Specifically, this dataset was created for regional terrestrial biodiversity assessment. These data are not intended to be used at scales larger than 1:100,000.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Dr. Kevin Gergely</cntper>
          <cntorg>USGS Core Science Systems, Core Science Analytics and Synthesis, Gap Analysis Program</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>National Program Manager</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>970 Lusk Street</address>
          <city>Boise</city>
          <state>ID</state>
          <postal>83706</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>208-426-5219</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>gergely@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <browse>
      <browsen>http://www.usgs.gov/core_science_systems/csas/images/gap2.jpg</browsen>
      <browsed>Thumbnail of GAP graphic. (92px x 112px). Source from Core Science Analytics and Synthesis (CSAS) page. URL http://www.usgs.gov/core_science_systems/csas/activities.html</browsed>
      <browset>JPG</browset>
    </browse>
    <datacred>The USGS Gap Analysis Program supports and relies on cooperative effort among regional, state, tribal and federal agencies, academic and non-governmental institutions, and other private groups as well as the mission areas of the U.S. Geological Survey. More than 500 different state, federal, local, and private organizations participate.  Cooperating agencies currently include:


Federal Agencies:


-EPA ? Environmental Protection Agency

-DOD ? Department of Defense

-NPS ? National Park Service

-BLM ? Bureau of Land Management

-USFS ? United States Forest Service

-USFWS ? United States Fish and Wildlife Service

-USGS ? United States Geological Survey





State Partnerships

-GAP coordinates with scores of state resource and
other agencies on a variety of data and analysis projects.

--PAD-US GRANTS:   As part of our Protected Areas Database of the United States (PAD-US), GAP initiated in 2010 a program of grant support to selected states. These grants support partners (PAD-US Stewards) in these states in their efforts to improve protected areas data.  



Non-Governmental Organizations:

-The Nature Conservancy

-Defenders of Wildlife

-Association of Fish and Wildlife Agencies

-GreenInfo Network

-National Conservation Easement Database consortium</datacred>
    <native>ArcInfo Geodatabase; 
IMG file; 
ESRI Grid file;
web services; 
tabular digital data; 
Native data set environment for Land Cover data: Microsoft Windows Server 2008 R2 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; ESRI ArcGIS 10.0.2.3200; 
Native Data Set Environment for Species data: Microsoft Windows 7, ESRI ArcCatalog 10.0
Native data set environment for Protected Areas Database: Microsoft Windows 7, ESRI ArcCatalog 10.0;</native>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Land cover data: Accuracy assessments have been conducted for part of the Northwestern United States and the Southwestern United States.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>Not available</logic>
    <complete>Land cover data: All cells within the continental United States have been assigned an Ecological System or land use Value and description. Work is ongoing to improve country wide consistancy in the class assignment process.</complete>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>No process steps have been described for this project,</procdesc>
        <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Dr. Kevin Gergely</cntper>
          <cntorg>USGS Core Science Systems, Core Science Analytics and Synthesis</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>National Program Manager</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>970 Lusk Street</address>
          <city>Boise</city>
          <state>ID</state>
          <postal>83706</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>208-426-5219</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>gergely@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>N/A</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>PADUS GAP Status Layer web service</formname>
          <formcont>Protected Areas Database of the United States (PADUS) version 1.3 GAP Status. The Protected Areas Database of the United States (PAD-US) is a geodatabase that illustrates and describes public land ownership, management and conservation lands nationally, including voluntarily provided privately protected areas. The lands included in PAD-US are assigned conservation measures that qualify their intent to manage lands for the preservation of biological diversity and to other natural, recreational and cultural uses; managed for these purposes through legal or other effective means. The geodatabase includes: 1) Geographic boundaries of public land ownership and voluntarily provided private conservation lands (e.g., Nature Conservancy Preserves); 2) The combination land owner, land manager, management designation or type, parcel name, GIS Acres and source of geographic information of each mapped land unit 3) GAP Status Code conservation measure of each parcel based on USGS National Gap Analysis Program (GAP) protection level categories which provide a measurement of management intent for long-term biodiversity conservation 4) IUCN category for a protected area's inclusion into UNEP-World Conservation Monitoring Centre's World Database for Protected Areas. IUCN protected areas are defined as, "A clearly defined geographical space, recognized, dedicated and managed, through legal or other effective means, to achieve the long-term conservation of nature with associated ecosystem services and cultural values" and are categorized following a classification scheme available through USGS GAP; 5) World Database of Protected Areas (WDPA) Site Codes linking the multiple parcels of a single protected area in PAD-US and connecting them to the Global Community. PAD-US version 1.2 updates include: 1) National Park Service (NPS) boundaries and GAP Status Code review in cooperation with NPScape and NPS Lands. 2) Department of Defense (DOD) boundaries in cooperation with DOD Partners in Flight 3) Official (member and eligible only) Marine Protected Areas as aggregated and accepted by the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA). 4)The Bureau of Land Management's (BLM) National Landscape Conservation System (NLCS) authoritative boundaries in cooperation with NLCS policy representitives and the Lands Division. Note: NLCS National Trails and Wild and Scenic Rivers were not updated as they are managed as Line files; however, PADUS already contained many of these protected areas. 5) Modified or newly created Wilderness Area boundaries created by The Omnibus Public Lands Act of 2009 in cooperation with Wilderness.net. 6) Protected areas in The US Virgin Islands 7) Protected areas in the Pacific Islands (Micronesia) 8) Washington Department of Fish and Wildlife protected areas The mission of the USGS Gap Analysis Program (GAP) is to provide state, regional and national assessments of the conservation status of native vertebrate species and natural land cover types and to facilitate the application of this information to land management activities. The PAD-US geodatabase is required to organize and assess the management status (i.e. apply GAP Status Codes) of elements of biodiversity protection. The goal of GAP is to keep common species common by identifying species and plant communities not adequately represented in existing conservation lands. Common species are those not currently threatened with extinction. By identifying their habitats, Gap Analysis gives land managers and policy makers the information they need to make better-informed decisions when identifying priority areas for conservation. In cooperation with UNEP-World Conservation Monitoring Centre, GAP ensures PAD-US also supports global analyses and policy decisions by maintaining World Database for Protected Areas (WDPA) Site Codes and data for International Union for the Conservation of Nature (IUCN) categorized protected areas in the United States. The USGS National Gap Analysis Program (GAP) aggregated the Protected Areas Database of the United States version 1.2 (PAD-US v1.1) with significant contributions from the Bureau of Land Management, The US Forest Service, GreenInfo Network, Applied Geographics and The Nature Conservancy, who provided a spatial dataset of public and private lands and waters secured by a conservation situation that includes an explicit level of security from future conversion and current incompatible uses. These are spatial data from TNC's Conservation Lands System (CLS) database, which is the legal database of record for all TNC land transactions (fee, easement, lease and deed restrictions). GAP seeks to increase the efficiency and accuracy of PAD-US updates by leveraging resources in protected areas data aggregation and maintenance as described in "A Map of the Future", published following the PAD-US Design Project (July, 2009) available from:http://www.protectedlands.net/. Download the full FGDC metadata record ftp://ftp.gap.uidaho.edu/outgoing/PADUS1_2/LayerFiles/PADUS1_2_metadata_html.html.</formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/gap/PADUS_Status/MapServer</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>PADUS Ownership Layer web service</formname>
          <formcont>Protected Areas Database of the United States (PADUS) version 1.3. Protected Area Owner Name. The Protected Areas Database of the United States (PAD-US) is a geodatabase that illustrates and describes public land ownership, management and conservation lands nationally, including voluntarily provided privately protected areas. The lands included in PAD-US are assigned conservation measures that qualify their intent to manage lands for the preservation of biological diversity and to other natural, recreational and cultural uses; managed for these purposes through legal or other effective means. The geodatabase includes: 1) Geographic boundaries of public land ownership and voluntarily provided private conservation lands (e.g., Nature Conservancy Preserves); 2) The combination land owner, land manager, management designation or type, parcel name, GIS Acres and source of geographic information of each mapped land unit 3) GAP Status Code conservation measure of each parcel based on USGS National Gap Analysis Program (GAP) protection level categories which provide a measurement of management intent for long-term biodiversity conservation 4) IUCN category for a protected area's inclusion into UNEP-World Conservation Monitoring Centre's World Database for Protected Areas. IUCN protected areas are defined as, "A clearly defined geographical space, recognized, dedicated and managed, through legal or other effective means, to achieve the long-term conservation of nature with associated ecosystem services and cultural values" and are categorized following a classification scheme available through USGS GAP; 5) World Database of Protected Areas (WDPA) Site Codes linking the multiple parcels of a single protected area in PAD-US and connecting them to the Global Community. PAD-US version 1.2 updates include: 1) National Park Service (NPS) boundaries and GAP Status Code review in cooperation with NPScape and NPS Lands. 2) Department of Defense (DOD) boundaries in cooperation with DOD Partners in Flight 3) Official (member and eligible only) Marine Protected Areas as aggregated and accepted by the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA). 4)The Bureau of Land Management's (BLM) National Landscape Conservation System (NLCS) authoritative boundaries in cooperation with NLCS policy representitives and the Lands Division. Note: NLCS National Trails and Wild and Scenic Rivers were not updated as they are managed as Line files; however, PADUS already contained many of these protected areas. 5) Modified or newly created Wilderness Area boundaries created by The Omnibus Public Lands Act of 2009 in cooperation with Wilderness.net. 6) Protected areas in The US Virgin Islands 7) Protected areas in the Pacific Islands (Micronesia) 8) Washington Department of Fish and Wildlife protected areas The mission of the USGS Gap Analysis Program (GAP) is to provide state, regional and national assessments of the conservation status of native vertebrate species and natural land cover types and to facilitate the application of this information to land management activities. The PAD-US geodatabase is required to organize and assess the management status (i.e. apply GAP Status Codes) of elements of biodiversity protection. The goal of GAP is to keep common species common by identifying species and plant communities not adequately represented in existing conservation lands. Common species are those not currently threatened with extinction. By identifying their habitats, Gap Analysis gives land managers and policy makers the information they need to make better-informed decisions when identifying priority areas for conservation. In cooperation with UNEP-World Conservation Monitoring Centre, GAP ensures PAD-US also supports global analyses and policy decisions by maintaining World Database for Protected Areas (WDPA) Site Codes and data for International Union for the Conservation of Nature (IUCN) categorized protected areas in the United States. The USGS National Gap Analysis Program (GAP) aggregated the Protected Areas Database of the United States version 1.2 (PAD-US v1.1) with significant contributions from the Bureau of Land Management, The US Forest Service, GreenInfo Network, Applied Geographics and The Nature Conservancy, who provided a spatial dataset of public and private lands and waters secured by a conservation situation that includes an explicit level of security from future conversion and current incompatible uses. These are spatial data from TNC's Conservation Lands System (CLS) database, which is the legal database of record for all TNC land transactions (fee, easement, lease and deed restrictions). GAP seeks to increase the efficiency and accuracy of PAD-US updates by leveraging resources in protected areas data aggregation and maintenance as described in "A Map of the Future", published following the PAD-US Design Project (July, 2009) available from http://www.protectedlands.net/. Download the full FGDC metadata record ftp://ftp.gap.uidaho.edu/outgoing/PADUS1_2/LayerFiles/PADUS1_2_metadata_html.html.</formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/gap/PADUS_Owner/MapServer</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>National Vegetation Classification-Land Use web service</formname>
          <formcont>GAP Land Cover 1 National Vegetation Classification-Land Use - dominant general growth forms adapted to basic moisture, temperature, and/or substrate or aquatic. The digital land cover dataset may be used for various purposes with user's discretion. Specifically, this dataset was created for regional terrestrial biodiversity assessment. These data are not intended to be used at scales larger than 1:100,000.</formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/gap/GAP_Land_Cover_NVC_Class_Landuse/MapServer</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>National Vegetation Classification-Subclass Land Use web service</formname>
          <formcont>GAP Land Cover 2 National Vegetation Classification-Subclass Land Use - global macroclimatic factors driven primarily by latitude and continental position, or reflect overriding substrate or aquatic conditions. The digital land cover dataset may be used for various purposes with user's discretion. Specifically, this dataset was created for regional terrestrial biodiversity assessment. These data are not intended to be used at scales larger than 1:100,000.</formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/gap/GAP_Land_Cover_NVC_Subclass_Landuse/MapServer</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>National Vegetation Classification-Formation Land Use web service</formname>
          <formcont>GAP Land Cover 3 National Vegetation Classification-Formation Land Use - global macroclimatic conditions as modified by altitude, seasonality of precipitation, substrates, hydrological conditions. The digital land cover dataset may be used for various purposes with user's discretion. Specifically, this dataset was created for regional terrestrial biodiversity assessment. These data are not intended to be used at scales larger than 1:100,000.</formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/gap/GAP_Land_Cover_NVC_Formation_Landuse/MapServer</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>National Vegetation Classification-Division Land Use web service</formname>
          <formcont>GAP Land Cover 4 National Vegetation Classification-Division Land Use - continental differences in mesoclimate, geology, substrates, hydrology, disturbance regimes. The digital land cover dataset may be used for various purposes with user's discretion. Specifically, this dataset was created for regional terrestrial biodiversity assessment. These data are not intended to be used at scales larger than 1:100,000.</formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/gap/GAP_Land_Cover_NVC_Division_Landuse/MapServer</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>National Vegetation Classification-Macro Group Land Use</formname>
          <formcont>GAP Land Cover 5 National Vegetation Classification-Macro Group Land Use - sub-continental to regional differences in mesoclimate, geology, substrates, hydrology, disturbance regimes. The digital land cover dataset may be used for various purposes with user's discretion. Specifically, this dataset was created for regional terrestrial biodiversity assessment. These data are not intended to be used at scales larger than 1:100,000.</formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/gap/GAP_Land_Cover_NVC_Macrogroup_Landuse/MapServer</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>National Vegetation Classification-Ecological Systems Land Use</formname>
          <formcont>GAP Land Cover 6 National Vegetation Classification-Ecological Systems Land Use - co-occuring plant communities influenced by similar ecological processes. The digital land cover dataset may be used for various purposes with user's discretion. Specifically, this dataset was created for regional terrestrial biodiversity assessment. These data are not intended to be used at scales larger than 1:100,000.</formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/gap/GAP_Land_Cover_Ecological_Systems_Landuse/MapServer</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Species Range and Distribution Model Map web services - Birds</formname>
          <formcont>Web Services for species ranges and distribution models for all GAP Birds. Bird data provided by NatureServe in collaboration with Robert Ridgely, James Zook, The Nature Conservancy's Migratory Bird Program, Conservation International's Center for Applied Biodiversity Science (CABS), World Wildlife Fund US, and Environment Canada's WILDSPACE.</formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/NAT_Species_Birds</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Species Range and Distribution Model Map web services - Mammals</formname>
          <formcont>Web Services for species ranges and distribution models for all GAP Mammals. Mammal data provided by NatureServe in collaboration with Bruce Patterson, Wes Sechrest, Marcelo Tognelli, Gerardo Ceballos, The Nature Conservancy's Migratory Bird Program, Conservation International's CABS, World Wildlife Fund US, and Environment Canada's WILDSPACE.</formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/NAT_Species_Mammals</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Species Range and Distribution Model Map web services - Amphibians</formname>
          <formcont>Web Services for species ranges and distribution models for all GAP Amphibians. Amphibian data developed as part of the Global Amphibian Assessment and provided by IUCN-World Conservation Union, Conservation International and NatureServe.</formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/NAT_Species_Amphibians</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Species Range and Distribution Model Map web services - Reptiles</formname>
          <formcont>Web Services for species ranges and distribution models for all GAP Reptiles. Reptile data were provided by the International Union for Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources (IUCN).</formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/NAT_Species_Reptiles</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
    <custom>For general information about GAP: http://gapanalysis.usgs.gov/ 

Land cover data: http://gapanalysis.usgs.gov/gaplandcover/

Species data: http://gapanalysis.usgs.gov/species/

Protected areas data: http://gapanalysis.usgs.gov/padus/

Web service connections for data sets: http://gapanalysis.usgs.gov/data/web-services/</custom>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20131202</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Julie Prior-Magee</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Core Science Systems</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing</addrtype>
          <address>PO Box 30003, MSC 4901</address>
          <city>Las Cruces</city>
          <state>NM</state>
          <postal>88003</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>575-557-1566</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>jpmagee@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>