<metadata><Source>http://www1.usgs.gov/metadata/mdata/vip/metamorrspatial.xml</Source>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Lesley Sneddon, NatureServe</origin>
        <origin>USGS/CSS/BIP/Center for Biological Informatics</origin>
        <pubdate>20071231</pubdate>
        <title>Morristown National Historical Park Vegetation Mapping Project - Spatial Vegetation Data</title>
        <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
        <onlink>http://www1.usgs.gov/vip/morr/morrgeodata.zip</onlink>
        <lworkcit>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>L. Sneddon, R.E. Zaremba, E. Largay, G. Podniesinski, S. Perles, and J. Thompson</origin>
            <pubdate>200804</pubdate>
            <title>Vegetation Classification and Mapping of Morristown National Historical Park, New Jersey, Technical Report NPS/NER/NRTR--2008/116</title>
            <geoform>report</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Philadelphia, PA</pubplace>
              <publish>National Park Service</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>http://www.usgs.gov/core_science_systems/csas/vip/parks/morr.html</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </lworkcit>
        <onlink>doi:10.5066/F7NG4NKB</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This geodatabase is an association-level map of the vegetation of the Morristown National Historical Park created using the US National Vegetation Classification (NVC). Fourteen NVC associations and four land use categories were mapped. Field work was conducted in 2003 and 2004 during which 22 vegetation plots were recorded on standardized field forms. Plot data were entered into the NPS PLOTS 2.0 database (NatureServe 2003), then exported to a spreadsheet. The data were analyzed using PC-ORD version 4.0 Multivariate Analysis package (McCune and Mefford 1999), and the resulting vegetation types were crosswalked to the NVC. Those types not previously described by the NVC were newly created provisional types. Altered vegetation and developed land were classified using land use categories. Existing spring black and white orthophotography dated spring 1999 was acquired from Morris County in print and digital form. Photointerpretation was done on stereo pairs of photograph prints using polypropylene sleeves and a mirror stereoscope. The photointerpreter conducted field work to verify signatures. Line work was digitized to GIS shapefiles via onscreen digitizing in ArcView v. 3.2a. Two forest associations were combined into a single map class because signatures were indistinguishable; all other associations were mapped individually. Minimum map unit was 0.5 ha except for associations that occur naturally in patch sizes below 0.5 ha. The final map was assessed for accuracy, with a resulting overall thematic accuracy of 68%.</abstract>
      <purpose>The vegetation map was developed as part of the USGS - NPS Vegetation Mapping Program. The purpose of the map is to represent the vegetation of Morristown National Historical Park using a nationally standardized vegetation classification system (NVC). The intended use is to provide a vegetation inventory and to provide a baseline from which to monitor change and to guide natural resource management.</purpose>
      <supplinf>The shapefile was imported into a geodatabase by the USGS/CSS/BIP/Center for Biological Informatics</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>20040801</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>None planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Morristown National Historical Park and environs</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-74.565451</westbc>
        <eastbc>-74.465659</eastbc>
        <northbc>40.798986</northbc>
        <southbc>40.739484</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>National Park Service Theme Category Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>Vegetation</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
        <themekey>biota</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>none</themekt>
        <themekey>vegetation</themekey>
        <themekey>vegetation map</themekey>
        <themekey>vegetation association</themekey>
        <themekey>vegetation alliance</themekey>
        <themekey>vegetation formation</themekey>
        <themekey>vegetation classification</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>National Park System Unit Name Thesaurus</placekt>
        <placekey>Morristown National Historical Park</placekey>
      </place>
      <place>
        <placekt>National Park System Unit Code Thesaurus</placekt>
        <placekey>MORR</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <taxonomy>
      <keywtax>
        <taxonkt>None</taxonkt>
        <taxonkey>Standardized National Vegetation Classification System</taxonkey>
        <taxonkey>vegetation classification</taxonkey>
        <taxonkey>alliance</taxonkey>
        <taxonkey>community association</taxonkey>
      </keywtax>
      <taxoncl>
        <taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
        <taxonrv>Plantae</taxonrv>
      </taxoncl>
    </taxonomy>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>None</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Brian R. Mitchell</cntper>
          <cntorg>National Park Service</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Inventory and Monitoring Coordinator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
          <address>Northeast Temperate Network</address>
          <address>National Park Service</address>
          <address>54 Elm Street</address>
          <city>Woodstock</city>
          <state>VT</state>
          <postal>05091</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>802-457-3368 x37</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>802-457-3405</cntfax>
        <cntemail>brian_r_mitchell@nps.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <browse>
      <browsen>http://www1.usgs.gov/vip/morr/morrvegmap.pdf</browsen>
      <browsed>Vegetation map; low resolution for web browsing.</browsed>
      <browset>PDF</browset>
    </browse>
    <native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.1.3000</native>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>Overall thematic accuracy is 68%.  Kappa Index is 61% with a 90% confidence interval of 10%</attraccr>
      <qattracc>
        <attraccv>61.0</attraccv>
        <attracce>Three associations attained 100% user's and producer's accuracy: Hemlock - Red Oak - Mixed Hardwood Forest, Smartweed - Cutgrass Wetland, and Skunk Cabbage - Orange Jewelweed Seep. Other classes achieving 100% user's accuracy included Black Locust Successional Forest, Montane Basic Seepage Swamp, Dry-Mesic Chestnut Oak - Red Oak Forest, and Northeastern Old Field. The Southern New England Seepage Swamp attained a fairly high user's accuracy of 75%, and the Northern Piedmont Mesic Oak - Beech Forest and Tuliptree Successional Forest map unit reached 60% user's accuracy.

Three forest associations had low user's accuracy. Tuliptree - Beech - Maple Forest, at 50% correct was mapped incorrectly as either Northern Piedmont Mesic Oak - Beech Forest, or Dry-Mesic Chestnut Oak - Red Oak Forest. Modified Successional Forest, at 40% correct was confused with Black Locust Successional Forest, and with Northeastern Old Field. Northeastern Dry Oak - Hickory Forest achieved only 33% user's accuracy, and was mapped incorrectly as Northern Piedmont Mesic Oak - Beech Forest and Successional Tuliptree Forest map unit. The Northeastern Modified Successional Forest achieved only 25% user's accuracy. In all, however, nine map units (eight associations and one combined map unit of two associations) had user's accuracies of greater than 60%, and eight achieved at least 70%.

Results for producer's error, or errors of omission, were similar. In addition to the three associations that had achieved 100%, five map units were greater than 67% correct. These included Northern Piedmont Mesic Oak - Beech and Successional Tuliptree Forest map unit (73%); Montane Basic Seepage Swamp, Northeastern Dry Oak - Hickory Forest, and Tuliptree - Beech - Maple Forest (all 67% accurate). Southern New England Red Maple Seepage Swamp achieved 60% accuracy.

Three associations had low producer's accuracy, indicating that they were under-represented on the map. Dry-Mesic Chestnut Oak - Red Oak Forest  was only 50% accurate, which means that for every mapped polygon of this type, there is another polygon of this type that is mapped as another type in error. Two successional forest types attained low producer's accuracy: Black Locust Successional Forest and Northeastern Modified Successional Forest. At 40% accuracy, each was under mapped to a considerable degree.</attracce>
      </qattracc>
    </attracc>
    <logic>The shapefile was imported into a geodatabase in ArcGIS9x and topology rules were added to verify there are no slivers or gaps.</logic>
    <complete>This layer is complete. The entire park is covered</complete>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Lockwood Mapping Company, Rochester, NY</origin>
            <pubdate>19990424</pubdate>
            <title>Morris County Spring 1999 black and white aerial photography, 1:16,800 Scale, Spring (leaf off)</title>
            <geoform>aerial photography</geoform>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <srcscale>16,800</srcscale>
        <typesrc>Black and white 1:16,800 leaf-off aerial photographs of Morris County, dated April 24, 1999. The photos were obtained from Lockwood Mapping Company, Rochester, New York</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
              <caldate>19990424</caldate>
            </sngdate>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Lockwood Mapping Company, 1999</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Aerial view of Morristown National Historical Park</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Aerial photograph interpretation of Morristown National Historical Park, Morris County, New Jersey was performed on black and white aerial photograph stereopairs at 1:16,800 scale (1 in = 1,400 ft.) using a mirror stereoscope. Aerial photograph interpretation and fieldwork were used to delineate vegetation into 14 U.S. National Vegetation Classification Associations and four Anderson et al. (1976) Level II (modified) Land Use Categories. Associations were mapped based on tone, texture, and position on the landscape.</procdesc>
        <srcused>Lockwood Mapping Company, 1999</srcused>
        <procdate>2004-2007</procdate>
        <proccont>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntper>Lesley Sneddon</cntper>
              <cntorg>NatureServe</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Senior Regional Ecologist</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
              <address>11 Avenue de Lafayette 5th Floor</address>
              <city>Boston</city>
              <state>MA</state>
              <postal>02111</postal>
              <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>617.542.1608 x 245</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>617.542.1620</cntfax>
            <cntemail>lesley_sneddon@natureserve.org</cntemail>
            <hours>9am - 5 pm</hours>
          </cntinfo>
        </proccont>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>The shapefile was imported into a geodatabase by the USGS/CSS/BIP/Center for Biological Informatics.</procdesc>
        <procdate>201102</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Metadata imported.</procdesc>
        <procdate>201102</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Vector</direct>
    <ptvctinf>
      <sdtsterm>
        <sdtstype>G-polygon</sdtstype>
        <ptvctcnt>86</ptvctcnt>
      </sdtsterm>
    </ptvctinf>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>18</utmzone>
            <transmer>
              <sfctrmer>0.999600</sfctrmer>
              <longcm>-75.000000</longcm>
              <latprjo>0.000000</latprjo>
              <feast>500000.000000</feast>
              <fnorth>0.000000</fnorth>
            </transmer>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
          <coordrep>
            <absres>0.000100</absres>
            <ordres>0.000100</ordres>
          </coordrep>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
        <ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.000000</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257222</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>MORR_VegPolys</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Feature class attribute table</enttypd>
        <enttypds>National Park Service</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>OBJECTID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Poly_ID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Unique identifier for each polygon</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>NPS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Unique plot code.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>MapUnit_ID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Code used to represent the Map Unit</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>NPS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Map unit code.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>MapUnit_Name</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Full Map Unit name</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>NPS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Map unit association common name.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>X_Centroid</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>X Coordinate (UTM Easting) of the centroid of the polygon</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>NPS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Easting coordinate.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Y_Centroid</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Y Coordinate (UTM Northing) of the centroid of the polygon</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>NPS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Northing coordinate.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Acres</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Area (unknown units)</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Hectares</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Perimeter (unknown units)</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape_Length</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Length of feature in internal units.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape_Area</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Area of feature in internal units squared.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>rc_VegPolys_tVegMapInfo</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Defines relationship between Veg polygons and basic vegetation attributes</enttypd>
        <enttypds>National Park Service</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>USGS/CSS/Core Science Analytics and Synthesis</cntorg>
          <cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Characterization Program Coordinator</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, MS 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>Colorado</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>(303) 202-4219</cntfax>
        <cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc>Downloadable data</resdesc>
    <distliab>The U.S. Geological Survey and the National Park Service shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.  These data and related graphics (if available) are not legal documents and are not intended to be used as such.

The information contained in these data is dynamic and may change over time.  The data are not better than the original sources from which they were derived.  It is the responsibility of the data user to use the data appropriately and consistent within the limitations of geospatial data in general and these data in particular.  Any related graphics (if available) are intended to aid the data user in acquiring relevant data; it is not approriate to use the related graphics as data.

The U.S. Geological Survey and the National Park Service gives no warranty, expressed or implied, as to the accuracy, reliability, or completeness of these data.  It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from an U.S. Geological Survey and National Park Service servers and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way.  Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the utility of the data on another system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data. Mention of trade names or commercial products in this metadata report does not constitute endorsement or recommendation for use by the U. S. Department of the Interior, U. S. Geological Survey and National Park Service.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>HTML</formname>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://www.usgs.gov/core_science_systems/csas/vip/parks/morr.html</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
            <accinstr>Internet Access</accinstr>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20080604</metd>
    <metrd>20110225</metrd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>USGS/CSS/Core Science Analytics and Synthesis</cntorg>
          <cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Characterization Program Coordinator</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, MS 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>Colorado</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>303-202-4219</cntfax>
        <cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.usgs.gov/core_science_systems/csas/metadata/index.html</onlink>
    </metextns>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>