<metadata><Source>http://www1.usgs.gov/metadata/mdata/vip/metapinnfield.xml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>National Park Service, Aerial Information Systems, NatureServe, California Native Plant Society</origin>
<origin>USGS/CSS/Core Science Analytics and Synthesis</origin>
<pubdate>Unpublished Material</pubdate>
<title>Pinnacles National Monument Vegetation Mapping Project - Field Plot and Accuracy Assessment Points</title>
<geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
<onlink>http://www1.usgs.gov/vip/pinn/pinngeodata.zip</onlink>
<onlink>doi:10.5066/F7WW7FN6</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>This metadata is for the accuracy assessment point spatial database created at/for Pinnacles National Monument, California. Assessment of map accuracy (AA) entailed sampling of 766 data points in 2008.</abstract>
<purpose>The AA data points were collected to calculate the thematic accuracy of the vegetation map for Pinnacles National Monument (PINN).</purpose>
<supplinf>
Accuracy Assessment

Introduction

Accuracy assessment (AA) is a statistical test of how well polygon map class attributes represent vegetation on the ground. The AA compares field observations with the map class assignment of the sampled polygon. Errors occur when mapped polygon labels differ from field observations. Results of the AA allow users to evaluate the utility of the vegetation mapping data for particular applications. Accuracy assessment results come in two forms: "producer's accuracy" (the probability that an AA point was mapped correctly, also referred to as "errors of omission"), and "user's accuracy" (the probability that the map represents what was found on the ground, also referred to as "errors of commission"). High producer's accuracy combined with low user's accuracy indicates that the map unit is under-mapped. Conversely, low producer's accuracy combined with high user's accuracy indicates that a type is over-mapped. Ideally, a map has both high user's and producer's accuracy.

The accuracy assessment was applied to both the association level classification version of the map and the alliance level version.

Methods

Sampling Design
A stratified random sampling approach was used to determine AA sampling locations. The AA included most vegetation map classes and was limited to lands within the PINN boundary and buffer zone; private and federal land in the Expanded Area (outside of the Monument buffer) were not included in the accuracy evaluation. Sample sizes for each evaluated map class were selected using the USGS-NPS Vegetation Characterization Program guidelines (TNC et al. 1994):

Scenario A: The class is abundant. It covers more than 50 ha (124 acres) and consists of at least 30 polygons. The recommended sample size is 30.

Scenario B: The class is relatively abundant. It covers more than 50 ha, but consists of fewer than 30 polygons. The recommended sample size is 20. The rationale for reducing the sample size for this type of class is that sample sites are more difficult to find because of the lower frequency of the class.

Scenario C: The class is relatively rare. It covers less than 50 ha but consists of more than 30 polygons. The recommended sample size is 20. The rationale for reducing the sample size is that the class occupies a small area. At the same time, however, the class consists of a considerable number of distinct polygons that are possibly widely distributed. The number of samples therefore remains relatively high because of the high frequency of the class.

Scenario D: The class is rare. It has more than five but fewer than 30 polygons and covers less than 50 ha. The recommended number of samples is five. The rationale for reducing the sample size is that the class consists of small polygons and the frequency of the polygons is low. Specifying more than five sample sites will likely result in multiple samples within the same (small) polygon. Collecting five samples will allow accuracy to be estimated, although the estimate will not be very precise.

Scenario E: The class is very rare. It has fewer than five polygons and occupies less than 50 ha. In this case, it is recommended that the existence of the class be confirmed by a visit to each polygon. The rationale for the recommendation is that with fewer than five sample sites (assuming one site per polygon), no estimate of level of confidence can be established for the sample and the accuracy of the class can only be confirmed through a field census.

Of the 39 alliance level map classes and 58 association level map classes that were originally mapped within the Park and buffer, 7 of the map classes were excluded from the accuracy assessment:
Vegetated Map Classes
3103 - Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit
3104 - Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit
9700 - Post Burn and Post Disturbance Undifferentiated Shrub and Grass-Herb
Regeneration Mapping Unit
Non-natural Map Classes
9100 - Built-up Mapping Unit
9200 - Agriculture Mapping Unit
9500 - Water Mapping Unit
9600 - Planted Trees and Shrubs Mapping Unit

The 3 vegetated map classes (3103, 3104 and 9700) were excluded from the AA because the vegetation had likely changed since time of the imagery exposure.  The other 4 classes were excluded because they are non-natural map classes.

Accuracy assessment sampling points were selected for each of the 32 remaining alliance level map classes and the 51 remaining association level map classes using guidelines A-E. The primary set of selected AA evaluation sites included 750 points. Secondary and tertiary sets of points were generated in case some of the points in the primary set could not be accessed safely. After all sets of points were selected, field crews sampled as many accessible polygons as possible given the restricted timing of the field season.  Location (UTM) coordinates for all selected AA polygons were downloaded to GPS units for field sampling. Only the AA points and vegetation polygon boundaries (no vegetation map attributes) were printed on paper maps with an orthophotograph and elevation contour background to help guide the field crews.  The field crew is therefore "blind" to the map classes assigned to the vegetation polygons.

AA Field Data Collection

Accuracy assessment point data were collected at PINN during the summer/fall of 2008. Field crews used GPS units, digital orthophotographs and topographic maps to navigate precisely to each pre-selected AA polygon. The crews evaluated the selected AA location using the protocol defined in Appendix F. The field form used is provided in Appendix G.  Environmental data collected in the field included elevation and descriptive comments of site history and stand age. Vegetation data included canopy cover for each stratum as well as for the dominant species and phenology of the dominant vegetation. A vegetation field key and mapping key were used to identify the vegetation type that best described the AA site location (Appendices D and I, respectively). In most cases, only one plant association name or map class was recorded. When vegetation relationships were less clear, a secondary or tertiary plant association name or map class was also recorded. Adjacent plant associations or map classes were recorded with a notation of the direction of adjacency to sampled polygon. Two or more digital photographs were taken at each AA point to provide visual documentation of the site.

The field team collected data at 766 AA points (Figure 7). AA point data were downloaded from GPS units into an Access plots database.  All vegetation and species data were manually entered into this same database and a thorough quality assessment/quality check (QA/QC) was performed on the data prior to analysis. Nomenclature standards and other data management procedures were the same as for the classification plot data (see Vegetation Classification and Description section). Digital photographs were archived into folders which are labeled by date.

Figure 7.  Location of Accuracy Assessment (AA) points.

Data Analysis

Accuracy assessment (AA) is a statistical test of how well polygon map class attributes represent vegetation on the ground. The AA compares field observations with the map class assignment of the sampled polygon. Errors occur when mapped polygon labels differ from field observations. Results of the AA allow users to evaluate the utility of the vegetation mapping data for particular applications. Accuracy assessment results come in two forms (Hop et al. 2005): "producer's accuracy" (the probability that an AA point was mapped correctly, also referred to as "errors of omission"), and "user's accuracy" (the probability that the map represents what was found on the ground, also referred to as "errors of commission"). High producer's accuracy combined with low user's accuracy indicates that the map class is under-mapped. Conversely, low producer's accuracy combined with high user's accuracy indicates that a type is over-mapped. Ideally, a map has both high user's and producer's accuracy.

The lead AIS photo interpreters and CNPS project ecologists reviewed the AA data for the 766 visited sites.  The field points were converted into a spatial data layer with coordinates and attributes. AA point data was intersected with the map polygon data.  Review consisted of evaluating calls for match or mismatch to the corresponding vegetation map polygon attribute.  The primary, secondary and tertiary plant association, alliance or other map class assigned to each AA point (in the field) were compared to the map class code for that polygon. Per protocol, if any of the three calls agreed with the labeled map class for a given polygon, the point was considered correct.

Each AA point mismatch (disagreement between field call and polygon label) was evaluated for the type of error (true or false). Sources of "false" error include GPS or positional errors, questionable field determinations, edge error, and inclusions (small patches of vegetation within larger map polygons). Mismatches were reviewed when a false error was identified and were either determined to be a match, mismatch, or were discarded. All other mismatches were deemed true errors.

Patterns of error were analyzed for classes falling below the accuracy threshold and possible solutions for raising map class accuracy formulated, i.e., lumping the class into a higher class in the vegetation hierarchy.

In May 2009, a series of conference calls were held among the Park staff and project cooperators to discuss the results of the AA process. Participants discussed the alternative solutions developed during the analysis, and decided on the best solution for the purposes of natural resource management. In some cases, meeting participants recommended combining certain map classes to achieve higher levels of accuracy and more meaningful vegetation map classes. In other cases, the group recommended retaining map classes with lower accuracy, as discussed below. A final contingency table was produced by project cartographers (Table 6), representing mapping to the finest level possible (macrogroup, group, alliance or plant association). The spatial database was revised to reflect the final map classes.

The results of this analysis were arrayed in a preliminary contingency table and "producer's" and "user's" accuracy were calculated for each map class. Producer's accuracy is computed by dividing correct-call samples by the total number of samples taken in polygons called that class. User's accuracy divides the correct-call samples by the total field samples called that map class (regardless of what the polygon was labeled).  Note that in the hierarchical classification, lower level codes that nest within the higher level codes were considered a match.  For example, an association nests into a corresponding alliance; a suballiance mapping unit will nest into its corresponding alliance; an alliance will nest into its corresponding group, and group into macrogroup.

Results and Discussion
Of the 766 AA samples collected in 2008, 738 were used in the analysis.  Post accuracy assessment resulted in 3 macrogroup, 3 group, 14 alliance, 3 plant association, 5 ad hoc unit level map classes representing the natural resource and an additional 4 classes representing human footprint and open water. The map classes shown in the following tables and figures represent the final map classes as a result of the accuracy assessment.  Final map classes are listed in Appendix H, and an illustrated guide with map class descriptions appears in Appendix J.  The final vegetation map can be seen in Figure 8, page 52.  To appreciate the fine-scale details and nuances the map is best viewed on a computer or on the poster-sized hard copy.

Final overall map "Producer's" accuracy is 84.4% (Kappa correction = 82.9%).  Final overall map "User" accuracy is 76.0% (Kappa correction = 73.6%).  Individual map class producer's and user's accuracy values are given with their 90% confidence intervals.  The width of each confidence interval is affected by sample size.  Individual map class Producer accuracy ranges from 62.5% to 100% (Table 11 and Table 12).  Individual map class User accuracy ranges from 33.3% to 100%.

Table 7 shows the nine map classes that met the 80% program standard.  Table 8 contains the thirteen map classes that did not meet the 80% program standard.  However, in every case but three, the User Accuracy 90% confidence interval includes 80%, so Park staff deemed the results to be acceptable.  Map classes 3300, 3330, and 3360 had &lt;80% in User accuracy, but were retained because they were all &gt;90% in Producer accuracy.

Two map classes did not achieve the 80% standard for either user's or producer's accuracy (Table 9).  In both cases the Producer's and User's accuracy 90% confidence interval is above 80%.  Again, Park staff decided these results were acceptable, and wished to retain the map classes.  A discussion of these two problematic map classes is provided below.

Table 6.  Final contingency table for 25 map classes whose accuracy was assessed.  Shaded boxes indicate the number of AA points that agree with the assigned map class.  To read the table, columns represent the map class observed in the field, while the rows represent the map class assigned by the photo interpreter.  Overall producer accuracy is 84.4% with kappa index of 82.9%.  Overall user accuracy is 76.0% with kappa index of 73.6%.  User's and producer's accuracy values for each map class appear in tables 7 and 8. Note that map unit 3510 is an error and should be Map unit 3410.

This page intentionally left blank.
Table 7.  Final PINN map classes with &gt;80% program standard for both User's and Producer's accuracy.
Map Class Code		Map Class Name	Producer's Accuracy (&#177;90% CI)	User's Accuracy (&#177;90% CI)
1311		California Sycamore-Coast Live Oak Woodland  Association	80%&#177;39%	100%&#177;12%
2110		Coast Live Oak Woodland Alliance	86%&#177;7%	87%&#177;6%
2210		Blue Oak Woodland Alliance	87%&#177;6%	84%&#177;6%
2230		Valley Oak Woodland Alliance	100%&#177;8%	83%&#177;33%
3160		California Scrub Oak Shrubland Alliance	80%&#177;26%	80%&#177;26
3210		Coyote Brush Shrubland Alliance	100%&#177;25%	100%&#177;25%
3510		California Rose Shrubland Alliance	100%&#177;50%	100%&#177;50%
4510		Deergrass Herbaceous Vegetation Alliance	100%&#177;50%	100%&#177;50%
9420		Cliffs, Rock Outcrops, and Steep Eroded Slopes Mapping Unit	86%&#177;9%	96%&#177;6%

Table 8.  Final PINN map classes with &lt; 80%  program standard for both User's or Producer's accuracy
Map Class Code		Map Class Name	Producer's Accuracy (&#177;90% CI)	User's Accuracy (&#177;90% CI)
1220		California Juniper Woodland Alliance	83%&#177;33%	71%&#177;35%
1300		Southwestern North American Riparian Evergreen and Deciduous Forest Group	73%&#177;16%	95%&#177;11%
2212		Blue Oak/Mixed Herbaceous Woodland Association	89%&#177;13%	66%&#177;14%
2220		California Buckeye Woodland Alliance	81%&#177;19%	77%&#177;20%
2231		Valley Oak-Coast Live Oak/ Grass Woodland Association	100%&#177;25%	50%&#177;50%
3100		Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup	76%&#177;15	83%&#177;22
3150		Hollyleaf Cherry Shrubland Alliance	85%&#177;14%	69%&#177;15%
3300		California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup	94%&#177;7%	44%&#177;22%
3330		California Wild Buckwheat Shrubland Alliance	96%&#177;8%	34%&#177;10%
3360		Black Sage Shrubland Alliance	100%&#177;12%	33%&#177;27%
3370		California Sagebrush-California Wild Buckwheat Shrubland Alliance	100%&#177;10%	56%&#177;33%
3400		Southwestern North American Riparian/Wash Scrub Shrubland Group	84%&#177;16%	70%&#177;18%
4300		Mediterranean California Naturalized Annual and Perennial Grassland Herbaceous Vegetation Macrogroup	78%&#177;13%	97%&#177;7%

Table 9.  Final PINN vegetation map classes where neither the User's or Producer's accuracy met the 80% program standard.
Map Class Code		Map Class Name	Producer's Accuracy (&#177;90% CI)	User's Accuracy (&#177;90% CI)
1210		Foothill Pine Woodland Alliance	71%&#177;11%	78%&#177;11%
4004		Alluvial Herb and Shrub Vegetation Mapping Unit	63%&#177;35%	71%&#177;35%

Map Class Code 1210 - Foothill Pine Woodland Alliance: This map class was problematic for two reasons.  The first is that in very sparse stands with about 5 to 12% tree cover, there was a discrepancy between the photointerpreters judgment of the tree density versus the AA field crew's estimate.  Therefore field crews tended to call the point a shrub type rather than a tree type.  It is reasonable for any field personnel to call sparse cover of foothill pine over shrubland either an open woodland or a shrubland, so the AA point was valid, even though it did not match the mapper's assessment.  A second reason for error was due to confusion between the photo signature of Foothill Pine and Blue Oak at some locations.  The error between these signatures is more localized in the Park rather than pervasive.  Since the Producer's and User's accuracy 90% confidence interval is above 80%, the Park decided to keep this class in the final database.

Map Class 4004 - Alluvial Herb and Shrub Vegetation Mapping Unit:   One of the most difficult areas to map were the bare alluvial wash on valley floors.  These areas are, for the most part, barren but can have narrow stringers of thick riparian vegetation.  Mapped polygons generally represented very sparsely vegetated gravel, cobble or sand bars and stream channels.  However some portions of the polygon are vegetated with riparian shrubs along very narrow channels that in many cases may be inclusive.  Field crews tended to describe the stringer vegetation, rather than the whole polygon, contrasting with the mapper's call of a mainly the open, bright, reflective bare alluvial substrate, with inclusions of narrow riparian vegetation.  In addition, these areas can change with time and flooding events.  Since the Producer's and User's accuracy 90% confidence interval is above 80%, the Park decided to keep this class in the final database.

Conclusion

Mapping the vegetation resource at Pinnacles National Monument required a variety of scales of map classes.  Twenty-eight map classes representing 67 plant associations, alliances or Park special types were mapped. Twenty five classes were within the 80% accuracy standard (90% confidence interval). Three map units were not assessed for accuracy. Map classes ranged from the broad inclusive scale (macrogroups) to individual plant associations.

Quantitative analysis of plot data collected by Park staff resulted in a classification of 67 plant associations, alliances or Park special vegetation types within the Monument and environs.  This classification represents 47 Alliances and 73 plant associations.  Fifty-one associations are recognized by the National Vegetation Classification, 22 are described as 'Park specials' because they are known only from the Monument.  The vegetation of the mapping project area is relatively diverse.  Chaparral, oak woodlands and dry herbaceous areas dominate the vegetation, accounting for ~35 associations.

A total of 6,141 map polygons representing 24 vegetation map classes (including tree and shrub cover attributes), fourteen land use map classes and 7 miscellaneous classes were developed for the PINN vegetation mapping project.  Of the 6,141 mapped polygons, 115 were assigned both a land use class and a vegetation class.  The average polygon size across all map classes is 3 ha (7.3 acres).  Natural and semi-natural vegetation classes cover 17,953 ha (44,362 acres), or 98.6% of the project area.  Land use polygons, including ranch developments, agriculture and Park facilities cover 250 ha (617 acres), or 1.4 % of the project area.  Final overall map Producer accuracy is 84.4% (Kappa correction = 83.1%). Final overall map User accuracy is 78.0% (Kappa correction = 75.6%).

Data were reformatted to match Plots V2.0 by the USGS/CSS/Core Science Analytics and Synthesis.
</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>2008</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>ground condition</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>As needed</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<descgeog>Pinnacles National Monument and environs</descgeog>
<bounding>
<westbc>-121.239816</westbc>
<eastbc>-121.103315</eastbc>
<northbc>36.566176</northbc>
<southbc>36.407680</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>None</themekt>
<themekey>Vegetation</themekey>
<themekey>Vegetation mapping</themekey>
<themekey>Vegetation Map</themekey>
<themekey>National Monument</themekey>
<themekey>National Park</themekey>
<themekey>Accuracy Assessment</themekey>
<themekey>Ground Data</themekey>
<themekey>Land Cover</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>None</placekt>
<placekey>Pinnacles National Monument</placekey>
<placekey>San Benito County</placekey>
<placekey>Monterey County</placekey>
<placekey>California</placekey>
<placekey>Gabilan Range</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<accconst>None.</accconst>
<useconst>Acknowledgment of Aerial Information Systems,Inc. (AIS) and the California Native Plant Society (CNPS) would be appreciated in products derived from these data.  Any person using the information presented here should fully understand the data collection and compilation process before beginning their analysis/use.  The burden of determining fitness for use lies with the user.</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Brent Johnson</cntper>
<cntorg>Pinnacles National Monument</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntpos>Park Botanist</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>50000 Highway 146</address>
<city>Paicines</city>
<state>California</state>
<postal>65043</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(831) 389-4486 ext. 259</cntvoice>
<cntfax>(831) 389-4489</cntfax>
<cntemail>brent_johnson@nps.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
<datacred>The AA data set was created by California Native Plant Society (CNPS).  Numerous individuals collected plot and accuracy assessment field data. We appreciate the hard work of Melinda Elster, Andra Forney and Betsy Harbert with oversight by Jennifer Buck, Eric Peterson, Donna Shorrock, and Kendra Sikes (CNPS). Analysis was conducted by CNPS (Julie Evens and Jennifer Buck) and AIS (Debbie Johnson, Ben Johnson, and Ed Reyes)</datacred>
<native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.0.1770</native>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<attracc>
<attraccr>None.</attraccr>
</attracc>
<logic>None</logic>
<complete>All points required for the accuracy assessment at Pinnacles National Monument included in this data layer.</complete>
<posacc>
<horizpa>
<horizpar>GPS accuracy varies for each plot. Error values were recorded on the plot form.</horizpar>
</horizpa>
<vertacc>
<vertaccr>Standard GPS Elevation Error</vertaccr>
</vertacc>
</posacc>
<lineage>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>National Park Service, Aerial Information Systems, California Native Plant Society, NatureServe</origin>
<pubdate>Unpublished Material</pubdate>
<title>Pinnacles National Monument Vegetation Mapping Project Accuracy Assessment Points</title>
<geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<typesrc>online</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>2008</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>Accuracy Assessment Points</srccitea>
<srccontr>Unknown</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<procstep>
<procdesc>
Accuray Assessment

Introduction

Accuracy assessment (AA) is a statistical test of how well polygon map class attributes represent vegetation on the ground. The AA compares field observations with the map class assignment of the sampled polygon. Errors occur when mapped polygon labels differ from field observations. Results of the AA allow users to evaluate the utility of the vegetation mapping data for particular applications. Accuracy assessment results come in two forms: "producer's accuracy" (the probability that an AA point was mapped correctly, also referred to as "errors of omission"), and "user's accuracy" (the probability that the map represents what was found on the ground, also referred to as "errors of commission"). High producer's accuracy combined with low user's accuracy indicates that the map unit is under-mapped. Conversely, low producer's accuracy combined with high user's accuracy indicates that a type is over-mapped. Ideally, a map has both high user's and producer's accuracy.

The accuracy assessment was applied to both the association level classification version of the map and the alliance level version.

Methods

Sampling Design
A stratified random sampling approach was used to determine AA sampling locations. The AA included most vegetation map classes and was limited to lands within the PINN boundary and buffer zone; private and federal land in the Expanded Area (outside of the Monument buffer) were not included in the accuracy evaluation. Sample sizes for each evaluated map class were selected using the USGS-NPS Vegetation Characterization Program guidelines (TNC et al. 1994):

Scenario A: The class is abundant. It covers more than 50 ha (124 acres) and consists of at least 30 polygons. The recommended sample size is 30.

Scenario B: The class is relatively abundant. It covers more than 50 ha, but consists of fewer than 30 polygons. The recommended sample size is 20. The rationale for reducing the sample size for this type of class is that sample sites are more difficult to find because of the lower frequency of the class.

Scenario C: The class is relatively rare. It covers less than 50 ha but consists of more than 30 polygons. The recommended sample size is 20. The rationale for reducing the sample size is that the class occupies a small area. At the same time, however, the class consists of a considerable number of distinct polygons that are possibly widely distributed. The number of samples therefore remains relatively high because of the high frequency of the class.

Scenario D: The class is rare. It has more than five but fewer than 30 polygons and covers less than 50 ha. The recommended number of samples is five. The rationale for reducing the sample size is that the class consists of small polygons and the frequency of the polygons is low. Specifying more than five sample sites will likely result in multiple samples within the same (small) polygon. Collecting five samples will allow accuracy to be estimated, although the estimate will not be very precise.

Scenario E: The class is very rare. It has fewer than five polygons and occupies less than 50 ha. In this case, it is recommended that the existence of the class be confirmed by a visit to each polygon. The rationale for the recommendation is that with fewer than five sample sites (assuming one site per polygon), no estimate of level of confidence can be established for the sample and the accuracy of the class can only be confirmed through a field census.

Of the 39 alliance level map classes and 58 association level map classes that were originally mapped within the Park and buffer, 7 of the map classes were excluded from the accuracy assessment:
Vegetated Map Classes
3103 - Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit
3104 - Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit
9700 - Post Burn and Post Disturbance Undifferentiated Shrub and Grass-Herb Regeneration Mapping Unit Non-natural Map Classes
9100 - Built-up Mapping Unit
9200 - Agriculture Mapping Unit
9500 - Water Mapping Unit
9600 - Planted Trees and Shrubs Mapping Unit

The 3 vegetated map classes (3103, 3104 and 9700) were excluded from the AA because the vegetation had likely changed since time of the imagery exposure. The other 4 classes were excluded because they are non-natural map classes. Accuracy assessment sampling points were selected for each of the 32 remaining alliance level map classes and the 51 remaining association level map classes using guidelines A-E. The primary set of selected AA evaluation sites included 750 points. Secondary and tertiary sets of points were generated in case some of the points in the primary set could not be accessed safely. After all sets of points were selected, field crews sampled as many accessible polygons as possible given the restricted timing of the field season. Location (UTM) coordinates for all selected AA polygons were downloaded to GPS units for field sampling. Only the AA points and vegetation polygon boundaries (no vegetation map attributes) were printed on paper maps with an orthophotograph and elevation contour background to help guide the field crews. The field crew is therefore "blind" to the map classes assigned to the vegetation polygons.

AA Field Data Collection Accuracy assessment point data were collected at PINN during the summer/fall of 2008. Field crews used GPS units, digital orthophotographs and topographic maps to navigate precisely to each pre-selected AA polygon. The crews evaluated the selected AA location using the protocol defined in Appendix F. The field form used is provided in Appendix G. Environmental data collected in the field included elevation and descriptive comments of site history and stand age. Vegetation data included canopy cover for each stratum as well as for the dominant species and phenology of the dominant vegetation. A vegetation field key and mapping key were used to identify the vegetation type that best described the AA site location (Appendices D and I, respectively). In most cases, only one plant association name or map class was recorded. When vegetation relationships were less clear, a secondary or tertiary plant association name or map class was also recorded. Adjacent plant associations or map classes were recorded with a notation of the direction of adjacency to sampled polygon. Two or more digital photographs were taken at each AA point to provide visual documentation of the site.

The field team collected data at 766 AA points (Figure 7). AA point data were downloaded from GPS units into an Access plots database. All vegetation and species data were manually entered into this same database and a thorough quality assessment/quality check (QA/QC) was performed on the data prior to analysis. Nomenclature standards and other data management procedures were the same as for the classification plot data (see Vegetation Classification and Description section). Digital photographs were archived into folders which are labeled by date.

Figure 7. Location of Accuracy Assessment (AA) points.
Data Analysis

Accuracy assessment (AA) is a statistical test of how well polygon map class attributes represent vegetation on the ground. The AA compares field observations with the map class assignment of the sampled polygon. Errors occur when mapped polygon labels differ from field observations. Results of the AA allow users to evaluate the utility of the vegetation mapping data for particular applications. Accuracy assessment results come in two forms (Hop et al. 2005): "producer's accuracy" (the probability that an AA point was mapped correctly, also referred to as "errors of omission"), and "user's accuracy" (the probability that the map represents what was found on the ground, also referred to as "errors of commission"). High producer's accuracy combined with low user's accuracy indicates that the map class is under-mapped. Conversely, low producer's accuracy combined with high user's accuracy indicates that a type is over-mapped. Ideally, a map has both high user's and producer's accuracy.

The lead AIS photo interpreters and CNPS project ecologists reviewed the AA data for the 766 visited sites. The field points were converted into a spatial data layer with coordinates and attributes. AA point data was intersected with the map polygon data. Review consisted of evaluating calls for match or mismatch to the corresponding vegetation map polygon attribute. The primary, secondary and tertiary plant association, alliance or other map class assigned to each AA point (in the field) were compared to the map class code for that polygon. Per protocol, if any of the three calls agreed with the labeled map class for a given polygon, the point was considered correct.

Each AA point mismatch (disagreement between field call and polygon label) was evaluated for the type of error (true or false). Sources of "false" error include GPS or positional errors, questionable field determinations, edge error, and inclusions (small patches of vegetation within larger map polygons). Mismatches were reviewed when a false error was identified and were either determined to be a match, mismatch, or were discarded. All other mismatches were deemed true errors.

Patterns of error were analyzed for classes falling below the accuracy threshold and possible solutions for raising map class accuracy formulated, i.e., lumping the class into a higher class in the vegetation hierarchy.

In May 2009, a series of conference calls were held among the Park staff and project cooperators to discuss the results of the AA process. Participants discussed the alternative solutions developed during the analysis, and decided on the best solution for the purposes of natural resource management. In some cases, meeting participants recommended combining certain map classes to achieve higher levels of accuracy and more meaningful vegetation map classes. In other cases, the group recommended retaining map classes with lower accuracy, as discussed below. A final contingency table was produced by project cartographers (Table 6), representing mapping to the finest level possible (macrogroup, group, alliance or plant association). The spatial database was revised to reflect the final map classes.

The results of this analysis were arrayed in a preliminary contingency table and "producer's" and "user's" accuracy were calculated for each map class. Producer's accuracy is computed by dividing correct-call samples by the total number of samples taken in polygons called that class. User's accuracy divides the correct-call samples by the total field samples called that map class (regardless of what the polygon was labeled). Note that in the hierarchical classification, lower level codes that nest within the higher level codes were considered a match. For example, an association nests into a corresponding alliance; a suballiance mapping unit will nest into its corresponding alliance; an alliance will nest into its corresponding group, and group into macrogroup.

Results and Discussion Of the 766 AA samples collected in 2008, 738 were used in the analysis. Post accuracy assessment resulted in 3 macrogroup, 3 group, 14 alliance, 3 plant association, 5 ad hoc unit level map classes representing the natural resource and an additional 4 classes representing human footprint and open water. The map classes shown in the following tables and figures represent the final map classes as a result of the accuracy assessment. Final map classes are listed in Appendix H, and an illustrated guide with map class descriptions appears in Appendix J. The final vegetation map can be seen in Figure 8, page 52. To appreciate the fine-scale details and nuances the map is best viewed on a computer or on the poster-sized hard copy.

Final overall map "Producer's" accuracy is 84.4% (Kappa correction = 82.9%). Final overall map "User" accuracy is 76.0% (Kappa correction = 73.6%). Individual map class producer's and user's accuracy values are given with their 90% confidence intervals. The width of each confidence interval is affected by sample size. Individual map class Producer accuracy ranges from 62.5% to 100% (Table 11 and Table 12). Individual map class User accuracy ranges from 33.3% to 100%.

Table 7 shows the nine map classes that met the 80% program standard. Table 8 contains the thirteen map classes that did not meet the 80% program standard. However, in every case but three, the User Accuracy 90% confidence interval includes 80%, so Park staff deemed the results to be acceptable. Map classes 3300, 3330, and 3360 had &lt;80% in User accuracy, but were retained because they were all &gt;90% in Producer accuracy.

Two map classes did not achieve the 80% standard for either user's or producer's accuracy (Table 9). In both cases the Producer's and User's accuracy 90% confidence interval is above 80%. Again, Park staff decided these results were acceptable, and wished to retain the map classes. A discussion of these two problematic map classes is provided below.

Table 6. Final contingency table for 25 map classes whose accuracy was assessed. Shaded boxes indicate the number of AA points that agree with the assigned map class. To read the table, columns represent the map class observed in the field, while the rows represent the map class assigned by the photo interpreter. Overall producer accuracy is 84.4% with kappa index of 82.9%. Overall user accuracy is 76.0% with kappa index of 73.6%. User's and producer's accuracy values for each map class appear in tables 7 and 8. Note that map unit 3510 is an error and should be Map unit 3410.

This page intentionally left blank.
Table 7. Final PINN map classes with &gt;80% program standard for both User's and Producer's accuracy.
Map Class Code            Map Class Name       Producer's Accuracy (&#177;90% CI)       User's Accuracy (&#177;90% CI)
1311             California Sycamore-Coast Live Oak Woodland Association       80%&#177;39%       100%&#177;12%
2110             Coast Live Oak Woodland Alliance       86%&#177;7%       87%&#177;6%
2210             Blue Oak Woodland Alliance       87%&#177;6%       84%&#177;6%
2230             Valley Oak Woodland Alliance       100%&#177;8%       83%&#177;33%
3160             California Scrub Oak Shrubland Alliance       80%&#177;26%       80%&#177;26
3210             Coyote Brush Shrubland Alliance       100%&#177;25%       100%&#177;25%
3510             California Rose Shrubland Alliance       100%&#177;50%       100%&#177;50%
4510             Deergrass Herbaceous Vegetation Alliance       100%&#177;50%       100%&#177;50%
9420             Cliffs, Rock Outcrops, and Steep Eroded Slopes Mapping Unit       86%&#177;9%       96%&#177;6%

Table 8. Final PINN map classes with &lt; 80% program standard for both User's or Producer's accuracy
Map Class Code             Map Class Name       Producer's Accuracy (&#177;90% CI)       User's Accuracy (&#177;90% CI)
1220             California Juniper Woodland Alliance       83%&#177;33%       71%&#177;35%
1300             Southwestern North American Riparian Evergreen and Deciduous Forest Group       73%&#177;16%       95%&#177;11%
2212             Blue Oak/Mixed Herbaceous Woodland Association       89%&#177;13%       66%&#177;14%
2220             California Buckeye Woodland Alliance       81%&#177;19%       77%&#177;20%
2231             Valley Oak-Coast Live Oak/ Grass Woodland Association       100%&#177;25%       50%&#177;50%
3100             Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup       76%&#177;15       83%&#177;22
3150             Hollyleaf Cherry Shrubland Alliance       85%&#177;14%       69%&#177;15%
3300             California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup       94%&#177;7%       44%&#177;22%
3330             California Wild Buckwheat Shrubland Alliance       96%&#177;8%       34%&#177;10%
3360             Black Sage Shrubland Alliance       100%&#177;12%       33%&#177;27%
3370             California Sagebrush-California Wild Buckwheat Shrubland Alliance       100%&#177;10%       56%&#177;33%
3400             Southwestern North American Riparian/Wash Scrub Shrubland Group       84%&#177;16%       70%&#177;18%
4300             Mediterranean California Naturalized Annual and Perennial Grassland Herbaceous Vegetation Macrogroup       78%&#177;13%       97%&#177;7%

Table 9. Final PINN vegetation map classes where neither the User's or Producer's accuracy met the 80% program standard.
Map Class Code             Map Class Name       Producer's Accuracy (&#177;90% CI)       User's Accuracy (&#177;90% CI)
1210             Foothill Pine Woodland Alliance       71%&#177;11%       78%&#177;11%
4004             Alluvial Herb and Shrub Vegetation Mapping Unit       63%&#177;35%       71%&#177;35%

Map Class Code 1210 - Foothill Pine Woodland Alliance: This map class was problematic for two reasons. The first is that in very sparse stands with about 5 to 12% tree cover, there was a discrepancy between the photointerpreters judgment of the tree density versus the AA field crew's estimate. Therefore field crews tended to call the point a shrub type rather than a tree type. It is reasonable for any field personnel to call sparse cover of foothill pine over shrubland either an open woodland or a shrubland, so the AA point was valid, even though it did not match the mapper's assessment. A second reason for error was due to confusion between the photo signature of Foothill Pine and Blue Oak at some locations. The error between these signatures is more localized in the Park rather than pervasive. Since the Producer's and User's accuracy 90% confidence interval is above 80%, the Park decided to keep this class in the final database.

Map Class 4004 - Alluvial Herb and Shrub Vegetation Mapping Unit: One of the most difficult areas to map were the bare alluvial wash on valley floors. These areas are, for the most part, barren but can have narrow stringers of thick riparian vegetation. Mapped polygons generally represented very sparsely vegetated gravel, cobble or sand bars and stream channels. However some portions of the polygon are vegetated with riparian shrubs along very narrow channels that in many cases may be inclusive. Field crews tended to describe the stringer vegetation, rather than the whole polygon, contrasting with the mapper's call of a mainly the open, bright, reflective bare alluvial substrate, with inclusions of narrow riparian vegetation. In addition, these areas can change with time and flooding events. Since the Producer's and User's accuracy 90% confidence interval is above 80%, the Park decided to keep this class in the final database.

Conclusion

Mapping the vegetation resource at Pinnacles National Monument required a variety of scales of map classes. Twenty-eight map classes representing 67 plant associations, alliances or Park special types were mapped. Twenty five classes were within the 80% accuracy standard (90% confidence interval). Three map units were not assessed for accuracy. Map classes ranged from the broad inclusive scale (macrogroups) to individual plant associations. Quantitative analysis of plot data collected by Park staff resulted in a classification of 67 plant associations, alliances or Park special vegetation types within the Monument and environs. This classification represents 47 Alliances and 73 plant associations. Fifty-one associations are recognized by the National Vegetation Classification, 22 are described as 'Park specials' because they are known only from the Monument. The vegetation of the mapping project area is relatively diverse. Chaparral, oak woodlands and dry herbaceous areas dominate the vegetation, accounting for ~35 associations. A total of 6,141 map polygons representing 24 vegetation map classes (including tree and shrub cover attributes), fourteen land use map classes and 7 miscellaneous classes were developed for the PINN vegetation mapping project. Of the 6,141 mapped polygons, 115 were assigned both a land use class and a vegetation class. The average polygon size across all map classes is 3 ha (7.3 acres). Natural and semi-natural vegetation classes cover 17,953 ha (44,362 acres), or 98.6% of the project area. Land use polygons, including ranch developments, agriculture and Park facilities cover 250 ha (617 acres), or 1.4 % of the project area. Final overall map Producer accuracy is 84.4% (Kappa correction = 83.1%). Final overall map User accuracy is 78.0% (Kappa correction = 75.6%).
</procdesc>
<procdate>2008</procdate>
<proccont>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Edward Reyes</cntper>
<cntorg>Aerial Information Systems</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntpos>Project Coordinator</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>physical address</addrtype>
<address>112 First Street</address>
<city>Redlands</city>
<state>California</state>
<postal>92373</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(909) 793-9493</cntvoice>
<cntfax>(909) 798-4430</cntfax>
<cntemail>ais@aisgis.com</cntemail>
<hours>8:00am - 5:00pm M-F</hours>
</cntinfo>
</proccont>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>Data were reformatted using Plots V2.0, and then the Shapefiles and the data was imported into a geodatabase by the USGS/CSS/Core Science Analytics and Synthesis.</procdesc>
<procdate>201301</procdate>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>Metadata imported.</procdesc>
<procdate>201301</procdate>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spdoinfo>
<direct>Vector</direct>
<ptvctinf>
<sdtsterm>
<sdtstype>Entity point</sdtstype>
<ptvctcnt>1358</ptvctcnt>
</sdtsterm>
</ptvctinf>
</spdoinfo>
<spref>
<horizsys>
<planar>
<gridsys>
<gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
<utm>
<utmzone>10</utmzone>
<transmer>
<sfctrmer>0.999600</sfctrmer>
<longcm>-123.000000</longcm>
<latprjo>0.000000</latprjo>
<feast>500000.000000</feast>
<fnorth>0.000000</fnorth>
</transmer>
</utm>
</gridsys>
<planci>
<plance>coordinate pair</plance>
<coordrep>
<absres>0.000100</absres>
<ordres>0.000100</ordres>
</coordrep>
<plandu>meters</plandu>
</planci>
</planar>
<geodetic>
<horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
<ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
<semiaxis>6378137.000000</semiaxis>
<denflat>298.257222</denflat>
</geodetic>
</horizsys>
</spref>
<eainfo>
<detailed>
<enttyp>
<enttypl>AA_Points_with_Tables</enttypl>
<enttypd>Pinnacles National Monument Vegetation Mapping Project Accuracy Assessment Vegetation Point Attribute Table</enttypd>
<enttypds>Aerial Information Systems and California Native Plant Society</enttypds>
</enttyp>
<attr>
<attrlabl>ObjectID</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Plot_Code</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Key identifier Database number, up to 8 characters long and usually ALPHAnumeric with project name and number with leading zeros (e.g., SERP0001)</attrdef>
<attrdefs>California Native Plant Society</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Unique plot number.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Pnts_Type</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Point type (accuracy assessment point, observation point or plot point)</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Plots V2.0</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Accuracy Assessment Point</edomv>
<edomvd>AA Point</edomvd>
<edomvds>Plots V2.0</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Observation Point</edomv>
<edomvd>Observation Point</edomvd>
<edomvds>Plots V2.0</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Plot Point</edomv>
<edomvd>Plot Point</edomvd>
<edomvds>Plots V2.0</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>X_Coord</attrlabl>
<attrdef>X Coordinate (UTM Easting)</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Aerial Information Systems and California Native Plant Society</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Easting coordinate.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Y_Coord</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Y Coordinate (UTM Northing)</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Aerial Information Systems and California Native Plant Society</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Northing coordinate.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
</detailed>
<detailed>
<enttyp>
<enttypl>rc_VegPoints_tAA_tPlots</enttypl>
<enttypd>Defines relationship between Veg points and basic AA/plot attributes</enttypd>
<enttypds>National Park Service</enttypds>
</enttyp>
</detailed>
<overview>
<eaover>
Vegetation PI codes:
1200	California Evergreen Coniferous Forest and Woodland Group
1210	Foothill Pine Woodland Alliance
1211	Foothill Pine/Chaparral Woodland Mapping Unit
1212	Foothill Pine/California Wild Buckwheat Alluvial Woodland Mapping Unit
1213	Foothill Pine/California Wild Buckwheat Thin Substrate Woodland Mapping Unit
1220	California Juniper Woodland Alliance
1221	California Juniper/Hollyleaf Cherry/Moss Woodland Association
1300	Southwestern North American Riparian Evergreen and Deciduous Forest Group
1301	Southwestern North American Riparian Evergreen and Deciduous Forest Group
1310	California Sycamore Temporarily Flooded Woodland Alliance
1311	California Sycamore-Coast Live Oak Woodland Association
2100	Californian Broadleaf Forest and Woodland Group [non-deciduous]
2101	Live Oak Woodland and Shrubland Mapping Unit
2110	Coast Live Oak Woodland Alliance
2112	Coast Live Oak/Annual Grass-Herb Woodland Association
2114	Coast Live Oak Alluvial Woodland Mapping Unit
2117	Coast Live Oak-Blue Oak Woodland Mapping Unit
2120	Interior Live Oak Woodland Alliance
2200	Californian Broadleaf Forest and Woodland Group [deciduous]
2210	Blue Oak Woodland Alliance
2211	Blue Oak/Chaparral/Grass Woodland Mapping Unit
2212	Blue Oak/Mixed Herbaceous Woodland Association
2213	Blue Oak-California Juniper Woodland Association
2216	Blue Oak-California Buckeye Woodland Mapping Unit
2217	Blue Oak-Foothill Pine Woodland Mapping Unit
2218	Blue Oak/Coastal Sage Scrub Woodland Mapping Unit
2220	California Buckeye Woodland Alliance
2230	Valley Oak Woodland Alliance
2231	Valley Oak-Coast Live Oak/Grass Woodland Association
2232	Valley Oak-Coast Live Oak/Mesic Grass Woodland Mapping Unit
3100	Californian Chaparral Shrubland Macrogroup
3101	Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Group
3102	Dry-Mesic Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit
3103	Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit
3104	Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit
3110	Chamise Shrubland Alliance
3113	Chamise-Black Sage Shrubland Association
3114	Chamise-Coastal Sage Scrub Shrubland Mapping Unit
3115	Chamise-California Wild Buckwheat Shrubland Mapping Unit
3150	Hollyleaf Cherry Shrubland Alliance
3160	California Scrub Oak Shrubland Alliance
3200	Evergreen Coastal Scrub Shrubland Group
3210	Coyote Brush Shrubland Alliance
3300	California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup [extended area]
3301	California Coastal Scrub Shrubland Macrogroup
3310	California Sagebrush Shrubland Alliance
3330	California Wild Buckwheat Shrubland Alliance
3331	California Wild Buckwheat Alluvial Shrubland Mapping Unit
3332	California Wild Buckwheat Thin Substrate Shrubland Mapping Unit
3350	Silver Lupine Shrubland Alliance
3360	Black Sage Shrubland Alliance
3370	California Sagebrush-California Wild Buckwheat Shrubland Alliance
3400	Southwestern North American Riparian/Wash Scrub Shrubland Group
3401	Southwestern North American Riparian/Wash Scrub Shrubland Group
3410	California Wildrose Shrubland Alliance
3510	California Rose Shrubland Alliance
4001	Western North American Freshwater Marsh Herbaceous Vegetation Macrogroup [Extended Area]
4002	Mediterranean California Naturalized Annual and Perennial Grassland and Herbaceous Vegetation Macrogroup [Extended Area]
4003	Open to Sparse Grass on Rocky Thin Substrate Herbaceous Vegetation Mapping Unit
4004	Alluvial Herb and Shrub Vegetation Mapping Unit
4100	Western North America Freshwater Marsh Herbaceous Vegetation
4101	Bulrush-Cattails Herbaceous Vegetation Mapping Unit
4201	Western North American Wet Meadow and Low Shrub Carr Herbaceous Vegetation Macrogroup
4300	Mediterranean California Naturalized Annual and Perennial Grassland Herbaceous Vegetation Macrogroup
4310	Mediterranean California Naturalized Annual and Perennial Grassland and Herbaceous Vegetation Macrogroup
4401	Alluvial Herb and Shrub Vegetation Mapping Unit
4500	Western North America Wet Meadow and Low Shrub Carr Herbaceous Vegetation Macrogroup
4510	Deergrass Herbaceous Vegetation Alliance
9100	Built-up Mapping Unit
9200	Agriculture Mapping Unit
9420	Cliffs, Rock Outcrops, and Steep Eroded Slopes Mapping Unit
9430	Sparsely Vegetated to Non-vegetated Stream Beds and Flats Mapping Unit
9500	Water Mapping Unit
9600	Planted Trees &amp; Shrubs Mapping Unit
9700	Post Burn and Post Disturbance Undifferentiated Shrub and Grass-Herb Regeneration Mapping Unit
9710	Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit
9720	Post Burn and Post Disturbance Californian Xeric Chaparral Shrubland Mapping Unit
</eaover>
<eadetcit>Pinnacles National Monument Vegetation</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS/CSS/Core Science Analytics and Synthesis</cntorg>
<cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntper>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, MS 302</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>303-202-4219</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
<distliab>
The U.S. Geological Survey and the National Park Service shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.  These data and related graphics (if available) are not legal documents and are not intended to be used as such.

The information contained in these data is dynamic and may change over time.  The data are not better than the original sources from which they were derived.  It is the responsibility of the data user to use the data appropriately and consistent within the limitations of geospatial data in general and these data in particular.  Any related graphics (if available) are intended to aid the data user in acquiring relevant data; it is not approriate to use the related graphics as data.

The U.S. Geological Survey and the National Park Service gives no warranty, expressed or implied, as to the accuracy, reliability, or completeness of these data.  It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from an U.S. Geological Survey and National Park Service servers and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way.  Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the utility of the data on another system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data. Mention of trade names or commercial products in this metadata report does not constitute endorsement or recommendation for use by the U. S. Department of the Interior, U. S. Geological Survey and National Park Service.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>HTML</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://www.usgs.gov/core_science_systems/csas/vip/parks/pinn.html</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
<accinstr>Internet Access</accinstr>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20110802</metd>
<metrd>20130129</metrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS/CSS/Core Science Analytics and Synthesis</cntorg>
<cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program Coordinator</cntper>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, MS 302</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>303-202-4219</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
<metextns>
<onlink>http://www.usgs.gov/core_science_systems/csas/metadata/index.html</onlink>
</metextns>
</metainfo>
</metadata>