<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>U.S. Geological Survey, Core Science Analytics and Synthesis Program</origin>
        <pubdate>201308</pubdate>
        <title>National Fish Habitat Partnership Data System</title>
        <geoform>Maps, Data, Publication, Software and Tools</geoform>
        <onlink>http://ecosystems.usgs.gov/fishhabitat/index.html</onlink>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7765CBS</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Version 3.0 of the NFHP Data System consists of data access and visualization tools and underlying data management tools and functions.  The NFHP National Assessment Results Viewer allows users to visualize the primary results reported in Through a Fish's Eye: The Status of Fish Habitats in the United States 2010 at various spatial scales. It depicts the condition of stream and coastal habitats across the country on a variety of base maps and provides one-click access to more detailed information at finer scales. The NFHP Data Theme Viewer provides a summarized look at available data by theme.  Datasets are displayed to show data distribution and data density nationally, compared to available data linked to the NFHP spatial framework.  The first theme to be provided is the Biological Data theme.  Future priority data themes will be determined through the efforts of the National Science and Data Committee.  The NFHP Data System provides streamlined data access and download capabilities for national and partnership data via a familiar Web page format.  Behind the scenes, data management and delivery tools are powered by two existing USGS systems to enhance the data sharing, documentation, and delivery capabilities available to partners: USGS ScienceBase provides the data file upload and catalog services, while the USGS Core Science Metadata Clearinghouse assists with data documentation and preservation best practices that will improve the ability for partners, researchers, and managers whom access and use data now and in the future.</abstract>
      <purpose>The National Fish Habitat Partnership Data System supports coordinated efforts of scientific assessment and data exchange among the partners and stakeholders of the aquatic habitat community. The underlying data management tools and best practices are the foundation enabling partners, researchers, and managers to access and use data now and in the future.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>2000</begdate>
          <enddate>Present</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>publication date</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>In work</progress>
      <update>Frequency of system enhancements are anticipated 2 times a year and as needed, frequency of embedded data catalog updates will be irregular and multiple times throughout the year</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Nationwide; conterminous U.S. including Alaska and Hawaii</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-180.0</westbc>
        <eastbc>-63</eastbc>
        <northbc>74.00000</northbc>
        <southbc>17.00000</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>fish</themekey>
        <themekey>fish habitat</themekey>
        <themekey>National Fish Habitat Partnership</themekey>
        <themekey>NFHP</themekey>
        <themekey>National Fish Habitat Action Plan</themekey>
        <themekey>national assessment</themekey>
        <themekey>aquatic conservation</themekey>
        <themekey>National Hydrography Dataset Plus</themekey>
        <themekey>NHD+</themekey>
        <themekey>spatial framework</themekey>
        <themekey>landscape scale</themekey>
        <themekey>Habitat Condition Index</themekey>
        <themekey>HCI</themekey>
        <themekey>inland aquatic systems</themekey>
        <themekey>coastal aquatic systems</themekey>
        <themekey>inland and coastal aquatic systems</themekey>
        <themekey>human disturbance</themekey>
        <themekey>data management practices</themekey>
        <themekey>data management</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>All data are open and non proprietary.</accconst>
    <useconst>The NFHP Data System has been established to house authoritative versions of the data generated under the auspices of the National Fish Habitat Action Plan.  It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from the NFHP Data System, and not indirectly through other sources, which may have changed the data in some way.  
Although the data disseminated via the NFHP Data System have undergone data formatting quality review prior to posting, errors or inaccuracies may still exist in the data.  Neither the U.S. Government, the Department of the Interior, nor the USGS, nor any of their employees, contractors, or subcontractors, make any warranty, express or implied, nor assume any legal liability or responsibility for the accuracy, completeness, or usefulness of any information, apparatus, product, or process disclosed, nor represent that its use would not infringe on privately owned rights.  No warranty, expressed or implied, is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual and aggregate uses of the data.  The USGS shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data retrieved from the National Fish Habitat Partnership Data System.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Andrea Ostroff</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>physical</addrtype>
          <address>12201 Sunrise Valley Drive</address>
          <city>Reston</city>
          <state>VA</state>
          <postal>20192</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>703.648.4070</cntvoice>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <browse>
      <browsen>http://fishhabitat.org/sites/default/files/www/FishHabitat-final-vertical-RGB.jpg</browsen>
      <browsed>Vertical version of the NFHP logo; The RGB version may look the same as the 4-color or 2-color version, but is available only in JPEG and GIF format, and should be reserved for on-screen applications, such as websites or PowerPoint, or for low-grade/home printers. RGB stands for Red, Green and Blue. The RGB values for logo are: dark blue: 0, 39, 118; light blue: 0, 101, 189; blue used in reverse version: 114, 199, 231</browsed>
      <browset>JPEG</browset>
    </browse>
    <native>The NFHP Data System is a collection of multiple datasets in a variety of formats.</native>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>National Fish Habitat Board</origin>
        <pubdate>2010</pubdate>
        <title>Through a Fish?s Eye: The Status of Fish Habitats in the United States 2010</title>
        <geoform>Report</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Washington D.C.</pubplace>
          <publish>Association of Fish and Wildlife Agencies</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <othercit>68 pp.</othercit>
        <onlink>http://www.fishhabitat.org/sites/default/files/www/fishhabitatreport_Status.pdf</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>National Fish Habitat Board</origin>
        <pubdate>2012</pubdate>
        <title>National Fish Habitat Action Plan</title>
        <edition>2nd</edition>
        <geoform>Report</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Washington, D.C.</pubplace>
          <publish>Association of Fish and Wildlife Agencies</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <othercit>40 pp.</othercit>
        <onlink>http://www.fishhabitat.org/sites/default/files/www/NFHP_AP_Final_0.pdf</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
  </idinfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Andrea Ostroff</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>physical</addrtype>
          <address>12201 Sunrise Valley Drive</address>
          <city>Reston</city>
          <state>VA</state>
          <postal>20192</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>703.648.4070</cntvoice>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc>Data can be obtained via two URLs:  
NFHP Data System Home page(http://ecosystems.usgs.gov/fishhabitat/index.html);
NFHP Data System Data Download page(http://ecosystems.usgs.gov/fishhabitat/nfhap_download.html)</resdesc>
    <distliab>None</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>nfhap_public_catchment</formname>
          <formcont>Tiled map service of the National Fish Habitat Partnership Habitat Condition Index scores by National Hydrography Dataset Plus catchments</formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/nfhap/nfhap_scores_tiled_catchments_PROD/MapServer</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>nfhap_public_huc12</formname>
          <formcont>Tiled map service of the National Fish Habitat Partnership Habitat Condition Index scores by Hydrologic Unit Code (HUC)12</formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/nfhap/nfhap_scores_tiled_huc12_PROD/MapServer</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>nfhap_public_huc8</formname>
          <formcont>National Fish Habitat Partnership Habitat Condition Index scores by Hydrologic Unit Code (HUC)8</formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/nfhap/nfhap_public_huc8/MapServer</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>nfhap_public_edu</formname>
          <formcont>National Fish Habitat Partnership Habitat Condition Index scores by Ecological Drainage Units (EDU)</formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/nfhap/nfhap_public_edu/MapServer</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>nfhap_public_coastal</formname>
          <formcont>National Fish Habitat Partnership Coastal Assessment scores</formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://gis1.usgs.gov/arcgis/rest/services/nfhap/nfhap_public_coastal/MapServer</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20130917</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Metadata Coordinator</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>physical</addrtype>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>303-202-4333</cntvoice>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>