<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Led by the USGS and hosted by the Smithsonian Institution, in cooperation with ITIS partners USDA, NOAA, EPA, US FWS, Agriculture and Agri-Food Canada, National Park Service, Conabio, NatureServe.</origin>
        <pubdate>2013</pubdate>
        <title>Integrated Taxonomic Information System (ITIS)</title>
        <geoform>Tools Software</geoform>
        <onlink>http://www.itis.gov</onlink>
        <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7KH0KBK</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>ITIS is an easily accessible database with reliable information on species names and their hierarchical classification that is publicly accessible with unlimited free use. The database is reviewed periodically to ensure high quality with valid classifications, revisions, and additions of newly described species. The ITIS includes documented taxonomic information of flora and fauna from both aquatic and terrestrial habitats.
For each scientific name, ITIS includes the authority, taxonomic rank, a unique taxonomic serial number, data source information, data quality indicators, and associated synonyms and vernacular names where available. Geographic coverage is worldwide, with an emphasis on North American taxa.
The ITIS Web Services provide the ability to search and retrieve data from ITIS by providing access to the data behind the ITIS web site (http://www.itis.gov/web_service.html#). There is also web interface for viewing reports, and several options for text downloads. Each part of the basic WSDL web services is provided by a web service API, which defines the name, input to, and output from the service for a particular data request. For more information visit http://www.itis.gov/ws_description.html . To develop a web service client visit http://www.itis.gov/ws_develop.html .</abstract>
      <purpose>Use of the ITIS facilitates sharing of biological information among researchers and cooperating agencies by providing a common framework for taxonomic data.</purpose>
      <supplinf>ITIS partners with the Species 2000 (http://www.sp2000.org/) program to index the world's biological diversity, and together produces the the Catalogue of Life (http://www.catalogueoflife.org/col/info/about) which is used as a taxonomic backbone by the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF) data portal (http://data.gbif.org) and Encyclopedia of Life (http://www.eol.org).

History:
ITIS went online in June, 1996 when the ITIS database was populated from NODC (National Oceanographic Data Center Taxonomic Code V8). The data have history dating as far back as 1972 (http://web.vims.edu/GreyLit/VIMS/ssr065.pdf)</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>1972</begdate>
          <enddate>Present</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>publication date</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>In work</progress>
      <update>Monthly</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Global</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-180</westbc>
        <eastbc>180</eastbc>
        <northbc>90</northbc>
        <southbc>-90</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>population</themekey>
        <themekey>aquatics</themekey>
        <themekey>game</themekey>
        <themekey>informatics</themekey>
        <themekey>information transfer</themekey>
        <themekey>invasive species</themekey>
        <themekey>inventory</themekey>
        <themekey>methods development</themekey>
        <themekey>monitoring</themekey>
        <themekey>standards and protocols</themekey>
        <themekey>status and trends</themekey>
        <themekey>taxonomy/systematics</themekey>
        <themekey>waterfowl</themekey>
        <themekey>wildlife</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>Data can be obtained via the web (www.itis.gov), via download (http://www.itis.gov/ftp_download.html), webservices, (http://www.itis.gov/web_service.html). For all data access options see http://www.itis.gov/access.html</accconst>
    <useconst>No restrictions or constraints, but note this disclaimer:
ITIS taxonomy is based on the latest scientific consensus available, and is provided as a general reference source for interested parties. However, it is not a legal authority for statutory or regulatory purposes. While every effort has been made to provide the most reliable and up-to-date information available, ultimate legal requirements with respect to species are contained in provisions of treaties to which the United States is a party, wildlife statutes, regulations, and any applicable notices that have been published in the Federal Register. For further information on U.S. legal requirements with respect to protected taxa, please contact the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service. 

The recommended citiation guidelines for ITIS are found here http://www.itis.gov/citation.html</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Gerald "Stinger" Guala</cntper>
          <cntorg>United States Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>physical</addrtype>
          <address>12201 Sunrise Valley Drive</address>
          <city>Reston</city>
          <state>VA</state>
          <postal>20192</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>703-648-4311</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>gguala@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <browse>
      <browsen>http://www.usgs.gov/core_science_systems/csas/images/ITIS.jpg</browsen>
      <browsed>Thumbnail of ITIS graphic. (92px x 112px). Source from Core Science Analytics and Synthesis (CSAS) page. URL http://www.usgs.gov/core_science_systems/csas/activities.

High resolution ITIS graphics found html http://www.atomicweb.com/itis/</browsed>
      <browset>JPG</browset>
    </browse>
    <datacred>Led by the USGS and hosted by the Smithsonian Institution, in cooperation with ITIS partners USDA, NOAA, EPA, US FWS, Agriculture and Agri-Food Canada, National Park Service, Conabio, NatureServe.

The recommended citation guidelines for ITIS are found here http://www.itis.gov/citation.html</datacred>
    <tool>
      <tooldesc>No third party tools used. Data preparation is completed in the ITIS Taxonomic Workbench or the ITIS Online Taxonomic Workbench.</tooldesc>
      <toolacc>
        <onlink>http://www.itis.gov/twb.html</onlink>
        <toolinst>Instructions provided in online link</toolinst>
      </toolacc>
    </tool>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>ITIS has 3 Data Quality Indicators for names (http://www.itis.gov/glossary.html):

Record Credibility Rating (Populated for all records.) A rating determined by criteria established by the ITIS Taxonomic Work Group reflecting the level of review of the entire records data elements and the perceived level of accuracy of the records scientific name and associated attributes.

    Values:
    verified standards met All data elements in the record and the position of the scientific name in the hierarchy are perceived to be accurate and are supported by one or more credible references (e.g., publication, database, expert, data steward).

    verified minimum standards met Data in the record are incomplete and/or contain accuracy, placement, or nomenclatural issues, or are from a non-peer reviewed source. Data issues cant be resolved without detailed consultation with systematists and/or the pertinent literature.

    unverified Data in the record are of unknown quality (legacy data).

Latest Record Review (Populated at the rank of genus or above.) The year a record was reviewed by ITIS. See also cited references for their currency.

    Values:
    date (e.g., 1999)
    unknown

Global Species Completeness (Populated at the rank of genus and above.) A rating indicating whether all of the known species are represented in ITIS.

    Values:
    complete - All of the known species of the group are represented in ITIS.
    partial - Not all of the known species of the group are represented in ITIS.
    unknown - It is uncertain whether or not all of the known species of the group are represented in ITIS</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>See http://www.itis.gov/standard.html#data_standards for more information on Data Standards</logic>
    <complete>Measured at the level of genus and above using the Global Species Completeness indicator. See attribute accuracy above.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>Not Applicable.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>Not Applicable.</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>ITIS data conform with the International Code of Botanical Nomenclature and the International Code of Zoological Nomenclature</procdesc>
        <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>ITIS was established as a cooperative project among several federal agencies to improve and expand upon taxonomic data maintained by the National Oceanographic Data Center (NODC), National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA). ITIS inherited approximately 210,000 scientific names with varying levels of data quality from the NODC data set. Data content development and quality assurance strategy proceeds on two tracks: (1) adding new names or checklists with a high level of taxonomic credibility, and (2) reviewing and verifying the legacy NODC data, thereby bringing it to a minimal, or higher, standard of data quality.

For a view of ITIS source information, see http://www.itis.gov/contrib.html</procdesc>
        <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>ITIS accepts submissions of taxonomic data from the world scientific community. Data stewards and other cooperating specialists in the systematics community submit and review data. Data are reviewed and verified, and each scientific name is assigned a Taxonomic Serial Number (TSN), which is a unique and persistent identifier of scientific names of biological organisms within the ITIS reference system. For complete guidelines see --http://www.itis.gov/submit_guidlines.html</procdesc>
        <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref>ITIS includes continental/oceanic geography for taxa at rank of species and below. See http://www.itis.gov/submit_guidlines.html#geographic</indspref>
  </spdoinfo>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>The required ITIS elements are
    Scientific Name of the species
    Author(s) of the scientific name
    Rank of the scientific name
    Usage (current standing: accepted/valid; not accepted/invalid)
    Parent scientific name (mandatory if Scientific Name is accepted/valid)
    Associated Accepted Name (mandatory if Scientific Name is not accepted/invalid)
    Unacceptability Reason (mandatory if Scientific Name is not accepted/invalid)
    Reference for scientific name

The associated data fields are
    Vernaculars (common names)
    Geographic/Distribution information
    Jurisdiction information

See http://www.itis.gov/submit_guidlines.html for complete definitions of these elements.
And note, ITIS uses ISO-8859-1 character set.</eaover>
      <eadetcit>See http://www.itis.gov/submit_guidlines.html for complete definitions of these elements.
And note, ITIS uses ISO-8859-1 character set.</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Gerald "Stinger" Guala; Thomass M. Orrell</cntper>
          <cntorg>Stinger - United States Geological Survey; Thomas - Smithsonian Institution, Smithsonian National Museum of Natural History</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>physical</addrtype>
          <address>12201 Sunrise Valley Drive</address>
          <city>Reston</city>
          <state>VA</state>
          <postal>20192</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>physical</addrtype>
          <address>10th and Constitution Avenues, NW</address>
          <city>Washington DC</city>
          <state>Dictrict of Columbia</state>
          <postal>20560-0153</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>Stinger - 703-648-4311; Thomas - 202-633-2151</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>Stinger - gguala@usgs.gov; Thomas - Orrellt@si.edu</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc>Data is freely available without restrictions to re-use</resdesc>
    <distliab>ITIS taxonomy is based on the latest scientific consensus available, and is provided as a general reference source for interested parties. However, it is not a legal authority for statutory or regulatory purposes. While every effort has been made to provide the most reliable and up-to-date information available, ultimate legal requirements with respect to species are contained in provisions of treaties to which the United States is a party, wildlife statutes, regulations, and any applicable notices that have been published in the Federal Register. For further information on U.S. legal requirements with respect to protected taxa, please contact the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>ITIS Web Services</formname>
          <formvern>NA</formvern>
          <formcont>The ITIS Web Services provide the ability to search and retrieve data from ITIS by providing access to the data behind the ITIS web site. There is also web interface for viewing reports, and several options for text downloads. 

Each part of the basic WSDL web services is provided by a web service API, which defines the name, input to, and output from the service for a particular data request. For more information see http://www.itis.gov/ws_description.html
 
The ITIS JSON services provide an API that matches the Web Service API. All calls for JSON data are made by substituting "jsonservice" into the Web Service call in place of the "services/ITISService" part of the URL.

Besides standard JSON output, you can also get JSON data from the web service in JSON-P format. This provides the JSON data wrapped in a JavaScript function for safer cross-domain Ajax calls.</formcont>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://www.itis.gov/web_service.html#</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
    <custom>Database, available in several download formats including MySQL, SQLite, SQL Server, and PostgreSql. Also available are basic WSDL web services and JSON Web Services. There is also web interface for viewing reports, and several options for text downloads.</custom>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20130917</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>David Mitchell</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>National Museum of Natural History
PO Box 37012, MRC 180
Washington, DC 20013-7012</addrtype>
          <city>Washington, DC</city>
          <state>District of Columbia</state>
          <postal>20013</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>+1 (202) 633-2150</cntvoice>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>