<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="duc_merp.49.16" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 eml.xsd">  <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"><allow><principal>public</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
</allow>
<allow><principal>uid=duc_iwwr,o=unaffiliated,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
<permission>write</permission>
<permission>changePermission</permission>
</allow>
</access>
<dataset> <title>Marsh Ecology Research Program (MERP): Aboveground Macrophyte Production data (MAG; 1980-1989)</title>
 <creator id="1321306208875"><individualName><salutation>Mr.</salutation>
 <givenName>Arnold</givenName>
 <surName>van der Valk</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Department of Botany, Iowa State University</organizationName>
 <address><city>Ames</city>
 <administrativeArea>Iowa</administrativeArea>
 </address>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1321306271687"><organizationName>Ducks Unlimited Canada</organizationName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 1160</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Stonewall</city>
 <administrativeArea>Manitoba</administrativeArea>
 <country>Canada</country>
 </address>
 </creator>
 <abstract><para>The Marsh Ecology Research Program (MERP) was a long-term interdisciplinary study on the ecology of prairie wetlands. A scientific team from a variety of disciplines (hydrology, plant ecology, invertebrate ecology, vertebrate ecology, nutrient dynamics, marsh management) was assembled to design and oversee a long-term experiment on the effects of water-level manipulation on northern prairie wetlands. Ten years of fieldwork (1980 -1989), combining a routine long-term monitoring program and a series of short-term studies, generated a wealth of new and diverse information on the ecology and function of prairie wetlands (Murkin, Batt, Caldwell, Kadlec and van der Valk, 2000). This data set includes aboveground macrophyte production (MAG; 1980-1989) data, collected as part of the vegetation section of MERP.
	Determination of aquatic macrophyte annual net primary production is vital to the understanding of the dynamics of freshwater marshes. Macrophyte biomass, both live and dead, is a major storage compartment for carbon, nitrogen and phosphorus in a marsh and a major potential energy and nutrient source for the faunal component of the marsh ecosystem. Macrophyte communities are also essential structural components of the habitat of both invertebrates and vertebrates. The major objective of the long-term monitoring of aquatic macrophytes was to determine the impact of the wet-dry cycle on macrophyte above and belowground net annual production. Standard harvest techniques were used because they were the most direct, simple and reliable techniques available for estimating net annual primary production of macrophytes per unit area (van der Valk, 1989).

For further information on the Marsh Ecology Research Program (MERP), please visit: http://www.ducks.ca/conserve/research/projects/merp/index.html

References:
Murkin, H.R., B.D.J. Batt, P.J. Caldwell, J.A. Kadlec and A.G. van der Valk. 2000a. Introduction to the Marsh Ecology Research Program. In Prairie Wetland Ecology: The Contribution of the Marsh Ecology Research Program. (Eds) H.R. Murkin, A.G. van der Valk and W.R. Clark. pp. 3-15. Ames: Iowa State University Press. 
van der Valk, A.G. 1994. Effects of prolonged flooding on the distribution and biomass of emergent species along a freshwater wetland coenocline. Vegetatio 110: 185-196.

Resulting Publications on MERP vegetation data:
van der Valk, A.G., and C.H. Welling. 1988. The development of zonation in freshwater wetlands: an experimental approach. In Diversity and Pattern in Plant Communities. (Eds.) H.J. During, M.J.A. Werger, and H.J. Willems, pp.l45-158. The Hague, Netherlands: SPB Publishers.
van der Valk, A.G., C.H. Welling, and RL. Pederson. 1989. Vegetation change in a freshwater wetland: a test of a priori predictions. In Freshwater Wetlands and Wildlife. (Eds.) RR. Sharitz and J.W. Gibbons, pp.207-217. USDOE Symposium Series 61, Oak Ridge: USDOE Office of Scientific and Technical Information.
van der Valk, A.G. 1994. Effects of prolonged flooding on the distribution and biomass of emergent species along a freshwater wetland coenocline. Vegetatio 110: 185-196.
van der Valk, AG., L. Squires, and C.H. Welling. 1994. Identifying the impacts of an increase in water level on wetland vegetation undergoing succession. Ecological Applications 4:525-534.
van der Valk, A.G. 2000. Vegetation dynamics and models. In Prairie Wetland Ecology: The Contribution of the Marsh Ecology Research Program. (Eds.) H.R. Murkin, A.G. van der Valk, and W.R. Clark, pp. 37-54. Iowa: Iowa State University Press.
Welling, C.H., R.L. Pederson, and AG. van der Valk. 1988a. Recruitment from the seed bank and the development of zonation of emergent vegetation during drawdown in a prairie marsh. Journal of Ecology 76:483-496.
Welling, C.H., R.L. Pederson, and AG. van der Valk. 1988b. Temporal patterns in recruitment from the seed bank during drawdowns in a prairie wetland. Journal of Applied Ecology 25:999-1007.


Supporting literature on MERP vegetation data:
Cornwell, J.C., C. Neill, and J.C. Stevenson. 1995. Biogeochemical origin of &#916;34S isotopic signatures in a prairie marsh. Canadian Journal of Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences 52: 1816-1820.
de Swart, E.O.A.M., A.G. van der Valk, KJ. Koehler, and A. Barendregt. 1994. Experimental evaluation of realized niche models for predicting responses of plant species to a change in environmental conditions. Journal of Vegetation Science 5:541-552.
Galinato, M.J., and A.G. van der Valk. 1986. Seed germination traits of annuals and emergents during drawdown in the Delta Marsh, Manitoba, Canada. Aquatic Botany 26:89-102.
McKee, K.L., I.A Mendelssohn, and D.M. Burdick. 1989. Effect of long-term flooding on root metabolic response in five freshwater marsh plant species: Canadian Journal of Botany 67:3446-3452.
Merendino, M.T., L.M. Smith, H.R. Murkin, and RL. Pederson. 1990. The response of prairie wetland vegetation to seasonality of drawdown. Wildlife Society Bulletin 18: 245-251.
Merendino, M.T., and L.M. Smith. 1991. Influence of drawdown date and subsequent reflood depth on wetland vegetation establishment. Wildlife Society Bulletin 19: 143-150.
Neckles, H.A., J.A. Nelson, and R.L. Pederson. 1985. Management of whitetop (Scholochloa festucacea) marshes for livestock forage and wildlife. Delta Waterfowl and Wetlands Research Station Technical Bulletin 1. 
Neckles, H.A., and R.L. Wetzel. 1989. Effects of forage harvest in seasonally flooded prairie marshes: simulation model experiments. In Freshwater Wetlands and Wildlife. (Eds.) RR. Sharitz and J.W. Gibbons, pp.127-143. USDOE Symposium Series 61, Oak Ridge: USDOE Office of Scientific and Technical Information.
Neill. C. 1990. Effects of nutrients and water levels on emergent macrophyte biomass in a prairie marsh. Canadian Journal of Botany 68:1007-1014.
Neill, C 1990. Nutrient limitation of hardstem bulrush (Scirpus acutus Muhl.) in a Manitoba Interlake Region Marsh. Wetlands 10: 69-76.
Neill, C. 1990. Effects of nutrients and water levels on species composition in prairie whitetop (Scholochloa festucacea) marshes. Canadian Journal of Botany 68: 1015-1020.
Neill, C. 1992. Comparison of soil coring and ingrowth methods for measuring below ground production. Ecology 73:1918-1922.
Neill, C. 1992. Life history and population dynamics of whitetop (Scolochloa festucacea) shoots under different levels of flooding and nitrogen supply. Aquatic Botany 42: 241-252.
Neill, C. 1993. Growth and resource allocation of whitetop (Scolochloa festucacea) along a water depth gradient. Aquatic Botany 46:235-246.
Neill, C. 1993. Seasonal flooding, soil salinity and primary production in northern prairie marshes. Oecologia (Berl.) 95:499-505.
Neill, C. 1995. Seasonal flooding, nitrogen mineralization and nitrogen utilization in a prairie marsh. Biogeochemistry 30:171-189.
Neill, C., and J.C. Cornwell. 1992. Stable carbon, nitrogen, and sulfur isotopes in a prairie marsh food web. Wetlands 12:217-224.
Pederson, R.L. 1981. Seed bank characteristics of the Delta Marsh: applications for wetland management. In Selected Proceedings of the Midwest Conference on Wetland Values and Management. (Ed.) B. Richardson, pp.61-69. St. Paul: Minnesota Water Planning Board.
Pederson, R.L., and A.G. van der Valk. 1984. Vegetation change and seed banks in marshes: ecological and management implications. Transactions of the North American Wildlife and Natural Resources Conference 49:271-280.
Pederson, RL., and L.M. Smith. 1988. Implications of wetland seed bank research: a review of Great Basin and prairie marsh studies. In Interdisciplinary Approaches to Freshwater Wetlands Research. (Ed.) D.A. Wilcox, pp.81-95. East Lansing: Michigan State University Press.
Seabloom, E.W., K.A. Moloney, and A.G. van der Valk. Constraints on the establishment of plants along a fluctuating water-depth gradient. Ecology 82: 2216-2232.
Squires, L., and A.G. van der Valk. 1992. Water depth tolerances of the dominant emergent macrophytes of the Delta Marsh, Manitoba. Canadian Journal of Botany 70: 1860-1867.
van der Valk, A.G. 1981. Succession in wetlands: a Gleasonian approach. Ecology 62:688-696.
van der Valk, A.G. 1982. Succession in temperate North American wetlands. In Wetlands: Ecology and Management. (Eds.) B. Gopal, RE. Turner, R.G. Wetzel, and D.E Whigham, pp.169-179. Jaipur, India: National Institute of Ecology.
van der Valk, A.G.1986. The impact of litter and annual plants on recruitment of species from the seed bank of a lacustrine marsh. Aquatic Botany 24:13-26.
van der Valk, A.G. 1992. Establishment, colonization, and persistence. In Plant Succession: Theory and Prediction. (Eds.) D.C. Glenn-Lewin, R.K. Peet, and T.T. Veben, pp.60-102. New York: Chapman &amp; Hall.
van der Valk, A.G. 1992. Response by wetland vegetation to a change in water level. Wetland Management and Restoration. Swedish Environmental Protection Agency Report 3492. (Eds.) C.M. Finlayson and T. Larsson, pp.7-16. Solna, Sweden: Swedish Environmental Protection Agency.
van der Valk, A.G., and L. Squires. 1992. Indicators of flooding derived from aerial photography in northern prairie wetlands. In Ecological Indicators: Volume 1. (Eds.) D.H. McKenzie, D.E. Hyatt, and V.J. McDonald, pp.593-602. London, &#8226;UK: Elsevier.
van der Valk, A.G., and R.L. Pederson. 1989. Seed banks and the management and restoration of natural vegetation. In The Ecology of Seed Banks. (Eds.) M.A. Leck, VT. Parker, and RL. Simpson, pp.329-346. New York: Academic Press.
van der Valk, A.G., R.L. Pederson, and C.B. Davis. 1992. Restoration and creation of freshwater wetlands using seed banks. Wetlands Ecology and Management 1:191-197.
van der Valk, A.G., L. Squires, and C.H. Welling. 1994. Identifying the impacts of an increase in water level on wetland vegetation undergoing succession. Ecological Applications 4:525-534.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>prairie wetland ecology</keyword>
 <keyword>wetlands</keyword>
 <keyword>marshes</keyword>
 <keyword>marsh ecology research program</keyword>
 <keyword>MERP</keyword>
 <keyword>wet-dry cycle</keyword>
 <keyword>Delta Marsh</keyword>
 <keyword>marsh management</keyword>
 <keyword>hydrology</keyword>
 <keyword>drawdown</keyword>
 <keyword>flooding</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet><keyword>macrophytes</keyword>
 <keyword>aboveground</keyword>
 <keyword>production</keyword>
 <keyword>emergents</keyword>
 <keyword>clip plot</keyword>
 <keyword>biomass</keyword>
 <keyword>nutrient content</keyword>
 <keyword>vegetation</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <intellectualRights><para>Please obtain written permission from the owners prior to using this data package. Please cite the owners of the data, including the principal investigator(s) and Ducks Unlimited Canada, in any publications that use this data. Although substantial efforts have been made to verify the accuracy of data and metadata contained within this data package, complete accuracy cannot be guaranteed.</para>
 </intellectualRights>
 <coverage> <temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1980-08-08</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate><calendarDate>1989-08-03</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 <taxonomicCoverage><taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Aster brachyactis</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Aster hesperius</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Atriplex argentea</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Atriplex patula</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Carex atherodes</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Ceratophyllum demersum</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Chenopodium rubrum</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Cirsium arvense</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Entromorpha intestinalis</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Hordeum jubatum</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Lactuca pulchella</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Lathyrus palustris</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Lemna minor</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Lemna trisulca</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Lycopus asper</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Mentha arvensis</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Myriophyllum exalbescens</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Phragmites australis</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Poa pratensis</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Potamogeton pectinatus</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Puccinellia nuttalliana</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Rumex maritimus</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Scholochloa festucacea</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Scirpus acutus</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Scirpus maritimus</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Scirpus validus</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Scutellaria galericulata</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Solidago canadensis</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Sonchus arvensis</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Stachys palustris</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Suaeda depressa</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Symphoricarpos occidentalis</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Teucrium occidentale</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Typha angustifolia</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Typha glauca</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Typha latifolia</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Unidentified algae</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Unidentified grass</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Urtica dioica</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Utricularia vulgaris</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Zannichellia palustris</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicCoverage>
 <geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Marsh Ecology Research Complex: The MERP study area was located on the Delta Marsh in south central Manitoba, Canada. The Delta Marsh is a large lacustrine marsh (approximately 50,000 ha) along the southern shore of Lake Manitoba. The experimental complex consisted of 10 contiguous wetland cells (approximately 5 ha each).</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-98.22</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>-98.12178</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>50.21</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>50.21</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact id="1321551258453"><organizationName>Institute for Wetland and Waterfowl Research, Ducks Unlimited Canada</organizationName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 1160</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Stonewall</city>
 <administrativeArea>Manitoba</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>R0C 2Z0</postalCode>
 <country>Canada</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">1-800-665-DUCK</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>library@ducks.ca</electronicMailAddress>
 </contact>
 <contact id="1321551272421"><individualName><givenName>Lisette</givenName>
 <surName>Ross</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Institute for Wetland and Waterfowl Research, Ducks Unlimited Canada</organizationName>
 <positionName>Wetland Biologist</positionName>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><title>MERP Aboveground Macrophyte Production data (1980-1989) methods</title>
 <para>Sampling for aboveground macrophyte production occurred once in late July or early August during the sampling season, as this is the period where standing emergents reach their maximum standing crop. The appearance of fully-grown Typha sp. was generally used to gauge if macrophytes had reached their maximum standing crop. Clip plot (MAGs) were one set of methods used to estimate aboveground production (van der Valk, 1989).</para>
 <para>Four randomly selected sample sites were determined on each of the 10 transects in all 12 cells each year, while respecting a 10m buffer zone around the perimeter of each cell, for a total of 480 clip quadrats. The sites were numbered consecutively from the northeast to the southwest corner of each cell.  At each site, depending on species present, a 1 x 1 m (Typha glauca syn. Typha &#215; glauca, Phragmites australis, or Scirpus spp.) or a &#188; x &#188; m (all other, smaller species) quadrat was used to clip the plots. Not all MAG sites from each cell were sampled at once; transects were grouped into pairs (1&amp;2, 3&amp;4, 5&amp;6, 7&amp;8, and 9&amp;10) and then each transect pair from each cell was randomly assigned a number from 1-60 and then sampled in that order (van der Valk, 1989). At dry sites, all live and dead standing vegetation was clipped. All specimens of the five dominant emergent species (i.e. Scholochloa festucacea, Typha spp., Phragmites australis, Scirpus acutus syn. Schoenoplectus acutus, and Carex atherodes; for the 1988 sampling year only, Scirpus validus syn. Schoenoplectus tabernaemontani was added as a sixth dominant emergent) were separated. If there were other species present at the sites with greater than 25% cover, they as well were separated by species. Species present with cover of less than 25% were combined and labeled &#8216;minor species&#8217;. All five major species, any other dominant species (i.e. greater than 25% cover) and the &#8216;minor species&#8217; group were also separated into live and dead fractions. From 1980-82, the % cover of each species present at the site was recorded in the field book. Burlap and paper bags were used to hold the samples and bring them back to the laboratory. Where there was water present, water depth was recorded starting in 1981. If submerged aquatic macrophytes were present, they were sampled by cutting along the edge of the quadrat and scooped into the sample bags. Filamentous algae was also sampled and separated from the other species present. The samples were dried to constant weight at 80 &#186;C and weighed. Select samples were then ground using a Wiley mill and then sent to the Freshwater Institute (1980-1984) or Iowa State University (1985-1989) for nutrient analysis of nitrogen, carbon and phosphorus (van der Valk 1989).</para>
 <para>Notes on reading the data:</para>
 <para>please note:</para>
 <para>-missing values (sample lost, equiptment malfunction, recording failure) in respective columns are represented by having two consecutive commas occur within the sample row.</para>
 <para>--For aboveground (i.e. clip plots, mag) macrophyte sampling, previously separate nutrient (i.e. nitrogen, phosphorus and carbon concentrations) and sample vegetation data (i.e. water level, species code, live or dead, etc.) computer files were merged into one data file for archiving purposes. Nutrient data was associated to its respective sample vegetation data using the ground number. An artifact of this merging process, however, is there were cases where nutrient data did not have a corresponding match (i.e. by ground number) in sample vegetation data, or that the corresponding ground number to nutrient data had been lost. This has created nutrient &#8216;orphans&#8217; (i.e. nutrient data with no corresponding information on sample vegetation) at the end of each sampling year in the data files. A potential source for this artifact is an error in the recording of ground numbers. However, the data was retained in the combined datafiles to increase the accuracy of a yearly cumulative nutrient estimation.</para>
 <para>References:</para>
 <para>van der Valk, A. 1989. Macrophyte production. In Marsh Ecology Research Program: Long-term Monitoring Procedures Manual. (Eds.) E.J. Murkin and H.R. Murkin, pp. 23-29. Manitoba, Canada: Delta Waterfowl Research Station.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Marsh Ecology Research Program: Objectives, study area and experimental design (1980-1989)</title>
 <para>Introduction</para>
 <para>Good et al. (1978) and Greeson et al. (1978) were among the first to summarize the state of our understanding in freshwater wetland ecology. They emphasized the need for expanded interdisciplinary research in freshwater wetlands. Ten years later, van der Valk (1989), in Northern Prairie Wetlands, focused specifically on prairie wetlands and the influence of water-level changes on the dynamics and productivity of these systems.</para>
 <para>Primary production, secondary production, vegetation composition and distribution, animal use, and nutrient budgets are all affected as water levels rise and fall with variation in precipitation. Ranging from tiny potholes to huge lacustrine complexes, prairie wetlands are among the world's most productive ecosystems (Murkin, 1989a). Their importance as wildlife production areas has drawn considerable attention to their conservation and management (Weller, 1978; Weller, 1981). This attention has increased in recent years with the need for information on the overall functions and values of wetlands within the prairie landscape (Murkin, 1998). Understanding wetland values is critical to the development of comprehensive wetland conservation programs. In addition, the ongoing destruction of wetlands through drainage, urban sprawl, and other human-induced changes has added a great deal of urgency to the need for a better understanding of the ecology and management of all remaining wetland areas (Murkin et al., 2000a).</para>
 <para>Objectives</para>
 <para>Recognizing the need for an improved understanding of prairie wetland ecology, the Marsh Ecology Research Program (MERP) was initiated in 1979 as a joint project of</para>
 <para>Ducks Unlimited Canada and the Delta Waterfowl and Wetlands Research Station (Murkin et al., 1984). The MERP was designed as a long-term replicated experiment addressing the impacts of various water levels on the main components of the prairie wetland ecosystem. The overall objective of MERP was to document the changes that occur within a prairie wetland during a simulated wet-dry cycle (van der Valk and Davis, 1978). More specifically, MERP was designed to determine the storage (pools) and movement (fluxes) of nitrogen (N), phosphorus (P), and carbon (C) during the various stages of the cycle (Murkin et al., 2000a). Specific objectives for each of the major ecosystem components were as follows:</para>
 <para>1. Hydrology: to estimate the terms of the water budget during all stages of the wet-dry cycle: surface water in and out, ground water in and out, change in storage, precipitation, and evapotranspiration.</para>
 <para>2. Water chemistry: to estimate the concentrations of N, P, C, and major ions in both surface and substrate pore-water pools and to monitor changes in these pools during the wet-dry cycle.</para>
 <para>3. Macrophytes: to estimate annual above- and below ground macrophyte productivity and standing crops and subsequent changes related to the wet-dry cycle. Storage and movement of N, P, and C in macrophytes during the wet-dry cycle also were determined.</para>
 <para>4. Macrophyte litter: to estimate the annual production of above- and belowground macrophyte litter and the loss and uptake of N, P, and C to and from the litter compartment.</para>
 <para>5. Algae: to estimate algal standing crops and productivity (phytoplankton, epiphyton, epipelon, and metaphyton) during the various stages of the wet-dry cycle.</para>
 <para>6. Invertebrates: to estimate standing crops of invertebrates (nekton, benthos, and emerging insects) during the various phases of the wet-dry cycle.</para>
 <para>7. Vertebrates: to monitor use by waterfowl, coots, blackbirds, and muskrats in response to habitat changes during the wet- dry cycle.</para>
 <para>The MERP experimental design and field-sampling protocols were developed to meet these objectives. Nutrient data were used to construct nutrient budgets for the experimental cells. Several additional objectives beyond those related specifically to nutrient storage and movement also were addressed. Examples are rate of recovery of plant communities following drawdown (Welling et al., 1988a), habitat use by various vertebrate groups during specific stages of the wet-dry cycle (Clark and Kroeker, 1993), and the effect of the wet-dry cycle on individual invertebrate species (Ross and Murkin, 1993; Murkin et al., 2000a).</para>
 <para>Study Area</para>
 <para>The MERP study area was located on the Delta Marsh in south-central Manitoba, Canada (50&#61616;11'N, 98&#176;19'W). The Delta Marsh is a large lacustrine marsh (&#61627;15,000 ha) along the southern shore of Lake Manitoba (see Batt, 2000). The marsh is of Pleistocene origin and is a remnant of glacial Lake Agassiz (L&#246;ve and L&#246;ve, 1954, Ehrlich et al., 1957). An important feature of the marsh is that its water level has been stabilized for many years (due to installation of a water-control structure on Lake Manitoba in 1961), resulting in lake marsh conditions described by van der Valk and Davis (1978) over much of its area (Murkin et al., 2000a). The site for the MERP experimental complex was chosen because of several features. First, the area had representative portions of shallow- and deep-marsh zones characteristic of the Delta Marsh and other northern prairie marshes. Second, the area was remote and completely within the private ownership of the Delta Waterfowl and Wetlands Research Station, thus ensuring access for researchers, while affording effective control of trespass and disturbance. Third, the site was served by an existing road system. This road system was crucial, given the large number of individuals working on the site each day; the large numbers and volumes of water, soil, vegetation, and animal samples to be handled; and the logistics of transporting and maintaining sampling devices. Finally, the existing road provided the northern boundary of the experimental cells, thereby reducing construction costs. The water levels used in the experiments were chosen to reflect conditions that had occurred naturally during the previous 5 decades. Thus, the experimental site and design has provided information that is relevant to any future management efforts on the Delta Marsh, specifically, and wetland management in general.</para>
 <para>The experimental cell complex consisted of 10 contiguous 4-6 ha marsh units (Cells 1-10), created in 1979 by building a series of dikes along the northern edge of the main marsh. The diked experimental cells were numbered 1 to 10 from west to east. The approximate dimension of each diked cell was 150m x 300m (see Table 1 for the specific dimensions of each cell). Disturbance due to dike construction was confined to the dikes and a 10m buffer strip on each side of the dike. Each diked cell was equipped with a water control structure and electric pump with automatic controls to adjust and maintain (&#61617;2cm) water levels according to the schedule (see Table 2). Besides the diked cells, two undiked areas of similar size within the Delta Marsh (Cells 11 &amp; 12) were monitored as reference cells (i.e. reference cells to the unmanipulated Delta Marsh). The vegetation within the diked cells prior to the experimental treatments was comparable to the reference cells and main Delta Marsh (Pederson 1981; Murkin et al., 2000a).</para>
 <para>Experimental Design</para>
 <para>The general MERP objective was to monitor the response of various aspects of the wetland ecosystem to a series of water-level manipulations intended to simulate the wet-dry cycle of prairie wetlands. The schedule for water-level treatments and the number of replicates for each treatment are shown in Tables 2 and 3. The study was basically divided into four phases. The first two phases (baseline and deep flooding) were designed to provide background information on the experimental cells and to bring all cells to a similar condition (lake marsh stage) before the actual wet-dry cycle was applied during the last two phases (drawdown and reflooding; Murkin et al., 2000a). The four phases of the experimental design were as follows:</para>
 <para>a.	Baseline year (1980-1981):</para>
 <para>During the first year of the study (1980), the control structures were left open and water levels within the cells were allowed to track the levels of the Delta Marsh. This method provided a year of baseline data before the actual water-level manipulations began. Two of the cells (3 and 7) were kept at baseline levels for a second year (1981) to allow for comparison of different durations of drawdown later in the study (see Table 3).</para>
 <para>b.	Deep flooding (aka Conditioning Period; 1981-1983):</para>
 <para>Following the baseline year(s), all diked cells were flooded to ~ 1 m above normal for a period of 2 years (Table 2). These levels were designed to flood the existing cattail (Typha spp.) stands to a depth of 1 m and were similar to actual natural high-water levels that occurred in the Delta Marsh in the 1950s. This deep flooding was intended to kill the existing emergent vegetation and set all the cells to the lake marsh stage described by van der Valk and Davis (1978). In part, deep flooding was also an attempt to reduce the variability in vegetation among the experimental cells prior to drawdown.</para>
 <para>c.	Drawdown (1983-1984):</para>
 <para>After the second year of above-normal flooding, the cells were drawn down (completely dewatered) by adjusting the water levels to 50 cm below the long-term level of the Delta Marsh (Table 2). Most cells were exposed to a 2-year drawdown. Two cells (3 and 7) were drawn down for 1 year to allow comparisons between drawdowns of 1- and 2-year durations. The drawdowns allowed vegetation to reestablish on the marsh substrates (Welling et al., 1988a, b).</para>
 <para>d.	Reflooding (1985-1989):</para>
 <para>It has been assumed that the rate at which prairie wetlands proceed through the various stages of the wet-dry cycle is determined by water depth, with deeper wetlands moving to the lake marsh stage more quickly than shallowly flooded wetlands (van der Valk and Davis, 1978). Following drawdown, the cells were reflooded to three different levels (Table 3). The normal level was the long-term mean level (247.50 m above mean sea level [AMSL]) of the Delta Marsh and the medium (247.80 m) and high (248.10 m) levels were 30 and 60 cm above the long-term mean, respectively (Murkin et al., 2000a).</para>
 <para>To ensure replicated treatments (on a hydrologic basis) during the reflooding experiments in 1985-1989, water-level treatments were assigned to the experimental cells as follows: the two low-water treatments with a 1-year drawdown (Table 3) were randomly assigned to the experimental complex, and the remaining treatments were then assigned to the other cells to ensure that each cell within a water-level treatment had a similar hydrologic setting (i.e. both low cells with 1-year drawdowns were flanked by cells with low and high treatments, both low 2-year drawdown cells by low and medium treatments, all medium treatment cells by high- and low-treatment cells, and the high-treatment cells by medium and low cells). This replicated hydrology is discussed in more detail in Kadlec (1983, 1993). The treatment assignments for the 1985-1989 period (Table 3) determined the water-level assignments during the early phases of the MERP experiments from 1981 to 1984 (Table 2).</para>
 <para>Long-term Monitoring Program</para>
 <para>The Scientific Team designed a program of standardized methods to monitor the experimental cells throughout the period of study. The basic strategy was to collect a comparable data set from year to year in each experimental cell for each of the major components being monitored, including hydrology, water chemistry, macrophytes, macrophyte litter, algae, invertebrates and vertebrates (Murkin et al., 2000a; Murkin, 1989b). The MERP long-term monitoring program involved a variety of techniques that were used to provide comparable datasets across the experimental cells and over the 10 years of fieldwork. Some of the techniques used were new, but most were adopted from other researchers. All have been modified to suit the needs for efficiency, economy and practicality for long-term large-scale ecosystem research (Murkin et al., 2000b). Each component has a section in the MERP Data Archive describing the techniques used.</para>
 <para>Short-term Studies</para>
 <para>Besides the long-term monitoring program, short-term studies were an integral component of the overall MERP program. Some of these studies provided background information needed to develop the long-term monitoring program (Pederson, 1981; Wrubleski, 1984). Some were integrated into the long-term monitoring program (Murkin, 1983a; Galinato, 1985; Hosseini, 1986; Welling, 1987; Merendino, 1989). Several aspects of the long-term monitoring program following drawdown began as short-term studies (Kroeker, 1988; Squires, 1991; Wrubleksi, 1991). Many of the short-term studies, however, were initiated because of questions raised by the long-term monitoring program. This approach was particularly true for studies of invertebrates (Nelson, 1982; Neckles, 1984; Bicknese, 1987; Campeau, 1990) and emergent macrophytes (Neill, 1988; Neill, 1992). Many of the short-term studies were conducted by graduate studies, a list of which can be found in merp_pubs_appx3_prairie_wetland_ecology_pdfa.pdf and whose theses can be found in the merp_publications_theses file (Murkin et al., 2000a).</para>
 <para>Main Transects, Work Lanes and Sampling Procedure</para>
 <para>To aid in the assignment of sampling stations, each cell was divided into 10 zones. Zone boundaries were parallel to the southern dike. To determine the zones, 10 areas of equal width were established between a line 10 m north of the south dike and a second line 10 m south of the road on the northern edge of the cell. These zones were permanently marked so they could be located from year to year.</para>
 <para>Each year, ten transects were randomly established within each cell, 1 per zone, numbered from north to south. These transects or &#8216;work lanes&#8217; were used for all types of routine sampling, in order to minimize disturbance and confine it within a designated region. All sampling took place as near as possible to the work lane. When a sampling point was some distance from the work lane, a path perpendicular to the work lane was established. Work lanes were reassigned each fall following the last day of sampling (Murkin, 1989b; Murkin et al., 2000b).</para>
 <para>A standard sampling procedure was maintained during all transect sampling. One or two random transects in each cell were sampled, repeating the same method for each cell until all samples were secured, rather than sampling all transects in a cell before moving on to the next cell. This randomized any effect due to time during the sampling period. As standard procedure, water depth at the sampling site was recorded during all types of sampling (Murkin, 1983b).</para>
 <para>Additional data packages generated from the Marsh Ecology Research Program can also be found on the Knowledge Network for Biocomplexity (KNB):</para>
 <para>AERIAL MAPS &amp; GIS</para>
 <para>Aerial photos, cover maps and GIS data (1980-1989)</para>
 <para>ALGAE:</para>
 <para>Algal data transect sampling (1985-1989)</para>
 <para>Metaphyton data (1985-1989)</para>
 <para>Epipelon data (1985-1989)</para>
 <para>Epiphyton data (1985-1989)</para>
 <para>Phytoplankton data (1985-1989)</para>
 <para>ANNUAL CLIMATIC FACTORS:</para>
 <para>Weather data (1980-1989)</para>
 <para>Marsh evaporation pan data (1981-1989)</para>
 <para>DECOMPOSITION:</para>
 <para>Short-term dead standing litter study data (1981-1984)</para>
 <para>Root decomposition litter bag study data (1986-1989)</para>
 <para>Shoot decomposition litter bag study data (1986-1989)</para>
 <para>Decomposition of mud-flat species litter bag study data (1985-1987)</para>
 <para>Decomposition of mud-flat species litter bag study data (1983-1985)</para>
 <para>Emergent macrophyte and metaphyton litter bag study data (1983-1984)</para>
 <para>Turnover plot litter bag study data (1981-1983)</para>
 <para>Conditioning period litter bag study data (1980-1981)</para>
 <para>Preliminary litter bag study data (1979-1982)</para>
 <para>Dead standing litter study data (1985-1989)</para>
 <para>HYDROLOGY:</para>
 <para>Hydraulic conductivity data (1982-1989)</para>
 <para>Water table levels (1982-1989)</para>
 <para>Pump meter data (1980-1989)</para>
 <para>Staff gauge data (1980-1989)</para>
 <para>INVERTEBRATES:</para>
 <para>Artificial substrates data (1985-1989)</para>
 <para>Substrate core data (1980-1982)</para>
 <para>Sweep net data (1980-1982)</para>
 <para>Emergence trap data (1980-1989)</para>
 <para>Activity trap data (1980-1989)</para>
 <para>Maximum-minimum water temperature data (1980-1984)</para>
 <para>Chironomidae (Diptera) responses to the experimental flooding of prairie marshes (1985-1988)</para>
 <para>PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT:</para>
 <para>Total suspended solids data (1980-1989)</para>
 <para>Sediment bulk density and percent organic matter data (1986-1989)</para>
 <para>SOIL NUTRIENTS:</para>
 <para>Soil nutrients and groundwater well site characterization data (1980-1985)</para>
 <para>VEGETATION:</para>
 <para>Matching stems study data (1986-1989)</para>
 <para>Belowground macrophyte production data (MBG; 1980-1989)</para>
 <para>Aboveground macrophyte production data (MAG; 1980-1989)</para>
 <para>Turnover plot data (1980-1989)</para>
 <para>VERTEBRATES:</para>
 <para>Nest count data (1980-1989)</para>
 <para>Avian census data (1980-1989)</para>
 <para>Muskrat habitat selection data (1986)</para>
 <para>Muskrat population data (1985-1989)</para>
 <para>WATER CHEMISTRY:</para>
 <para>Water chemistry data (1980-1989)</para>
 <para>Tables</para>
 <para>Table 1: Dimensions of the MERP cells (from Murkin, 1983b)</para>
 <para>Cells	Width (m)a	Length (m)b	Work zone width (m)	Area (ha)</para>
 <para>1	155	300	30	5.68</para>
 <para>2	190	300	30	7.5</para>
 <para>3	130	330	33	5.48</para>
 <para>4	135	310	31	6.08</para>
 <para>5	135	300	30	6.04</para>
 <para>6	135	320	32	6.45</para>
 <para>7	161	320	32	6.01</para>
 <para>8	153	300	30	5.75</para>
 <para>9	151	280	28	5.50</para>
 <para>10	200	200	20	5.80</para>
 <para>11	150	300	30	5.40</para>
 <para>12	150	320	32	5.75</para>
 <para>a  - measured from a point 10m east of the borrow ditch to a second point 10m west of the east dike. Since the width of an individual cell varies from north to south these are the mean values.</para>
 <para>b  - measured from a line 10m north of the south dike to a parallel line 10m south of the north edge of the cell.</para>
 <para>Table 2: Schedule of water levels for MERP experimental cells (from Murkin et al., 2000a).</para>
 <para>Year	Water Levels</para>
 <para>1980	10 cells normal levels of Delta Marsh (247.50m AMSL)</para>
 <para>1981	8 cells flooded to conditioning level (&#61627;1m above normal; 248.41m AMSL)</para>
 <para>2 cells (3 &amp; 7) at normal levels of Delta Marsh (247.50m AMSL)</para>
 <para>1982	10 cells at conditioning level (&#61627;1m above normal; 248.41m AMSL)</para>
 <para>1983	8 cells drawn down (247.00m AMSL)</para>
 <para>2 cells (3 &amp; 7) remain at conditioning level (&#61627;1m above normal; 248.41m AMSL)</para>
 <para>1984	10 cells drawn down (247.00m AMSL)</para>
 <para>1985-1989	4 cells (3,4,7 &amp; 8) flooded at normal level (247.50m AMSL)</para>
 <para>3 cells (1,5 &amp; 9) flooded at medium level (247.80m AMSL)</para>
 <para>3 cells (2,6 &amp; 10) flooded at high level (248.10m AMSL)</para>
 <para>Table 3: Experimental cells within each of the water levels following drawdown (1985-1989; from Murkin et al., 2000a).</para>
 <para>Water level after drawdown (AMSL)</para>
 <para>Drawdown duration (years)	Shallow (247.50m)	Medium (247.80m)	High (248.19m)</para>
 <para>1	3,7</para>
 <para>2	4,8	1,5,9	2,6,10</para>
 <para>Table 4: Common MERP Prefixes</para>
 <para>Prefix	MERP Sample Type</para>
 <para>MBG	Macrophyte belowground samples</para>
 <para>MAG	Macrophyte aboveground samples</para>
 <para>TO	Turnover plot samples</para>
 <para>DSL (CQ)	Dead standing litter (clip-quadrat) samples</para>
 <para>LB	Litterbag samples</para>
 <para>MS (PERM)	Matching stems (Permanent clips) samples</para>
 <para>SW	Surface water samples</para>
 <para>GW	Groundwater samples</para>
 <para>PO	Pump water samples (out of cell)</para>
 <para>PI	Pump water samples (into cell)</para>
 <para>RW	Rain water samples</para>
 <para>AS	Artificial substrate samples</para>
 <para>AT	Activity trap samples</para>
 <para>ET	Emergence trap samples</para>
 <para>References</para>
 <para>Batt, B.D.J. 2000. The Delta Marsh. In Prairie Wetland Ecology: The Contribution of the Marsh Ecology Research Program. (Eds) H.R. Murkin, A.G. van der Valk and W.R. Clark. pp. 17-33. Ames: Iowa State University Press.</para>
 <para>Bicknese, N.A. 1987. Factors influencing the decomposition of fallen macrophyte litter at the Delta Marsh, Manitoba, Canada. M.S. thesis, Iowa State University. Ames, Iowa.</para>
 <para>Campeau, S. 1990. The relative importance of algae and detritus to freshwater wetland food chains. M.S. thesis, McGill University, Montreal, Quebec.</para>
 <para>Clark, W.R., and D. W. Kroeker. 1993. Population dynamics of muskrats in experimental marshes at Delta, Manitoba. Canadian Journal of Zoology 71: 1620-1 628.</para>
 <para>Ehrlich, W.A., E.A. Poyser, and L.E. Pratt. 1957. Report on the reconnaissance soil survey of Carberry map sheet area. Soils Report 7, Manitoba Soils Survey, Winnipeg, Manitoba.</para>
 <para>Galinato, M.I. 1985. Seed germination studies of dominant mudflat-annual and emergent species of the Delta Marsh. M.S. thesis, Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa.</para>
 <para>Good, R. E., D.F. Whigham, and R.L. Simpson (Eds.). 1978. Freshwater Wetlands: Ecological Processes and Management Potential. New York: Academic Press.</para>
 <para>Greeson, P.E., J.R. Clark, and J.E. Clark (Eds.). 1978. Wetland Functions and Values: The State of Our Understanding. American Water Resources Association Technical Publication TPS79-2.</para>
 <para>Hosseini, S.M. 1986. The effects of water level fluctuations on algal communities of freshwater marshes. Ph.D. dissertation, Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa.</para>
 <para>Kadlec, J.A. 1983. Water budgets for small diked marshes. Water Resources Bulletin 19:223-229.</para>
 <para>Kadlec, J.A. 1993. Effect of depth of flooding on summer water budgets for small diked marshes. Wetlands 13: 1-9.</para>
 <para>Kroeker, D.W. 1988. Population dynamics of muskrats in managed marshes at Delta, Manitoba. M.S. thesis, Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa.</para>
 <para>L&#246;ve, A., and D. L&#246;ve. 1954. Vegetation of a prairie marsh. Bulletin of the Torrey Botanical Club 81:16-34.</para>
 <para>Merendino, M.T. 1989. The response of vegetation to seasonality of drawdown and reflood depth. M.S. thesis, Texas Tech University, Lubbock, Texas.</para>
 <para>Murkin, H.R. 1983a. Responses by aquatic macroinvertebrates to prolonged flooding of marsh habitat. Ph.D. dissertation, Utah State University, Logan, Utah.</para>
 <para>Murkin, H.R. 1983b. Introduction. In Marsh Ecology Research Program: Long-term Monitoring Procedures Manual. (Ed.) H.R. Murkin. pp. 1-9. Manitoba: Delta Waterfowl Research Station.</para>
 <para>Murkin, H.R. 1989a. The basis for food chains in prairie wetlands. In Northern Prairie Wetlands. (Ed.) A.G. van der Valk, pp.316-338. Ames: Iowa State University Press.</para>
 <para>Murkin, H.R. 1989b. Introduction to the Marsh Ecology Research Program. In Marsh Ecology Research Program: Long-term Monitoring Procedures Manual. (Eds.) E.J. Murkin and H.R. Murkin. pp. 1-3. Manitoba: Delta Waterfowl Research Station.</para>
 <para>Murkin, H.R. 1998. Freshwater functions and values of prairie wetlands. Great Plains Research 8:3-15.</para>
 <para>Murkin, H.R., B.D.J. Batt, P.J. Caldwell, C.B. Davis, J.A. Kadlec, and A.G. van der Valk. 1984. Perspectives on the Delta Waterfowl Research Station- Ducks Unlimited Canada Marsh Ecology Research Program. Transactions of the North American Wildlife and Natural Resources Conference 49:253-261.</para>
 <para>Murkin, H.R., B.D.J. Batt, P.J. Caldwell, J.A. Kadlec and A.G. van der Valk. 2000a. Introduction to the Marsh Ecology Research Program. In Prairie Wetland Ecology: The Contribution of the Marsh Ecology Research Program. (Eds) H.R. Murkin, A.G. van der Valk and W.R. Clark. pp. 3-15. Ames: Iowa State University Press.</para>
 <para>Murkin, H.R., W.R. Clark, S.E. Gurney, J.A. Kadlec, G.G.C. Robinson, L.C.M. Ross and A.G. van der Valk. 2000b. Summary of MERP techniques and sampling program. In Prairie Wetland Ecology: The Contribution of the Marsh Ecology Research Program. (Eds) H.R. Murkin, A.G. van der Valk and W.R. Clark. pp. 359-379. Ames: Iowa State University Press.</para>
 <para>Neckles, H.A. 1984. Plant and macroinvertebrate responses to water regime in a whitetop marsh. M.S. thesis, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, Minnesota.</para>
 <para>Neill, C. 1988. Control of primary productivity of emergent macrophytes in prairie marshes: effects of water depth and nutrient availability. M.S. thesis, University of Massachusetts, Amherst, Massachusetts.</para>
 <para>Neill, C. 1992. Relationships between emergent plant production and seasonal flooding in prairie whitetop (Scholochloa festucacea) marshes. Ph.D. dissertation, University of Massachusetts, Amherst, Massachusetts.</para>
 <para>Nelson, J.W. 1982. Effects of varying detrital nutrient concentrations on macroinvertebrate abundance and biomass. M.S. thesis, Utah State University, Logan, Utah.</para>
 <para>Pederson, R.L. 1981. Abundance, distribution, and diversity of buried seed populations in the Delta Marsh, Manitoba, Canada. Ph.D. dissertation, Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa.</para>
 <para>Ross, L.C.M., and H.R. Murkin. 1993. The effect of above-normal flooding of a northern prairie marsh on Agraylea multipunctata Curtis (Trichoptera, Hydroptilidae). Journal of Freshwater Ecology 8:27-35.</para>
 <para>Squires, L. 1991. Water depth tolerances of emergent species in the Delta Marsh, Manitoba. M.S. thesis, Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa.</para>
 <para>van der Valk, A.G. (Ed.). 1989. Northern Prairie Wetlands. Ames: Iowa State University Press.</para>
 <para>van der Valk, A.G., and CB. Davis. 1978. The role of seed banks in the vegetation dynamics of prairie glacial marshes. Ecology 59: 322-335.</para>
 <para>van der Valk, A.G., C.H. Welling. and RL. Pederson. 1989. Vegetation change in a freshwater wetland: a test of a priori predictions. In Freshwater Wetlands and Wildlife. (Eds.) R.R. Sharitz and J.W. Gibbons, pp.207-217. USDOE Symposium Series No. 61 , Oak Ridge: USDOE Office of Scientific and Technical Information.</para>
 <para>Weller, M.W. 1978. Management of freshwater marshes for wildlife. In Freshwater Wetlands: Ecological Processes and Management Potential. (Eds.) R.E. Good, D.E Whigham, and R.L. Simpson, pp.267-284. New York: Academic Press.</para>
 <para>Weller, M.W. 1981. Freshwater Marshes: Ecology and Wildlife Management. University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis, Minnesota.</para>
 <para>Welling, C.H. 1987. Reestablishment of perennial emergent macrophytes during a drawdown in a lacustrine marsh. M.S. thesis, Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa.</para>
 <para>Welling, C.H., R.L Pederson, and A.G. van der Valk. 1988a. Recruitment from the seed bank and the development of zonation of emergent vegetation during a drawdown in a prairie wetland. Journal of Ecology 76: 483-496.</para>
 <para>Welling. C.H., R.L Pederson, and A.G. van der Valk. 1988b. Temporal patterns in recruitment from the seed bank during drawdowns in a prairie wetland. Journal of Applied Ecology 25: 999-1007.</para>
 <para>Wrubleski, D.A. 1984. Chironomid (Diptera: Chironomidae) species composition, emergence phenologies, and relative abundances in the Delta Marsh, Manitoba. M.S. thesis, University of Manitoba, Winnipeg, Manitoba.</para>
 <para>Wrubleski, D.A. 1991. Chironomid recolonization of marsh drawdown surfaces following reflooding. Ph.D. dissertation, University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 <project><title>Marsh Ecology Research Program</title>
 <personnel><references>1321551258453</references>
 <role>Custodian/Steward</role>
 </personnel>
 <funding><para>Amoco Canada Petroleum, James F. Bell Foundation, Richard A.N. Bonnycastle, Peter D. Curry, Devonian Group of Charitable Foundations, Delta Waterfowl Foundation (formerly the North American Wildlife Foundation), Donner Foundation, Ducks Unlimited Canada, Ducks Unlimited Foundation, Ducks Unlimited Incorporated, William P. Elliott, Edson I. Gaylord, Richard Ivey Foundation, Laidlaw Foundation, John M.S. Lecky, Molson Foundation, Murphy Foundation, McLean Foundation, Senator Norman Patterson Foundation, Richardson Century Fund, and R. Howard Webster</para>
 </funding>
 </project>
 <dataTable id="1321308326218"><entityName>MERP Macrophyte aboveground production data (MAG; 1980-1989) species list</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Species list of macrophyte species sampled at MAG sites.</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1321308165937"><objectName>merp_veg_magspplist.txt</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">970</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/duc_merp.46.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1321308326234"><attributeName>Species name</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Species name</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Species list of emergent macrophyte species names from Macrophyte aboveground production (1980-1989) data</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Species name</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>48</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 <dataTable id="1321310307171"><entityName>MERP Aboveground macrophyte production data (MAG; 1980)</entityName>
 <entityDescription>MERP Aboveground macrophyte production (MAG) data for 1980. Although MAG data was collected from 1980-1989, this dataset contains only data from 1980 and has been kept separate from other years as it does not contain water depth data as found in the other data sets (1981, 1982, 1983-1989)</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1321309001093"><objectName>merp_veg_mag1980_data.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">88183</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/duc_merp.47.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1321310307187"><attributeName>day</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling day</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sampling for aboveground macrophyte production occurred once in late July or early August during the sampling season, as this is the period where standing emergents reach their maximum standing crop. The appearance of fully-grown Typha sp. was generally used to gauge if macrophytes had reached their maximum standing crop.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>dd</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321310307203"><attributeName>month</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling month</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sampling for aboveground macrophyte production occurred once in late July or early August during the sampling season, as this is the period where standing emergents reach their maximum standing crop. The appearance of fully-grown Typha sp. was generally used to gauge if macrophytes had reached their maximum standing crop.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>mm</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321310307218"><attributeName>year</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling year</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sampling for aboveground macrophyte production occurred once in late July or early August during the sampling season, as this is the period where standing emergents reach their maximum standing crop. The appearance of fully-grown Typha sp. was generally used to gauge if macrophytes had reached their maximum standing crop.  Although aboveground macrophyte production data was collected from 1980-1989, this dataset only contains the data for 1980.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>yyyy</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321310307234"><attributeName>cell_num</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>cell number</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>cells were numbered 1 to 10 from west to east in the diked study area.
cell 11 was outside the diked boundary to the west and cell 12 is outside to the east as controls.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>cell number (1-12)</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321310307250"><attributeName>zone</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling zone</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>each cell was divided into 10 equal zones.These zones were marked permanently with transects and used each year.
transects at each cell were grouped into 5 pairs (1 and 2, 3 and 4, 5 and 6, 7 and 8, and 9 and 10) for a total of 60 transect groups.
each transect group was assigned a random number between 1 and 60 and then sampled in the resulting order</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>sampling zone (1-10)</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321310307265"><attributeName>samp_site</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling site</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>four sample sites were randomly selected along with each transect in each cell before the beginning of the spring sampling. 
sites were numbered starting at the northeast corner of the marsh with sites 1, 2, 3, and 4 along transect 1, sites 5, 6, 7, and 8 along transect 2, etc.
if a mag sample fell on the site of another sampling plot from the MERP project sampling (e.g. belowground macrophyte production, turnover plot), a fifth random sample site was used.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>sampling site (1-40)</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321310307281"><attributeName>water_level_amsl</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Staff gauge reading (metres Above Mean Sea Level; m AMSL)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>staff gauges were located in each cell near the control structures and in the south perimeter ditch near the transformer on cell 6.
water levels were recorded each day and included with the mag data.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321310307296"><attributeName>spec_code</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>macrophyte species code</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>macrophytes were identified by a six-digit species code, which can be further divided into taxons of specific levels;

digits 1-2 = family
digits 3-4 = genus
digits 5-6 = species

summation Lines:
vegetation with a species code 000001 and 01 for live is the vegetation of "live other" species that could not be identified.
vegetation with a species code 000001 and 02 for dead is the vegetation of "dead other" species that could not be identified .                
vegetation with a species code 000001 and 00 for live and dead col. is the total no. of vegetation of "dead other" or "live other" species that could not be identified.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><entityCodeList><entityReference>1321310424921</entityReference>
 <valueAttributeReference>1321310424937</valueAttributeReference>
 <definitionAttributeReference>1321310424953</definitionAttributeReference>
 </entityCodeList>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321310307312"><attributeName>per_cover</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>site vegetation percent cover value</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>the percent cover of each macrophyte species was visually estimated at each sample site</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>Percent</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321310307328"><attributeName>live_dead</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>living or dead (condition of sample)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>All five major species, any other dominant species (i.e. greater than 25% cover) and the &#8216;minor species&#8217; group were  separated into live and dead fractions.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>1</code>
 <definition>live</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>2</code>
 <definition>dead</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321310307343"><attributeName>quad_size</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>quadrat size</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>At each site, depending on species present, a 1 x 1 m (Typha glauca syn. Typha &#215; glauca, Phragmites australis, or Scirpus spp.) or a &#188; x &#188; m (all other, smaller species) quadrat was used to clip the plots.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>1</code>
 <definition>1m x 1m quadrat</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>2</code>
 <definition>.25m x .25 m quadrat</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321310307359"><attributeName>biomass_g</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sample dry weight</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>In order to determine biomass, samples were dried to constant weight at 80 &#186;C and weighed.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321310307375"><attributeName>grd_num</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>ground number</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>after being dried, macrophyte samples were ground in a Wiley mill and then placed in a Whirlpak bag.
each sample was assigned a consecutive ground number.
these samples were then sent to Iowa State University for nitrogen, carbon, and phosphorus concentration analysis of the ground macrophyte samples.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>ground number</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321310307390"><attributeName>n_mg_g</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>nitrogen concentration (mg/g)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Samples weresent to the Freshwater Institute (1980-1984) or Iowa State University (1985-1989) for nutrient analysis of nitrogen, carbon and phosphorus.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>MilligramsPerGram</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321310307406"><attributeName>c_mg_g</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>carbon concentration (mg/g)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Samples weresent to the Freshwater Institute (1980-1984) or Iowa State University (1985-1989) for nutrient analysis of nitrogen, carbon and phosphorus.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>MilligramsPerGram</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321310307421"><attributeName>p_mg_g</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>phosphorus concentration (mg/g)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Samples weresent to the Freshwater Institute (1980-1984) or Iowa State University (1985-1989) for nutrient analysis of nitrogen, carbon and phosphorus.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>MilligramsPerGram</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>1763</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 <dataTable id="1321310424921"><entityName>MERP Aboveground macrophyte production (MAG; 1980-1989) species coding</entityName>
 <physical id="1321310353578"><objectName>merp_veg_magsppcodes.txt</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">1750</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/duc_merp.48.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1321310424937"><attributeName>species code</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>species code</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>six-digit species code can be further divided into taxons of specific levels;

digits 1-2 = family
digits 3-4 = genus
digits 5-6 = species</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>species code</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321310424953"><attributeName>species name</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>species names for aboveground macrophyte production study (1980-1989)</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>species name</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>48</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 <dataTable id="1321371108937"><entityName>MERP Aboveground macrophyte production data (MAG; 1981)</entityName>
 <entityDescription>MERP Aboveground macrophyte production (MAG) data for 1981. Although MAG data was collected from 1980-1989, this dataset contains only data from 1981 and has been kept separate from other years as it does not contain staff gauge readings as found in the other data sets (1980, 1982, 1983-1989)</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1321370039765"><objectName>merp_veg_mag1981_data.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">55930</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/duc_merp.50.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1321371108953"><attributeName>day</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling day</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sampling for aboveground macrophyte production occurred once in late July or early August during the sampling season, as this is the period where standing emergents reach their maximum standing crop. The appearance of fully-grown Typha sp. was generally used to gauge if macrophytes had reached their maximum standing crop.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>dd</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321371108968"><attributeName>month</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling month</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sampling for aboveground macrophyte production occurred once in late July or early August during the sampling season, as this is the period where standing emergents reach their maximum standing crop. The appearance of fully-grown Typha sp. was generally used to gauge if macrophytes had reached their maximum standing crop.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>mm</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321371108984"><attributeName>year</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling year</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sampling for aboveground macrophyte production occurred once in late July or early August during the sampling season, as this is the period where standing emergents reach their maximum standing crop. The appearance of fully-grown Typha sp. was generally used to gauge if macrophytes had reached their maximum standing crop. Although aboveground macrophyte production data was collected from 1980-1989, this dataset only contains the data for 1981.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>yyyy</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321371109000"><attributeName>cell_num</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>cell number</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>cells were numbered 1 to 10 from west to east in the diked study area. cell 11 was outside the diked boundary to the west and cell 12 is outside to the east as controls.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>cell number (1-12)</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321371109015"><attributeName>zone</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling zone</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>each cell was divided into 10 equal zones.These zones were marked permanently with transects and used each year. transects at each cell were grouped into 5 pairs (1 and 2, 3 and 4, 5 and 6, 7 and 8, and 9 and 10) for a total of 60 transect groups. each transect group was assigned a random number between 1 and 60 and then sampled in the resulting order</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>sampling zone (1-10)</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321371109031"><attributeName>samp_site</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling site</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>four sample sites were randomly selected along with each transect in each cell before the beginning of the spring sampling. sites were numbered starting at the northeast corner of the marsh with sites 1, 2, 3, and 4 along transect 1, sites 5, 6, 7, and 8 along transect 2, etc. if a mag sample fell on the site of another sampling plot from the MERP project sampling (e.g. belowground macrophyte production, turnover plot), a fifth random sample site was used.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>sampling site (1-40)</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321371109046"><attributeName>water_depth_cm</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>water depth at sample site (cm)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>water depth measurements were taken in the center of the quadrat</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321371109062"><attributeName>spec_code</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>macrophyte species code</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>macrophytes were identified by a six-digit species code, which can be further divided into taxons of specific levels; digits 1-2 = family digits 3-4 = genus digits 5-6 = species summation Lines: vegetation with a species code 000001 and 01 for live is the vegetation of "live other" species that could not be identified. vegetation with a species code 000001 and 02 for dead is the vegetation of "dead other" species that could not be identified . vegetation with a species code 000001 and 00 for live and dead col. is the total no. of vegetation of "dead other" or "live other" species that could not be identified.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><entityCodeList><entityReference>1321310424921</entityReference>
 <valueAttributeReference>1321310424937</valueAttributeReference>
 <definitionAttributeReference>1321310424953</definitionAttributeReference>
 </entityCodeList>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321371109078"><attributeName>per_cover</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>site vegetation percent cover value</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>the percent cover of each macrophyte species was visually estimated at each sample site</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>Percent</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321371109093"><attributeName>live_dead</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>living or dead (condition of sample)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>All five major species, any other dominant species (i.e. greater than 25% cover) and the &#8216;minor species&#8217; group were separated into live and dead fractions.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>0</code>
 <definition>combined</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>1</code>
 <definition>living</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>2</code>
 <definition>dead</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321371109109"><attributeName>quad_size</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Quadrat size</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>At each site, depending on species present, a 1 x 1 m (Typha glauca syn. Typha &#215; glauca, Phragmites australis, or Scirpus spp.) or a &#188; x &#188; m (all other, smaller species) quadrat was used to clip the plots.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>1</code>
 <definition>1m x 1m</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>2</code>
 <definition>0.25m x 0.25m</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321371109125"><attributeName>biomass_g</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Sample dry weight (g)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>In order to determine biomass, samples were dried to constant weight at 80 &#186;C and weighed.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321371109140"><attributeName>grd_num</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>ground number</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>after being dried, macrophyte samples were ground in a Wiley mill and then placed in a Whirlpak bag. each sample was assigned a consecutive ground number. these samples were then sent to Iowa State University for nitrogen, carbon, and phosphorus concentration analysis of the ground macrophyte samples.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Ground number</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321371109156"><attributeName>n_mg_g</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>nitrogen concentration (mg/g)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Samples weresent to the Freshwater Institute (1980-1984) or Iowa State University (1985-1989) for nutrient analysis of nitrogen, carbon and phosphorus.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>MilligramsPerGram</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321371109171"><attributeName>c_mg_g</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>carbon concentration (mg/g)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Samples weresent to the Freshwater Institute (1980-1984) or Iowa State University (1985-1989) for nutrient analysis of nitrogen, carbon and phosphorus.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>MilligramsPerGram</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321371109187"><attributeName>p_mg_g</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>phosphorus concentration (mg/g)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Samples weresent to the Freshwater Institute (1980-1984) or Iowa State University (1985-1989) for nutrient analysis of nitrogen, carbon and phosphorus.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>MilligramsPerGram</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>1159</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 <dataTable id="1321372590125"><entityName>MERP Aboveground macrophyte production data (MAG; 1982)</entityName>
 <entityDescription>MERP Aboveground macrophyte production (MAG) data for 1982. Although MAG data was collected from 1980-1989, this dataset contains only data from 1982 and has been kept separate from other years (1980, 1982, 1983-1989)</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1321371328593"><objectName>merp_veg_mag1982_data.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">49630</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/duc_merp.51.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1321372590140"><attributeName>day</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling day</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sampling for aboveground macrophyte production occurred once in late July or early August during the sampling season, as this is the period where standing emergents reach their maximum standing crop. The appearance of fully-grown Typha sp. was generally used to gauge if macrophytes had reached their maximum standing crop.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>dd</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321372590156"><attributeName>month</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling month</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sampling for aboveground macrophyte production occurred once in late July or early August during the sampling season, as this is the period where standing emergents reach their maximum standing crop. The appearance of fully-grown Typha sp. was generally used to gauge if macrophytes had reached their maximum standing crop.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>mm</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321372590171"><attributeName>year</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling year</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sampling for aboveground macrophyte production occurred once in late July or early August during the sampling season, as this is the period where standing emergents reach their maximum standing crop. The appearance of fully-grown Typha sp. was generally used to gauge if macrophytes had reached their maximum standing crop. Although aboveground macrophyte production data was collected from 1980-1989, this dataset only contains the data for 1982.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>yyyy</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321372590187"><attributeName>cell_num</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>cell number</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>cells were numbered 1 to 10 from west to east in the diked study area. cell 11 was outside the diked boundary to the west and cell 12 is outside to the east as controls.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>cell number (1-12)</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321372590203"><attributeName>zone</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling zone</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>each cell was divided into 10 equal zones.These zones were marked permanently with transects and used each year. transects at each cell were grouped into 5 pairs (1 and 2, 3 and 4, 5 and 6, 7 and 8, and 9 and 10) for a total of 60 transect groups. each transect group was assigned a random number between 1 and 60 and then sampled in the resulting order</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>sampling zone (1-10)</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321372590218"><attributeName>samp_site</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling site</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>four sample sites were randomly selected along with each transect in each cell before the beginning of the spring sampling. sites were numbered starting at the northeast corner of the marsh with sites 1, 2, 3, and 4 along transect 1, sites 5, 6, 7, and 8 along transect 2, etc. if a mag sample fell on the site of another sampling plot from the MERP project sampling (e.g. belowground macrophyte production, turnover plot), a fifth random sample site was used.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>sampling site (1-40)</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321372590234"><attributeName>water_level_amsl</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>staff gauge readings (amsl)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>staff gauges were located in each cell near the control structures and in the south perimeter ditch near the transformer on cell 6.
water levels were recorded each day and included with the mag data.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>AboveMeanSeaLevel</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321372590250"><attributeName>water_depth_cm</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>water depth at sample site (cm)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>water depth measurements were taken in the center of the quadrat</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321372590265"><attributeName>spec_code</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>macrophyte species code</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>macrophytes were identified by a six-digit species code, which can be further divided into taxons of specific levels; digits 1-2 = family digits 3-4 = genus digits 5-6 = species summation Lines: vegetation with a species code 000001 and 01 for live is the vegetation of "live other" species that could not be identified. vegetation with a species code 000001 and 02 for dead is the vegetation of "dead other" species that could not be identified . vegetation with a species code 000001 and 00 for live and dead col. is the total no. of vegetation of "dead other" or "live other" species that could not be identified.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><entityCodeList><entityReference>1321310424921</entityReference>
 <valueAttributeReference>1321310424937</valueAttributeReference>
 <definitionAttributeReference>1321310424953</definitionAttributeReference>
 </entityCodeList>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321372590281"><attributeName>per_cover</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>site vegetation percent cover value</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>the percent cover of each macrophyte species was visually estimated at each sample site</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321372590296"><attributeName>live_dead</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>living or dead (condition of sample)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>All five major species, any other dominant species (i.e. greater than 25% cover) and the &#8216;minor species&#8217; group were separated into live and dead fractions.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>0</code>
 <definition>combined</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>1</code>
 <definition>living</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>2</code>
 <definition>dead</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321372590312"><attributeName>quad_size</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>quadrat size</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>At each site, depending on species present, a 1 x 1 m (Typha glauca syn. Typha &#215; glauca, Phragmites australis, or Scirpus spp.) or a &#188; x &#188; m (all other, smaller species) quadrat was used to clip the plots.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>1</code>
 <definition>1m x 1m quadrat</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>2</code>
 <definition>0.25m x 0.25m quadrat</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321372590328"><attributeName>biomass_g</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Sample dry weight (g)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>In order to determine biomass, samples were dried to constant weight at 80 &#186;C and weighed.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321372590343"><attributeName>grd_num</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>ground number</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>after being dried, macrophyte samples were ground in a Wiley mill and then placed in a Whirlpak bag. each sample was assigned a consecutive ground number. these samples were then sent to Iowa State University for nitrogen, carbon, and phosphorus concentration analysis of the ground macrophyte samples.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>ground number</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321372590359"><attributeName>n_mg_g</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>nitrogen concentration (mg/g)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Samples weresent to the Freshwater Institute (1980-1984) or Iowa State University (1985-1989) for nutrient analysis of nitrogen, carbon and phosphorus.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>MilligramsPerGram</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321372590375"><attributeName>c_mg_g</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>carbon concentration (mg/g)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Samples weresent to the Freshwater Institute (1980-1984) or Iowa State University (1985-1989) for nutrient analysis of nitrogen, carbon and phosphorus.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>MilligramsPerGram</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321372590390"><attributeName>p_mg_g</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>phosphorus concentration (mg/g)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Samples weresent to the Freshwater Institute (1980-1984) or Iowa State University (1985-1989) for nutrient analysis of nitrogen, carbon and phosphorus.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>MilligramsPerGram</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>915</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 <dataTable id="1321374055750"><entityName>MERP Aboveground macrophyte production data (MAG; 1983-1989)</entityName>
 <entityDescription>MERP Aboveground macrophyte production (MAG) data for 1983-1989. Although MAG data was collected from 1980-1989, this dataset contains only data from 1983-1989 and has been kept separate from other years as it does not contain site vegetation percent cover data, as found in the other data sets (1980, 1981, 1982)</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1321372993453"><objectName>merp_veg_mag1983-1989_data.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">720247</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/duc_merp.52.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1321374055765"><attributeName>day</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling day</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sampling for aboveground macrophyte production occurred once in late July or early August during the sampling season, as this is the period where standing emergents reach their maximum standing crop. The appearance of fully-grown Typha sp. was generally used to gauge if macrophytes had reached their maximum standing crop.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>dd</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321374055781"><attributeName>month</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling month</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sampling for aboveground macrophyte production occurred once in late July or early August during the sampling season, as this is the period where standing emergents reach their maximum standing crop. The appearance of fully-grown Typha sp. was generally used to gauge if macrophytes had reached their maximum standing crop.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>mm</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321374055796"><attributeName>year</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling year</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sampling for aboveground macrophyte production occurred once in late July or early August during the sampling season, as this is the period where standing emergents reach their maximum standing crop. The appearance of fully-grown Typha sp. was generally used to gauge if macrophytes had reached their maximum standing crop. Although aboveground macrophyte production data was collected from 1980-1989, this dataset only contains the data for 1983-1989.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>yyyy</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321374055812"><attributeName>cell_num</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>cell number</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>cells were numbered 1 to 10 from west to east in the diked study area. cell 11 was outside the diked boundary to the west and cell 12 is outside to the east as controls.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>cell number (1-12)</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321374055828"><attributeName>zone</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling zone</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>each cell was divided into 10 equal zones.These zones were marked permanently with transects and used each year. transects at each cell were grouped into 5 pairs (1 and 2, 3 and 4, 5 and 6, 7 and 8, and 9 and 10) for a total of 60 transect groups. each transect group was assigned a random number between 1 and 60 and then sampled in the resulting order.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>sampling zone (1-10)</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321374055843"><attributeName>samp_site</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling site</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>four sample sites were randomly selected along with each transect in each cell before the beginning of the spring sampling. sites were numbered starting at the northeast corner of the marsh with sites 1, 2, 3, and 4 along transect 1, sites 5, 6, 7, and 8 along transect 2, etc. if a mag sample fell on the site of another sampling plot from the MERP project sampling (e.g. belowground macrophyte production, turnover plot), a fifth random sample site was used.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>sampling site (1-40)</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321374055859"><attributeName>water_level_amsl</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>staff gauge reading (metres above mean sea level; m AMSL)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>staff gauges were located in each cell near the control structures and in the south perimeter ditch near the transformer on cell 6. water levels were recorded each day and included with the mag data.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321374055875"><attributeName>water_depth_cm</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>water depth at sample site (cm)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>water depth measurements were taken in the center of the quadrat</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321374055890"><attributeName>spec_code</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>macrophyte species code</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>macrophytes were identified by a six-digit species code, which can be further divided into taxons of specific levels; digits 1-2 = family digits 3-4 = genus digits 5-6 = species summation Lines: vegetation with a species code 000001 and 01 for live is the vegetation of "live other" species that could not be identified. vegetation with a species code 000001 and 02 for dead is the vegetation of "dead other" species that could not be identified . vegetation with a species code 000001 and 00 for live and dead col. is the total no. of vegetation of "dead other" or "live other" species that could not be identified.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><entityCodeList><entityReference>1321310424921</entityReference>
 <valueAttributeReference>1321310424937</valueAttributeReference>
 <definitionAttributeReference>1321310424953</definitionAttributeReference>
 </entityCodeList>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321374055906"><attributeName>live_dead</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>living or dead (condition of sample)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>All five major species, any other dominant species (i.e. greater than 25% cover) and the &#8216;minor species&#8217; group were separated into live and dead fractions.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>0</code>
 <definition>combined</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>1</code>
 <definition>living</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>2</code>
 <definition>dead</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321374055921"><attributeName>quad_size</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>quadrat size</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>At each site, depending on species present, a 1 x 1 m (Typha glauca syn. Typha &#215; glauca, Phragmites australis, or Scirpus spp.) or a &#188; x &#188; m (all other, smaller species) quadrat was used to clip the plots.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>1</code>
 <definition>1m x 1m quadrat</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>2</code>
 <definition>0.25m x 0,25m quadrat</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321374055937"><attributeName>biomass_g</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sample dry weight (g)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>In order to determine biomass, samples were dried to constant weight at 80 &#186;C and weighed.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321374055953"><attributeName>grd_num</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>ground number</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>after being dried, macrophyte samples were ground in a Wiley mill and then placed in a Whirlpak bag. each sample was assigned a consecutive ground number. these samples were then sent to Iowa State University for nitrogen, carbon, and phosphorus concentration analysis of the ground macrophyte samples.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>ground number</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321374055968"><attributeName>n_mg_g</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>nitrogen concentration (mg/g)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Samples weresent to the Freshwater Institute (1980-1984) or Iowa State University (1985-1989) for nutrient analysis of nitrogen, carbon and phosphorus.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>MilligramsPerGram</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321374055984"><attributeName>c_mg_g</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>carbon concentration (mg/g)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Samples weresent to the Freshwater Institute (1980-1984) or Iowa State University (1985-1989) for nutrient analysis of nitrogen, carbon and phosphorus.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>MilligramsPerGram</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321374056000"><attributeName>p_mg_g</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>phosphorus concentration</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Samples weresent to the Freshwater Institute (1980-1984) or Iowa State University (1985-1989) for nutrient analysis of nitrogen, carbon and phosphorus.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>MilligramsPerGram</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>14081</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 </dataset>
 <additionalMetadata><metadata><unitList><unit id="AboveMeanSeaLevel" multiplierToSI=" " name="AboveMeanSeaLevel" parentSI="meter" unitType="length"><description>AboveMeanSeaLevel</description>
 </unit>
 </unitList>
 </metadata>
 </additionalMetadata>
 <additionalMetadata><metadata><unitList><unit id="Percent" multiplierToSI=" " name="Percent" parentSI="mole" unitType="amount"><description>Dimensionless quantity</description>
 </unit>
 </unitList>
 </metadata>
 </additionalMetadata>
 <additionalMetadata><metadata><unitList><unit id="MilligramsPerGram" multiplierToSI=" " name="MilligramsPerGram" parentSI="gramsPerGram" unitType="massPerMass"><description>MilligramsPerGram</description>
 </unit>
 </unitList>
 </metadata>
 </additionalMetadata>
 </ns0:eml>