<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="duc_merp.44.13" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 eml.xsd">  <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"><allow><principal>public</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
</allow>
<allow><principal>uid=duc_iwwr,o=unaffiliated,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
<permission>all</permission>
</allow>
</access>
<dataset> <title>Marsh Ecology Research Program (MERP): Soil nutrients and groundwater well site characterization data (1980-1985)</title>
 <creator id="1320866853500"><individualName><salutation>Mr.</salutation>
 <givenName>John</givenName>
 <surName>Kadlec</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>College of Natural Resources, Utah State University</organizationName>
 <address><city>Logan</city>
 <administrativeArea>Utah</administrativeArea>
 </address>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1320866862578"><individualName><salutation>Mr.</salutation>
 <givenName>Henry</givenName>
 <surName>Murkin</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Ducks Unlimited Canada</organizationName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 1160</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Stonewall</city>
 <administrativeArea>Manitoba</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>R0C 2Z0</postalCode>
 <country>Canada</country>
 </address>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1320866874000"><organizationName>Ducks Unlimited Canada</organizationName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 1160</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Stonewall</city>
 <administrativeArea>Manitoba</administrativeArea>
 <country>Canada</country>
 </address>
 </creator>
 <abstract><para>The Marsh Ecology Research Program (MERP) was a long-term interdisciplinary study on the ecology of prairie wetlands. A scientific team from a variety of disciplines (hydrology, plant ecology, invertebrate ecology, vertebrate ecology, nutrient dynamics, marsh management) was assembled to design and oversee a long-term experiment on the effects of water-level manipulation on northern prairie wetlands. Ten years of fieldwork (1980 -1989), combining a routine long-term monitoring program and a series of short-term studies, generated a wealth of new and diverse information on the ecology and function of prairie wetlands (Murkin, Batt, Caldwell, Kadlec and van der Valk, 2000). This data set includes soil nutrient and site vegetation characetization data for all groundwater well sites.
	The main objective for monitoring soil nutrients in the MERP was to quantify sediments as a nutrient pool in wetlands and to characterize the sediments of the MERP cells over time. Along with monitoring the other major nutrient pools (surface water, plants and plant litter, animals and interstitial waters), yearly changes in the sediment nutrient pool can provide important information on the nutrient cycling within wetlands. In addition, the effects of deep flooding and drawdown on nutrients in marsh sediments was also evaluated (Kadlec, 1985a; Kadlec, 1985b; Kaldec, 1989).

For further information on the Marsh Ecology Research Program (MERP), please visit: http://www.ducks.ca/conserve/research/projects/merp/index.html

References:
Kadlec, J.A. 1985a. Nutrient dynamics. In: Marsh Ecology Research Program: Long-term Monitoring Procedures Manual. (Ed.) H.R. Murkin, pp. 27-40. Manitoba , Canada: Delta Waterfowl and Wetlands Research Station.
Kadlec, J.A. 1985b. Physical environment In: Marsh Ecology Research Program: Long-term Monitoring Procedures Manual. (Ed.) H.R. Murkin, pp. 15-17. Manitoba , Canada: Delta Waterfowl and Wetlands Research Station.
Kadlec, J.A. 1989. Effects of deep flooding and drawdown on freshwater marsh sediments. In: Freshwater Wetlands and Wildlife. (Eds.) R.R. Sharitz and J.W. Gibbons, pp. 127-143. USDOE Symposium Series 61, USDOE Office of Scientific and Technical Information, Oak Ridge.
Murkin, H.R., B.D.J. Batt, P.J. Caldwell, J.A. Kadlec and A.G. van der Valk. 2000a. Introduction to the Marsh Ecology Research Program. In Prairie Wetland Ecology: The Contribution of the Marsh Ecology Research Program. (Eds) H.R. Murkin, A.G. van der Valk and W.R. Clark. pp. 3-15. Ames: Iowa State University Press.

Resulting Publications on MERP soil nutrients data:
Kadlec, J.A. 1989. Effects of deep flooding and drawdown on freshwater marsh sediments. In: Freshwater Wetlands and Wildlife. (Eds.) R.R. Sharitz and J.W. Gibbons, pp. 127-143. USDOE Symposium Series 61, USDOE Office of Scientific and Technical Information, Oak Ridge.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>prairie wetland ecology</keyword>
 <keyword>wetlands</keyword>
 <keyword>marshes</keyword>
 <keyword>MERP</keyword>
 <keyword>marsh ecology research program</keyword>
 <keyword>wet-dry cycle</keyword>
 <keyword>Delta Marsh</keyword>
 <keyword>hydrology</keyword>
 <keyword>marsh management</keyword>
 <keyword>flooding</keyword>
 <keyword>drawdown</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet><keyword>soil</keyword>
 <keyword>marsh sediments</keyword>
 <keyword>nurtrient analysis</keyword>
 <keyword>groundwater well site</keyword>
 <keyword>macrophyte site characterization</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <intellectualRights><para>Please obtain written permission from the owners prior to using this data package. Please cite the owners of the data, including the principal investigator(s) and Ducks Unlimited Canada, in any publications that use this data. Although substantial efforts have been made to verify the accuracy of data and metadata contained within this data package, complete accuracy cannot be guaranteed.</para>
 </intellectualRights>
 <coverage> <temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1980-06-24</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate><calendarDate>1985-07-08</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 <taxonomicCoverage><taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Acer negundo</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Aster brachyactis</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Aster hesperius</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Atriplex argentea</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Atriplex patula</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Carex atherodes</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Cerastium arvense</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Ceratophyllum demersum</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Chenopodium rubrum</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Cicuta maculata</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Cirsium arvense</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Convolvulus sepium</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Distichlis stricta</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Epilobium angustifolium</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Galium trifidum</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Hordeum jubatum</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Impatiens biflora</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Lactuca pulchella</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Lemna minor</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Lemna trisulca</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Lycopus asper</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Mentha arvensis</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Myriophyllum exalbescens</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Phragmites australis</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Poa pratensis</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Potamogeton pectinatus</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Potamogeton richardsonii</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Potamogeton vaginatus</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Puccinellia nuttalliana</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Ranunculus sceleratus</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Salicornia rubra</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Scirpus acutus</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Scirpus maritimus</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Scirpus validus</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Scolochloa festucacea</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Scutellaria galericulata</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Solidago canadensis</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Sonchus arvensis</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Species name</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Stachys palustris</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Suaeda depressa</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Symphoricarpos occidentalis</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Teucrium occidentale</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Typha angustifolia</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Typha glauca</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Typha latifolia</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Urtica dioica</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Utricularia vulgaris</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicCoverage>
 <geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Marsh Ecology Research Complex: The MERP study area was located on the Delta Marsh in south central Manitoba, Canada. The Delta Marsh is a large lacustrine marsh (approximately 50,000 ha) along the southern shore of Lake Manitoba. The experimental complex consisted of 10 contiguous wetland cells (approximately 5 ha each).</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-98.22</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>-98.12178</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>50.21</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>50.21</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact id="1321551771031"><organizationName>Institute for Wetland and Waterfowl Research (IWWR), Ducks Unlimited Canada</organizationName>
 <positionName>IWWR Librarian</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 1160</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Stonewall</city>
 <administrativeArea>Manitoba</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>R0C 2Z0</postalCode>
 <country>Canada</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">1-800-665-DUCK</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>library@ducks.ca</electronicMailAddress>
 </contact>
 <contact id="1321551782734"><individualName><givenName>Lisette</givenName>
 <surName>Ross</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Institute for Wetland and Waterfowl Research, Ducks Unlimited Canada</organizationName>
 <positionName>Wetland Biologist</positionName>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><title>MERP Soil nutrients and groundwater well site characterization data (1980-1985) methods</title>
 <para>Soil samples were collected on an annual basis for nutrient analysis, during the last week of June or early July (with the exception of 1984, when samples were collected in August and October). Soil samples were collected at five groundwater well sites per cell (in all cells except 9, where samples were collected from the 10 groundwater (GW) well sites), using the invertebrate core sampler (5 cm inner diameter, 20 cm length; Kadlec, 1985a).</para>
 <para>Enough cores were taken to completely fill a wide-mouth Mason jar, which was labeled with the date, and groundwater well number. All soil nutrient samples were sent to the Provincial Soil Testing Lab at the University of Manitoba in Winnipeg (Manitoba, Canada), to determine total nitrogen, available nitrogen, total phosphorous, available phosphorous, total sulpher, available potassium, sediment water content (as a percent of the soil dry weight) and percent organic matter (added in 1983). A master sheet with sample numbers 1-65 was used to keep track of each sample. As per requirements of the Soil Testing Lab, each wet sediment sample was homogenized in a blender before being transferred the sample boxes provided by the Soil Testing Lab, and stored in a freezer (Kadlec, 1985a). All anaylses were performed on wet samples. The analytic procedure was modified so that subsamples for analyses of available N (NO3--N + NO2-N), available P (dissolved and some adsorbed P), and available K were not dried prior to extraction, as drying affects extractable quantities of most ions in organic soils (Kadlec, 1989; Anderson and Beverly, 1985; Gilliam and Richter, 1985). N and P subsamples were extracted with 0.5M NaHCO3 at pH 8.5 and K subsamples with 1N NH4OAc at pH 7. The N and P extracts were analyzed on a Technicon Auto Analyzer, N by a modification of the procedure of Kampshake et al. (1967) and P by the ascorbic acid-ammonium molybdate method (Page et al., 1982). K was analyzed by flame photometry. Analyses for total P and total S were performed on dried sediment samples which were digested with HNO3 and HClO4. Total N was determined by the Kjeldahl method. Organic matter was determined by the potassium dichromate reduction procedure (Page et al., 1982).</para>
 <para>In addition to the Manitoba Provincial Soil Testing Laboratory measured sediment water content, at the field laboratory, separate known volume cores, taken at the same time as the cores for nutrient analysis, were analyzed for dry weight and water per unit volume. However, this data was not able to be archived. Because of the range in sediment consistency in the marshes, Kaldec (1989) was also not confident that the coring technique provided accurate data for bulk density calculations. Nevertheless, it was the best available procedure for largescale routine use at the time.</para>
 <para>Sampling for the characterization of macrophytes at groundwater well sites occurred once in late July or early August during the sampling season, as this is the period where standing emergents reach their maximum standing crop. The groundwater well sites were examined for plant species present, density or percent cover, and live or dead plants. To characterize the sites, a square meter quadrat was randomly placed within a 2 metre radius of the well site. Within the quadrat, the number of stems of emergent or upland species were counted. For submergent species, a percent cover value in the total quadrat area was estimated. Macrophytes were coded to species when possible. For the 1982 sampling year only, surveys also recorded if the species was live or dead.</para>
 <para>Notes on reading the data:</para>
 <para>-Note that, for 1982 soil nutrient analyses, TN, TP and TS at all marsh sites (including the control cells 11 &amp;12) decreased significantly, as compared to soil nutrient values for all other years. No explanation related to the experiment could be provided from the Kadlec (1989) publication, as well as from consultation with soil nutrient experts, for this anomalous data. As QA/QC data were not available for the Manitoba Provincial Soil Testing Laboratory reports for 1982, the possibility of an error related to laboratory analyses should not be overlooked. Therefore, the 1982 soil nutrient data should be treated with caution.</para>
 <para>-For nutrient analyses on soil samples, zero values indicate that a particular parameter was measured and its&#8217; value was zero.</para>
 <para>-For nutrient analyses on soil samples, blanks for a particular parameter indicate that an insufficient amount of sample was available to run a particular analysis, that a sample was not able to be taken/recorded properly and that information is considered to be lost, or that a particular parameter was not recorded in that sampling year (i.e. percent organic matter for 1980-1982).</para>
 <para>-For 1982 soil nutrient analyses, TN, TP and TS at all marsh sites (including the control cells 11 &amp;12) decreased significantly, as compared to soil nutrient values for all other years. No explanation could be provided in the Kadlec (1989) publication, as well as from consultation with soil nutrient experts, for this anomalous data. As QA/QC data were not available for the Manitoba Provincial Soil Testing Laboratory reports for 1982, the possibility of an error related to laboratory analyses should not be overlooked. Therefore, the 1982 soil nutrient data should be treated with caution.</para>
 <para>-For vegetation data on groundwater well site characterizations, zero values for both quadrat density/percent cover value and species indicates that there was no vegetation at that particular groundwater well site.</para>
 <para>-For vegetation data on groundwater well site characterizations, a blank entry indicates:</para>
 <para>-where a particular parameter was not recorded for that sampling year (i.e. &#8216;live or dead&#8217; in all sampling years but 1982), or</para>
 <para>-that a sample was not able to be taken/recorded properly at that groundwater well site and that the information is considered to be lost, or</para>
 <para>-a total for all other (unknown or minor) &#8216;live&#8217; or &#8216;dead&#8217; species, where the &#8216;plant species present&#8217; parameter is blank, but a value for &#8216;live or dead&#8217; and &#8216;density or cover value&#8217; is given (1982 only).</para>
 <para>References</para>
 <para>Anderson, D.L. and R.B. Beverly. 1985. The effects of drying upon extractable P, K and bulk density of organic and mineral soils of the Everglades. Soil Science Society of America 49: 362-366.</para>
 <para>Gilliam, F.S. and D.D. Richter. 1985. Increases in extractable ions in infertile aquults caused by sample preparation. Soil Society of America Journal 49: 1576-1578.</para>
 <para>Kadlec, J.A. 1985a. Nutrient dynamics. In: Marsh Ecology Research Program: Long-term Monitoring Procedures Manual. (Ed.) H.R. Murkin, pp. 27-40. Manitoba , Canada: Delta Waterfowl and Wetlands Research Station.</para>
 <para>Kadlec, J.A. 1985b. Physical environment In: Marsh Ecology Research Program: Long-term Monitoring Procedures Manual. (Ed.) H.R. Murkin, pp. 15-17. Manitoba , Canada: Delta Waterfowl and Wetlands Research Station.</para>
 <para>Kadlec, J.A. 1989. Effects of deep flooding and drawdown on freshwater marsh sediments. In: Freshwater Wetlands and Wildlife. (Eds.) R.R. Sharitz and J.W. Gibbons, pp. 127-143. USDOE Symposium Series 61, USDOE Office of Scientific and Technical Information, Oak Ridge.</para>
 <para>Kampshake, L.J., S.A. Hannah and J.M. Cohen. 1967. Automated analysis for nitrate by hydrazine reduction. Water Resources Research 1: 205-216.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Marsh Ecology Research Program: Objectives, study area and experimental design (1980-1989)</title>
 <para>Introduction</para>
 <para>Good et al. (1978) and Greeson et al. (1978) were among the first to summarize the state of our understanding in freshwater wetland ecology. They emphasized the need for expanded interdisciplinary research in freshwater wetlands. Ten years later, van der Valk (1989), in Northern Prairie Wetlands, focused specifically on prairie wetlands and the influence of water-level changes on the dynamics and productivity of these systems.</para>
 <para>Primary production, secondary production, vegetation composition and distribution, animal use, and nutrient budgets are all affected as water levels rise and fall with variation in precipitation. Ranging from tiny potholes to huge lacustrine complexes, prairie wetlands are among the world's most productive ecosystems (Murkin, 1989a). Their importance as wildlife production areas has drawn considerable attention to their conservation and management (Weller, 1978; Weller, 1981). This attention has increased in recent years with the need for information on the overall functions and values of wetlands within the prairie landscape (Murkin, 1998). Understanding wetland values is critical to the development of comprehensive wetland conservation programs. In addition, the ongoing destruction of wetlands through drainage, urban sprawl, and other human-induced changes has added a great deal of urgency to the need for a better understanding of the ecology and management of all remaining wetland areas (Murkin et al., 2000a).</para>
 <para>Objectives</para>
 <para>Recognizing the need for an improved understanding of prairie wetland ecology, the Marsh Ecology Research Program (MERP) was initiated in 1979 as a joint project of</para>
 <para>Ducks Unlimited Canada and the Delta Waterfowl and Wetlands Research Station (Murkin et al., 1984). The MERP was designed as a long-term replicated experiment addressing the impacts of various water levels on the main components of the prairie wetland ecosystem. The overall objective of MERP was to document the changes that occur within a prairie wetland during a simulated wet-dry cycle (van der Valk and Davis, 1978). More specifically, MERP was designed to determine the storage (pools) and movement (fluxes) of nitrogen (N), phosphorus (P), and carbon (C) during the various stages of the cycle (Murkin et al., 2000a). Specific objectives for each of the major ecosystem components were as follows:</para>
 <para>1. Hydrology: to estimate the terms of the water budget during all stages of the wet-dry cycle: surface water in and out, ground water in and out, change in storage, precipitation, and evapotranspiration.</para>
 <para>2. Water chemistry: to estimate the concentrations of N, P, C, and major ions in both surface and substrate pore-water pools and to monitor changes in these pools during the wet-dry cycle.</para>
 <para>3. Macrophytes: to estimate annual above- and below ground macrophyte productivity and standing crops and subsequent changes related to the wet-dry cycle. Storage and movement of N, P, and C in macrophytes during the wet-dry cycle also were determined.</para>
 <para>4. Macrophyte litter: to estimate the annual production of above- and belowground macrophyte litter and the loss and uptake of N, P, and C to and from the litter compartment.</para>
 <para>5. Algae: to estimate algal standing crops and productivity (phytoplankton, epiphyton, epipelon, and metaphyton) during the various stages of the wet-dry cycle.</para>
 <para>6. Invertebrates: to estimate standing crops of invertebrates (nekton, benthos, and emerging insects) during the various phases of the wet-dry cycle.</para>
 <para>7. Vertebrates: to monitor use by waterfowl, coots, blackbirds, and muskrats in response to habitat changes during the wet- dry cycle.</para>
 <para>The MERP experimental design and field-sampling protocols were developed to meet these objectives. Nutrient data were used to construct nutrient budgets for the experimental cells. Several additional objectives beyond those related specifically to nutrient storage and movement also were addressed. Examples are rate of recovery of plant communities following drawdown (Welling et al., 1988a), habitat use by various vertebrate groups during specific stages of the wet-dry cycle (Clark and Kroeker, 1993), and the effect of the wet-dry cycle on individual invertebrate species (Ross and Murkin, 1993; Murkin et al., 2000a).</para>
 <para>Study Area</para>
 <para>The MERP study area was located on the Delta Marsh in south-central Manitoba, Canada (50&#61616;11'N, 98&#176;19'W). The Delta Marsh is a large lacustrine marsh (&#61627;15,000 ha) along the southern shore of Lake Manitoba (see Batt, 2000). The marsh is of Pleistocene origin and is a remnant of glacial Lake Agassiz (L&#246;ve and L&#246;ve, 1954, Ehrlich et al., 1957). An important feature of the marsh is that its water level has been stabilized for many years (due to installation of a water-control structure on Lake Manitoba in 1961), resulting in lake marsh conditions described by van der Valk and Davis (1978) over much of its area (Murkin et al., 2000a). The site for the MERP experimental complex was chosen because of several features. First, the area had representative portions of shallow- and deep-marsh zones characteristic of the Delta Marsh and other northern prairie marshes. Second, the area was remote and completely within the private ownership of the Delta Waterfowl and Wetlands Research Station, thus ensuring access for researchers, while affording effective control of trespass and disturbance. Third, the site was served by an existing road system. This road system was crucial, given the large number of individuals working on the site each day; the large numbers and volumes of water, soil, vegetation, and animal samples to be handled; and the logistics of transporting and maintaining sampling devices. Finally, the existing road provided the northern boundary of the experimental cells, thereby reducing construction costs. The water levels used in the experiments were chosen to reflect conditions that had occurred naturally during the previous 5 decades. Thus, the experimental site and design has provided information that is relevant to any future management efforts on the Delta Marsh, specifically, and wetland management in general.</para>
 <para>The experimental cell complex consisted of 10 contiguous 4-6 ha marsh units (Cells 1-10), created in 1979 by building a series of dikes along the northern edge of the main marsh. The diked experimental cells were numbered 1 to 10 from west to east. The approximate dimension of each diked cell was 150m x 300m (see Table 1 for the specific dimensions of each cell). Disturbance due to dike construction was confined to the dikes and a 10m buffer strip on each side of the dike. Each diked cell was equipped with a water control structure and electric pump with automatic controls to adjust and maintain (&#61617;2cm) water levels according to the schedule (see Table 2). Besides the diked cells, two undiked areas of similar size within the Delta Marsh (Cells 11 &amp; 12) were monitored as reference cells (i.e. reference cells to the unmanipulated Delta Marsh). The vegetation within the diked cells prior to the experimental treatments was comparable to the reference cells and main Delta Marsh (Pederson 1981; Murkin et al., 2000a).</para>
 <para>Experimental Design</para>
 <para>The general MERP objective was to monitor the response of various aspects of the wetland ecosystem to a series of water-level manipulations intended to simulate the wet-dry cycle of prairie wetlands. The schedule for water-level treatments and the number of replicates for each treatment are shown in Tables 2 and 3. The study was basically divided into four phases. The first two phases (baseline and deep flooding) were designed to provide background information on the experimental cells and to bring all cells to a similar condition (lake marsh stage) before the actual wet-dry cycle was applied during the last two phases (drawdown and reflooding; Murkin et al., 2000a). The four phases of the experimental design were as follows:</para>
 <para>a.	Baseline year (1980-1981):</para>
 <para>During the first year of the study (1980), the control structures were left open and water levels within the cells were allowed to track the levels of the Delta Marsh. This method provided a year of baseline data before the actual water-level manipulations began. Two of the cells (3 and 7) were kept at baseline levels for a second year (1981) to allow for comparison of different durations of drawdown later in the study (see Table 3).</para>
 <para>b.	Deep flooding (aka Conditioning Period; 1981-1983):</para>
 <para>Following the baseline year(s), all diked cells were flooded to ~ 1 m above normal for a period of 2 years (Table 2). These levels were designed to flood the existing cattail (Typha spp.) stands to a depth of 1 m and were similar to actual natural high-water levels that occurred in the Delta Marsh in the 1950s. This deep flooding was intended to kill the existing emergent vegetation and set all the cells to the lake marsh stage described by van der Valk and Davis (1978). In part, deep flooding was also an attempt to reduce the variability in vegetation among the experimental cells prior to drawdown.</para>
 <para>c.	Drawdown (1983-1984):</para>
 <para>After the second year of above-normal flooding, the cells were drawn down (completely dewatered) by adjusting the water levels to 50 cm below the long-term level of the Delta Marsh (Table 2). Most cells were exposed to a 2-year drawdown. Two cells (3 and 7) were drawn down for 1 year to allow comparisons between drawdowns of 1- and 2-year durations. The drawdowns allowed vegetation to reestablish on the marsh substrates (Welling et al., 1988a, b).</para>
 <para>d.	Reflooding (1985-1989):</para>
 <para>It has been assumed that the rate at which prairie wetlands proceed through the various stages of the wet-dry cycle is determined by water depth, with deeper wetlands moving to the lake marsh stage more quickly than shallowly flooded wetlands (van der Valk and Davis, 1978). Following drawdown, the cells were reflooded to three different levels (Table 3). The normal level was the long-term mean level (247.50 m above mean sea level [AMSL]) of the Delta Marsh and the medium (247.80 m) and high (248.10 m) levels were 30 and 60 cm above the long-term mean, respectively (Murkin et al., 2000a).</para>
 <para>To ensure replicated treatments (on a hydrologic basis) during the reflooding experiments in 1985-1989, water-level treatments were assigned to the experimental cells as follows: the two low-water treatments with a 1-year drawdown (Table 3) were randomly assigned to the experimental complex, and the remaining treatments were then assigned to the other cells to ensure that each cell within a water-level treatment had a similar hydrologic setting (i.e. both low cells with 1-year drawdowns were flanked by cells with low and high treatments, both low 2-year drawdown cells by low and medium treatments, all medium treatment cells by high- and low-treatment cells, and the high-treatment cells by medium and low cells). This replicated hydrology is discussed in more detail in Kadlec (1983, 1993). The treatment assignments for the 1985-1989 period (Table 3) determined the water-level assignments during the early phases of the MERP experiments from 1981 to 1984 (Table 2).</para>
 <para>Long-term Monitoring Program</para>
 <para>The Scientific Team designed a program of standardized methods to monitor the experimental cells throughout the period of study. The basic strategy was to collect a comparable data set from year to year in each experimental cell for each of the major components being monitored, including hydrology, water chemistry, macrophytes, macrophyte litter, algae, invertebrates and vertebrates (Murkin et al., 2000a; Murkin, 1989b). The MERP long-term monitoring program involved a variety of techniques that were used to provide comparable datasets across the experimental cells and over the 10 years of fieldwork. Some of the techniques used were new, but most were adopted from other researchers. All have been modified to suit the needs for efficiency, economy and practicality for long-term large-scale ecosystem research (Murkin et al., 2000b). Each component has a section in the MERP Data Archive describing the techniques used.</para>
 <para>Short-term Studies</para>
 <para>Besides the long-term monitoring program, short-term studies were an integral component of the overall MERP program. Some of these studies provided background information needed to develop the long-term monitoring program (Pederson, 1981; Wrubleski, 1984). Some were integrated into the long-term monitoring program (Murkin, 1983a; Galinato, 1985; Hosseini, 1986; Welling, 1987; Merendino, 1989). Several aspects of the long-term monitoring program following drawdown began as short-term studies (Kroeker, 1988; Squires, 1991; Wrubleksi, 1991). Many of the short-term studies, however, were initiated because of questions raised by the long-term monitoring program. This approach was particularly true for studies of invertebrates (Nelson, 1982; Neckles, 1984; Bicknese, 1987; Campeau, 1990) and emergent macrophytes (Neill, 1988; Neill, 1992). Many of the short-term studies were conducted by graduate studies, a list of which can be found in merp_pubs_appx3_prairie_wetland_ecology_pdfa.pdf and whose theses can be found in the merp_publications_theses file (Murkin et al., 2000a).</para>
 <para>Main Transects, Work Lanes and Sampling Procedure</para>
 <para>To aid in the assignment of sampling stations, each cell was divided into 10 zones. Zone boundaries were parallel to the southern dike. To determine the zones, 10 areas of equal width were established between a line 10 m north of the south dike and a second line 10 m south of the road on the northern edge of the cell. These zones were permanently marked so they could be located from year to year.</para>
 <para>Each year, ten transects were randomly established within each cell, 1 per zone, numbered from north to south. These transects or &#8216;work lanes&#8217; were used for all types of routine sampling, in order to minimize disturbance and confine it within a designated region. All sampling took place as near as possible to the work lane. When a sampling point was some distance from the work lane, a path perpendicular to the work lane was established. Work lanes were reassigned each fall following the last day of sampling (Murkin, 1989b; Murkin et al., 2000b).</para>
 <para>A standard sampling procedure was maintained during all transect sampling. One or two random transects in each cell were sampled, repeating the same method for each cell until all samples were secured, rather than sampling all transects in a cell before moving on to the next cell. This randomized any effect due to time during the sampling period. As standard procedure, water depth at the sampling site was recorded during all types of sampling (Murkin, 1983b).</para>
 <para>Additional data packages generated from the Marsh Ecology Research Program can also be found on the Knowledge Network for Biocomplexity (KNB):</para>
 <para>AERIAL MAPS &amp; GIS</para>
 <para>Aerial photos, cover maps and GIS data (1980-1989)</para>
 <para>ALGAE:</para>
 <para>Algal data transect sampling (1985-1989)</para>
 <para>Metaphyton data (1985-1989)</para>
 <para>Epipelon data (1985-1989)</para>
 <para>Epiphyton data (1985-1989)</para>
 <para>Phytoplankton data (1985-1989)</para>
 <para>ANNUAL CLIMATIC FACTORS:</para>
 <para>Weather data (1980-1989)</para>
 <para>Marsh evaporation pan data (1981-1989)</para>
 <para>DECOMPOSITION:</para>
 <para>Short-term dead standing litter study data (1981-1984)</para>
 <para>Root decomposition litter bag study data (1988-1989)</para>
 <para>Shoot decomposition litter bag study data (1986-1989)</para>
 <para>Decomposition of mud-flat species litter bag study data (1985-1987)</para>
 <para>Decomposition of mud-flat species litter bag study data (1983-1985)</para>
 <para>Emergent macrophyte and metaphyton litter bag study data (1983-1984)</para>
 <para>Turnover plot litter bag study data (1981-1983)</para>
 <para>Conditioning period litter bag study data (1980-1981)</para>
 <para>Preliminary litter bag study data (1979-1982)</para>
 <para>Dead standing litter study data (1985-1989)</para>
 <para>HYDROLOGY:</para>
 <para>Hydraulic conductivity data (1982-1989)</para>
 <para>Water table levels (1982-1989)</para>
 <para>Pump meter data (1980-1989)</para>
 <para>Staff gauge data (1980-1989)</para>
 <para>INVERTEBRATES:</para>
 <para>Artificial substrates data (1985-1989)</para>
 <para>Substrate core data (1980-1982)</para>
 <para>Sweep net data (1980-1982)</para>
 <para>Emergence trap data (1980-1989)</para>
 <para>Activity trap data (1980-1989)</para>
 <para>Maximum-minimum water temperature data (1980-1984)</para>
 <para>Chironomidae (Diptera) responses to the experimental flooding of prairie marshes (1985-1988)</para>
 <para>PHYSICAL ENVIRONMENT:</para>
 <para>Total suspended solids data (1980-1989)</para>
 <para>Sediment bulk density and percent organic matter data (1986-1989)</para>
 <para>SOIL NUTRIENTS:</para>
 <para>Soil nutrients and groundwater well site characterization data (1980-1985)</para>
 <para>VEGETATION:</para>
 <para>Matching stems study data (1986-1989)</para>
 <para>Belowground macrophyte production data (MBG; 1980-1989)</para>
 <para>Aboveground macrophyte production data (MAG; 1980-1989)</para>
 <para>Turnover plot data (1980-1989)</para>
 <para>VERTEBRATES:</para>
 <para>Nest count data (1980-1989)</para>
 <para>Avian census data (1980-1989)</para>
 <para>Muskrat habitat selection data (1986)</para>
 <para>Muskrat population data (1985-1989)</para>
 <para>WATER CHEMISTRY:</para>
 <para>Water chemistry data (1980-1989)</para>
 <para>Tables</para>
 <para>Table 1: Dimensions of the MERP cells (from Murkin, 1983b)</para>
 <para>Cells	Width (m)a	Length (m)b	Work zone width (m)	Area (ha)</para>
 <para>1	155	300	30	5.68</para>
 <para>2	190	300	30	7.5</para>
 <para>3	130	330	33	5.48</para>
 <para>4	135	310	31	6.08</para>
 <para>5	135	300	30	6.04</para>
 <para>6	135	320	32	6.45</para>
 <para>7	161	320	32	6.01</para>
 <para>8	153	300	30	5.75</para>
 <para>9	151	280	28	5.50</para>
 <para>10	200	200	20	5.80</para>
 <para>11	150	300	30	5.40</para>
 <para>12	150	320	32	5.75</para>
 <para>a  - measured from a point 10m east of the borrow ditch to a second point 10m west of the east dike. Since the width of an individual cell varies from north to south these are the mean values.</para>
 <para>b  - measured from a line 10m north of the south dike to a parallel line 10m south of the north edge of the cell.</para>
 <para>Table 2: Schedule of water levels for MERP experimental cells (from Murkin et al., 2000a).</para>
 <para>Year	Water Levels</para>
 <para>1980	10 cells normal levels of Delta Marsh (247.50m AMSL)</para>
 <para>1981	8 cells flooded to conditioning level (&#61627;1m above normal; 248.41m AMSL)</para>
 <para>2 cells (3 &amp; 7) at normal levels of Delta Marsh (247.50m AMSL)</para>
 <para>1982	10 cells at conditioning level (&#61627;1m above normal; 248.41m AMSL)</para>
 <para>1983	8 cells drawn down (247.00m AMSL)</para>
 <para>2 cells (3 &amp; 7) remain at conditioning level (&#61627;1m above normal; 248.41m AMSL)</para>
 <para>1984	10 cells drawn down (247.00m AMSL)</para>
 <para>1985-1989	4 cells (3,4,7 &amp; 8) flooded at normal level (247.50m AMSL)</para>
 <para>3 cells (1,5 &amp; 9) flooded at medium level (247.80m AMSL)</para>
 <para>3 cells (2,6 &amp; 10) flooded at high level (248.10m AMSL)</para>
 <para>Table 3: Experimental cells within each of the water levels following drawdown (1985-1989; from Murkin et al., 2000a).</para>
 <para>Water level after drawdown (AMSL)</para>
 <para>Drawdown duration (years)	Shallow (247.50m)	Medium (247.80m)	High (248.19m)</para>
 <para>1	3,7</para>
 <para>2	4,8	1,5,9	2,6,10</para>
 <para>Table 4: Common MERP Prefixes</para>
 <para>Prefix	MERP Sample Type</para>
 <para>MBG	Macrophyte belowground samples</para>
 <para>MAG	Macrophyte aboveground samples</para>
 <para>TO	Turnover plot samples</para>
 <para>DSL (CQ)	Dead standing litter (clip-quadrat) samples</para>
 <para>LB	Litterbag samples</para>
 <para>MS (PERM)	Matching stems (Permanent clips) samples</para>
 <para>SW	Surface water samples</para>
 <para>GW	Groundwater samples</para>
 <para>PO	Pump water samples (out of cell)</para>
 <para>PI	Pump water samples (into cell)</para>
 <para>RW	Rain water samples</para>
 <para>AS	Artificial substrate samples</para>
 <para>AT	Activity trap samples</para>
 <para>ET	Emergence trap samples</para>
 <para>References</para>
 <para>Batt, B.D.J. 2000. The Delta Marsh. In Prairie Wetland Ecology: The Contribution of the Marsh Ecology Research Program. (Eds) H.R. Murkin, A.G. van der Valk and W.R. Clark. pp. 17-33. Ames: Iowa State University Press.</para>
 <para>Bicknese, N.A. 1987. Factors influencing the decomposition of fallen macrophyte litter at the Delta Marsh, Manitoba, Canada. M.S. thesis, Iowa State University. Ames, Iowa.</para>
 <para>Campeau, S. 1990. The relative importance of algae and detritus to freshwater wetland food chains. M.S. thesis, McGill University, Montreal, Quebec.</para>
 <para>Clark, W.R., and D. W. Kroeker. 1993. Population dynamics of muskrats in experimental marshes at Delta, Manitoba. Canadian Journal of Zoology 71: 1620-1 628.</para>
 <para>Ehrlich, W.A., E.A. Poyser, and L.E. Pratt. 1957. Report on the reconnaissance soil survey of Carberry map sheet area. Soils Report 7, Manitoba Soils Survey, Winnipeg, Manitoba.</para>
 <para>Galinato, M.I. 1985. Seed germination studies of dominant mudflat-annual and emergent species of the Delta Marsh. M.S. thesis, Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa.</para>
 <para>Good, R. E., D.F. Whigham, and R.L. Simpson (Eds.). 1978. Freshwater Wetlands: Ecological Processes and Management Potential. New York: Academic Press.</para>
 <para>Greeson, P.E., J.R. Clark, and J.E. Clark (Eds.). 1978. Wetland Functions and Values: The State of Our Understanding. American Water Resources Association Technical Publication TPS79-2.</para>
 <para>Hosseini, S.M. 1986. The effects of water level fluctuations on algal communities of freshwater marshes. Ph.D. dissertation, Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa.</para>
 <para>Kadlec, J.A. 1983. Water budgets for small diked marshes. Water Resources Bulletin 19:223-229.</para>
 <para>Kadlec, J.A. 1993. Effect of depth of flooding on summer water budgets for small diked marshes. Wetlands 13: 1-9.</para>
 <para>Kroeker, D.W. 1988. Population dynamics of muskrats in managed marshes at Delta, Manitoba. M.S. thesis, Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa.</para>
 <para>L&#246;ve, A., and D. L&#246;ve. 1954. Vegetation of a prairie marsh. Bulletin of the Torrey Botanical Club 81:16-34.</para>
 <para>Merendino, M.T. 1989. The response of vegetation to seasonality of drawdown and reflood depth. M.S. thesis, Texas Tech University, Lubbock, Texas.</para>
 <para>Murkin, H.R. 1983a. Responses by aquatic macroinvertebrates to prolonged flooding of marsh habitat. Ph.D. dissertation, Utah State University, Logan, Utah.</para>
 <para>Murkin, H.R. 1983b. Introduction. In Marsh Ecology Research Program: Long-term Monitoring Procedures Manual. (Ed.) H.R. Murkin. pp. 1-9. Manitoba: Delta Waterfowl Research Station.</para>
 <para>Murkin, H.R. 1989a. The basis for food chains in prairie wetlands. In Northern Prairie Wetlands. (Ed.) A.G. van der Valk, pp.316-338. Ames: Iowa State University Press.</para>
 <para>Murkin, H.R. 1989b. Introduction to the Marsh Ecology Research Program. In Marsh Ecology Research Program: Long-term Monitoring Procedures Manual. (Eds.) E.J. Murkin and H.R. Murkin. pp. 1-3. Manitoba: Delta Waterfowl Research Station.</para>
 <para>Murkin, H.R. 1998. Freshwater functions and values of prairie wetlands. Great Plains Research 8:3-15.</para>
 <para>Murkin, H.R., B.D.J. Batt, P.J. Caldwell, C.B. Davis, J.A. Kadlec, and A.G. van der Valk. 1984. Perspectives on the Delta Waterfowl Research Station- Ducks Unlimited Canada Marsh Ecology Research Program. Transactions of the North American Wildlife and Natural Resources Conference 49:253-261.</para>
 <para>Murkin, H.R., B.D.J. Batt, P.J. Caldwell, J.A. Kadlec and A.G. van der Valk. 2000a. Introduction to the Marsh Ecology Research Program. In Prairie Wetland Ecology: The Contribution of the Marsh Ecology Research Program. (Eds) H.R. Murkin, A.G. van der Valk and W.R. Clark. pp. 3-15. Ames: Iowa State University Press.</para>
 <para>Murkin, H.R., W.R. Clark, S.E. Gurney, J.A. Kadlec, G.G.C. Robinson, L.C.M. Ross and A.G. van der Valk. 2000b. Summary of MERP techniques and sampling program. In Prairie Wetland Ecology: The Contribution of the Marsh Ecology Research Program. (Eds) H.R. Murkin, A.G. van der Valk and W.R. Clark. pp. 359-379. Ames: Iowa State University Press.</para>
 <para>Neckles, H.A. 1984. Plant and macroinvertebrate responses to water regime in a whitetop marsh. M.S. thesis, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, Minnesota.</para>
 <para>Neill, C. 1988. Control of primary productivity of emergent macrophytes in prairie marshes: effects of water depth and nutrient availability. M.S. thesis, University of Massachusetts, Amherst, Massachusetts.</para>
 <para>Neill, C. 1992. Relationships between emergent plant production and seasonal flooding in prairie whitetop (Scholochloa festucacea) marshes. Ph.D. dissertation, University of Massachusetts, Amherst, Massachusetts.</para>
 <para>Nelson, J.W. 1982. Effects of varying detrital nutrient concentrations on macroinvertebrate abundance and biomass. M.S. thesis, Utah State University, Logan, Utah.</para>
 <para>Pederson, R.L. 1981. Abundance, distribution, and diversity of buried seed populations in the Delta Marsh, Manitoba, Canada. Ph.D. dissertation, Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa.</para>
 <para>Ross, L.C.M., and H.R. Murkin. 1993. The effect of above-normal flooding of a northern prairie marsh on Agraylea multipunctata Curtis (Trichoptera, Hydroptilidae). Journal of Freshwater Ecology 8:27-35.</para>
 <para>Squires, L. 1991. Water depth tolerances of emergent species in the Delta Marsh, Manitoba. M.S. thesis, Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa.</para>
 <para>van der Valk, A.G. (Ed.). 1989. Northern Prairie Wetlands. Ames: Iowa State University Press.</para>
 <para>van der Valk, A.G., and CB. Davis. 1978. The role of seed banks in the vegetation dynamics of prairie glacial marshes. Ecology 59: 322-335.</para>
 <para>van der Valk, A.G., C.H. Welling. and RL. Pederson. 1989. Vegetation change in a freshwater wetland: a test of a priori predictions. In Freshwater Wetlands and Wildlife. (Eds.) R.R. Sharitz and J.W. Gibbons, pp.207-217. USDOE Symposium Series No. 61 , Oak Ridge: USDOE Office of Scientific and Technical Information.</para>
 <para>Weller, M.W. 1978. Management of freshwater marshes for wildlife. In Freshwater Wetlands: Ecological Processes and Management Potential. (Eds.) R.E. Good, D.E Whigham, and R.L. Simpson, pp.267-284. New York: Academic Press.</para>
 <para>Weller, M.W. 1981. Freshwater Marshes: Ecology and Wildlife Management. University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis, Minnesota.</para>
 <para>Welling, C.H. 1987. Reestablishment of perennial emergent macrophytes during a drawdown in a lacustrine marsh. M.S. thesis, Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa.</para>
 <para>Welling, C.H., R.L Pederson, and A.G. van der Valk. 1988a. Recruitment from the seed bank and the development of zonation of emergent vegetation during a drawdown in a prairie wetland. Journal of Ecology 76: 483-496.</para>
 <para>Welling. C.H., R.L Pederson, and A.G. van der Valk. 1988b. Temporal patterns in recruitment from the seed bank during drawdowns in a prairie wetland. Journal of Applied Ecology 25: 999-1007.</para>
 <para>Wrubleski, D.A. 1984. Chironomid (Diptera: Chironomidae) species composition, emergence phenologies, and relative abundances in the Delta Marsh, Manitoba. M.S. thesis, University of Manitoba, Winnipeg, Manitoba.</para>
 <para>Wrubleski, D.A. 1991. Chironomid recolonization of marsh drawdown surfaces following reflooding. Ph.D. dissertation, University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 <project><title>Marsh Ecology Research Program</title>
 <personnel><references>1321551771031</references>
 <role>Custodian/Steward</role>
 </personnel>
 <funding><para>Amoco Canada Petroleum, James F. Bell Foundation, Richard A.N. Bonnycastle, Peter D. Curry, Devonian Group of Charitable Foundations, Delta Waterfowl Foundation (formerly the North American Wildlife Foundation), Donner Foundation, Ducks Unlimited Canada, Ducks Unlimited Foundation, Ducks Unlimited Incorporated, William P. Elliott, Edson I. Gaylord, Richard Ivey Foundation, Laidlaw Foundation, John M.S. Lecky, Molson Foundation, Murphy Foundation, McLean Foundation, Senator Norman Patterson Foundation, Richardson Century Fund, and R. Howard Webster</para>
 </funding>
 </project>
 <dataTable id="1321283736343"><entityName>Groundwater Well Site Characterization species list (1980-1985)</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Species list for MERP Soil nutrients and groundwater well site characterization (1980-1985) data</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1321283645406"><objectName>merp_gwchar_spplist.txt</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">998</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>0</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/duc_merp.39.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1321283736359"><attributeName>Species name</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Species name</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Species list of macrophytes sampled at groundwater well sites for MERP groundwater well site characterization data (1980-1985).</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Species name</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>53</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 <dataTable id="1321286568578"><entityName>MERP Groundwater well site characterization data (1980-1985)</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Characterization of macrophyte species at groundwater well sites, collected as part of the MERP Soil nutrients and groundwater well site characterization data (1980-1985). Soil nutrient data for groundwater well sites is contained within a separate data file in this data package.</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1321285880734"><objectName>merp_gwchar1980-1985_data.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">32913</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/duc_merp.42.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1321286568593"><attributeName>day</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling day</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sampling for the characterization of macrophytes at groundwater well sites occurred once in late July or early August during the sampling season, as this is the period where standing emergents reach their maximum standing crop.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>dd</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321286568609"><attributeName>month</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling month</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sampling for the characterization of macrophytes at groundwater well sites occurred once in late July or early August during the sampling season, as this is the period where standing emergents reach their maximum standing crop.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>mm</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321286568625"><attributeName>year</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling year</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>For 1980-1985, sampling for the characterization of macrophytes at groundwater well sites occurred once in late July or early August during the sampling season, as this is the period where standing emergents reach their maximum standing crop.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>yyyy</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321286568640"><attributeName>cell_num</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>cell number</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>cells were numbered 1 to 10 from west to east in the diked study area. cell 11 (outside the diked boundary to the west) and cell 12 (outside to the east) were controls.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Cell number (1-12).</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321286568656"><attributeName>transect</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling transect</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>each cell was divided into 10 equal zones by the main sampling transects. these zones were marked permanently and used each year.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>sampling transect (1-10)</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321286568671"><attributeName>gw_well</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Groundwater well site</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>each cell had groundwater well sample sites randomly placed on the main sampling transects; For cell 9, one sample site placed on all 10 transects (1-10); for all other cells (1-8, 10-12), 	one sample site placed on 5 of the 10 main sampling transects (1-5)</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Groundwater well sites (1-10)</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321286568687"><attributeName>species</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>macrophyte species present</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>each code consists of 6 digits, where digits 1-2 indicate family, digits 3-4 indicate genus and digits 5-6 indicate species.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><entityCodeList><entityReference>1321286723984</entityReference>
 <valueAttributeReference>1321286724000</valueAttributeReference>
 <definitionAttributeReference>1321286724015</definitionAttributeReference>
 </entityCodeList>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321286568703"><attributeName>live_dead</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>alive or dead</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Collected for 1982 only, codes whether macrophyte species observed were alive or dead. Note that where a plant was observed to be dead, plant species code is blank in most cases as dead plant could not be identified to species.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>1</code>
 <definition>alive</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>2</code>
 <definition>dead</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321286568718"><attributeName>dens_cvr</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>density (m2) or cover value (%)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>for emergent or upland species, density of stems per m2 is indicated
for submergent species, % cover value is indicated
note: when trace amounts of a species was present, a value of one was given.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>squareMeter</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>1195</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 <dataTable id="1321286723984"><entityName>MERP Groundwater well site characterization (1980-1985) species codes</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Macrophyte species codes for MERP Groundwater well site characterization (1980-1985) data</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1321286641375"><objectName>merp_gwchar_sppcodes.txt</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">2198</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/duc_merp.43.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1321286724000"><attributeName>Code</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Plant species code</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>each code consists of 6 digits, where digits 1-2 indicate family, digits 3-4 indicate genus and digits 5-6 indicate species</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Plant species code</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321286724015"><attributeName>Species</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Macophyte species name</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Macrophyte species name, for plant species codes, used in Groundwater well site characterization data (1980-1985).</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Macrophyte species name</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>58</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 <dataTable id="1321298803343"><entityName>MERP soil nutrients data (1980-1985)</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Soil nutrient data, collected from groundwater well sites, as part of the MERP Soil nutrients and groundwater well site characterization data (1980-1985). Grounwater well site characterization data is contained in a separate data file, as part of this data package.</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1321297399203"><objectName>merp_soilnut1980-1985_data.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">18311</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/duc_merp.45.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1321298803359"><attributeName>day</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling day</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Soil samples from groundwater well sites were collected on an annual basis for nutrient analysis, during the last week of June or early July (with the exception of 1984, when samples were collected in August and October).</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>dd</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321298803375"><attributeName>month</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling month</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Soil samples from groundwater well sites were collected on an annual basis for nutrient analysis, during the last week of June or early July (with the exception of 1984, when samples were collected in August and October).</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>mm</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321298803390"><attributeName>year</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling year</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Soil samples from groundwater well sites were collected on an annual basis (1980-1985) for nutrient analysis, during the last week of June or early July (with the exception of 1984, when samples were collected in August and October).</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>yyyy</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321298803406"><attributeName>cell_num</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>cell number</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>cells were numbered 1 to 10 from west to east in the diked study area.
cell 11 (outside the diked boundary to the west) and cell 12 (outside to the east) were controls.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>cell number (1-12)</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321298803421"><attributeName>transect</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sampling transect</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>each cell was divided into 10 equal zones by the main sampling transects
these zones were marked permanently and used each year.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>sampling transect (1-10)</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321298803437"><attributeName>gw_well</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>groundwater well site</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>each cell had groundwater well sample sites randomly placed on the main sampling transects; For celll 9, one sample site placed on all 10 transects (1-10); for all other cells (1-8, 10-12), one sample site placed on 5 of the 10 main sampling transects (1-5)</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Groundwater well site (1-10)</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321298803453"><attributeName>avail_N</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>available Nitrogen (ppm)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>As per requirements of the Soil Testing Lab, each wet sediment sample was homogenized in a blender before being transferred to the Soil Testing Lab, and stored in a freezer (Kadlec, 1985a). All anaylses were performed on wet samples. The analytic procedure was modified so that subsamples for analyses of available N (NO3--N + NO2-N)  were not dried prior to extraction, as drying affects extractable quantities of most ions in organic soils (Kadlec, 1989; Anderson and Beverly, 1985; Gilliam and Richter, 1985). N subsamples were extracted with 0.5M NaHCO3 at pH 8.5  The N extracts were analyzed on a Technicon Auto Analyzer, N by a modification of the procedure of Kampshake et al. (1967).</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>PartsPerMillion</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321298803468"><attributeName>TN</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Total Nitrogen (%)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>As per requirements of the Soil Testing Lab, each wet sediment sample was homogenized in a blender before being transferred to the Soil Testing Lab, and stored in a freezer (Kadlec, 1985a). Total N was determined by the Kjeldahl method.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>Percent</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321298803484"><attributeName>avail_P</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>available Phosphorus (ppm)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>As per requirements of the Soil Testing Lab, each wet sediment sample was homogenized in a blender before being transferred to the Soil Testing Lab, and stored in a freezer (Kadlec, 1985a). All anaylses were performed on wet samples. The analytic procedure was modified so that subsamples for analyses of available P (dissolved and some adsorbed P) were not dried prior to extraction, as drying affects extractable quantities of most ions in organic soils (Kadlec, 1989; Anderson and Beverly, 1985; Gilliam and Richter, 1985). P subsamples were extracted with 0.5M NaHCO3 at pH 8.5. The P extracts were analyzed on a Technicon Auto Analyzer, P by the ascorbic acid-ammonium molybdate method (Page et al., 1982)</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>PartsPerMillion</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321298803500"><attributeName>TP</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Total Phosphorus (%)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>As per requirements of the Soil Testing Lab, each wet sediment sample was homogenized in a blender before being transferred to the Soil Testing Lab, and stored in a freezer (Kadlec, 1985a). Analyses for total P were performed on dried sediment samples which were digested with HNO3 and HClO4.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>Percent</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321298803515"><attributeName>avail_K</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Available Potassium (ppm)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>As per requirements of the Soil Testing Lab, each wet sediment sample was homogenized in a blender before being transferred to the Soil Testing Lab, and stored in a freezer (Kadlec, 1985a). All anaylses were performed on wet samples. The analytic procedure was modified so that subsamples for analyses of available K were not dried prior to extraction, as drying affects extractable quantities of most ions in organic soils (Kadlec, 1989; Anderson and Beverly, 1985; Gilliam and Richter, 1985). K subsamples were extracted with 1N NH4OAc at pH 7.K was analyzed by flame photometry.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>PartsPerMillion</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321298803531"><attributeName>TS</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Total sulfur (ppm)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Analyses for total P and total S were performed on dried sediment samples which were digested with HNO3 and HClO4</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>PartsPerMillion</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321298803546"><attributeName>perc_h2o</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>percent moisture (%)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>as a percent of the soil dry weight.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>Percent</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1321298803562"><attributeName>om</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Organic matter (%)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Organic matter was determined by the potassium dichromate reduction procedure (Page et al., 1982).</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>Percent</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>388</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 </dataset>
 <additionalMetadata><metadata><unitList><unit id="PartsPerMillion" multiplierToSI=" " name="PartsPerMillion" parentSI="mole" unitType="amount"><description>Dimensionless quanitity</description>
 </unit>
 </unitList>
 </metadata>
 </additionalMetadata>
 <additionalMetadata><metadata><unitList><unit id="Percent" multiplierToSI=" " name="Percent" parentSI="mole" unitType="amount"><description>Dimensionless quantity</description>
 </unit>
 </unitList>
 </metadata>
 </additionalMetadata>
 </ns0:eml>