<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="df35d.124.19" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"><allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow><principal>cn=evos,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 <permission>write</permission>
 <permission>changePermission</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset scope="document">  <title>Historical humpback whale abundance estimates in Prince William Sound, Alaska: 1978 - 2009</title>
<creator id="1363199590958"><individualName><givenName>Suzanne</givenName>
 <surName>Teerlink</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Juneau Center, School of Fisheries and Ocean Sciences, University of Alaska Fairbanks</organizationName>
 <electronicMailAddress>s.teerlink@alaska.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1363120603324"><individualName><givenName>Terrance</givenName>
 <surName>Quinn</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>University of Alaska Fairbanks, School of Fisheries &amp; Ocean Sciences</organizationName>
 <positionName>Full Professor</positionName>
 <electronicMailAddress>terry.quinn@alaska.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1363120757391"><individualName><givenName>Jan</givenName>
 <surName>Straley</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>University of Alaska Southeast</organizationName>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1363120804538"><individualName><givenName>Olga</givenName>
 <surName>Von Ziegesar</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Eye of the Whale</organizationName>
 </creator>
 <associatedParty id="1365725511734"><individualName><givenName>Shelly</givenName>
 <surName>Gill</surName>
 </individualName>
 <role>Content Provider</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty id="1365725528319"><individualName><givenName>Gerry</givenName>
 <surName>Sanger</surName>
 </individualName>
 <role>Content Provider</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty id="1364406317407"><individualName><givenName>John</givenName>
 <surName>Moran</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>NOAA</organizationName>
 <role>Collaborator</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty id="1364406358538"><individualName><givenName>Eva</givenName>
 <surName>Saulitis</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>North Gulf Oceanic Society</organizationName>
 <electronicMailAddress>elsaulitis@gmail.com</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Collaborator</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty id="1364406348248"><individualName><givenName>Craig</givenName>
 <surName>Matkin</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>North Gulf Oceanic Society</organizationName>
 <positionName>Director</positionName>
 <electronicMailAddress>cmatkin@acsalaska.net</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Collaborator</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty id="1365725498414"><individualName><givenName>Beth</givenName>
 <surName>Goodwin</surName>
 </individualName>
 <role>Content Provider</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty id="1365725643138"><individualName><givenName>Ron</givenName>
 <surName>Heintz</surName>
 </individualName>
 <role>Collaborator</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty id="1365725730335"><individualName><givenName>Sarah</givenName>
 <surName>Clark</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis</organizationName>
 <positionName>Projects Data Coordinator</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>735 State Street, Suite 300</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Santa Barbara</city>
 <administrativeArea>California</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>93101</postalCode>
 </address>
 <electronicMailAddress>sclark@nceas.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Metadata Provider</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty id="1365725659667"><individualName><givenName>Stanley</givenName>
 <surName>Rice</surName>
 </individualName>
 <role>Collaborator</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty id="1365725538666"><organizationName>Woods Hole Oceanographic Institute</organizationName>
 <role>Content Provider</role>
 </associatedParty>
<abstract><para>The principal objectives of this study were to analyze historical data on humpback whales (late 1970s to present) collected by research organization Eye of the Whale and others to develop time series of abundance for humpback whales in Prince William Sound. This historical data is proprietary and was not analyzed in depth. Annual high-quality surveys used photo-identification, so that numbers were counted accurately. In this work a relative index was also calculated from sightings and sampling effort but found to be of little value. Mark-recapture models were developed from the sighting histories to produce annual estimates of abundance. These estimates were then used in an age-structured assessment model of Pacific herring to estimate the historical effect of whale predation on herring.  The main result was that humpback whales constitute an important component of predation on Prince William Sound herring. The recovery of the Pacific herring population may be limited by this predation along with other factors. This project is an offshoot from Project 090804 and gives a 30 year perspective to the findings of that project. This study was graduate student Suzie Teerlink's master's thesis under the advisement of Dr. Terrance Quinn II, Professor of Fish Population Dynamics, University of Alaska Fairbanks, Juneau Center, School of Fisheries and Ocean Sciences. No field work was required for this data salvage project.

Publications and Presentations:
Teerlink, S.F., von Ziegesar, O., Straley, J.M., Quinn, T.J., Matkin, C.O., Saulitis, E.L. 2013. First time series of estimated humpback whale (Megaptera novaeangliae) abundance in Prince William Sound. (Chapter 1 of Teerlink's Masters Thesis). Juneau Center, School of Fisheries and Ocean Sciences, University of Alaska Fairbanks. Submitted for publication to a peer-reviewed journal and is in review.

Teerlink, S., von Ziegesar, O., Straley, J., Quinn, T. 2010. Humpback whale predation on Pacific herring Part 1: Construction of historical time series of humpback whale abundance in Prince William Sound relative to Pacific herring dynamics. Presentation to the 2010 Alaska Marine Science Symposium.

Heintz, R., Moran, J., Vollenweider, J., Straley, J., Quinn, T., et al. 2010. Humpback Whale Predation on Herring Part 5: Impacts of Whale Foraging on Three Herring Populations in Alaska. Presentation to the 2010 Alaska Marine Science Symposium.</para>
</abstract>
<keywordSet><keyword>humpback whale</keyword>
<keyword>Prince William Sound</keyword>
<keyword>population</keyword>
<keyword>abundance estimates</keyword>
<keyword>mark-recapture</keyword>
<keyword>photoidentification</keyword>
</keywordSet>
<keywordSet><keyword>EVOSTC</keyword>
<keyword>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council</keyword>
<keyword>Oil Spill</keyword>
<keyword>Exxon Valdez</keyword>
<keyword>Alaska</keyword>
<keyword>Pelagic</keyword>
<keyword>Mammals</keyword>
<keywordThesaurus>Gulf Watch Alaska Thesaurus</keywordThesaurus>
</keywordSet>
<intellectualRights><para>This material is based upon work funded in part by the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council.  Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed herein are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views or positions of the Trustee Council.
 
Standard scientific norms for attribution and credit should be followed when using these data including to the Owners, Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council and other sources of funding. Please let the Owners know when this data is used.
 
These data are licensed under CC0. The person who associated a work with this deed has dedicated the work to the public domain by waiving all of his or her rights to the work worldwide under copyright law, including all related and neighboring rights, to the extent allowed by law. You can copy, modify, distribute and perform the work, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</para>
</intellectualRights>
    <coverage scope="document"> <temporalCoverage scope="document"> <rangeOfDates> <beginDate> <calendarDate>1978</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate> <calendarDate>2009</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 <taxonomicCoverage scope="document"> <taxonomicClassification> <taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Megaptera</taxonRankValue>
 <taxonomicClassification> <taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>novaeangliae</taxonRankValue>
 <commonName>Humpback whale</commonName>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicCoverage>
 <geographicCoverage scope="document"> <geographicDescription>western Prince William Sound, Alaska, USA</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates> <westBoundingCoordinate>-148.375</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>-145.875</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>61.5</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>60.0</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact scope="document"> <references>1363120603324</references>
 </contact>
<methods><methodStep><description><section><title>Procedural and Scientific Methods</title>
<para>In order to better understand the historical population-level interactions between humpback whales and herring in PWS, we intend to develop the first time series of humpback whale abundance for this region. Humpback whales are individually identifiable by the unique pigmentation pattern on the ventral side of their flukes. By periodically identifying individuals in the study area using fluke photographs (i.e. "sampling"), it is possible to estimate the relative abundance using mark recapture theory (Straley et al. 2009).</para>
<para>In order to make this retrospective analysis we have identified and recruited an additional collaborator, Olga von Ziegesar (Eye of the Whale (EOW) Research), who is providing humpback whale sighting data she has collected in PWS from 1980 to the present. Woods Hole Oceanographic Institute collected data from 1977 to 1980 and are available through the EOW catalog. Some funding from current EVOS project 090804 is making this possible. This data is in the form of whale counts and sighting histories which consist of individual whale photographs across years. Tracklines were first recorded in 1984, a necessary source of information for calculating sampling effort. In detail, EOW Research will provide: (1) an Excel spreadsheet of sighting histories of humpback whales seen each year during summer field surveys from 1977 to 2009, (2) copies of field data sheets for determining days of effort and survey tracklines, (3) a digital catalog of photographs of individual humpback whale flukes (von Ziegesar et al. 2001), and (4) loan of the negatives (1980 to 2003) or a digital image (2004-2009) of the best photo of each whale seen each year to assess for photo quality. Graduate student Suzie Teerlink will organize the data in an Access database (AK_Humpback_Database, currently used for EVOS project 090804) under the guidance of Straley.</para>
<para>Specific steps needed for getting these data organized into a usable format for this analysis are: (1) sighting histories will need to be error checked, compiled and entered into the Photo and Group tables in AK_Humpback_Database, (2) trackline data will need to be assessed for format compatibility and some field data will need to be digitized or converted before it can be entered into the effort table in the AK_Humpback_Database, and (3) photo quality will need to be assessed and entered into the database Photo table for each sighting of each whale each year. Quality of photos will be taken into account in this analysis. Poor photo quality can significantly affect the estimates generated (Stevick et al, 2001, Calambokidis et al., 2008). Therefore, photo quality will be assessed using the protocol adopted by Calambokidis et al., 2008, and photos ranked poor will be excluded from the analysis.</para>
<para>We will use the recent data from the EVOS project 090804 to compliment this historic sighting data. Together, these data will be used to develop two time series of relative humpback whale abundance; one will employ count per unit effort, and the other will utilize the Jolly-Seber method and mark-recapture theory (Seber 1982, see next section for specifics). The time series start year will need to be determined once all available data are gathered and assessed for consistency because the early years may have insufficient detail to be included in a complex mark recapture analyses. However, these early years may be suitable for the analysis using counts.</para>
</section>
</description>
</methodStep>
<methodStep><description><section><title>Data Analysis and Statistical Methods</title>
<para>Abundance estimation from the previous field study: The final report for Project 090804 (due April 2010) will contain mark-recapture analysis of both years of field data (2007-2008 and 2008-2009). Most of this modeling work has already been completed using Program Mark. Data from the second year of field work led to more precise abundance estimates. Secondly, it was possible to characterize variability in seasonal distribution with a second year of data. It appears that the seasonable distribution in the second year was more uniform with an earlier peak than the first year, although this requires additional analysis. This peak in late season whales is very similar to other areas of SE Alaska.</para>
<para>Whale time series: The modeling of the herring population in this current proposal is necessary to separate the effects of predation by humpback whales from disease and other factors. To get a historical view of the impact of whale predation, the age-structured assessment model can be extended to include whale predation. This requires the development of a whale time series back to 1980, which has not previously been done. Specifically, we will develop two series. The first is based on whale counts per unit effort. The second utilizes the Jolly-Seber method to obtain estimates of abundance and mortality using mark-recapture theory (Seber 1982). Whale abundance will be estimated from photographic data as described in Straley et al (2008).</para>
<para>For the mark-recapture analysis, we will be using the state-of-the-art platform for assessment of mark-recapture data, program MARK. This was developed by Gary White, Ken Burnham, David Anderson, and their colleagues at Colorado State University; it contains most of the newly developed models in a fairly intuitive Windows-based environment (White and Burnham 1999). The structure allows several hierarchical and non-hierarchical models to be estimated and compared. Both likelihood ratio tests and AIC statistics are provided, as well as detailed estimation output. In addition to mark-recapture data, covariates can be used to improve estimation and parameters can be added, fixed, and set equal across time periods, groups, and strata. The models within program MARK that will be utilized for this analysis include: basic closed population models, which will generate estimates of annual abundance, and Pradel models, which estimate the population trend over years. The closed population models will be structured to assume that the population is closed within a given study season and then allowed to be open between those periods; an important factor for a migratory species such as humpbacks.</para>
<para>Pradel models utilize the basic concepts of a Cormack-Jolly-Seber (CJS) approach though, by reversing the sighting histories, estimate the probability of individuals entering (not leaving) the population. So, in essence, the Pradel model removes the estimation of Phi (probability of persisting in the population from ti to ti+1) and instead estimates Gamma, the probability that</para>
<para>individuals seen at ti were in fact present at ti-1. This parameter is referred to as seniority. With the use of seniority as a parameter, we will be able to maximize the amount of information extracted from the data while modeling the population trend. (See Pradel (1996) for a full explanation of this method.)</para>
<para>In these analyses, we will employ the features of MARK to assist us in comparing models built to address various considerations. Among these considerations are: varying capture probabilities with time (difference in sightability conditions, etc), survey effort, heterogeneity and misidentification. Effort will be introduced as a covariate in both model types. Magnitude of effort is undoubtedly an important factor in the frequency of marks and recaptures acquired in a given sampling session. For this analysis, we will introduce effort as both nautical miles traveled and hours spent "on effort" for each sampling session. We will then evaluate which form of effort best explains variability in the model. For the closed capture population models we will also introduce parameters to estimate heterogeneity and misidentification. Heterogeneity, an inequality in capture probabilities due to individual behavioral response to boat presence, has been cited as a potential source of error for humpback mark-recapture analysis (Hammond 1990, Stevick et al, 2001). To correct for this we will generate models that include an estimate of heterogeneity. This is done by allowing the model to divide the population into groups of individuals that have higher and lower capture probabilities within each survey occasion. Misidentification, the situation where individuals are falsely categorized as new individuals when they are actually recaptures, can also be estimated and accounted for. While this is likely an infrequent occurrence, it can significantly alter results and therefore should be considered (Stevick et al, 2001).</para>
<para>We would then calibrate the relative abundance series to absolute estimates obtained from the ABL fall-winter mark-recapture studies of 2007 and 2008. This would require making the assumption that if whale abundance in the summer increases, then so would whale abundance in the fall-winter.</para>
</section>
</description>
</methodStep>
<methodStep><description><section><title>TeerlinkThesisMethods_StudyArea</title>
<para>Prince William Sound is located in the Gulf of Alaska (60 35 N, 147 10 W), and is comprised of numerous islands, glacial fjords, and bays. The western portion of PWS was designated as our study area (Fig. 1), as this is where the majority of surveys from the dataset were conducted. The dataset also includes some data from neighboring areas; however, because these areas are not consistently surveyed over the time series, these data were removed from our analyses.</para>
</section>
</description>
</methodStep>
<methodStep><description><section><title>TeerlinkThesisMethods_DescriptionData</title>
<para>The dataset includes humpback whale sightings and identification photos of the ventral surface of humpback whale flukes, taken annually between April and September from 1978-2009. The documentation of the unique pigmentation patterns of the ventral flukes is a commonly used method to identify and track individual humpback whales over time (Katona et al. 1979). No data were collected in 1982, and data from 1981 was thrown out because effort in this year was relatively small and data collection was compromised by weather complications. Photos were taken using single-lens reflex cameras from 1978-2002 and using digital cameras from 2003-2009. Photo identification records include &gt;5,000 photographic sightings of ~575 individual humpback whale flukes over the time series. Depending on the year, between one and three research teams collected data on separate boats. Research teams however had different specific goals, namely; some specifically targeted humpback whales (von Ziegasar, EOW), while others targeted killer whales (Orcinus orca) and gathered humpback whale data only opportunistically (Matkin and Saulitis, NGOS). The total number of whales sighted, unique identifications, and newly identified individuals are summarized by year.</para>
</section>
</description>
</methodStep>
<methodStep><description><section><title>TeerlinkThesisMethods_DataOrganization</title>
<para>Data describing effort, humpback whale sightings, and individual fluke characteristics in Microsoft Excel files (EOW) were transferred into the Alaska Humpback Whale Database, a Microsoft Access database designed specifically for storage and querying of humpback whale photographic data (Straley 2009, pers. comm.). The database contains tables to hold information pertaining to a given whale at the time of the sighting, unique and long-lasting characteristics of that whale, and information specific to the survey effort. During this entry process, sighting histories were error-checked by verifying Excel entries with actual photos and with hard-copy datasheets. The best photograph of each individual whale each year was identified and, for years where photos were archived as negatives (1987-2002), the photos were digitized by scanning the negatives.</para>
</section>
</description>
</methodStep>
<methodStep><description><section><title>TeerlinkThesisMethods_Effort</title>
<para>Three measures of effort were available from the dataset: nautical miles traveled, hours spent searching, and number of boat-days. For early years, where track lines were recorded by hand on photocopied maps, track lines were manually digitized. In more recent years, many of the surveys had digital track lines from handheld GPS units. For surveys conducted within the defined study area, each measure of effort (nautical miles, hours, and days) was totaled by year, and the different measures were analyzed to determine which was most appropriate for this study (Table 1). Many surveys had no record of the track line taken and/or the number of hours spent searching; years known to have &gt;10% missing effort data are indicated in Table 1.</para>
</section>
</description>
</methodStep>
<methodStep><description><section><title>TeerlinkThesisMethods_CountPerUnitEffort</title>
<para>All recorded sightings of humpback whales - both those whales that were photographed and those that were sighted and noted only - were tallied for each year. An annual index of relative abundance was calculated as the number of sightings divided by the amount of effort. A regression line was fitted to determine if there was a trend over time. Additionally, an index of the number of unique whales identified each year divided by the amount of effort was also constructed. Again, a regression line was fitted to assess any trends over time.</para>
</section>
</description>
</methodStep>
<methodStep><description><section><title>TeerlinkThesisMethods_MarkRecaptureModel</title>
<para>Quality of identification photos was considered for the mark-recapture portion of this analysis, as poor quality photos can cause misidentification of individuals and result in bias in a mark-recapture setting. Typically, in the case of photo identification of humpback whales, it is unlikely to have false positive errors, namely, instances where photos are wrongly designated as re-sightings. However, occurrence of false negative errors, instances where photos are wrongly designated as new sightings when they are actually re-sightings, is increased with the inclusion of poor quality photos (Friday et al. 2000; Friday et al. 2008; Stevick et al. 2001). Efforts were taken to reduce the occurrence of this type of error by removing the photographs determined to be of poor quality. This was done by ranking the quality of the photo with a value of 1 through 3 in six categories. Values from each of the six categories were then summed to generate an overall index of quality for each photo; thus, index values could range from 6-18, with lower values indicating a better quality photo. Criteria used to rank these photos are a modified version of the protocols described by others  (Calambokidis et al. 2008; Friday et al. 2000). We deemed all photos with a total photo quality index greater than or equal to 9 to be poor and removed them from the analysis.</para>
<para>Fluke distinctiveness could also play a role in producing false negative errors that would introduce bias into a mark-recapture analysis (Friday et al. 2000; Friday et al. 2008; Stevick et al. 2001). Flukes bear wildly different patterns and markings, making some individuals more identifiable than others. Thus, it is more likely that a match of an individual with nondescript flukes would be overlooked resulting in a false negative error. To evaluate the importance of fluke distinctiveness in the sighting histories of this dataset, we evaluated all flukes in this analysis by ranking them with four criteria. The ranking system used  is a modified version of that by Friday et al. (2000). Each pair of flukes was assigned a value, 1 through 3, in each category. Values from each of the four categories were then summed to generate an overall index of fluke distinctiveness for each pair of flukes; index values could therefore range from 4-12, with lower values indicating more distinct flukes. This index was then used to measure the importance of fluke distinctiveness in recapture probability (after the photo quality standard was applied) by assessing the relationship, if any, between total number of sightings for each individual and the distinctiveness index of its flukes. Additionally, this index was used as an individual covariate to the probability of capture in mark recapture models as explained in later sections.</para>
<para>The ubiquitous mark-recapture program MARK was used to obtain maximum likelihood parameter estimates (MLEs) and model fits (White and Burnham 1999).  Its structure allows several models to be estimated and compared and permits the addition of covariates and allows for parameters to be added, fixed, and set equal across time periods, groups, and strata. Sightings of all first year calves were removed from the mark-recapture analyses as their probability of capture is complicated by co-occurrence with their mothers.</para>
<para>For this study, we chose two open-population model types: Cormack-Jolly-Seber (CJS) and Pradel. Open-population models were chosen because we were interested in population level changes as a result of recruitment (births or immigration) and loss (death and emigration). The CJS model, a widely used and accepted model for open populations (Lebreton et al. 1992), was chosen because it generates annual estimates of apparent survival (phi), and probability of capture (p), which are then used to derive estimates of annual abundance to form a time series. Because the results from the Pradel model (Pradel 1996) are so similar to the CJS model yet less precise, we limit our reporting on the Pradel model and instead focus our discussion on the CJS model.</para>
<para>The CJS model generates estimates of parameters by allowing each possible sighting history combination to be modeled as a multinomial distribution. The CJS model is a modified version of the traditional open Jolly-Seber model that conditions on the first sighting and, based on the subsequent sighting histories, estimates survival, phi(t), and probability of capture, pt in year t. As a result, the model is less vulnerable to heterogeneity in the capture probabilities of the population than the basic Jolly-Seber model (Lebreton et al. 1992). Estimates of standard error come from the variance-covariance matrix, and the estimates of the lower and upper 95% confidence intervals of the phis and ps are made using the likelihood profile for the MLE (Lebreton et al. 1992).</para>
<para>Various model parameterizations were developed within MARK and compared in order to identify the most parsimonious model. The phi parameters were modeled as dependent on time period, phi(t); or constant, phi(.). The p parameters were modeled with the following scenarios: time-dependent, p(t); constant, p(.); a linear function of effort, p(eff); dependent on fluke distinctiveness through use of an individual covariate, p(FD); and dependent on a combination of both time and fluke distinctiveness, p(t,FD). Models using all possible combinations of the above parameterizations were constructed and compared. For parameters that either failed to converge or converged so close to the boundary that their estimates and/or variance estimates were unrealistic, models were re-run with problematic parameters set equal to the parameter of the next closest time period.</para>
<para>Competing models were evaluated using the Akaike's Information Criterion (AIC) adjusted for small sample sizes, AICc (Burnham and Anderson 2002). The best model was selected using the guidelines offered by Burnham and Anderson (2002): the model with the lowest AICc value is considered "best" and other models are given in terms of the difference, delta AICc with the best model. Any model with delta AICc less than or equal to 2 has "...no credible evidence that the model should be ruled out". Models with delta AICc of 2-4 offer "weak evidence of not being the best model", models with delta AICc of 4-7 offer "definite evidence", delta AICc of 7-10 offer "strong evidence", and delta AICc greater than 10 offer "very strong evidence of not being the best model".</para>
<para>Photos from some early years were not available to be assessed for quality (specifically: 1980, 1983-85, and 1987). Because there is no means of measuring or compensating for this, we anticipated that there would be some level of bias introduced by data from these years. To address this, we conducted a sensitivity analysis to determine the effect of these early years on the remainder of the time series. We did this by re-running the selected CJS model using only data from 1988-2009, years where all photos were assessed for quality. Estimates from this model were then compared to estimates from the complete time series both graphically and by calculating the correlation coefficient for the overlapping portion of both time series.</para>
<para>To assess the impact of emigrating whales on the abundance estimates, another sensitivity analysis was conducted. Survival was fixed equal to 0.98 in the selected CJS model and the model was re-estimated. A survival of 0.98 was selected because this is the rate that was found in the only other assessment of survival of humpback whales in PWS (Mizroch et al. 2004). The results were then compared to those from the base CJS model to assess how a different survival would affect the model outputs.</para>
</section>
</description>
</methodStep>
<methodStep><description><section><title>TeerlinkThesisMethods_ModelComparisons</title>
<para>Results from all four time series models, the two count per effort models and the CJS and Pradel mark-recapture models, were compared in a correlation analysis to evaluate their similarity for this dataset.</para>
<para>The ROI, defined as the average annual population growth rate, was calculated from the abundance estimates for the selected CJS model. Variance estimates for the ROI estimates were found by use of the delta method (Seber 1982), using the empirical standard error (SE) of the annual changes in log abundance as the CV of the ROI. Equation (5) was then used to convert this into the SE of the ROI, and SE was used to generate a 95% CI for ROI (eq. 6). This method is the same as was used by Calambokidis et al. (2008) to generate ROI estimates for the SPLASH study, and was employed to make direct comparisons possible.</para>
</section>
</description>
</methodStep>
</methods>
 <project><title>Historical Humpback Whale Abundance in Prince William Sound in Relation to Pacific Herring Dynamics</title>
<personnel id="1365725016883"><individualName><givenName>Suzanne</givenName>
<surName>Teerlink</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>Juneau Center, School of Fisheries and Ocean Sciences, University of Alaska Fairbanks</organizationName>
<electronicMailAddress>s.teerlink@alaska.edu</electronicMailAddress>
<role>Principal Investigator</role>
</personnel>
<personnel id="1365725031428"><individualName><givenName>Terrance</givenName>
<surName>Quinn</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>University of Alaska Fairbanks, School of Fisheries &amp; Ocean Sciences</organizationName>
<positionName>Full Professor</positionName>
<electronicMailAddress>terry.quinn@alaska.edu</electronicMailAddress>
<role>Principal Investigator</role>
</personnel>
<personnel id="1365725072693"><individualName><givenName>Jan</givenName>
<surName>Straley</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>University of Alaska Southeast</organizationName>
<role>Principal Investigator</role>
</personnel>
<personnel id="1365725091229"><individualName><givenName>Olga</givenName>
<surName>Von Ziegesar</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>Eye of the Whale</organizationName>
<role>Principal Investigator</role>
</personnel>
<funding><para>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council project 10100128; additional funding came from the Cooperative Institute for Arctic Research with funds from the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration under cooperative agreement NA17RJ1224 with the University of Alaska</para>
</funding>
</project>
  <dataTable id="1363121810559" scope="document"> <entityName>abundanceResults.csv</entityName>
 <physical id="1363121679093" scope="document"> <objectName>abundanceResults.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">829</size>
 <dataFormat> <textFormat> <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited> <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution> <online> <url>ecogrid://knb/df35d.123.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList> <attribute id="1363121810560" scope="document"> <attributeName>Year</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Year</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <dateTime> <formatString>YYYY</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1363121810561" scope="document"> <attributeName>Unique IDs</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Whale count (I believe, since there are reps of the IDs)</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <interval> <unit> <standardUnit>mole</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain> <numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </interval>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1363121810562" scope="document"> <attributeName>Abundance Estimate</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Abundance estimate based on model</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <interval> <unit> <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain> <numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </interval>
 </measurementScale>
 <missingValueCode> <code>NA</code>
 <codeExplanation>no data</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1363121810563" scope="document"> <attributeName>Lower Confidence Interval</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>statistics: confidence interval</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <interval> <unit> <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain> <numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </interval>
 </measurementScale>
 <missingValueCode> <code>NA</code>
 <codeExplanation>no data</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1363121810564" scope="document"> <attributeName>Upper Confidence Interval</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>statistics: confidence interval</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <interval> <unit> <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain> <numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </interval>
 </measurementScale>
 <missingValueCode> <code>NA</code>
 <codeExplanation>no data</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>30</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>