<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="df35d.455.4" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 eml.xsd">  <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"><allow><principal>public</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
</allow>
<allow><principal>cn=evos,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
<permission>all</permission>
</allow>
</access>
<dataset>  <title>Site Photographs from the Assessment of Bivalve Recovery on Treated Mixed-Soft Beaches In Prince William Sound, Alaska: 2002</title>
<creator id="1359152118258"><individualName><salutation>Mr.</salutation>
 <givenName>Dennis</givenName>
 <surName>Lees</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Littoral Ecological and Environmental Services</organizationName>
 <positionName>Principal Investigator</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>1075 Urania Ave.</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Leucadia</city>
 <administrativeArea>CA</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>92024</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">760-635-7998</phone>
 <phone phonetype="fax">760-635-7999</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>dennislees@earthlink.net</electronicMailAddress>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1380828018568"><individualName><givenName>William</givenName>
 <surName>Driskell</surName>
 </individualName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>6536 20th Ave. NE</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Seattle</city>
 <administrativeArea>WA</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>98115</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">206-522-5930</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>bdriskell@comcast.net</electronicMailAddress>
 </creator>
 <associatedParty id="1359152217358"><individualName><givenName>William</givenName>
 <surName>Driskell</surName>
 </individualName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>6536 20th Ave. NE</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Seattle</city>
 <administrativeArea>WA</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>98115</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">206-522-5930</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>bdriskell@comcast.net</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty id="1370043036135"><individualName><givenName>Emma</givenName>
 <surName>Freeman</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis</organizationName>
 <positionName>Graduate Student Researcher</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>735 State Street</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>Suite 300</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Santa Barbara</city>
 <administrativeArea>California</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>93101</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">1.805.892.2500</phone>
 <onlineUrl>http://www.nceas.ucsb.edu</onlineUrl>
 <role>Processor</role>
 </associatedParty>
<abstract><para>National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration treatment effects studies from 1989 through 1997 suggested that bivalve assemblages on beaches in Prince William Sound treated with high-pressure washing were severely injured in terms of abundance, species composition, and function. Restoration Project 040574 assessed the generality and persistence of this apparent injury to this assemblage. We found that the initial conclusions were accurate, indicating that a considerable proportion of mixed-soft beaches in treated areas of the sound remained extremely disturbed and that these beaches are functionally impaired in terms of their ability to support foraging by humans and damaged nearshore vertebrate predators such as sea otters 13 years after the spill. Large, long-lived hard-shell clams remained 66% less abundant at Treated sites than at Reference sites. We also found that standard sediment properties did not appear implicated in lagging recovery. But, based on several lines of evidence, we deduced that a major cause for the delay was the disruption of surface armoring (a stratified organization of mixed-soft shoreline sediments common in southcentral Alaska), an effect of beach washing. Based on the apparent recovery trajectory, we predict that recovery to pre-spill status will take several more decades. We also found that sedimentary components and the biota in the armored mixed-soft sediments in Prince William Sound do not respond according to traditionally described paradigms for homogeneous sediments.
Citation: Lees, D. C., and W. B. Driskell.  2007.  Assessment of Bivalve Recovery on Treated Mixed-Soft Beaches in Prince William Sound, Alaska.  Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Restoration Project Final Report (Restoration Project 040574).  National Oceanic &amp; Atmospheric Administration National Marine Fisheries Service, Office of Oil Spill Damage &amp; Restoration, Auke Bay, Alaska.</para>
</abstract>
<keywordSet><keyword>armoring</keyword>
<keyword>sediment condition</keyword>
<keyword>recruitment</keyword>
<keyword>shoreline treatment</keyword>
<keyword>beach washing</keyword>
<keyword>bivalves</keyword>
<keyword>clams</keyword>
<keyword>Prince William Sound</keyword>
<keyword>Hiatella arctica</keyword>
<keyword>Protothaca staminea</keyword>
<keyword>Leukoma staminea</keyword>
<keyword>Saxidomus gigantea</keyword>
<keyword>high-pressure hot water wash</keyword>
<keyword>injury</keyword>
<keyword>recovery</keyword>
</keywordSet>
<keywordSet><keyword>EVOSTC</keyword>
<keyword>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council</keyword>
<keyword>Oil Spill</keyword>
<keyword>Exxon Valdez</keyword>
<keyword>Alaska</keyword>
<keyword>Benthic</keyword>
<keyword>Invertebrates and Algae</keyword>
<keyword>Oil and Contaminants</keyword>
<keyword>Shoreline Habitat and Sensitivity</keyword>
<keyword>Imagery</keyword>
<keywordThesaurus>Gulf Watch Alaska Thesaurus</keywordThesaurus>
</keywordSet>
<intellectualRights><para>This material is based upon work funded by the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council.  Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed herein are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views or positions of the Trustee Council.

Standard scientific norms for attribution and credit should be followed when using these data including to the Owners, Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council and other sources of funding. Please let the Owner know when these data are used.

These data are licensed under CC0. The person who associated a work with this deed has dedicated the work to the public domain by waiving all of his or her rights to the work worldwide under copyright law, including all related and neighboring rights, to the extent allowed by law. You can copy, modify, distribute and perform the work, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</para>
</intellectualRights>
     <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Western Prince William Sound</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-148.047</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>-147.604</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>60.5435</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>60.0653</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2002-08-07</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate><calendarDate>2002-08-14</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
  <taxonomicCoverage><taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Phylum</taxonRankName>
<taxonRankValue>Mollusca</taxonRankValue>
<taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Class</taxonRankName>
<taxonRankValue>Bivalvia</taxonRankValue>
<taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
<taxonRankValue>Hiatella</taxonRankValue>
<taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
<taxonRankValue>arctica</taxonRankValue>
<commonName>Nestling clam</commonName>
</taxonomicClassification>
</taxonomicClassification>
</taxonomicClassification>
</taxonomicClassification>
<taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Phylum</taxonRankName>
<taxonRankValue>Mollusca</taxonRankValue>
<taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Order</taxonRankName>
<taxonRankValue>Bivalvia</taxonRankValue>
<taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
<taxonRankValue>Leukoma</taxonRankValue>
<taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
<taxonRankValue>staminea</taxonRankValue>
<commonName>Littleneck clam</commonName>
</taxonomicClassification>
</taxonomicClassification>
</taxonomicClassification>
</taxonomicClassification>
<taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Phylum</taxonRankName>
<taxonRankValue>Mollusca</taxonRankValue>
<taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Order</taxonRankName>
<taxonRankValue>Bivalvia</taxonRankValue>
<taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
<taxonRankValue>Saxidomus</taxonRankValue>
<taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
<taxonRankValue>gigantea</taxonRankValue>
<commonName>Butter clam</commonName>
</taxonomicClassification>
</taxonomicClassification>
</taxonomicClassification>
</taxonomicClassification>
</taxonomicCoverage>
</coverage>
 <contact><references>1359152118258</references>
 </contact>
<methods><methodStep><description><section><title>Site selection</title>
<para>To optimize the potential for detecting treatment effects, sampling was focused on intertidal mixed-soft sediment beaches in central and southwestern PWS where the greatest quantities of oil from the spill were stranded.  Using the NOAA Shoreline Segment Summary and Alaska Department of Natural Resources GIS databases and historic spill-survey documents from 1989 and 1990, appropriate shoreline segments were selected based on exposure, sediment type, degree of oiling, and recommended treatment history.  A random selection of appropriate shoreline segments was made from this list.  Each of the selected segments was then physically viewed during an aerial reconnaissance to determine where suitable sites with an adequate stretch of beach composed of mixed-soft sediments existed at an appropriate tidal elevation.  Final selections were made randomly from this final list of confirmed workable sites.  Four sites from the previous NOAA program were included to assess the degree of consistency with the NOAA studies.  These included one reference site (Bay of Isles) and three treated sites (Northwest Bay West Arm, Shelter Bay, and Sleepy Bay).</para>
<para>Determining the treatment history for any particular stretch of shoreline was a somewhat difficult and complex task.  In the manner previously reported by Mearns (1996), we used NOAA's Shoreline Segment Summary database to assign substrate type, relative degree of oiling (no-, light-, moderate-, or heavy oiling), types of treatment (e.g., moderate- to high-pressure or warm- or hot-water), number of types of treatment, and number of treatment days on a segment.  Mearns (1996) concluded that, although "...treatment varied greatly among shorelines...treatment effort was generally proportional to the amount of oil present." According to his data for Eleanor and Ingot Islands, 81% of the heavily oiled sites were exposed to warm or hot water and 71% were exposed to both.  In addition, 80% of the moderately oiled sites were exposed to warm or hot water.  Only about 10% of the moderately or heavily oiled segments were not treated or did not have accompanying treatment characterization.  From these data, one can conclude that most heavily or moderately oiled sites were washed with hot or warm water.</para>
<para>However, we are unaware of any available public records that actually record treatment for the particular beaches within a portion of a shoreline segment.  Detailed oiling reports and recommended treatments are recorded in the Shoreline Cleanup Assessment Team (SCAT) reports (available at the Alaska Resource Library and Information Services in Anchorage), which include sketches of the distribution of oil and sediments.  The oiling reports and treatment recommendations in these records formed the predominant basis for our decisions on which beaches to survey.  However, it should be clear that, except for the NOAA Treated sites, where we were able to observe treatment underway in 1989, the treatment history of both Treated and Reference sites is based only on educated conjecture.  It is likely that some of the sites were inadvertently misclassified.</para>
</section>
</description>
</methodStep>
<methodStep><description><section><title>Shoreline Exposure</title>
<para>Because many physical and biological variables can be correlated with the intensity of exposure to wave action, variations in exposure to wave action can be a confounding factor.  One commonly used method for estimating exposure is to measure fetch, i.e., the unobstructed distance across open water that wind or waves travel before encountering a beach at a perpendicular angle.  Accordingly, we estimated fetch for each site by measuring the distance to the nearest landfall in a directly offshore direction using a navigation chart.</para>
<para>Nevertheless, using fetch as a measure of exposure is a very crude and potentially inaccurate approach.  It ignores the importance of the direction from which the dominant wind or waves arrive, the seasonal differences in the potential velocity and frequency of winds from the direction of the fetch, and the mitigating effects of local topography and offshore bathymetry (subtidal reefs, etc.), all of which are poorly known in this region.  Consequently, we devised another approach that integrates a variety of exposure-related physical and biological factors to provide an index of exposure.  Using our site photos and field notes to assess the various criteria, we devised an ordinal evaluation of twelve site conditions that reflect the degree of exposure.  The factors included seven physical characteristics of the beach (shape and weathering of individual rocks, degree of imbrication or armoring of the rock population, presence of silt on coarser sediments or rocks, and the susceptibility of the site to current or wave action), and five biological characteristics (absence or level of development of epibenthic algae, animals, or an amorphous biological turf on the rocks, eelgrass or burrowing organisms in the sediments).  Each feature was scored on a scale of 1 to 5.  We then averaged factor scores for each site to provide an integrated exposure score for each site.  By this method, low exposure scores indicate protected sites whereas high scores indicate exposed sites.  Each site was scored without knowledge of its treatment classification in order to avoid biasing the score.  The exposure scores were then paired with the appropriate environmental or biological variables for each site to evaluate the importance of exposure in any observed patterns.</para>
</section>
</description>
</methodStep>
</methods>
<project><title>Assessment of Bivalve Recovery on Treated Mixed-Soft Beaches in Prince William Sound</title>
<personnel id="1366224269385"><individualName><givenName>Dennis</givenName>
<surName>Lees</surName>
</individualName>
<role>PI</role>
</personnel>
<funding><para>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council project numbers 02574, 030574, 040574, 10100574</para>
</funding>
</project>
      <dataTable id="1362166532457"><entityName>Lees_bivalve_sites.csv</entityName>
 <physical id="1362166180563"><objectName>Lees_bivalve_sites.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">3349</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/df35d.21.2</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1362166532458"><attributeName>Site</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Name of site</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>name of site</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1362166532459"><attributeName>Treatment</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>treated or reference site</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>Reference</code>
 <definition>reference site</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>Treated</code>
 <definition>treated (washed) site</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>NA</code>
 <definition>unknown</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1362166532460"><attributeName>Latitude (degree in decimals)</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>latitude in decimal degrees</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1362166532461"><attributeName>Longitude (degree in decimals)</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>longitude in decimal degrees</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1362166532462"><attributeName>Latitude (degrees)</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>latitude in degrees</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1362166532463"><attributeName>Latitude (seconds)</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>latitude in seconds</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1362166532464"><attributeName>Longitude (degrees)</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>longitude in degrees</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1362166532465"><attributeName>Longitude (seconds)</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>longitude seconds</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
     </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>40</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 <otherEntity><entityName>EVOS bivalve site photos.zip</entityName>
<entityDescription>Zipped folder with JPEGs of site photos.</entityDescription>
<physical><objectName>EVOS bivalve site photos.zip</objectName>
<size unit="byte">468426606</size>
<dataFormat><externallyDefinedFormat><formatName>application/octet-stream</formatName>
</externallyDefinedFormat>
</dataFormat>
<distribution id="1386632671202"><online><url function="download">ecogrid://knb/df35d.456.1</url>
</online>
</distribution>
</physical>
<entityType>Other</entityType>
</otherEntity>
</dataset>
 <additionalMetadata><metadata><unitList><unit id="miligramsPerKilogram" multiplierToSI=" " name="miligramsPerKilogram" parentSI="gramsPerGram" unitType="massPerMass"><description>miligramsPerKilogram</description>
 </unit>
 </unitList>
 </metadata>
 </additionalMetadata>
 </ns0:eml>