<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="df35b.80.10" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"><allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow><principal>cn=evos,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 <permission>write</permission>
 <permission>changePermission</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset>  <title>Pacific Herring (Clupea pallasi) sample data from Sitka Sound, Alaska (2007-2008)</title>
<creator id="1375137848905"><individualName><givenName>Heather</givenName>
 <surName>Meuret-Woody</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Spruce Islands Research and Development</organizationName>
 <positionName>Research Biologist</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>5 Maksoutoff Street</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Sitka</city>
 <administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>99835</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <electronicMailAddress>bwoodyham@gmail.com</electronicMailAddress>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1375138080198"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation>
 <givenName>Nate</givenName>
 <surName>Bickford</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Univeristy of Great Falls</organizationName>
 <positionName>Associate Professor of Biology</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>1301 20th Street South</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Great Falls</city>
 <administrativeArea>MT</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>59405</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">(406) 791-5950</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>nbickford01@ugf.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <onlineUrl>http://ugf.frogcms6.com/Academics/Faculty/FullTimeFaculty/NateBickford/tabid/849/Default.aspx</onlineUrl>
 </creator>
 <associatedParty><references>1375137848905</references>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty><references>1375138080198</references>
 <role>Author</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty id="1375138328370"><individualName><givenName>Jessica</givenName>
 <surName>Couture</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis</organizationName>
 <positionName>Research Assistant</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis, Unversity of California, Santa Barbara</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>735 State St.</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Santa Barbara</city>
 <administrativeArea>CA</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>93101</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">805-892-2500</phone>
 <phone phonetype="fax">805-892-2510</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>couture@nceas.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Metadata Provider</role>
 </associatedParty>
<abstract><para>The primary objective of this project was to obtain information leading to better identification of essential fish habitat in Prince William Sound. The data here are include information on herring samples pulled from Sitka Sound in Alaska for otolith analysis as well as site locations. By using trace element signatures of edge portions of juvenile herring otoliths, we identified the otolith chemical signature of individual rearing bays within Sitka Sound. We used trace element signatures of edge portions of adult herring otoliths to identify the otolith chemical signature of spawning areas within Sitka Sound. We also used trace element signatures of edge portions to compare to core portions of juvenile and adult herring to identify source and sink habitat in Sitka Sound. The results of the technique used in this project indicate that herring use different and distinct habitats in Sitka Sound during their life. Once we know which population contributes more to the spawning groups, we can then identify those variables that enhance the life histories of the source population. This will allow managers to protect the most important populations and also identify which variables can be altered to improve habitat f or other populations. These techniques used in Sitka Sound can be directly transferred to Prince William Sound, leading to better identification of essential fish habitat in Prince William Sound.

***Data here include herring sample collections. For otolith chemical data see project df35b.81.8 at http://evos.nceas.ucsb.edu/#view/df35b.81.8.</para>
</abstract>
  <keywordSet><keyword>adult herring</keyword>
 <keyword>Clupea pallasi</keyword>
 <keyword>essential habitat</keyword>
 <keyword>juvenile herring</keyword>
 <keyword>Pacific herring</keyword>
 <keyword>restoration</keyword>
 <keyword>Sitka Sound</keyword>
 <keyword>pelagic</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>Project</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet><keyword>EVOSTC</keyword>
 <keyword>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council</keyword>
 <keyword>Oil Spill</keyword>
 <keyword>Exxon Valdez</keyword>
 <keyword>Alaska</keyword>
 <keyword>Environmental Drivers</keyword>
 <keyword>Pelagic</keyword>
 <keyword>Fish</keyword>
 <keyword>Shoreline Habitat and Sensitivity</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>Gulf Watch Alaska Thesaurus</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <intellectualRights><para>This material is based upon work funded by the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council.  Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed herein are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views or positions of the Trustee Council.

Standard scientific norms for attribution and credit should be followed when using these data including to the Owners, Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council and other sources of funding. Please let the Owner know when these data are used.
 
These data are licensed under CC0. The person who associated a work with this deed has dedicated the work to the public domain by waiving all of his or her rights to the work worldwide under copyright law, including all related and neighboring rights, to the extent allowed by law. You can copy, modify, distribute and perform the work, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</para>
 </intellectualRights>
 <coverage><temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2007</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate><calendarDate>2008</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 <taxonomicCoverage><taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Clupea</taxonRankValue>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>pallasi</taxonRankValue>
 <commonName>Pacific Herring</commonName>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact><references>1375137848905</references>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><title>Herring Collection</title>
 <para>Water temperature and salinity were sampled at 1-meter at each collection site using an YSI 85 hand-held meter. A Garmin eTrex Legend hand-held GPS unit was used to record coordinates of collection locations. The coordinates were entered into maps created in ArcMap GIS 9.2. A random sample of 25 winter herring was collected during the 2007 winter bait fishery. During the spawning event in March and April 2007, random samples of adult herring were collected during the spring from 9 different collection sites. A total of 374 adult herring were collected in 2007 (Figure 1). The herring were sampled for weight, length, sex, maturity, and otoliths were excised. The fish were lightly rinsed and wiped down. Each fish was weighed to the nearest 0.01g using an Ohaus Scout Pro digital scale. Each fish was measured from snout to hypural plate to the nearest 0.01 mm using Tesa IP65 waterproof digital calipers. Sex was determined by a visual inspection and will be classified as mature, spent, or immature. Sagittal otoliths were extracted from the herring in a clean environment using standard techniques (Bickford et al., 2003; Campana, 1999; Campana, et al., 1995). The otoliths were then rinsed and cleaned with distilled water, and placed in micro centrifuge tubes. Each tube was labeled with the fish identification number, date and collection site information. All adult herring otolith pairs were sent to Dr. Nate Bickford and then processed at the University of Massachusetts for trace metal analysis.</para>
 <para>Random samples of juvenile herring were collected during winter 2007 from five near shore nurseries. A total of 407 juvenile herring were collected in 2007 (Figure 1). All juvenile fish were lightly rinsed. Each individual juvenile fish was then wiped off using paper towels. The fish were identified as 1-50 according to date and sample site. Each juvenile fish was weighed to the</para>
 <para>nearest 0.01 g using an Ohaus Scout Pro digital scale. Each juvenile fish was measured from snout to hypural plate to the nearest 0.01 mm using Tesa IP65 waterproof digital calipers. Because these were immature fish, they were not sexed. Sagittal otoliths were extracted from the herring in a clean environment using standard techniques (Bickford et al., 2003; Campana, 1999; Campana et al., 1995). The otoliths were then rinsed and cleaned with distilled water, and placed in micro centrifuge tubes. Each tube was labeled with the fish identification number, date, and collection site information. All juvenile herring otolith pairs were sent to Dr. Nate Bickford and then processed at the University of Massachusetts for trace metal analysis.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 <instrumentation>YSI 85 hand-held meter</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>Garmin eTrex Legend hand-held GPS unit</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>Ohaus Scout Pro digital scale</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>Tesa IP65 waterproof digital calipers</instrumentation>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Otolith Chemical Analysis</title>
 <para>Sagittal otoliths were thin sectioned using a Beuhler isomet low speed saw. This exposed the otolith core and edge for chemical analysis and aging (Campana, 1999). The sagittal otoliths were analyzed for concentrations of trace metals using a laser ablation (LA; New Wave UP 213nm Nd:YAG) Perkin Elmer inductively coupled plasma - mass spectrometer (ICP-MS) located at the University of Massachusetts. These analyses were performed on thin sections of otoliths on a transect extending from the core across to the otolith margin. All analyses were calibrated using the external matrix-matched standard USGS MACS-1 (carbonate standard).</para>
 <para>Each sample measurement was preceded by a gas blank measurement with re-calibration (gas blank and MACS-1) every 10 samples. The concentration of all elements was calculated relative to MACS-1 after proper correction for the gas blank, matrix, and drift effects. Elemental abundances were compared to relative Calcium content among otolith samples (Campana, 1999; Campana &amp; Neilson, 1985).</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 <instrumentation>Perkin Elmer inductively coupled plasma-mass spectrometer (ICP-MS)</instrumentation>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Statistical Analysis</title>
 <para>Statistical analysis included analysis of variance (ANOVA  = 0.05) to distinguish differences in the otolith chemical signature (Mg/Ca, Mn/Ca, Sr/Ca, Sr86/Sr87, and Ba/Ca):</para>
 <para>- Juvenile edge (nursery) vs. juvenile core (natal): if the signature is the same, then the fish has not left spawning grounds.</para>
 <para>- Juvenile core (natal) vs. juvenile core (natal): if the signature is the same, then the fish were spawned in the same area.</para>
 <para>- Juvenile edge (nursery) vs. adult area just outside the core (nursery): if the signature is the same, then the adult used the same nursery habitat as the juvenile.</para>
 <para>- Adult edge (spawning area) vs. adult core (natal): if the signature is the same, then the adult returned to spawn in the same area in which it hatched.</para>
 <para>- Adult core (natal) vs. adult core (natal): if the signature is the same, then the adults were hatched in the same area.</para>
 <para>Linear discriminant analysis (LDA) explicitly attempts to model the difference between classes of data. The LDA results geographically distinguished the distinct groups of herring and allowed us to classify the individuals into groups (i.e., natal group, nursery group).</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
<project><title>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Restoration Project Final Report Identifying Essential Habitat (Source vs. Sink Habi tat) for Pacific Herring (Clupea pallasi) in Sitka Sound Using Otolith Microchemistry</title>
<personnel id="1375295735553"><individualName><givenName>Heather</givenName>
<surName>Meuret-Woody</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>Sitka Tribe of Alaska</organizationName>
<positionName>Research Biologist</positionName>
<address><deliveryPoint>456 Katlian Street</deliveryPoint>
<city>Sitka</city>
<administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>99835</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
<electronicMailAddress>bwoodyham@gmail.com</electronicMailAddress>
<role>Principal Investigator</role>
</personnel>
<funding><para>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council project numbers 080834, 070834; Sitka Tribe of Alaska</para>
</funding>
</project>
  <dataTable id="1375207374892"><entityName>herrCollData.csv</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Herring collection data, Sitka Sound, Alaska, 2007</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1375205938167"><objectName>herrCollData.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">102416</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/df35b.78.3</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1375207374893"><attributeName>date</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Date</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Date sample was collected</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>YYYY-MM-DD</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375207374894"><attributeName>zone</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Zone</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>General zone where sample was collected (see attached pdf).</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>zones</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375207374895"><attributeName>site</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Site</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Specific site of sample collection (see attached pfd)</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>site</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375207374896"><attributeName>lat</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Latitude</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Latitude in degrees and minutes.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </interval>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375207374897"><attributeName>lon</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Longitude</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Longitude in degrees and minutes.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </interval>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375207374898"><attributeName>samplingGrp</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Sampling Group</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Origin of samples. Samples collected directly for this study will be labeled NA.  Fishing vessels (F/V) were used to collect seaweed and gut contents sampling.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>sampling origin</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 <missingValueCode><code>NA</code>
 <codeExplanation>Samples collected for this study</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375207374899"><attributeName>timeDay</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Time of Day</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Approximate time of day varies in specificity from morning/afternoon to general time.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>time of day</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375207374900"><attributeName>temp</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Temperature</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Temperature collected 1 meter below the surface. Recorded in degrees Celsius.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </interval>
 </measurementScale>
 <missingValueCode><code>NA</code>
 <codeExplanation>data not collected or not recorded</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375207374901"><attributeName>sal</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Salinity</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Salinity collected 1 meter below the sureface of the water.  Recorded in partsPerThousand (ppt).</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>gramsPerKilogram</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <precision>0.1</precision>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375207374902"><attributeName>ageGrp</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Stage</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Age Group or stage at collection.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>juvUnderSix</code>
 <definition>Juvinile, under six inches</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>adult</code>
 <definition>Adult</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>juv</code>
 <definition>Juvenile</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>preSpawnAdult</code>
 <definition>Pre-spawning Adult</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>schoolAdult</code>
 <definition>Schooling Adult</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>spawnAdult</code>
 <definition>Spawuning Adult</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>Troll King gut samples</code>
 <definition>Gut samples from Troll King</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375207566196"><attributeName>sampleID</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>sample Identifier</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Numeric identifiers are specific to the sampling group/effort.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </interval>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375207374903"><attributeName>length</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Length</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Length of herring recorded in millimeters (mm).</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>millimeter</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375207374904"><attributeName>weight</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Weight</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Weight of herring, recorded in grams(g).</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375207374905"><attributeName>sex</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Sex</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sex of herring</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>F</code>
 <definition>Female</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>M</code>
 <definition>Male</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>NA</code>
 <definition>unknown</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>unknown</code>
 <definition>unknown</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 <missingValueCode><code>NA</code>
 <codeExplanation>unknown</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 <missingValueCode><code>unknown</code>
 <codeExplanation>unknown</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375207374906"><attributeName>comments</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Comments</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Comments/notes</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>comments</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>801</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 <otherEntity><entityName>Herring Collection Sites (pdf)</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Sites and Zones where Clupea pallasi were collected for analysis</entityDescription>
 <physical><objectName>herrSitesHMW.pdf</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">95995</size>
 <dataFormat><externallyDefinedFormat><formatName>application/pdf</formatName>
 </externallyDefinedFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/df35b.82.2</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <entityType>Other</entityType>
 </otherEntity>
 <otherEntity><entityName>Herring Collection Sites (GIS)</entityName>
 <entityDescription>GIS files of herring collection sties.</entityDescription>
 <physical><objectName>herringMapFinal.zip</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">60113</size>
 <dataFormat><externallyDefinedFormat><formatName>application/octet-stream</formatName>
 </externallyDefinedFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/df35b.85.3</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <entityType>Other</entityType>
 </otherEntity>
 </dataset>
 <additionalMetadata><metadata><unitList><unit id="gramsPerKilogram" multiplierToSI="0.001" name="gramsPerKilogram" parentSI="gramsPerGram" unitType="massPerMass"><description>gramsPerKilogram</description>
 </unit>
 </unitList>
 </metadata>
 </additionalMetadata>
 </ns0:eml>