<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="df35d.441.2" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 eml.xsd">  <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"><allow><principal>public</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
</allow>
<allow><principal>cn=evos,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
<permission>all</permission>
</allow>
</access>
<dataset>  <title>Physical oceanographic characteristics of sites in Orca Inlet, Cordova, Alaska: 2004-2005</title>
<creator id="1385512012945"> <individualName><givenName>Richard</givenName>
 <surName>Crawford</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Prince William Sound Science Center</organizationName>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1385512077585"><individualName><givenName>Gary</givenName>
 <surName>Thomas</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>University of Miami, Rosenstiel School of Marine &amp; Atmospheric Science</organizationName>
 <positionName>Professor</positionName>
 <address><city>Miami</city>
 <administrativeArea>Florida</administrativeArea>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">305.421.4733</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>gthomas@rsmas.miami.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1385512145174"><individualName><givenName>Shelton</givenName>
 <surName>Gay</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Texas A&amp;M University, Department of Biology</organizationName>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1385512173843"><individualName><givenName>Kenwyn</givenName>
 <surName>George</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Alaska Department of Environmental Conservation</organizationName>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1385511728611"><individualName><givenName>Richard</givenName>
 <surName>Thorne</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Prince William Sound Science Center</organizationName>
 <positionName>Senior Scientist &amp; Director, Acoustics Research Program</positionName>
 <address><city>Cordova</city>
 <administrativeArea>Alaska</administrativeArea>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">907-424-5800 x 226</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>rthorne@pwssc.org</electronicMailAddress>
 <onlineUrl>http://pwssc.org</onlineUrl>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1385511820223"><individualName><givenName>Mary Anne</givenName>
 <surName>Bishop</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Prince William Sound Science Center</organizationName>
 <positionName>Research Ecologist</positionName>
 <address><city>Cordova</city>
 <administrativeArea>Alaska</administrativeArea>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">907-424-5800, x 228</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>mbishop@pwssc.org</electronicMailAddress>
 <onlineUrl>http://pwssc.org</onlineUrl>
 </creator>
<abstract><para>In 1975 EPA produced effluent discharge guidelines for the seafood processor industry that required wastes to be ground to less than 1.27 cm prior to discharge. Subsequently, several negative impacts were observed around Cordova, including noticeable decreases in crab and halibut harvests and a substantial increase in numbers of gulls. We hypothesized that the change removed a food source for the large bottom-oriented animals and increased availability to the surface-oriented gulls. In 2004, we began a three year study to examine impacts of seafood waste discharge into Orca Inlet, including evaluation of alternative discharge and disposal methods. The study included model development and control-treatment experiments. We developed a dispersal model that incorporated both physical and biological transport mechanisms and demonstrated improvements over current practices. We dumped over 325,000 lbs of salmon heads and carcasses at an experimental site and monitored the biotic response. Methodologies included underwater cameras, traps, acoustic tags attached to salmon heads and visual surveys of birds and marine mammals. The results show that the heads and carcasses disperse rapidly and are efficiently incorporated into the food chain with no negative consequences, a very favorable contrast to the current EPA-mandated practice. The model also revealed that the historic practice of dumping fish carcasses was a far more effective recycling mechanism. In fact fish production may have been substantially reduced with the change in disposal practices since natural recycling is hindered by the discharge of ground waste. We conclude that it is overdue for some rethinking of fish waste practices. The policy of grinding fish waste to the same 1/2" grind size that was historically used for sewage wastes in the 1970's needs to change. We need to better understand natural recycling with regard to disposal practices. Fish processing waste is potentially a healthy source of food for marine fauna. In locations like Orca Inlet ground discharge of fish waste is not only deleterious but may also substantially reduce fish production by hindering natural recycling.

During the summer of 2004 and the spring of 2005 physical oceanographic conditions were measured in three regions of Orca Inlet, near Cordova Alaska, investigated as potential locations for the alternative disposal of fish offal from Cordova&#8217;s seafood processors. Two of the regions were surveyed in July and September 2004, including a northern site next to Salmo Point and North Island and a southern site within lower Orca Inlet adjacent to Cordova. A third region was surveyed in May 2005 along a channel that connects the southeastern and northeastern portions of the inlet. The data included profiles of currents, temperature and salinity taken over semi-diurnal tidal cycles. All three sites differ significantly in both hydrography and circulation due to a number of factors including variation in bottom depths, basin geometry, sources of freshwater input, and the strength and pattern of the tidal currents. The northern site is characterized by both high stratification from freshwater originating from glacial runoff into the Rude River and deep inflow of cold, saline water advected from Orca Bay. This region therefore becomes highly stratified in the summer and baroclinic currents occur over depth throughout the tidal cycle. The currents also exhibit significant spatial variation ranging from &lt; 5 to 50 cm/sec due to convergences and divergences caused by both estuarine input and bathymetric effects. In contrast, lower Orca Inlet is characterized by strong, barotrophic flows (&gt;100 cm/sec), and all inputs of heat and freshwater (including glacial sources advected from the north) are rapidly dissipated due to turbulent mixing. The northeastern channel also exhibits barotrophic flows similar in magnitude to lower Orca Inlet, but in contrast to the latter site vertical mixing produces fronts extending to depth as stratified water from Nelson Bay is advected across a shallow region and undergoes tidal mixing. All three locations would potentially serve as fish offal discharge sites if maximum dispersion is the goal. The northern site, however, may achieve better results due to its deep (80m) basin and the baroclinic nature of the currents. The higher population of ground fish in this region would also benefit more from disposal of offal at this site.

Publications:
Thorne, R.E., M.A. Bishop, R.E. Crawford, G.L. Thomas, S.M Gay III and K. George 2008. Impacts of seafood waste discharge in Orca Inlet, Prince William Sound. Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Gulf Ecosystem Monitoring and Research Project Final Report, (GEM Project 040725), Prince William Sound Science Center, Cordova, Alaska.</para>
</abstract>
  <keywordSet><keyword>EVOSTC</keyword>
 <keyword>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council</keyword>
 <keyword>Oil Spill</keyword>
 <keyword>Exxon Valdez</keyword>
 <keyword>Alaska</keyword>
 <keyword>Environmental Drivers</keyword>
 <keyword>Satellites and Sensors</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>Gulf Watch Alaska Thesaurus</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet><keyword>Orca Inlet</keyword>
 <keyword>CTD</keyword>
 <keyword>ADCP</keyword>
 <keyword>current</keyword>
 <keyword>hydrography</keyword>
 <keyword>seafood waste</keyword>
 <keyword>offal</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <intellectualRights><para>This material is based upon work funded by the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council. Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed herein are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views or positions of the Trustee Council. Standard scientific norms for attribution and credit should be followed when using these data including to the Owners, Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council and other sources of funding. Please let the Owner know when these data are used. These data are licensed under CC0. The person who associated a work with this deed has dedicated the work to the public domain by waiving all of his or her rights to the work worldwide under copyright law, including all related and neighboring rights, to the extent allowed by law. You can copy, modify, distribute and perform the work, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</para>
 </intellectualRights>
 <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Orca Inlet, Cordova, Alaska</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-146.375</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>-144.875</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>60.875</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>60.0</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2004</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate><calendarDate>2005</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact><references>1385511728611</references>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><title>Methods from Final Report</title>
 <para>The data on currents were collected with an RD Instruments 600 kHz acoustic Doppler current profiler (ADCP), towed with an aluminum Biosonics sled suspended from a davit on a small fishing vessel. Towing speeds ranged from 2.0 to 2.5 m s-1 and with 20 water pings and 10 bottom pings per ensemble, the estimated standard deviation and horizontal resolution for current vectors was 1.37 cm s-1 and 25 m respectively. Vertical (depth bin) resolution was 1m, which is four times the minimum stated bin size of the instrument (0.25 m bin depths). Transects were repeated at least 9 times during semi-diurnal tides giving a Nyquist frequency of ~0.333 cph (i.e. 1/(2&#8710;t) = 1/(2*1.5 hr)).Transects in the northern and lower portions of Orca Inlet were designed with an alternating cross-channel pattern covering lengths of ~1.0 km with an along-channel spacing of 0.5-0.6km. This resulted in a total distance of nearly 10 km and an area of coverage ranging from 2.7 to 1.9 km2 within Sites A and B respectively. Site C also had a total transect length of nearly 10 km, but the pattern differed from the other sites in that transects were set up in a diagonal ('zig-zag') pattern following along, a narrow channel. The total channel length at Site C was 5.1 km and the average cross-channel width was 0.65 km, giving this site an area of coverage of about 3.3 km2.</para>
 <para>The hydrography was measured using a Seabird Elecronics (SBE) 19.03 CTD profiler. This instrument has a maximum sample frequency of 2 Hz, which yields a resolution of 3-4 points per meter depending on the rate of descent. The number and spacing of stations is shown in figures in the text. This differed at each site depending in part on the expected variability in T/S properties due to differences in freshwater input, stratification and convergence of water masses with differing physical properties. Site B was the first location surveyed and therefore a large number of cross-channel stations were established (14-15) with a spacing of about 0.3 km. This resulted in over-sampling. However, this was deemed necessary to obtain a good initial measure of spatial variability in the T/S properties to be used as a basis for sampling in the other sites.</para>
 <para>The hydrography data were processed with standard SBE algorithms for filtering data, removing spurious values, aligning sensors in time to remove salinity spikes, and averaging to 1m depth bins. The ADCP data were processed by first averaging the raw data into segments comprised of 2 ensembles (i.e. ~40 water pings) and checking for bad data based on percent good returns, error velocities and other diagnostic parameters. Further data processing involved merging Global Positioning System (GPS) data into midpoints for segments, filling in missing GPS coordinates by interpolation, removing spurious values (i.e. high &#8710;U/&#8710;x) and bin averaging. During runs with CTD casts, multiple current vectors were obtained over short distances due to vessel drift. These were smoothed by averaging u and v components to obtain single vectors. This procedure produced a final average vector spatial resolution of ~50 m.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 <project><title>Impacts of Seafood Waste Discharge in Orca Inlet, PWS</title>
 <personnel><references>1385511728611</references>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </personnel>
 <funding><para>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council project number 040725</para>
 </funding>
 </project>
 <otherEntity><entityName>Thorne - 040725 - Orca Inlet.zip</entityName>
 <entityDescription>ADCP and CTD data files, metadata file and final report in zipped folder. Data appears to be in original format but most can be viewed in a text editor.</entityDescription>
 <physical><objectName>Thorne - 040725 - Orca Inlet.zip</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">48282085</size>
 <dataFormat><externallyDefinedFormat><formatName>application/octet-stream</formatName>
 </externallyDefinedFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution id="1385512764521"><online><url function="download">ecogrid://knb/df35d.440.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <entityType>Other</entityType>
 </otherEntity>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>