<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="df35b.140.6" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 eml.xsd">  <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"><allow><principal>public</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
</allow>
<allow><principal>cn=evos,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
<permission>write</permission>
<permission>changePermission</permission>
</allow>
</access>
<dataset> <title>Injury Assessment to Herring around Kodiak Island and Alaska Peninsula - AWL data (1970-1990)</title>
<creator id="1379527689179"><individualName><givenName>Kevin</givenName>
<surName>Brennan</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>Division of Commercial Fisheries, Alaska Department of Fish &amp; Game</organizationName>
<positionName>Fisheries Biologist</positionName>
<address><city>Kodiak</city>
<administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
</creator>
<associatedParty><references>1379527689179</references>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </associatedParty>
<associatedParty><references>1379528527346</references>
 <role>Custodian/Steward</role>
 </associatedParty>
<associatedParty id="1379528792958"><individualName><givenName>Jessica</givenName>
 <surName>Couture</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis</organizationName>
 <positionName>Research Assistant</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis, Unversity of California, Santa Barbara</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>735 State St.</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Santa Barbara</city>
 <administrativeArea>CA</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>93101</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">805-892-2500</phone>
 <phone phonetype="fax">805-892-2510</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>couture@nceas.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Metadata Provider</role>
 </associatedParty>
     <abstract><para>The occurrence and biomass of Pacific herring (Clupea pallasi) spawning stocks around Kodiak Island and the Alaska Peninsula in 1989 were documented by aerial surveys (not recorded here). The surveys were less than thorough because they began after spawning had started, and because of hazardous flying conditions and limited availability of charter aircraft. Therefore Age-Weight-Length-Sex data from test and commecial catches were used for analysis and are reported here.

Biomass estimates used by the Kodiak Area Management staff for setting "Guideline Harvest Levels" are the best estimates ofthe size ofthe Kodiak and Alaska Peninsula herring populations. The estimated spawning biomass in 1989 was approximately 9,550 tons. Maps of historical population aggregation areas and spawning areas were compiled to identify areas of potential oil spill impact. No direct herring mortality was observed in 1989, and an influx of juvenile herring (ages 1 and 2) was noted in many bays ofthe Kodiak area Comprehensive damage assessment studies of oil impacts on herring fecundity, on egg deposition, and on egg and larvae survival and development were conducted in Prince William Sound, and the results from those studies were planned to be used to extrapolate probable damage on Kodiak Alaska Peninsula stocks. Historical data on herring length at age, from age-weight-length-sex (AWL) samples taken during herring sac roe fisheries, 1981-1990, are being compiled and analyzed to test for year, area, and possible oil spill effects on herring growth.

Herring from the commercial catch and test fishing are sampled for sex, size and age annually by field crews in coastal waters of the state from Ketchikan to Kotzebue to form a data base essential to the management of the state's herring resources. This information is drawn upon by management and research biologists for monitoring and regulating harvest levels, determining run timing, entry patterns and distribution of herring arriving on the spawning grounds, monitoring sexual maturity and age composition of herring spawning populations, developing
methods to forecast herring abundance and determine optimum spawning goals, and to gain a better understanding of the biology of each stock. The usefulness of this AWL data depends on the manner and accuracy in which the samples were taken.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>Exxon Valdez</keyword>
 <keyword>oil spill</keyword>
 <keyword>Alaska</keyword>
 <keyword>EVOSTC</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>EVOSTC</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet><keyword>age</keyword>
 <keyword>alaska peninsula</keyword>
 <keyword>Clupea pallasi</keyword>
 <keyword>kodiak island</keyword>
 <keyword>pacific herring</keyword>
 <keyword>spawning stocks</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>FS12</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <intellectualRights><para>This material is based upon work funded by the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council.  Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed herein are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views or positions of the Trustee Council.

Standard scientific norms for attribution and credit should be followed when using these data including to the Owners, Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council and other sources of funding. Please let the Owner know when these data are used.
 
These data are licensed under CC0. The person who associated a work with this deed has dedicated the work to the public domain by waiving all of his or her rights to the work worldwide under copyright law, including all related and neighboring rights, to the extent allowed by law. You can copy, modify, distribute and perform the work, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</para>
 </intellectualRights>
 <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Gulf of Alaska, Alaksa</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-159.8752</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>-121.65</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>61.77312</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>43.83333</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1976-04-05</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate><calendarDate>1990-08-15</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 <taxonomicCoverage><taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Clupea</taxonRankValue>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>pallasi</taxonRankValue>
 <commonName>pacific herring</commonName>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicCoverage>
 </coverage>
<contact id="1379528527346"><individualName><givenName>Nicholas</givenName>
<surName>Sagalkin</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>Division of Commercial Fisheries, Alaska Department of Fish &amp; Game</organizationName>
<positionName>Fisheries Biologist</positionName>
<address><deliveryPoint>351 Research Court</deliveryPoint>
<city>Kodiak</city>
<administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>99615</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
<phone phonetype="voice">(907)486-1873</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>nick.sagalkin@alaska.gov</electronicMailAddress>
</contact>
   <methods><methodStep><description><section><title>General Project Methods and Data Sources</title>
 <para>With the inception of State/Federal Natural Resource Damage Assessment Plans, an Alaska Department ofFish and Game (ADF&amp;G) fishery biologist was assigned to conduct fixed wing aerial surveys. The survey area comprised all ofthe Kodiak and Alaska Peninsula Pacific herring management areas. Special emphasis was placed on those locations where herring spawn had been reported or stocks were reaching sexual maturity, as indicated by ADF&amp;G field personnel, commercial fishermen or spotters. Survey data was collected in field "Rite-in-the-Rain" notebooks, or on aerial survey forms. The location, number, relative size (small, medium, large), and an estimate oftotal biomass observed was noted for all schools of herring and forage fish. Location, duration, and size ofspawn were recorded. Similar information was collected by ADF&amp;G herring field crews. Additionally, observations from fishermen, spotters, or oil assessment crews were evaluated and included where possible.</para>
 <para>Impact of oil to all areas was evaluated using the same criteria developed for observational studies in Prince William Sound. Studies in Prince William Sound seek to determine the effect ofthe oil impacts on adult herring growth and fecundity, egg deposition, and egg and larvae survival and development through field and laboratory studies. Quantifiable damage assessment from the Prince William Sound studies was to be directly applied to the spawning stocks in similarly impacted areas ofthe Kodiak/Alaska Peninsula area.</para>
 <para>The ADF&amp;G has collected age-weight-length (AWL) and sex data from samples of Kodiak/Alaska Peninsula stocks during the sac-roe fishery since 1979. Between 4,000-9,000 fish were sampled each year. Detailed methodology for collecting AWL samples is described here as well.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Westward Region Procedures of Collecting Data from Test and Commercial Fishing Catches</title>
 <para>Herring from the commercial catch and test fishing are sampled for sex, size and age annually by field crews in coastal waters ofthe state from Ketchikan to Kotzebue to form a data base essential to the management ofthe state's herring resources. This information is drawn upon by management and research biologists for monitoring and regulating harvest levels, determining run timing, entry patterns and distribution ofherring arriving on the spawning grounds, monitoring sexual maturity and age composition ofherring spawning populations, developing methods to forecast herring abundance and determine optimum spawning goals, and to gain a better understanding ofthe biology of each stock. The usefulness of this AWL data depends on the-manner and accuracy-in which the samples were taken.</para>
 <para>LENGTH: Standard length must be measured for every herring sampled unless the specimen has been too badly mangled. Place each herring on the measuring board so that its anterior extremity is against the stop at the 0 mm line of the ruler (make sure the herring's mouth is closed). Locate the area where the audal (tail) fm rays meet the hypural plate by sharply bending the tail and noting the location ofthe crease. Record the measurement (to the nearest mm) from the anterior most extremity ofthe herring (the tip ofthe lower jaw) to the middle of the crease formed when the tail is bent.</para>
 <para>SEX: Sex must be determined for every herring sampled, and appropriate column 1-4 marked under the SEX heading. If herring are not ripe and running eggs or milt, they must be dissected to visually inspect the gonads. Ifherring are immature (virgin), it is not possible to determine the sex without use of a microscope. Simply record these specimens as juveniles on the A-W-L. If specimens cannot be sexed for some other reason (i.e. specimen badly mutilated, etc.) record as unknown on the A-W-L form.</para>
 <para>SCALE SAMPLING: Only one readable scale will be taken from each herring with a maximum of 10 scales placed on each slide. Remove each scale from one ofthe preferred body areas on the left side ofthe fish (right side used as alternate site if necessary) using forceps. Body area locations are numbered in order of preference. If stock separation is intended find a scale form the blackened area only and mark P in the margin next to that fish. You will be instructed if this is necessary.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 <instrumentation>Plain glass microscope slides (25 x 75 x 1mm)</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>Forceps</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>Scissors</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>Scalpel</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>Lead pencils (number 1 or 2)</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>Small beakers (at least two)</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>Wide mouth sample jars containing Gilsons Fluid (fecundity samples)</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>Ziplock plastic bags</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>Measuring board (calibrated in mm)</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>Dial-a-Gram or Lume-O-Gram scale</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>Small vials with caps (otolith sampling)</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>Labels</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>Paper towels</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>Mucilage glue</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>Water</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>Ethanol or glycerol (otolith sampling)</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>A-W-L Mark Sense data forms</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>Formalin</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>Eyedropper (otolith sampling)</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>Stick-on white labels 5/8 inches by 7/8 inches</instrumentation>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 <project><title>Hydrocarbon Injury Assessment Kodiak and Alaska Peninsula Herring</title>
 <personnel><references>1379527689179</references>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </personnel>
 <funding><para>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council project number FS12</para>
 </funding>
 </project>
 <dataTable id="1379537381392"><entityName>kodiakHerringSamples.csv</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Herring samples from the Kodiak Area (1976-1990)</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1379534673255"><objectName>kodiakHerringSamples.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">21949509</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/df35b.143.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1379537381393"><attributeName>sampleID</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Sample Identifier</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>unique number for each sample</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>sample ID</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379537381394"><attributeName>sampleNum</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Sample Number</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sample Number</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Sample Number</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379537381395"><attributeName>mgmtArea</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Management area</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Commercial management area (as defined in regulation).</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>Kodiak</code>
 <definition>Kodiak Management Area</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>SouthPen</code>
 <definition>South Peninsula Management Area, Area M</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>Aleutian</code>
 <definition>Aleutian Islands Management Area</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 <missingValueCode><code>NA</code>
 <codeExplanation>Missing data</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379537381396"><attributeName>district</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>District</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>The district within the management area where the sample was obtained.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>district</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379537381397"><attributeName>subDistrict</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Sub-district</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Smaller spatial unit defined in regulation where sample was obtained</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>sub-district</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379537381398"><attributeName>location</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Location</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Further description on location of sample if available, often similar to sub-district.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>location</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379537381399"><attributeName>date</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Date</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Date sample was collected</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>yyyy-mm-dd</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379537381400"><attributeName>gear</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Gear Type</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Gear used to collect sample.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>dipNet</code>
 <definition>Dip net</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>purseSeine</code>
 <definition>Purse seine</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>setGillnet</code>
 <definition>Set gillnet</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>doubleOtterTrawl</code>
 <definition>Double otter trawl</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>mechanicalJig</code>
 <definition>Mechanical jig</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>herringGillnet</code>
 <definition>Herring gillnet</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>sunkenGillnet</code>
 <definition>Sunken gillnet</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379537381401"><attributeName>lenType</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Description of gear length type</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>LenType</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379537381402"><attributeName>ageType</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Age measure</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Structure used in age determination.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>Scale</code>
 <definition>Herring Scales</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>Otolith</code>
 <definition>Herring otolith</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 <missingValueCode><code>NA</code>
 <codeExplanation>Missing data</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379537381403"><attributeName>fishery</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Fishery type</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Type of fishery inwhich sample was collected: test, sac/row, food, bait fisheries</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>fishery type</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379537381404"><attributeName>specimenID</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Specimen ID</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Unique number assigned to specimen sample</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>sample ID</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379537381405"><attributeName>specimenNum</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Specimen Number</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Unique number assigned to specimen sample</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>specimen ID</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379537381406"><attributeName>length</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Standard Length</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Standard Length of fish, measured in millimeters, from the anterior extremity to the end of the hypural plate.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>millimeter</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379537381407"><attributeName>weight</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Herring Weight</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Weight of herring sample measured in grams</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379537381408"><attributeName>sex</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Sex</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sex of specimen</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>Male</code>
 <definition>male</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>Female</code>
 <definition>female</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>Unknown</code>
 <definition>undetermined</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379537381409"><attributeName>gonadWt</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Gonad Weight</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Weight of gonad in grams</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 <missingValueCode><code>NA</code>
 <codeExplanation>no data</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379537381410"><attributeName>age</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>age</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Age estimated from defined structure</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>nominalYear</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 <missingValueCode><code>NA</code>
 <codeExplanation>no data</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379537381411"><attributeName>ageError</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Age Error</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Qualifier for age estimate</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>age error</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379537381412"><attributeName>gonadNotes</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Gonad Notes</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Notes on gonad size, color, status</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>gonad notes</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>80404</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>