<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="df35b.10.8" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 eml.xsd">  <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"><allow><principal>public</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
</allow>
<allow><principal>cn=evos,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
<permission>write</permission>
<permission>changePermission</permission>
</allow>
</access>
<dataset> <title>Evaluation of Alaska Harbor Seal (Phoca vitulina) population surveys: A simulation study (1995-1996)</title>
<creator> <references>1362776134341</references>
 </creator>
<associatedParty id="1362778859557"><individualName><givenName>David</givenName>
 <surName>Withrow</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>NOAA National Marine Fisheries Service, National Marine Mammal Laboratory</organizationName>
 <positionName>Research Fish Biologist</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>7600 Sand Point WayNE</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Seattle</city>
 <administrativeArea>WA</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>98115-0070</postalCode>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">(206) 526-4019</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>dave.withrow@noaa.gov</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Custodian/Steward</role>
 </associatedParty>
<associatedParty id="1374791948802"><individualName><givenName>Jessica</givenName>
 <surName>Couture</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis</organizationName>
 <positionName>Research Assistant</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>735 State St., Suite 300</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Santa Barbara</city>
 <administrativeArea>CA</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>93101</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <electronicMailAddress>couture@nceas.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Metadata Provider</role>
 </associatedParty>
<associatedParty><references>1362776134341</references>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </associatedParty>
<associatedParty id="1362778337166"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation>
 <givenName>Terrance</givenName>
 <surName>Quinn</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>School of Fisheries and Ocean Sciences, University of Alaska Fairbanks</organizationName>
 <positionName>Professor</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>Fisheries Division</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>17101 Point Lena Loop Rd.</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Juneau</city>
 <administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>99801-8344</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">(907) 796-5457</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>terry.quinn@alaska.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Author</role>
 </associatedParty>
<associatedParty id="1362779492561"><individualName><givenName>Robert J.</givenName>
 <surName>Small</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Alaska Department of Fish and Game</organizationName>
 <positionName>Wildlife Scientist</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>Fish and Game DWC-WILDLIFE HQ</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>PO Box 115526</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Juneau</city>
 <administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>99811-5526</postalCode>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">(907) 465-6167</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>bob.small@alaska.gov</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Author</role>
 </associatedParty>
       <abstract><para>We used simulation to investigate robust designs for the Alaska harbor seal population surveys. We employed an operating model approach, creating simulated harbor seal population dynamics and haulout behavior that incorporated all factors thought to potentially affect the performance of aerial surveys. We found that adjusting counts for the effects of covariates such as survey date or stage of tide was both possible and essential. Annual estimates of the average fraction of the population hauled out are also advised.

This project is primarily a re-analysis of existing empirical data collected by the ADF&amp;G and NMFS during studies to assess the population trend and abundance of harbor seals in the Gulf of Alaska, including Prince William Sound. These data are primarily counts of harbor seals obtained from both aerial surveys and land-based
monitoring studies. Additional data include the geographic location of the seal haulout where the counts were obtained, and records of environmental variables associated with the count data: e.g., date, time, tidal stage.

The data here include NMFS survey and tag-and-recapture data, ADF&amp;G data collected by Kathryn Frost, et al. has been archived in package df35b.71.9 and can be found at http://evos.nceas.ucsb.edu/evos/metacat/df35b.71.9/default

Adkison, M. D., T. J. Quinn 11, and R. J. Small. 2001. Evaluation of Alaska Harbor Seal (Phoca vitulina) population surveys: A simulation study, Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Restoration Project Final Report (Restoration Project 00509), Alaska Department of Fish &amp; Game, Division of Wildlife Conservation, Juneau, Alaska.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>harbor seal</keyword>
 <keyword>Phoca vitulina</keyword>
 <keyword>survey design</keyword>
 <keyword>aerial count</keyword>
 <keyword>Gulf of Alaska</keyword>
 <keyword>simulation</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>EVOS report</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet><keyword>Exxon Valdez</keyword>
 <keyword>Oil Spill</keyword>
 <keyword>Alaska</keyword>
 <keyword>EVOSTC</keyword>
 <keyword>exxon valdez oil spill trustee council</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>EVOS</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <intellectualRights><para>This material is based upon work funded by the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council under Project No. 209.  Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed herein are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views or positions of the Trustee Council.

Funding and support also provided by: 
The National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration
Alaska Department of Fish and Game

Standard scientific norms for attribution and credit should be followed when using this data including to the Owners, Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council and other sources of funding. Please let the Owner know when this data is used.

This data is licensed under CC0. The person who associated a work with this deed has dedicated the work to the public domain by waiving all of his or her rights to the work worldwide under copyright law, including all related and neighboring rights, to the extent allowed by law. You can copy, modify, distribute and perform the work, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</para>
 </intellectualRights>
 <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Gulf of Alaska</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-156.25</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>-133.5</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>61.875</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>54.0</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <taxonomicCoverage><taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Phoca</taxonRankValue>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>vitulina</taxonRankValue>
 <commonName>harbor seal</commonName>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicCoverage>
 </coverage>
<contact id="1362776134341"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation>
 <givenName>Milo</givenName>
 <surName>Adkison</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>School of Fisheries and Ocean Sciences, University of Alaska Fairbanks</organizationName>
 <positionName>Professor</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>235 O'Neil</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Fairbanks</city>
 <administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>99775</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">(907) 474-7204</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>mdadkison@alaska.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 </contact>
<contact><references>1362778859557</references>
 </contact>
<contact><references>1362779492561</references>
 </contact>
    <methods><methodStep><description><section><title>Operating Model Approach</title>
 <para>The operating model approach (also known as operational management procedure) is an emerging technology that is becoming widely used in evaluating the robustness of natural resource management strategies. Pioneered by the Scientific Committee of the International Whaling Commission (Kirkwood 1997), it has found use in fisheries management, particularly in South Africa (Butterworth and Bergh 1993, Butterworth et al. 1997, Cochran et al. 1998). The goal is to find a management procedure that achieves resource conservation objectives by conducting large-scale simulations over a wide variety of operating conditions and hypotheses. In our context, the management strategy is the design of the Gulf of Alaska harbor seal population abundance and trend surveys conducted by NMFS and ADF&amp;G, respectively. We use the operating model approach to provide a framework, using a known population, for evaluating the robustness of alternative survey designs. By robustness, we mean designs that produce reasonable estimates (low bias and variability) even when assumptions are not strictly met. The operating model contains all the known and hypothesized factors affecting the population and the survey. The operating model contains an estimation module that translates the data into estimates of key quantities. Often a simplified estimation model replaces the usual one, in order that large numbers of simulations can be performed. The inputs to the operational model consist of relevant information about the Gulf of Alaska harbor seal surveys, as well as basic principles of sampling and survey design. We obtained raw data from the survey, gathered literature results and values, and attended meetings with marine mammal scientists to obtain expert opinions. We found that the Bayesian hierarchical model of Ver Hoef and Frost (1999, 2000) provided a logical starting point for development of our model. Knowing that this model would be too complex to use for large-scale simulations, we reanalyzed the raw count data and came up with a general linear model formulation (described below) to approximate results from the Bayesian model.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Reanaysis of Prince William Sound trend route 'A' sites</title>
 <para>We performed individual analyses for each of the 25 sites that comprise the ADF&amp;G PWS 'A' trend survey route using a general linear model formulation similar to Ver Hoef and Frost (1999). The dependent variable was ln(count+l). The model contained a</para>
 <para>categorical variable for year and covariates for date, time of day, tide, and tide height (with quadratic terms for the first three covariates). Because tide height and time of day were the least significant variables, we dropped those variables and reran a reduced general linear model. Results were fairly similar to Ver Hoef and Frost (1999), so we used parameters from the reduced model in subsequent work. The estimated deviation of the trend at each site from the average trend is shown in Figure 2. There is large inter-site variability in trend, with deviations ranging from - 0.28 to 0.22. These deviations are a key ingredient in the operating model. The estimated effect of day on ln(count+l) is shown for each site and averaged across sites (Figure 3). On this scale the estimated effects range generally from -1 to 1 from 10 days before the mean survey day of August 28 to 20 days after that day (corresponding to the range in the data). The effects also range from minimal (flat) to concave downward (the expected effect) to concave upwards (somewhat counterintuitive). Averaged across sites, the overall effect is concave downward. The</para>
 <para>peak cannot be seen on the graph but occurs about 15 days before August 28. The estimated effect of tide on ln(count+l) is shown for each site and averaged across sites (Figure 4). On this scale the estimated effects range generally from -2 to 1</para>
 <para>from 3 hr before low tide to 3 hr after low tide (corresponding to the range in the data). The effects range mainly from minimal (flat) to concave downward (the expected effect). Averaged across sites, the overall effect is concave downward with a peak about low tide. The individual site parameters (linear and quadratic coefficients) for day and tide are used in the operating model. The average across sites in the above graphs can be used to predict the average impact of each factor on the counts.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Spatial Structure</title>
 <para>The model was multi-year (12 years) to correspond to the longest length of survey trend data available for the Gulf of Alaska Region. The model was multi-area (PWS, Kodiak, AK Peninsula, Cook Inlet, Kenai, Figure 5) to correspond to the 5 regions of interest in the EVOS spill area. All potential sites within the area were classified by substrate., as either ice or non-ice. Sites were identified from the 1996 NMFS survey and the ADF&amp;G Kodiak and PWS trend routes, with some pooling of sites in close proximity, resulting in a total of 244 sites. The sites were sorted, mainly by decreasing longitude [west to east], and classified into 8 survey sub-areas within the 5 major areas. The survey sub-areas were chosen to approximate actual practice during the 1996 survey.</para>
 <para>With the exception of survey 8, these survey routes correspond to entire areas or subdivisions of areas as defined for population dynamics.</para>
 <para>**Survey Sub-Areas: Survey 1 = Area 1(AK Penninusla) 53 sites; Survey 2 = Area 2 (Kodiak) 37 sites; Survey 3 = Area 2 (Kodiak) 35 sites; Survey 4 = Area 3 (Cook Inlet): 34 sites; Survey 5 = Area 4 (Kenai) 12 sites; Survey 6 = Area 5 (PWS A stations) 19 sites; Survey 7 = Area 5 (PWS B stations) 27 sites; Survey 8 = Area 5 (PWS C+Copper River) 27 sites**</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Population Dynamics</title>
 <para>The model follows the abundance of harbor seals at all sites over the course of the simulation period. Because the survey design was the key factor in this study, we kept the model's population dynamics simple and deterministic. We define abundance as the</para>
 <para>count of animals that would occur on the date of peak attendance during the molt period at low tide with no unknown covariate present. By doing so, we avoid the problems of modeling the calibration between counts and abundance, such as occurs in the calculation of the minimum abundance estimate.</para>
 <para>(Details of calculations can be found on attached pdf)</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 <dataTable id="1374854626271"><entityName>cordovaRecapture95.csv</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Harbor seal tag recapture data - 1996</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1374792068887"><objectName>cordovaRecapture95.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">50814</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/df35b.68.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1374854626272"><attributeName>dateTime</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Date &amp; Time</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Date and time of tag record (Alaska Standard Time)</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>YYYY-MM-DD hh:mm:ss</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374854626273"><attributeName>julDay</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Julian Day</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Julian day, day of the year tag record was taken.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>nominalDay</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </interval>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374854626274"><attributeName>beforeAfterTideHt</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Tide height (ft)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Tide height relative to zero measured in feet.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>foot</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>integer</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374854626276"><attributeName>t5024</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Tag #5024</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sightings of individual with tag #5024</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374854626277"><attributeName>t5043</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Tag #5043</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sightings of individual with tag #5043</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374854626278"><attributeName>t5064</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Tag #5064</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sightings of individual with tag #5064</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374854626279"><attributeName>t5084</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Tag #5084</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sightings of individual with tag #5084</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374854626280"><attributeName>t5103</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Tag #5103</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sightings of individual with tag #5103</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374854626281"><attributeName>t5123</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Tag #5123</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sightings of individual with tag #5123</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374854626282"><attributeName>t5144</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Tag #5144</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sightings of individual with tag #5144</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374854626283"><attributeName>t5164</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Tag #5164</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sightings of individual with tag #5164</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374854626284"><attributeName>t5183</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Tag #5183</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sightings of individual with tag #5183</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374854626285"><attributeName>t5203</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Tag #5203</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>sightings of individual with tag #5203</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374854626286"><attributeName>t5223</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Tag #5223</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sightings of individual with tag #5223</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374854626287"><attributeName>t5243</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Tag #5243</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sightings of individual with tag #5243</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374854626288"><attributeName>t5264</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Tag #5264</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sightings of individual with tag #5264</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374854626289"><attributeName>t5284</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Tag #5284</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sightings of individual with tag #5284</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374854626290"><attributeName>t5305</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Tag #5284</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sightings of individual with tag #5284</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374854626291"><attributeName>t5324</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Tag #5324</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sightings of individual with tag #5324</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374854626292"><attributeName>t5364</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Tag #5364</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sightings of individual with tag #5364</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374854626293"><attributeName>t5384</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Tag #5384</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sightings of individual with tag #5384</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374854626294"><attributeName>t5423</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Tag #5423</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sightings of individual with tag #5423</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374854626295"><attributeName>total</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Total sightings</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Total number of sightings per observation time.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>722</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 <dataTable id="1374862901236"><entityName>gulf96master.csv</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Harbor seal survey locations, conditions, counts and covariate data</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1374855654282"><objectName>gulf96master.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">195226</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/df35b.69.3</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1374862901237"><attributeName>site</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Site</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Site where survey was conducted in Prince William Sound, Ak. Locations of these sites are visualized on attached pdf (harborSealSitesPWS96.pdf)</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Sites</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374862901238"><attributeName>zone</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Survey Zone</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Zone of Prince William Sound that site is in. Zones are visually displayed on the attached pdf (harborSealSitesPWS96.pdf)</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Survey zones</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374862901239"><attributeName>dateTime</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Date &amp; Time</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Date and time surveys were conducted (Alaska Standard Time)</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>YYYY-MM-DD hh:mm:ss</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374862901240"><attributeName>count</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Harbor Seal Counts</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Number of harbor seals (Phoca vitulina) observed in survey.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374862901241"><attributeName>tideHt</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Tide Height</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Tide height relative to zero, measured in feet.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>foot</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374862901243"><attributeName>lowTideHt</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Low Tide Height</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Height of low tide measured in feet.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>foot</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374862901244"><attributeName>timeBA</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Before or After Tide</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Defines if observations were taken before or after ***LOW*** tide</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>before</code>
 <definition>Before</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>after</code>
 <definition>After</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374862901245"><attributeName>tideTimeDiff</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Tide Time Difference</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Direction based on previous column, amount of time before or after ***slack *** tide.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>hh:mm:ss</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374862901246"><attributeName>tideDist</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Distance from the observation location to the nearest tidal station used to compute tide height at time of sighting.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>nauticalMile</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374862901247"><attributeName>windCond</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Wind Conditions</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Qualitative description of the wind weather at time of observation.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>wind conditions</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 <missingValueCode><code>NA</code>
 <codeExplanation>No record</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374862901248"><attributeName>windSpd</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Approximate Wind Speed</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Wind speed ranges measured in knots</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>knots</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374862901249"><attributeName>skyCond</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Sky Conditions</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Qualitative cloud cover weather at the time of observation.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>cloud cover/weather</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374862901250"><attributeName>minTemp</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Minimum Temperature</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Minimum temperature at the time of observation, recorded in Fahrenheit.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>fahrenheit</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>integer</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </interval>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374862901251"><attributeName>maxTemp</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Maximum Temperature</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Maximum temperature at the time of observation, recorded in Fahrenheit</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>fahrenheit</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>integer</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </interval>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374862901252"><attributeName>ice</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Presnce or absence of ice</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Defines whether observations were made on land or ice</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>notIce</code>
 <definition>No ice, observations taken on land</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>ice</code>
 <definition>Onservations taken on ice sheet</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1374862901253"><attributeName>observer</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Observer's Name</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Name of observer who collected data.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Observer last name</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>1368</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 <otherEntity><entityName>Harbor Seal Survey Site Map</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Map of Zones and sites of surveys in Prince William Sound, 1996.</entityDescription>
 <physical><objectName>harborSealSitesPWS96.pdf</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">898022</size>
 <dataFormat><externallyDefinedFormat><formatName>application/pdf</formatName>
 </externallyDefinedFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution id="1374862976980"><online><url function="download">ecogrid://knb/df35b.70.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <entityType>Other</entityType>
 </otherEntity>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>