<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="df35d.97.17" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"><allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow><principal>cn=evos,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 <permission>write</permission>
 <permission>changePermission</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset> <title>Aerial Surveys of Harbor Seals in Prince William Sound, Alaska: 1989 - 2001</title>
 <creator id="1360886555567"> <individualName><givenName>Kathryn</givenName>
 <surName>Frost</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>University of Alaska, Fairbanks</organizationName>
 <positionName>Affiliate Faculty</positionName>
 <electronicMailAddress>kjfrost@hawaii.rr.com</electronicMailAddress>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1360886567601"><individualName><givenName>Sara</givenName>
 <surName>Iverson</surName>
 </individualName>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1360886589783"><individualName><givenName>Lloyd</givenName>
 <surName>Lowry</surName>
 </individualName>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1360886601409"><individualName><givenName>Mike</givenName>
 <surName>Simpkins</surName>
 </individualName>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1360886634106"><individualName><givenName>Jay</givenName>
 <surName>Ver Hoef</surName>
 </individualName>
 </creator>
<associatedParty id="1365723503202"><individualName><givenName>Sarah</givenName>
<surName>Clark</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis</organizationName>
<positionName>Projects Data Coordinator</positionName>
<address><deliveryPoint>735 State Street, Suite 300</deliveryPoint>
<city>Santa Barbara</city>
<administrativeArea>California</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>93101</postalCode>
</address>
<phone phonetype="voice">(805) 892-2500</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>sclark@nceas.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
<role>Metadata Provider</role>
</associatedParty>
  <abstract><para>Study History: Restoration Project 01064 began in 1993 as a continuation of the initial post-spill study effort conducted as Marine Mammal Study Number 5 (Assessment of Injury to Harbor Seals in Prince William Sound, Alaska, and Adjacent Areas) in 1989 through 1991 and reclassified as Restoration Study Number 73 (Harbor Seal Restoration Study) in 1992. A final report was issued in 1994 for the combined Marine Mammal Study Number 5 and Restoration Study Number 73, entitled Assessment of Injury to Harbor Seals in Prince William Sound, Alaska, and Adjacent Areas Following the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill. Subsequently, annual reports were submitted entitled Habitat Use, Behavior, and Monitoring of Harbor Seals in Prince William Sound: 1994 Annual Report, 1995 Annual Report, 1996 Annual Report , 1997 Annual Report, 1998 Annual Report, and 1999 Annual Report . Fatty acid studies funded under Restoration Project 94320-F (Trophic Interactions of Harbor Seals in Prince William Sound) were included in the 1994 annual report for 94064. Fatty acid studies were continued and reported as part of this study for the duration of the project.

Abstract: We used aerial counts to monitor the trend in numbers of harbor seals in Prince William Sound, Alaska, following the 1989 Exxon Valdez oil spill. Repetitive counts were made at 25 haul-out sites during the annual molt period each year from 1990 through 1997. A generalized linear model indicated that time of day, date, and time relative to low tide significantly affected seal counts. When Poisson regression was used to adjust counts to a standardized set of survey conditions, results showed a highly significant decline of 4.6% per year. Unadjusted counts indicated a slight, but not statistically significant, decline in the number of seals. The number of harbor seals on the trend-count route in eastern and central PWS has been declining since at least 1984, with an overall population reduction of 63% through 1997. Programs to monitor long-term changes in animal population sizes should account for factors that can cause short-term variations in indices of abundance. The inclusion of such factors as covariates in models can improve the accuracy of monitoring programs.

Publications:

Adkison, M. D., T. J. Quinn II, and R. J. Small. 2003. Evaluation of the Alaska harbor seal population (Phoca vitulina) population survey: a simulation study. Marine Mammal Science 19: 764-90.

Boveng, P. L., J. L. Bengtson, D. E. Withrow, J. C. Cesarone, M. A. Simpkins, K. J. Frost, and J. J. Burns. 2003. The abundance of harbor seals in the Gulf of Alaska. Marine Mammal Science 19: 111-27.

Frost, K.J., Lowry, L.F., Ver Hoef, J.M., Iverson, S.J., Simpkins, M.A. 2005. Monitoring Habitat Use, and Trophic Interactions of Harbor Seals in Prince William Sound, Alaska. Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council Report (Project #01064, 99064, 98064, 97064, 96064, 95064, 94064, 93064, R073, MM05). Alaska Department of Fish and Game, Fairbanks, Alaska.

Frost, K. J., L. F. Lowry, and J. Ver Hoef. 1999. Monitoring the trend of harbor seals in Prince William Sound, Alaska, after the Exxon Valdez oil spill. Marine Mammal Science 15, no. 2: 494-506.

Ver Hoef, J. M., and K. J. Frost. 2003. A Bayesian hierarchical model for monitoring harbor seal changes in Prince William Sound, Alaska. Environmental and Ecological Statistics 10: 201-9.</para>
 </abstract>
<keywordSet><keyword>trend analysis</keyword>
<keyword>Phoca vitulina richardsi</keyword>
<keyword>population monitoring</keyword>
<keyword>aerial survey</keyword>
<keyword>harbor seal</keyword>
<keyword>prince william sound</keyword>
</keywordSet>
<keywordSet><keyword>EVOSTC</keyword>
<keyword>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council</keyword>
<keyword>Alaska</keyword>
<keyword>Pelagic</keyword>
<keyword>Mammals</keyword>
</keywordSet>
<intellectualRights><para>This material is based upon work funded by the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council.  Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed herein are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views or positions of the Trustee Council.
 
Standard scientific norms for attribution and credit to the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council and any additional funding agencies should be followed when using these data. 
 
These data are licensed under CC0. The person who associated a work with this deed has dedicated the work to the public domain by waiving all of his or her rights to the work worldwide under copyright law, including all related and neighboring rights, to the extent allowed by law. You can copy, modify, distribute and perform the work, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</para>
</intellectualRights>
    <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Prince William Sound, Alaska, USA</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-148.4</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>-146.0</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>61.22</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>59.93</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <taxonomicCoverage><taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Phoca</taxonRankValue>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>vitulina richardsi</taxonRankValue>
 <commonName>Harbor Seal</commonName>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1989-09-03</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate><calendarDate>2001-08-25</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 </coverage>
<contact id="1365723593932"><individualName><givenName>Gail</givenName>
 <surName>Blundell</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Alaska Department of Fish and Game, Harbor Seal Research Program</organizationName>
 <positionName>Program Leader</positionName>
 <electronicMailAddress>gail.blundell@alaska.gov</electronicMailAddress>
 </contact>
<contact id="1365723611372"><individualName><givenName>Christine</givenName>
 <surName>Schmale</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Alaska Department of Fish and Game</organizationName>
 <electronicMailAddress>christine.schmale@alaska.gov</electronicMailAddress>
 </contact>
   <methods><methodStep><description><section><title>Aerial Surveys</title>
 <para>Aerial Surveys:</para>
 <para>We conducted aerial surveys along a trend-count route that covered 25 harbor seal haul-out sites in eastern and central PWS. The route included seven sites that were substantially affected by the Exxon Valdez oil spill and 18 unoiled sites that were outside of the primary affected area. Surveys were flown during the molting period (August-September) in 1984 and 1988-1997.</para>
 <para>Visual counts of seals were conducted from a single-engine fixed-wing air- craft (Cessna 185) at altitudes of 200-300 m, usually with the aid of 7X binoculars. Counts were usually conducted from two hours before low tide to two hours after low tide. A survey normally included counts at all 25 sites, but occasionally some sites could not be counted because of poor weather or a rapidly rising tide. For each survey the date, time and height of low tide, and time of sunrise and sunset were recorded. Each site was circled until the observer was confident that an accurate count had been made, and the time of the count was recorded. For larger groups of seals (generally those of 40 or more) color photographs were taken using a hand-held 35-mm camera, and seals were counted from images projected on a white surface. Each year several survey flights, usually 7-10, were made. The total number of counts for all sites and all years was 2,014.</para>
 <para>Factors Affecting When Seals Are Hauled Out:</para>
 <para>We used a generalized linear model (McCullagh and Nelder 1989) with a log link function and a Poisson distribution to analyze the factors that may affect the number of seals hauled out and available to be counted during surveys. The model may be written where 'p' is a parameter vector and 'x' is a vector containing information on the state of covariates: year, site, time of tide, height of tide, time of day, and date for the jth flight at site i in year t.</para>
 <para>To estimate the average count at each site in any given year, we first used a model that contained site, year, and the interaction of site with year. These factors were used in all models. Then, effects for time of day, time of low tide, date, and tide height were entered into the model one at a time. If a factor with m parameters increased 2*log-likelihood by more than a x2-distribution with m degrees of freedom at a = 0.05, we considered the factor to affect significantly the number of seals counted at haul-outs. The factor with the largest x2-value was retained in the model, and then other factors were again entered into the model one at a time until any remaining factors were not significant. Time of day and time relative to low tide were analyzed as categorical data. Time increments before and after midday were placed in six separate categories and increments before and after low tide in eight categories. We combined some categories within a factor when preliminary analysis indicated that it could be done without changing the fit (again, if combining two categories decreased 2*log-likelihood by more than a x2-distribution with one degree of freedom, we considered that the fit was essentially unchanged). Date was a continuous variable entered into the model as a polynomial up to a quadratic power. Dates were numbered beginning 15 August and scaled so that each day was equal to 0.1 to keep parameter estimates from becoming too small (causing problems with significant digits in software packages). To construct the initial model, we used data from all surveys conducted during 1984-1997. The final model was checked using deviance residuals (McCullagh and Nelder 1989). The residuals were plotted against each factor, by year, to examine whether or not the effects were constant across years.</para>
 <para>After obtaining a parsimonious model and fitting the parameters as described above, the count data were adjusted to a standardized set of covariates. The adjustment amounts to estimating counts at each site for each year as the expected count under optimal conditions.</para>
 <para>(from Frost, K. J., L. F. Lowry, and J. Ver Hoef. 1999. Monitoring the trend of harbor seals in Prince William Sound, Alaska, after the Exxon Valdez oil spill. Marine Mammal Science 15, no. 2: 494-506.)</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Trend Analysis</title>
 <para>Trend Analysis:</para>
 <para>A linear regression model was fitted to the adjusted yearly count estimates for 1990-1997. This model assumes constant amount of change per year. We also considered a model on the log-scale, where the rate of change is constant. Again, we used a generalized linear model (McCullagh and Nelder 1989) with a log link function and a Poisson distribution to model trend through time. This is also called Poisson regression. Linear and Poisson regressions were also fitted to the unadjusted counts.</para>
 <para>This analysis was complicated because we first adjusted yearly counts for each site to a standardized date, time of day, and time relative to low tide, then summed over sites to get a yearly index, and then used the index in a trend regression analysis. Under these circumstances it is difficult to pass the uncertainty associated with adjusting the counts to the trend analysis. Therefore, we used bootstrap methods (Efron and Tibshirani 1993, Manly 1997) for the whole procedure. We resampled with replacement from the daily flights for each year, with the number of resamples equal to the actual number of flights for that year. After obtaining the bootstrap sample, we used the generalized linear model to re-estimate parameters, adjusted the counts based on the bootstrap parameter estimates, and then did both linear and Poisson regression trend estimation on the bootstrap samples. The trend parameters from the bootstrap appeared symmetrically distributed and centered on the original parameter estimate. Bootstrapping the whole procedure was quite computer-intensive and only 200 resampled estimates were obtained, so we used the standard bootstrap method  (Manly 1997) and if 0 was contained in the interval, there was little evidence of trend for the stated alpha-level. Bootstrapping was used to estimate variance of the unadjusted counts by resampling from the actual count values for each site in each year. (from Frost, K. J., L. F. Lowry, and J. Ver Hoef. 1999. Monitoring the trend of harbor seals in Prince William Sound, Alaska, after the Exxon Valdez oil spill. Marine Mammal Science 15, no. 2: 494-506.)</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Bayesian Hierarchical Model</title>
 <para>see publication Ver Hoef, J. M., and K. J. Frost. 2003. A Bayesian hierarchical model for monitoring harbor seal changes in Prince William Sound, Alaska. Environmental and Ecological Statistics 10: 201-9.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
<project><title>Monitoring, Habitat Use, and Trophic Interactions of Harbor Seals in PWS, Alaska</title>
 <personnel><references>1360886555567</references>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </personnel>
 <personnel><references>1360886634106</references>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </personnel>
 <personnel><references>1360886589783</references>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </personnel>
 <personnel><references>1360886601409</references>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </personnel>
 <personnel><references>1360886567601</references>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </personnel>
 <funding><para>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council projects 01064, 99064, 98064, 97064, 96064, 95064, 94064, 93064, R073, MM05</para>
 </funding>
 </project>
  <dataTable id="1360888195906"><entityName>aerialSurveys_formatted.txt</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Aerial survey harbor seal counts in Prince William Sound, Alaska, USA: 1989 - 2001</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1360887591836"><objectName>aerialSurveys_formatted.txt</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">369838</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/df35d.96.7</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1360888195907"><attributeName>Loc #</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>unique number assigned to a survey location by ADF&amp;G.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>ID</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 <missingValueCode><code>NA</code>
 <codeExplanation>no data</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1360888195908"><attributeName>Loc Name</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Common name of survey location</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Place name</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 <missingValueCode><code>NA</code>
 <codeExplanation>no data</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1360888195909"><attributeName>Latitude</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>latitude of survey location; decimal degrees</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </interval>
 </measurementScale>
 <missingValueCode><code>NA</code>
 <codeExplanation>no data</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1360888195910"><attributeName>Longitude</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>longitude of survey location; decimal degrees</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </interval>
 </measurementScale>
 <missingValueCode><code>NA</code>
 <codeExplanation>no data</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1360888195911"><attributeName>Date</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>date of aerial survey; mm/dd/yy</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>MM/DD/YYYY</formatString>
 <dateTimePrecision>0</dateTimePrecision>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 <missingValueCode><code>NA</code>
 <codeExplanation>no data</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1360888195912"><attributeName>Jdate</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>julian date of aerial survey</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>julian</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 <missingValueCode><code>NA</code>
 <codeExplanation>no data</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1360888195913"><attributeName>Time</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>time of harbor seal count at the survey location;</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>HHMM</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 <missingValueCode><code>NA</code>
 <codeExplanation>no data</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1360888195914"><attributeName>Seals</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>count of harbor seals at the survey location</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </interval>
 </measurementScale>
 <missingValueCode><code>NA</code>
 <codeExplanation>no data</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1360888195915"><attributeName>Wind</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>description of wind at the survey location.  This was not collected in a consistent manner.  Do not have definitions for the codes.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Lost codes</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 <missingValueCode><code>NA</code>
 <codeExplanation>no data</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1360888195916"><attributeName>Sky</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>description of the sky at the survey location.  This was not collected in a consistent manner.  Do not have definitions for the codes.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Lost codes</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 <missingValueCode><code>NA</code>
 <codeExplanation>no data</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1360888195917"><attributeName>Temp</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>air temperature at the survey location; in Fahrenheit</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>fahrenheit</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </interval>
 </measurementScale>
 <missingValueCode><code>NA</code>
 <codeExplanation>no data</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1360888195918"><attributeName>Altitude</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>altitude of survey plane at the survey location; in feet</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>foot</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </interval>
 </measurementScale>
 <missingValueCode><code>NA</code>
 <codeExplanation>no data</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1360888195919"><attributeName>Use</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>this was used for in-house analysis purposes.  N means don't use the data for analysis.  Y means use the data for analysis.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>N</code>
 <definition>not used in ADF&amp;G analysis</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>Y</code>
 <definition>used in ADF&amp;G analysis</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>B</code>
 <definition>?</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 <missingValueCode><code>NA</code>
 <codeExplanation>no data</codeExplanation>
 </missingValueCode>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>4567</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>