<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="df35a.38.7" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"><allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow><principal>cn=evos,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>all</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset> <title>Genetic discrimination of herring populations in Prince William Sound, Alaska: 1994-1998</title>
 <creator id="1366742889285"><individualName><givenName>Jeffrey</givenName>
 <surName>Olsen</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Conservation Genetics Laboratory, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</organizationName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>1011 East Tudor Road</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Anchorage</city>
 <administrativeArea>Alaska</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>99503</postalCode>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">907-786-3598</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>jeffrey_olsen@fws.gov</electronicMailAddress>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1366743064755"><individualName><givenName>Paul</givenName>
 <surName>Bentzen</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Dalhousie University</organizationName>
 <positionName>DFO Chair, Fisheries Resource Conservation Genetics</positionName>
 <address><city>Halifax</city>
 <administrativeArea>Nova Scotia</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>B3H 4R2</postalCode>
 <country>Canada</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">+1 (902) 494-3515</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>paul.bentzen@dal.ca</electronicMailAddress>
 <onlineUrl>http://biology.dal.ca/People/faculty/bentzen/bentzen.htm#</onlineUrl>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1366743229837"><individualName><givenName>Jonathan</givenName>
 <surName>Wright</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Dalhousie University</organizationName>
 <positionName>Professor</positionName>
 <address><city>Halifax</city>
 <administrativeArea>Nova Scotia</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>B3H 4R2</postalCode>
 <country>Canada</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">+1 (902) 494-3515</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>J.M.Wright@Dal.ca</electronicMailAddress>
 <onlineUrl>http://biology.dal.ca/People/faculty/bentzen/bentzen.htm#</onlineUrl>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1366741092760"><individualName><givenName>Jim</givenName>
 <surName>Seeb</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>University of Washington, School of Aquatic &amp; Fishery Sciences</organizationName>
 <positionName>Research Professor</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>Box 355020</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Seattle</city>
 <administrativeArea>Washington</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>98195-5020</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">206-685-2097</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>jseeb@u.washington.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <onlineUrl>https://fish.washington.edu/people/seeb_j/</onlineUrl>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1366742684305"><individualName><givenName>Lisa</givenName>
 <surName>Seeb</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>University of Washington, Aquatic &amp; Fishery Sciences</organizationName>
 <positionName>Research Professor</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>Box 355020</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Seattle</city>
 <administrativeArea>Washington</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>98195-5020</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">206-685-3723</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>lseeb@u.washington.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <onlineUrl>http://fish.washington.edu/people/seeb_l/</onlineUrl>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1366742755119"><individualName><givenName>Susan</givenName>
 <surName>Merkouris</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Alaska Department of Fish and Game</organizationName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>333 Raspberry Road</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Anchorage</city>
 <administrativeArea>Alaska</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>99518-1599</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <electronicMailAddress>suem@fishgame.state.ak.us</electronicMailAddress>
 </creator>
 <associatedParty id="1366741244298"><individualName><givenName>Gavin</givenName>
 <surName>McDonald</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>The National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis (NCEAS)</organizationName>
 <positionName>Graduate Student Researcher</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>735 State Street</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>Suite 300</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Santa Barbara</city>
 <administrativeArea>California</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>93101</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">(805) 892-2500</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>sclark@nceas.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <onlineUrl>http://www.nceas.ucsb.edu/</onlineUrl>
 <role>Metadata Provider</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <abstract><para>We examined spatial and temporal patternsof genetic variation at five microsatellite loci and one mtDNA gene in seven spawning aggregations of Pacific herri(nCglupeaharengus) sampled in 1995 and 1996. Sample locations included Prince William Sound (4 sites) and Kodiak Island(1site)intheGulfof Alaska, and Togiak Bay (1 site) and Norton Sound (1 site) in the Bering Sea. An analysis of molecular variance revealed a marked genetic discontinuity between herring in the Bering Sea and Gulfof Alaska. The estimatesof genetic differentiation between populations from the two sea basins (F_BT) were significant (P&lt;0.001) and ranged from 0.169 for mtDNA to 0.209 for microsatellites. The estimates of genetic differentiation within sea basins (F_SB) were 0.013 for mtDNA and 0.030f or microsatellites and were significant (P&lt;0.001). The microsatellites also showed significant (P&lt;0.001) temporal variation within the Gulf of Alaska. The estimates of genetic variation between years at each sample location(F_SL) were 0.011 formicrosatellites and 0.012 for mtDNA. The temporal shifts in genetic structure may reflect large inter-annual variation in reproductive success and hamper the use of genetic markers for discrete stock management of herring in Prince William Sound.

This multi-year study was initiated in FY94 as Restoration Project 94165. However, a return failure of herring in Prince William Sound in 1994 delayed implementation until FY95. During the first two years (FY95, FY96) new molecular markers were developed and tested for population genetic analyses. In addition, herring samples were collected from spawning aggregations within Prince William Sound (4 sites), Kodiak Island(1 site), TogiakBay (1 site), and Norton Sound(1 site). During the final two years (FY97, FY98) samples were genotyped and genetic data were analyzed. Preliminary results were reported to the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill (EVOS)Trustee Council and EVOS project reviewers in a poster session at the January1996 EVOS workshop in Anchorage. A synthesis of the herring genetic data was reported to the EVOS peer reviewers in February 1998. Four reports were submitted consulting scientists detailing the development and application of mtDNA and microsatellite markers. One progress report was submitted by the principal investigators in 1996 under the title Genetic Discrimination of Prince William Sound Herring Populations.

In total, 2,117,781 raw sequencing reads were generated with an average length of 254 bp. All data was submitted to NBCI's Short Read Archive under accession number SRX022719. This can be found at http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra/?term=SRX022719 .</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>Clupea pallasii</keyword>
 <keyword>DNA</keyword>
 <keyword>genetics</keyword>
 <keyword>Pacific herring</keyword>
 <keyword>populations</keyword>
 <keyword>Prince William Sound</keyword>
 <keyword>restoration</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet><keyword>EVOSTC</keyword>
 <keyword>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council</keyword>
 <keyword>Alaska</keyword>
 <keyword>Pelagic</keyword>
 <keyword>Fish</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>Gulf Watch Alaska Thesaurus</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <intellectualRights><para>This material is based upon work funded by the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council.  Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed herein are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views or positions of the Trustee Council.
 
Standard scientific norms for attribution and credit should be followed when using these data including to the Owners, Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council and other sources of funding. Please let the Owner know when these data are used.
 
These data are licensed under CC0. The person who associated a work with this deed has dedicated the work to the public domain by waiving all of his or her rights to the work worldwide under copyright law, including all related and neighboring rights, to the extent allowed by law. You can copy, modify, distribute and perform the work, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</para>
 </intellectualRights>
 <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Prince William Sound, Alaska</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-150.396372</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>-144.143808</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>61.470047</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>59.545139</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1994</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate><calendarDate>1998</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 <taxonomicCoverage><taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Kingdom</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Animalia</taxonRankValue>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Phylum</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Chordata</taxonRankValue>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Class</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Actinopterygii</taxonRankValue>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Order</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Clupeiformes</taxonRankValue>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Family</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Clupeidae</taxonRankValue>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Subfamily</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Clupeinae</taxonRankValue>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Clupea</taxonRankValue>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>pallasii</taxonRankValue>
 <commonName>Pacific herring</commonName>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact id="1366741235593"><individualName><givenName>Jim</givenName>
 <surName>Seeb</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>University of Washington, School of Aquatic &amp; Fishery Sciences</organizationName>
 <positionName>Research Professor</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>Box 355020</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Seattle</city>
 <administrativeArea>Washington</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>98195-5020</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">206-685-2097</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>jseeb@u.washington.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <onlineUrl>https://fish.washington.edu/people/seeb_j/</onlineUrl>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><title>Tissue Collection</title>
 <para>Liver and testes samples from sexually mature Pacific herring were provided by the Alaska Department of Fish and Game from</para>
 <para>four locations; three in the Gulf of Alaska (Kodiak Island, Prince William Sound and Sitka Sound) and one in the Bering Sea (Togiak Bay). Six fish each were sampled at Kodiak Island, Prince William Sound, and Togiak Bay, and five fish were sampled from Sitka. Tissue samples were immediately preserved in RNAlater (Ambion).</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Sample Preperation</title>
 <para>Individual tissue samples were transferred to TriReagent (Molecular Research Center), and total RNA was isolated as per manufacturer's instruction. Individual liver and testes RNA samples (four fish and three fish per location, respectively) were pooled in equal quantity for the construction of two Pacific herring transcriptome libraries. Messenger RNA was isolated from each total RNA pool with the MicroPoly(A) Purist Kit (Ambion) according to the manufacturer's protocol. The isolated mRNA was purified again with the MicroPoly(A) Purist Kit (Ambion) to further minimize residual rRNA carryover. Libraries were constructed by MOgene, LC (St. Louis, MO), following standard protocols from Roche Life Sciences.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Sequencing and Analysis</title>
 <para>Both libraries were sequenced using the Genome Sequencer FLX System (Roche) at MOgene, LC (St. Louis, MO). Initially, all sequences were trimmed based on quality scores of 0.05 [27], [28] and a maximum allowance of two ambiguous nucleotides. Sequences smaller than 100 bp were removed. De novo assembly was carried out using CLC Genomics Workbench v3.7 (CLC Bio) with the following parameters: similarity = 0.98, length frac- tion=0.9, insertion cost=3, deletion cost=3, mismatch cost=2 and minimum size = 300. Where reference assemblies were performed, the same parameters were applied. Consensus sequences were compared to the Swiss-Prot database (http:// uniprot.org) in order to determine putative annotation. Associated GO terms (Gene Ontology database: http://www.geneontology. org) were used to classify sequences based on biological process as well as categorize genes into parent categories (GO slim).</para>
 <para>RNA-seq analysis was used to characterize the transcriptome tissue specificity (CLC Genomics Workbench v3.7 (CLC Bio)). Expression values were measured in RPKM (reads per kilobase of exon model per million mapped reads, see [29]). Parameters for RNA-seq analysis included an unspecific match limit of 10 and a minimum length fraction of 0.9. Given the resources necessary to perform pyrosequencing and the absence of the sequenced genome in herring, we evaluated the relative benefit of additional sequencing effort by rarefaction analysis. Specifically, quality trimmed reads from each library were sequentially sampled in 16105 sequence read increments and de novo assembled as described.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>SNP Discovery</title>
 <para>Candidate SNPs were identified from assembled reads using CLC Genomics Workbench v3.7 (CLC Bio). Parameters were as follows: maximum gap and mismatch count = 2, minimum average quality = 15, minimum central quality = 20, minimum coverage = 4, minimum variant frequency (%) = 35.0, window length = 11. In order to determine whether a SNP resulted in a potential amino acid substitution, putative open reading frames were identified and SNP detection carried out as described. Specifically, open reading frames were identified in the consensus sequences from the de novo assembly of all reads based on the inclusion of start and stop codons, with a minimum size of 100 bp, using getorf (EMBOSS). All quality trimmed reads were then mapped back to these possible open reading frames, and SNP detection was carried out as described (CLC Genomics Work- bench v3.7 (CLC Bio)). Consensus sequences generated with getorf (EMBOSS) which contained putative SNPs were compared to the Swiss-Prot database.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>SNP Selection and Primer Testing</title>
 <para>Ninety-six putative SNPs were selected for validation. Selection stringency was increased from parameters described above to include a window length of 151. In addition, functional annotation was taken into consideration. PCR primers were designed using Primer3 [30] to amplify a template approximately 200 bp long that contained a single putative SNP in the ascertainment fish. A PCR test was done using 26 LightCycler480 High Resolution Melting Master (Roche Applied Science) following manufacturer's instructions. Primer pairs that produced a single, clean amplicon were sequenced. Specifically, six individuals were sequenced in both directions using ABI PRISM BigDye Terminator version 3.1 Cycle Sequencing Kit and analyzed on a 3730 DNA Analyzer (AB) by High-Throughput Sequencing Solutions (University of Washington, Department of Genome Sciences). Sequence chro- matograms were aligned and visually screened for polymorphisms using Sequencher 4.9 (GeneCodes Corporation).</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>High Resolution Melt Analysis and Genotyping</title>
 <para>Those SNPs validated using Sanger sequencing were genotyped using high resolution melt analysis (HRMA) [31], [32]. A total of 95 individuals from each of three populations sampled from Kodiak Island, Prince William Sound, and Togiak Bay, Alaska, were genotyped. Genomic DNA was extracted using DNeasy 96 Blood &amp; Tissue Kits (QIAGEN) and quantified using Quant-iT PicoGreen dsDNA Assay Kit (Invitrogen) following manufacturer's instructions. Fluorescence was measured in a 200 mL reaction on a VICTOR3 multilabel microplate reader (Perkin Elmer). DNA concentrations were then normalized for HRMA. PCR was conducted in a 10 mL volume containing 10 ng of genomic DNA, 16 LightCycler 480 High Resolution Melting Master (Roche Applied Science), 3.5 mM MgCl2, and 0.2 mM each PCR primer. Primers used for HRMA are provided in Table 2. Thermal cycling was performed on a Veriti 384-Well Thermal Cycler (Applied Biosystems; AB) as follows: 95uC hold for 10 min followed by 45 cycles of 95uC for 15 sec, 60uC for 15 sec, and 72uC for 15 sec. The plates were transferred to a LightCycler 480 Real-Time PCR System (Roche Diagnostics) after PCR and heated to 95uC for 1 min, then cooled to 40uC for 1 min. HRMA data were collected between 62uC and 95uC at 25 acquisitions per u1C, using a ramp rate of 0.02uC per second. The amplicons were analyzed for the presence of discrete melt-curve families, signaling the presence of SNPs, using the LightCycler 480 Gene Scanning Software v. 1.5.0 SP1 (Roche Diagnostics). Genotypes were inferred from clearly resolved melt families [8], [32].</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Data Analyses</title>
 <para>Deviations from Hardy Weinberg Equilibrium (HWE) and significance of population differentiation were tested using Fisher's exact test in Genepop 4 [33]. A hierarchical locus-by-locus AMOVA was carried out in Arlequin v 3.5 [23], with ocean basins (Gulf of Alaska, Bering Sea) as groups.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 <project><title>Genetic Discrimination of PWS Herring Populations</title>
 <personnel id="1366741320358"><individualName><givenName>Jim</givenName>
 <surName>Seeb</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>University of Washington, School of Aquatic &amp; Fishery Sciences</organizationName>
 <positionName>Research Professor</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>Box 355020</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Seattle</city>
 <administrativeArea>Washington</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>98195-5020</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">206-685-2097</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>jseeb@u.washington.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <onlineUrl>https://fish.washington.edu/people/seeb_j/</onlineUrl>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </personnel>
 <personnel id="1366743251157"><individualName><givenName>Jeffrey</givenName>
 <surName>Olsen</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Conservation Genetics Laboratory, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</organizationName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>1011 East Tudor Road</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Anchorage</city>
 <administrativeArea>Alaska</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>99503</postalCode>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">907-786-3598</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>jeffrey_olsen@fws.gov</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </personnel>
 <personnel><references>1366743229837</references>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </personnel>
 <personnel id="1366743269629"><individualName><givenName>Lisa</givenName>
 <surName>Seeb</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>University of Washington, Aquatic &amp; Fishery Sciences</organizationName>
 <positionName>Research Professor</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>Box 355020</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Seattle</city>
 <administrativeArea>Washington</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>98195-5020</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">206-685-3723</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>lseeb@u.washington.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <onlineUrl>http://fish.washington.edu/people/seeb_l/</onlineUrl>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </personnel>
 <personnel id="1366743279836"><individualName><givenName>Paul</givenName>
 <surName>Bentzen</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Dalhousie University</organizationName>
 <positionName>DFO Chair, Fisheries Resource Conservation Genetics</positionName>
 <address><city>Halifax</city>
 <administrativeArea>Nova Scotia</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>B3H 4R2</postalCode>
 <country>Canada</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">+1 (902) 494-3515</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>paul.bentzen@dal.ca</electronicMailAddress>
 <onlineUrl>http://biology.dal.ca/People/faculty/bentzen/bentzen.htm#</onlineUrl>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </personnel>
 <personnel id="1366743289988"><individualName><givenName>Susan</givenName>
 <surName>Merkouris</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Alaska Department of Fish and Game</organizationName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>333 Raspberry Road</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Anchorage</city>
 <administrativeArea>Alaska</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>99518-1599</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <electronicMailAddress>suem@fishgame.state.ak.us</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </personnel>
 <funding><para>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council project numbers 94165, 95165, 96165, 97165, 98165, 10100165</para>
 </funding>
 </project>
 <otherEntity><entityName>Roberts 2012 herring transcriptome.pdf</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Published paper relating to this data.

Roberts SB, Hauser L, Seeb LW, Seeb JE (2012) Development of Genomic Resources for Pacific Herring through Targeted Transcriptome Pyrosequencing. PLoS ONE 7(2): e30908. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0030908</entityDescription>
 <physical><objectName>Roberts 2012 herring transcriptome.pdf</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">482869</size>
 <dataFormat><externallyDefinedFormat><formatName>application/pdf</formatName>
 </externallyDefinedFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution id="1366742353982"><online><url function="download">ecogrid://knb/df35a.37.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <entityType>Other</entityType>
 </otherEntity>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>