<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="df35a.22.16" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"><allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow><principal>cn=evos,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>all</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset>  <title>Herring data and information portal for Prince William Sound, Alaska: 2007-2009</title>
<creator id="1358364266400"><individualName><givenName>Steve</givenName>
 <surName>Moffitt</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Alaska Department of Fish and Game</organizationName>
 <positionName>Principal Investigator during 2007-2008</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>401 Railroad Avenue P.O. Box 669</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Cordova</city>
 <administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>99574</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">907-424-3212</phone>
 <phone phonetype="fax">907-424-3235</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>steve.moffitt@alaska.gov</electronicMailAddress>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1358364277441"><individualName><givenName>Rob</givenName>
 <surName>Bochenek</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Axiom Consulting &amp; Design</organizationName>
 <positionName>Principal Investigator during 2009, Data Custodian</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>523 West 8th Ave</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>Suite 104</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Anchorage,</city>
 <administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>99501</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">(907)-230-0304</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>rob@axiomalaska.com</electronicMailAddress>
 </creator>
 <associatedParty id="1366401682854"><individualName><givenName>Gavin</givenName>
 <surName>McDonald</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>The National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis (NCEAS)</organizationName>
 <positionName>Graduate Student Researcher</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>735 State Street</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>Suite 300</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Santa Barbara</city>
 <administrativeArea>California</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>93101</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">(805) 892-2500</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>sclark@nceas.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <onlineUrl>http://www.nceas.ucsb.edu/</onlineUrl>
 <role>Metadata Provider</role>
 </associatedParty>
<abstract><para>This project has developed a web-based data portal and consolidated, documented, and entered data sets, metadata, and other electronic resources into that web portal. The efforts of this project have resulted in a considerable increase in available historic time series data regarding herring ecosystem dynamics in Prince William Sound. The web portal provides public access to information, data and GIS visualizations. Scientist and researchers can use the web portal as a resource to assist in consolidating, accessing and synthesizing herring data. This project has also developed an ArcPad application for collecting herring aerial survey data directly into a GIS format. Also produced by this project are a set of technical Standard Operating Procedures (SOPs) for efficiently ingesting, managing and serving ecological datasets in an open, scalable and standardized way. These SOPs were developed in the last phase of this effort and also document the technical architecture of system implementation. The project was conceived during an EVOS-sponsored workshop in April 2006 that was tasked to identify Prince William Sound herring data gaps and develop restoration or research projects to help herring recovery. Participants indicated that knowledge of the spatial and temporal aspects of herring related data sets (e.g., herring spawn) was necessary to understand how restoration activities might affect herring abundance trajectories. This project has improved data quality and provided easier access and visualization of selected herring data sets and other electronic resources.

EVOSTC project 090822 was originally a one year pilot project (070822) that began in spring 2007 and was extended for the 2008 and 2009 fiscal years. Work performed in 2008 is associated with EVOSTC project number 080822. Steve Moffitt, Alaska Department of Fish &amp; Game Division of Commercial Fisheries, was the PI for the project during 2007 and 2008. In 2009 the PI responsibility was transferred to Rob Bochenek of Axiom Consulting &amp; Design. This project suffered a serious impediment during 2008 when Jim Vansant, lead ADF&amp;G data salvage technician, was killed in a construction accident.

The data can be found at the AOOS Data Resources page, http://www.aoos.org/aoos-data-resources/ under "Prince William Sound Herring Portal".

A zip file Containing the GIS shapefiles, xml files, and databases used to create the herring data portal is also attached.</para>
</abstract>
  <keywordSet><keyword>Pacific Herring</keyword>
 <keyword>Clupea pallasi</keyword>
 <keyword>Prince William Sound</keyword>
 <keyword>Data Management</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet><keyword>EVOSTC</keyword>
 <keyword>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council</keyword>
 <keyword>Alaska</keyword>
 <keyword>Pelagic</keyword>
 <keyword>Fish</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>Gulf Watch Alaska Thesaurus</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <intellectualRights><para>This material is based upon work funded by the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council.  Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed herein are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views or positions of the Trustee Council.
 
Standard scientific norms for attribution and credit to funding agencies should be followed when using these data. Please let the Owner know when these data are used.
 
These data are licensed under CC0. The person who associated a work with this deed has dedicated the work to the public domain by waiving all of his or her rights to the work worldwide under copyright law, including all related and neighboring rights, to the extent allowed by law. You can copy, modify, distribute and perform the work, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</para>
 </intellectualRights>
 <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Prince William Sound</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-148.25</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>-146.25</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>61.15</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>59.9</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2007</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate><calendarDate>2009</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 <taxonomicCoverage><taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Clupea</taxonRankValue>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>pallasi</taxonRankValue>
 <commonName>Pacific Herring</commonName>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact><references>1358364277441</references>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><title>Objective 1: Consolidate herring data sets, metadata and other electronic resources to publicly accessible web portal for herring information</title>
 <para>Existing herring data sets and electronic resources were assessed, salvaged, documented with metadata and centralized to a common access point for distribution and public access. Much of this work was manual and extremely tedious in nature, required substantial staff resources within ADF&amp;G and required a large amount of the funding provided by this project to spatially enable and digitize these datasets. Data sets were documented via the Federal Geographic Data Committee (FGDC) metadata standard. The metadata document will provide critical contextual information for researchers to use, locate and interpret the data set. Data sets will be stored in aggregated standardized file formats and corresponding FGDC metadata will be authored as an XML document. Both the data set and corresponding metadata document will be available for public download and have been submitted to EVOSTC with this report.</para>
 <para>ADF&amp;G technicians were responsible for digitizing and aggregating data sets contained within the Cordova ADF&amp;G office. Staff members at Axiom Consulting &amp; Design were involved in directing digitization efforts at ADF&amp;G and dictated intermediary data formats for prepping data for secondary processing. Once data were digitized and aggregated by ADF&amp;G staff, Axiom staff further processed the digitized data files into flattened relational database tables. The data was then integrated into the PWS Herring Data Portal data management system. Finally, FGDC metadata was created to document the salvaged data resource.</para>
 <para>In order to efficiently integrate and manage the various data sets necessary to performing the data salvage required by this study, the study team adhered to a standard geospatial data framework. The following section details the specific data management methods that enabled the principal investigators to efficiently manage the diverse data sets required to perform the activities of this project.</para>
 <para>Geospatial Data Model</para>
 <para>Initially, data integration efforts undertaken by this project used a geospatial data structure developed during 2007 and 2008 to store and manage spatially enabled information. In late 2008 and 2009, this initial approach was abandoned in light of emerging open source interoperability systems, standards and formats. The first initial data model was engineered using Online Analytical Processing (OLAP) data warehousing specifications. This type of data structure is inherently designed to store data and information that is in a static and finalized state. This type of database schema is optimized for analysis and rapid data access. As more data sets were salvaged, processed and loaded into the below structure, it became clear that this approach was not flexible enough to store and manage the wide array of potentially valuable data sets (raster, imagery and model outputs) requested by users of the PWS Herring Portal. Additionally, as data were imported into the OLAP structure's fact table the performance of the system did not scale well with increasing data volume. By the end of the project's second year it became clear to PIs that this strategy would not be viable for providing high performance access and data visualization and that a new approach would need to be adopted.</para>
 <para>Late in 2008 the principal investigators changed their data management approach to focus on interoperability systems and formats which provided a number of tangible benefits over the previous strategy. The new framework relied upon interoperability concepts to provide an extremely flexible environment for storing a wide variety of data types and formats. The technical foundation of the data management platform relies upon a suite of existing and mature open source software tools and informatics efforts that are actively supported by the open source community and prolifically used by data management experts on a worldwide scale. Consequently, this framework allowed investigators to build upon a constantly maturing set of technologies by simply tapping into the efforts of a large body of programmers and developers who are committed to advancing these technologies. Using open source technologies also enabled the system to scale in a cost-effective manner by allowing additional hardware to be configured to support the growing user base without increases in software licensing costs. Integrating available sources of interoperable data feeds into data access applications and data management systems allowed a variety of data resources to be accessed by the PWS Herring Data Portal at low cost. Large quantities of real-time and historical sensor information, remote sensing satellite information and marine habitat and biological data for the Alaska region are openly available for use through interoperability protocols. For example, NASA Earth Observations (NEO) provides an expansive array of long-term oceanographic, climate and atmospheric remote sensing datasets. Real-time and historical sensor data feeds for the PWS region are available for sensors via SNOTEL, the National Data Buoy Center (NDBC), the Center for Operational Oceanographic Products and Services (CO-OPS) and other NOAA programs. Additional sources of interoperable data include those hosted at NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory (JPL), U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) TerraServer and other research organizations.</para>
 <para>Data Standards</para>
 <para>This effort adhered to the following data and metadata standards.</para>
 <para>Open Geospatial Consortium (OGC) Simple Feature Specification</para>
 <para>Federal Geospatial Data Committee (FGDC) metadata standard</para>
 <para>This project did not collect measurements; rather, it digitized and geospatially enabled data sets existing within ADF&amp;G in an unorganized state. This involved the creation of FGDC compliant metadata for those resources lacking metadata. Data sets were also up scaled in their data structures to ensure that information contained within the resource could be accessible to and understood by other scientists and the public. Methods such as standard-based naming conventions and normalization of relational database structures were used whenever appropriate. GIS information was structured into a geospatial database following Open GIS Consortium standards to ensure longevity and usability of the geospatial data.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Objective 2: Provide web-accessible map-based visualizations of geospatially enabled herring data and provide user interfaces for querying and downloading raw data and metadata</title>
 <para>A core strategy of the PWS Herring Data Portal was to create web-based access to spatially explicit visualizations of salvaged data sets. Early in this project, Google Earth was chosen as a platform for visualization of data sets to be served off the PWS Herring Portal. These 4- dimensional visualizations allowed users to view spatial and temporal aspects of the data set. Users could filter by location or time span.</para>
 <para>Data visualizations channeled through Google Earth provide a method for users to rapidly assess and comprehend data sets in their entirety, but this platform only provides data visualization.</para>
 <para>After a series of demonstrations to various user groups (scientists, resource managers and the general public), it became apparent that users required both visualization and data access in order for the portal to be truly useful as a data management platform. For this reason, PIs determined in year two of the project that a web-based interface to the underlying data must be developed in order to create tools for users to query and extract data in raw formats. This change in the strategy for developing the PWS Herring Data Portal interface was driven by user feedback to the PWS Herring Portal. The Standard Operating Procedures document included as an appendix to this report goes into greater detail regarding the process of acquiring user feedback, isolating user groups and consolidating feedback into formulating the new technical strategy. The overall response from users was consolidated into the following directives regarding redesign:</para>
 <para>1. Data stored in the portal needs to be made available in the following formats when applicable (ESRI Shapefile Output, Excel Files, Microsoft Access Databases).</para>
 <para>2. Users need to be able to create and download subsets of information that have been queried by space, time and measurements values.</para>
 <para>3. Users will need to have the ability to query across multiple data sets via the same parameters (space, time and measurements).</para>
 <para>This new system involved storing spatial data directly in the PostgresSQL PostGIS spatial database.</para>
 <para>The following is a description of the technologies referenced in Figure 3 broken into logical information processing tiers. Tier 1 corresponds to data storage (Database), tier 2 corresponds with analysis and aggregation of information (Business Logic) and tier 3 concerns visualization and access tools (Client Interfaces).</para>
 <para>Relational Database</para>
 <para>SQL Server 2008 database: SQL Server 2008 is a robust and mature platform for storing complex tabular, relational and spatial information. It is compliant with both ASCI SQL and Open Geospatial Consortium (OGC) specifications, enabling SQL Server to communicate with other enterprise relational databases and commercial and public GIS interfaces such as Geoserver, Mapserver and ESRI products. More information about OGC can be found at http://www.opengeospatial.org/standards. The SQL server was used to store a database of underlying data layers and their associated metadata and dimensional characteristics. This component of the data system is distinct from the GIS data and constitutes the asset catalogue which will be further described in this document.</para>
 <para>PostgreSQL: Is an open source relational database which provides advanced functionality to store and analyze spatial information. It is also OGC compliant liker SQL Server. All GIS enabled data layers were stored in the PostgreSQL instance.</para>
 <para>Web Services</para>
 <para>OGC Services were handled by Geoserver (www.geoserver.org), an open source java-based server system designed to render web accessible maps and package data into a wide variety of data formats. Geoserver is OGC compliant and works well with many GIS clients (ESRI Arc View, Google Maps, Google Earth and others). The Geoserver instance allows data to be accessed via Web Map Services (WMS) and Web Feature Services (WFS).</para>
 <para>Web Services for the PWS Herring Data Portal user interface were written in Cold Fusion for rapid prototyping. This included the services which powered the user interface tools.</para>
 <para>Tier 3 User Interface</para>
 <para>Data visualization, processing and extraction tools for the users are available via a web-based browser interface using the JQuery javascript library and Google maps code base.</para>
 <para>The PWS Herring Data Portal is powered by an internal database (asset catalogue) of data sources and their characteristics. The asset catalogue implemented for the data management framework is a simple system that stores information about available</para>
 <para>data resources. At the most granular level, the system tracks information about individual data layers including name, description, time span, access methods, service urls and symbology. These layers are grouped into various layer groups and further organized into specific application configurations. Time period information is also stored for data resources with discrete time coverages. A web service library developed by Axiom software engineers provides the application with access to information in the asset catalog through simplified methods such as GetDataCatalog, GetLayers and GetTimePeriods. The use of an intermediate web service library allows multiple applications running in different domains to access the asset catalogue while simultaneously concealing its inner complexities. Several automated import tools have been developed which periodically update the asset catalogue with information about data resources on remote systems.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Objective 3: Develop Standard Operating Procedures (SOPs) which document system implementation and provide direction for the absorption of additional herring ecosystem data sets, metadata and information to the centralized herring data system</title>
 <para>The Standard Operating Procedures (SOPs) technical document is attached as an appendix to this final report and provides a strategic approach to developing data management tools for ecological and physical data sets as they pertain to an ecosystem based herring monitoring program. The document is driven by the best practices and conceptual understanding that was developed during the project. Additionally, this document details technical underpinnings of the PWS Herring Data Portal (technical documentation). The ultimate goal of this document is to direct future data management efforts to power ecosystem approaches to research.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Objective 4: Develop Arcpad application to automate herring spawn data collection</title>
 <para>PIs were also tasked with developing and supporting an ESRI Arcpad application to facilitate automated data collection of herring aerial survey spawn and biomass observations in addition to ancillary species observations. This primarily involved software engineering and data preparation for GIS base layers to power the Aerial Survey application. The tool underwent several seasonal revisions (three separate releases over three years) based upon feedback and functionality requests of biologists using the application. The application was updated and overhauled at the beginning of each season based upon functional limitations isolated from the previous season's aerial survey program. ADF&amp;G staff members beta tested the application and were tasked with providing comments which were prioritized and then implemented by Axiom software engineers.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 <project><title>Herring Data and Information Portal</title>
 <personnel id="1366401557493"><individualName><givenName>Steve</givenName>
 <surName>Moffitt</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Alaska Department of Fish and Game</organizationName>
 <positionName>Principal Investigator during 2007-2008</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>401 Railroad Avenue P.O. Box 669</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Cordova</city>
 <administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>99574</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">907-424-3212</phone>
 <phone phonetype="fax">907-424-3235</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>steve.moffitt@alaska.gov</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </personnel>
 <personnel id="1366401530214"><individualName><givenName>Rob</givenName>
 <surName>Bochenek</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Axiom Consulting &amp; Design</organizationName>
 <positionName>Principal Investigator during 2009, Data Custodian</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>523 West 8th Ave</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>Suite 104</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Anchorage,</city>
 <administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>99501</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">(907)-230-0304</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>rob@axiomalaska.com</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </personnel>
 <funding><para>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Countil (EVOSTC) project numbers 090822, 080822, 070822, 98225, 98220-CLO</para>
 </funding>
 </project>
 <otherEntity><entityName>Moffitt - Herring Data Portal.zip</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Contains GIS shapefiles, xml files, and databases used to create the herring data portal.</entityDescription>
 <physical><objectName>Moffitt - Herring Data Portal.zip</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">84745379</size>
 <dataFormat><externallyDefinedFormat><formatName>application/octet-stream</formatName>
 </externallyDefinedFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution id="1367344376600"><online><url function="download">ecogrid://knb/df35a.42.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <entityType>Other</entityType>
 </otherEntity>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>