<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="df35b.114.6" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"><allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow><principal>cn=evos,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>all</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset> <title>Evaluating Harlequin Duck Population Recovery: CYP1A Monitoring and Population Data (2006, 2007, 2009)</title>
 <creator id="1375741618557"> <individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation>
 <givenName>Dan</givenName>
 <surName>Esler</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Simon Fraser Univeristy</organizationName>
 <positionName>Adjunct Professor, research associate</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>Centre for Wildlife Ecology</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>5421 Robertson Road</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Delta</city>
 <administrativeArea>BC</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>V4K 3N2</postalCode>
 <country>Canada</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">778-782-3980</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>desler@sfu.ca</electronicMailAddress>
 <onlineUrl>http://www.sfu.ca/biology/wildberg/desler/index.html</onlineUrl>
 </creator>
 <associatedParty><references>1375741618557</references>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty id="1375742050201"><individualName><givenName>Samuel</givenName>
 <surName>Iverson</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Carleton University, Ottawa</organizationName>
 <positionName>PhD candidate</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>Department of Biology</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>1125 Colonel By Drive</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Ottawa</city>
 <administrativeArea>ON</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>K1S 5B6</postalCode>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">613-998-7294</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>siverson@fastmail.fm</electronicMailAddress>
 <onlineUrl>https://sites.google.com/site/siversoncarelton/Home</onlineUrl>
 <role>Author</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty id="1375742223253"><individualName><givenName>Jessica</givenName>
 <surName>Couture</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis</organizationName>
 <positionName>Research Assistant</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis, Unversity of California, Santa Barbara</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>735 State St.</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Santa Barbara</city>
 <administrativeArea>CA</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>93101</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">805-892-2500</phone>
 <phone phonetype="fax">805-892-2510</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>couture@nceas.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Metadata Provider</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <abstract><para>Harlequin ducks have been studied extensively in Prince William Sound during the restoration phase following the Exxon Valdez oil spill, leading to one of the most thorough considerations of wildlife population injury and recovery following a major oil spill ever undertaken. These efforts have included population monitoring by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service and the Alaska Department of Fish and Game, as well as a series of directed research projects designed to elucidate the process of, and constraints to, population recovery. These studies demonstrated that harlequin ducks were exposed to lingering oil over a much longer time frame (i.e., through at least 2005, 16 years following the spill) than expected at the time of the spill, based on elevated levels of cytochrome P4501A induction in birds from oiled areas. In addition, several lines of evidence suggested that population injury occurred through at least 1998. Specifically, female winter survival probabilities were found to differ between oiled and unoiled areas, and densities were shown to be lower in oiled than unoiled areas after accounting for habitat-related effects. More recent data have indicated that female winter survival did not differ between oiled and unoiled sites during 2000-03, suggesting that direct effects of oil exposure on demographic properties may have abated.
In response to the data described above, the work here was proposed to add to the existing cytochrome P4501A monitoring data to track the timeline of exposure to lingering oil, and to assemble the demographic data collected during previous restoration studies into a quantitative population model to allow consideration of the timing and magnitude of oil spill injury, the mechanisms by which injury occurred and population recovery was constrained, and the current status of recovery, including predictions for timing of full recovery.

 FINDINGS: We found that cytochrome P4501A induction during winters 2005, 2006-07, and 2009 was higher in harlequin ducks captured in areas of Prince William Sound oiled by the 1989 Exxon Valdez spill, relative to unoiled areas. Cytochrome P4501A induction did not vary in relation to age, sex, or mass of individuals, nor did it vary strongly by season in samples collected early and late in the winter. We interpret these results to indicate that harlequin ducks continued to be exposed to residual Exxon Valdez oil up to 20 years after the original spill. Population modeling efforts indicated that female mortality related to chronic exposure to lingering oil was nearly double that estimated during the acute phase (the weeks and months immediately post-spill). Full recovery to pre-spill numbers was estimated to require between 13 and 32 years, with the most likely recovery scenario requiring roughly 24 years. Taken together, the data presented in this report add to a growing body of literature suggesting that effects of oil spills on wildlife have the potential to be expressed over much longer time frames than previously assumed.

More details on methods and analysis can be found in the final report: Esler, D. and S. A. Iverson. 2010. Evaluating harlequin duck population recovery: CYP1A monitoring and a demographic population model. Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Restoration Project Final Report (Project 070816), Centre for Wildlife Ecology, Simon Fraser University, Delta, British Columbia, Canada.</para>
 </abstract>
<keywordSet><keyword>biomarker</keyword>
<keyword>cytochrome P4501A</keyword>
<keyword>demography</keyword>
<keyword>harlequin ducks</keyword>
<keyword>Historionicus historionicus</keyword>
<keyword>oil exposure</keyword>
<keyword>population model</keyword>
<keyword>Prince William Sound</keyword>
<keyword>recovery</keyword>
<keywordThesaurus>Report</keywordThesaurus>
</keywordSet>
<keywordSet><keyword>EVOSTC</keyword>
<keyword>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council</keyword>
<keyword>Oil Spill</keyword>
<keyword>Exxon Valdez</keyword>
<keyword>Pelagic</keyword>
<keyword>Birds</keyword>
<keyword>Oil and Contaminants</keyword>
<keywordThesaurus>Gulf Watch Alaska Thesaurus</keywordThesaurus>
</keywordSet>
   <intellectualRights><para>This material is based upon work funded by the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council.  Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed herein are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views or positions of the Trustee Council.

Standard scientific norms for attribution and credit should be followed when using these data including to the Owners, Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council and other sources of funding. Please let the Owner know when these data are used.
 
These data are licensed under CC0. The person who associated a work with this deed has dedicated the work to the public domain by waiving all of his or her rights to the work worldwide under copyright law, including all related and neighboring rights, to the extent allowed by law. You can copy, modify, distribute and perform the work, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</para>
 </intellectualRights>
 <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Prince William Sound, Alaska</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-152.62762</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>-145.99754</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>61.12401</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>58.50127</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2006</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate><calendarDate>2007</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><singleDateTime><calendarDate>2009</calendarDate>
 </singleDateTime>
 </temporalCoverage>
 <taxonomicCoverage><taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Histrionicus</taxonRankValue>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>histrionicus</taxonRankValue>
 <commonName>Harlequin duck</commonName>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact><references>1375741618557</references>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><title>Capture</title>
 <para>To facilitate comparisons, the present study closely followed the design and procedures of Trust et al. (2000). We captured wintering harlequin ducks using a modified floating mist net (Kaiser et al. 1995) during four capture periods: March 2005, November 2006, March and April 2007, and March 2009. Birds were captured in a number of areas oiled during the Exxon Valdez spill, including Bay of Isles (60 deg 22' N, 147 deg 40' W), Crafton Island (60 deg 29' N, 147deg 57' W), Green Island (60 deg18'N, 147 deg 24' W), and Foul Pass (60 deg 29' N, 147 deg 38' W). Also, birds were captured on nearby northwestern Montague Island (60 deg 15' N, 147deg 12' W), which was not oiled and thus was considered a reference site. Harlequin ducks in Prince William Sound exhibit high site fidelity during winter, with 94% remaining all winter on the same island or coastline region where they were originally captured and only 2% moving between oiled and unoiled areas (Iverson and Esler 2006). We assume that this level of movement had little influence on our ability to draw inferences about differences in EROD activity between areas. Captured birds were placed in portable pet carriers and transported by skiff to a chartered research vessel for processing. Each individual was marked with a uniquely-numbered, U.S. Fish and Wildlife metal tarsus band; the band number was used to identify the data and samples for that individual. Sex of each bird was determined by plumage and cloacal characteristics, and age class was determined by the depth of the bursa of Fabricius for females and bursal depth and plumage characteristics for males (Mather and Esler 1999, Smith et al. 1998). Age class was summarized as either hatch-year (HY), i.e., hatched the previous breeding season, or after-hatch-year (AHY). Numbers of individuals used in analyses of CYP1A induction are indicated in Table 1, by year, season, age class, sex, and area (oiled versus unoiled).</para>
 <para>Iverson, S. A., and D. Esler. 2006. Site fidelity and the demographic implications of winter movements by a migratory bird, the harlequin duck. Journal of Avian Biology 37: 219-228.</para>
 <para>Kaiser, G. W., A. E. Derocher, S. C. Crawford, M. J. Gill, and I. A. Manley. 1995. A capture technique for marbled murrelets in coastal inlets. Journal of Field Ornithology 66: 321-333.</para>
 <para>Mather, D. D., and D. Esler. 1999. Evaluation of bursal depth as an indicator of age class of harlequin ducks. Journal of Field Ornithology 70: 200-205.</para>
 <para>Smith, C. M., R. I. Goudie, and F. Cooke. 1998. Winter age ratios and the assessment of recruitment of Harlequin Ducks. Waterbirds 24: 39-44.</para>
 <para>Trust, K. A., D. Esler, B. R. Woodin, and J. J. Stegeman. 2000. Cytochrome P450 1A induction in sea ducks inhabiting nearshore areas of Prince William Sound, Alaska. Marine Pollution Bulletin 40: 397-403.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Tissue sample collection</title>
 <para>Small (&lt; 0.5 g) liver biopsies were surgically removed by a veterinarian from each harlequin duck while they were under general anesthesia using vaporized and inhaled Isoflurane. Once removed, liver samples were immediately placed into a labeled cryovial and frozen in liquid nitrogen. All samples were maintained in liquid nitrogen or a -80 degC freezer until they were shipped to the lab in liquid nitrogen.</para>
 <para>During March 2005 sampling, two liver biopsies were taken from each individual and sent to different laboratories for EROD analysis. Dual samples were taken to allow inter-laboratory comparisons for validation of analytical integrity and inference of exposure between oiled and unoiled areas. One of the paired samples was sent to Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution (WHOI), where all pre-2005 samples were analyzed, and the other to the University of California Davis (UCD), where analyses were conducted in subsequent years. Both labs conducted all analyses without a priori knowledge of the areas from which the samples were collected and neither lab had access to the data from the other.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Statisitcal Analyses</title>
 <para>Four analyses were conducted to evaluate variation in EROD activity. First, results from the WHOI and UCD laboratories were compared for paired samples collected during March 2005 to determine if consistent results were obtained. Next, EROD activity was evaluated in relation to capture location (oiled or unoiled area) and individual attributes (age, sex, and body mass) for the March 2005 samples using data from both WHOI and UCD laboratories. Third, EROD activity was evaluated in relation to location of capture, individual attributes, and season for samples obtained during November 2006 and March/April 2007 and analyzed at the UCD laboratory. Finally, variation in EROD activity was analyzed in relation to capture location and individual attributes for birds captures during March 2009. Separate analyses were run for data from each winter because we wished to compare results from both labs in 2005, so analyzing 2005 separately facilitated direct comparison of inferences from each data set. Also, considerable variation can occur between laboratory runs (Esler 2008); this does not affect contrasts between treatments within runs, but could complicate interpretation across runs. Finally, different sets of explanatory variables were used among winters, as seasonal effects could only be evaluated using data from winter 2006-07. For consistency, results from the UCD lab were used as the primary data, although results and inferences were contrasted across both labs for the 2005 data.</para>
 <para>Esler, D. 2008. Quantifying temporal variation in Harlequin Duck cytochrome P4501A induction. Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council Gulf Ecosystem Monitoring and Research Project Final Report (GEM Project 050777), Centre for Wildlife Ecology, Simon Fraser University, Delta, British Columbia, Canada.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
<project><title>Evaluating Harlequin Duck Population Recovery: CYP1A Monitoring and a Demographic Population Model</title>
<personnel><references>1375741618557</references>
<role>Principal Investigator</role>
</personnel>
<funding><para>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council project number 070816</para>
</funding>
</project>
  <dataTable id="1375807700982"><entityName>harDuckRecovCY1A.csv</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Harlequin duck EROD and samples data</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1375806421890"><objectName>harDuckRecovCY1A.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">12669</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/df35b.116.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1375807700983"><attributeName>date</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Date</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Date of capture</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>YYYY-MM-DD</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375807700984"><attributeName>oiled</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>oiled site?</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Indicates whether birds were captured in areas &#8220;oiled&#8221; by the Exxon Valdez spill or in &#8220;unoiled&#8221; areas.  This is not intended to imply whether or not oil was present at the time of capture.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>oiledUnoiled</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375807700985"><attributeName>site</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>site of capture</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Capture location</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>DISKI</code>
 <definition>Disk Island</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>SPORTCHAL</code>
 <definition>South Port Chalmers</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>BAYOFISL</code>
 <definition>Bay of Isles</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>CRAFTONI</code>
 <definition>Crafton Island</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>SSTCKDALE</code>
 <definition>South Stockdale Harbor</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>NGREEN</code>
 <definition>North Green Island</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>WGREEN</code>
 <definition>West Green Island</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>HERRING</code>
 <definition>Herring Bay</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>GIBBONS</code>
 <definition>Gibbons Anchorage</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>PORTCHAL</code>
 <definition>Port Chalmers</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>STCKDALE</code>
 <definition>Stockdale Harbor</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>NSTCKDALE</code>
 <definition>North Stockdale Harbor</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375807700986"><attributeName>lat</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Latitude</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Latitude in degrees minutes</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </interval>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375807700987"><attributeName>lon</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Longitude</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Longitude in degrees minutes</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </interval>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375807700988"><attributeName>bandNum</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Band Number</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>The unique number on the metal U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service band affixed to the bird&#8217;s leg.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>band number</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375807700989"><attributeName>species</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>speceis</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Abbreviation for the species of each individual (HADU = harlequin duck).</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>HADU</code>
 <definition>Halequin duck</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375807700990"><attributeName>sex</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Sex</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Abbreviation for the sex of each individual.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>M</code>
 <definition>male</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>F</code>
 <definition>female</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375807700991"><attributeName>age</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Age class</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Abbreviation for the age class of each individual. ('hatch year', HY, designated individuals hatched in the previous summer)</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>AHY</code>
 <definition>after hatch year</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>ATY</code>
 <definition>after third year</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>HY</code>
 <definition>hatch year</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>TY</code>
 <definition>third year</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>SY</code>
 <definition>second year</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375807700992"><attributeName>age2</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Age Class 2</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Abbreviation for the age class of each individual, simplified into 2 categories. ('hatch year', HY, designated individuals hatched in the previous summer)</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>AHY</code>
 <definition>after hatch year</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>HY</code>
 <definition>hatch year</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375807700993"><attributeName>bodywt</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Body weight</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Mass of each individual (g)</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1375807700994"><attributeName>erod</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>EROD activity</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>7-ethoxyresorufin-O-deethylase activity (pmol/min/mg)</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>129</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>