<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="df35b.3.16" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"> <allow> <principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow> <principal>cn=evos,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 <permission>write</permission>
 <permission>changePermission</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset scope="document"> <title>Pacific Herring (Clupea pallasii) Stable Isotope Tracers: Food Webs of Fishes-Prince William Sound, Alaska (1994-1998)</title>
 <creator id="1352251165373" scope="document"> <individualName> <givenName>Thomas C.</givenName>
 <surName>Kline</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Prince William Sound Science Center</organizationName>
 <address scope="document"> <deliveryPoint>P. O. Box 705</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Cordova</city>
 <administrativeArea>Alaska</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>99574</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <electronicMailAddress>tkline@pwssc.org</electronicMailAddress>
 </creator>
 <associatedParty id="1370018950898"><individualName><givenName>Jessica</givenName>
 <surName>Couture</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis</organizationName>
 <positionName>Research Assistant</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>735 State St</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Santa Barbara</city>
 <administrativeArea>CA</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>93101</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <electronicMailAddress>couture@nceas.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Metadata Provider</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <abstract><para>This project is a component of the Sound Ecosystem Assessment (SEA) program, a multi-disciplinary effort to acquire an ecosystem level understanding of the marine and freshwater processes that interact to constrain levels of fish, marine bird, and marine mammal production in Prince William Sound (PWS). Research conducted under the Sound Ecosystem Assessment project (SEA, /320) has shown that Pacific herring have significant dependence on Gulf of Alaska carbon. Accordingly, herring are subject to changes in carbon flow occurring between the Gulf of Alaska and Prince William Sound. The first step in understanding how this fundamental environmental process affects herring recruitment is to isotopically analyze a time series of herring for which energetic data have been collected. This will expand upon the data series available from SEA, providing a total four-year time period corresponding to one period in the cyclicity of herring population abundance in Prince William Sound. (Source: EVOSTC website)

-----Funding and Support Provided by: 
Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council (EVOSTC), 
Sound Ecosystme Assessment (SEA), 
Global Ocean Ecosystem Dynamics (GLOBEC)

-----Sources cited:

Norcross, B. L., E. D. Brown, K. D. E. Stokesbury, and M. Frandsen. 1996. Juvenile herring growth and habitat, Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Restoration Project Annual Report (Restoration Project 95320T), University of Alaska Fairbanks, Institute of Marine Science, Fairbanks, Alaska.

Kline, T.C. 1999. Temporal and spatial variability of 13C/12C and 15N/14N in pelagic biota of Prince Willam Sound, Alaska. canadian Journal of Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences 56(Suppl. 1):94-117.

Kline, T.C. Jr. 2001. The trophic position of Pacific herring in Prince William Sound, Alaska based on their stable isotope abundance. In: F. Funk, J. Blakkburn, D. Hay, A.J. Paul, R. Stephenson, R. Toresen and D. Witherell, editors. Herring: Expectations for a New Millenium. University of Alaska Sea Grant, Fairbanks, AK. AK-SG-01-04. p. 69-80. 


-----Publications:

Kline, T. C. Jr. 1997. Confirming forage fish food web dependencies in the Prince William Sound ecosystem using natural stable isotope tracers. Proceedings of the International Symposium on the Role of Forage Fishes in Marine Ecosystems. Alaska Sea Grant College Program Report No. 9701. University of Alaska Fairbanks. P. 257 - 269.

Kline, T. C. Jr. 1998. Salmon Fry. In: T. A. Okey and D. Pauly (eds), A Trophic Mass-Balance Model of Alaskas Prince William Sound Ecosystem, for the Post-Spill Period 1994-1996. Fisheries Centre Research Reports 1998 Volume 6 Number 4. Fisheries Centre, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, Canada. p. 26-3 1. (included in the ECOPATH project (Pauly and Pimm, P.1.s) final report)

Kline, T.C. Jr. and D. Pauly. 1998. Cross-validation of trophic level estimates from a mass-balance model of Prince William Sound using 15N/14N data. In: Funk, F., T.J. Quinn II, J. Heifetz, J.N. Ianelli, J.E. Powers, J.F. Schweigert, P.J. Sullivan, and C.I. Zhang (eds.), Fishery Stock Assessment Models. University of Alaska Sea Grant, AK-SG-98-01. Fairbanks, Alaska. p. 693-702. 

Kline, T.C., Jr. 1999. Temporal and spatial variability of 13C/12C and 15N/14N in pelagic biota of Prince William Sound, Alaska. Canadian Journal of Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences. Vol. 56, Suppl. 1, pg. 94-117. 
 
Kline, T. C. Jr. 1999. Carbon and Nitrogen Isotopic Composition of Prince William Sound Pelagic Biota Shift on Annual Time Scales: A Tool for Monitoring Changes in Oceanographic Forcing. In: Ecosystem Consideration in Fisheries Management. Proceedings of the International Symposium on Ecosystem Consideration in Fisheries Management. Alaska Sea Grant College program Report No. 99-01. University of Alaska Fairbanks. IN PRESS: (included in Project 3 11 (Kline P.I.) final report)

Norcross, B. L., E. D. Brown, S. Gay, R. J. Foy, M. Jin, T. Kline, J. Kirsch, D. Mason, C. N. K. Mooers, V. Patrick, A. J. Paul, IS. D. E. Stokesbury, S. J. Thornton, S. Vaughan, J. Wang. Biological and Physical Effects on the Early Life History of Herring in Prince William Sound, Alaska. (to be submitted to Fisheries Oceanography, included in project 320 SEA-Synthesis (Cooney et al.) final report)

Kline, T.C. Jr. 1999a. Monitoring Changes in Oceanographic Forcing Using the Carbon and Nitrogen Isotopic Composition of Prince William Sound Pelagic Biota. In: Ecosystem Approaches for Fisheries Management. University of Alaska Sea Grant, AK-SG-99-01, Fairbanks. p. 87-95

Kline, Thomas C., Jr. 2000. Prince William Sound Food Webs: Structure and Change, Exxon Valdez Restoration Project Annual Report (Restoration Project 99393), Prince William Sound Science Center, Cordova, Alaska.

Eslinger, D.L., R.T. Cooney, C.P. McRoy, A. Ward, T.C. Kline Jr., E.P. Simpson, J. Wang and J.R. Allen. 2001. Plankton dynamics: observed and modeled responses to physical conditions in Prince William Sound, Alaska. Fisheries Oceanography 10 (Suppl. 1):81-96.

Norcross, B.L., E.D. Brown, R.J. Foy, M. Frandsen, S.M. Gay III, T.C. Kline Jr., D.M. Mason, E.V. Patrick, A.J. Paul and K.D.E. Stokesbury. 2001. A synthesis of the life history and ecology of juvenile Pacific herring in Prince William Sound, Alaska. Fisheries Oceanography 10, (Suppl. 1):42-57.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>Pacific Herring</keyword>
 <keyword>Stable Isotopes</keyword>
 <keyword>Food Web</keyword>
 <keyword>Carbon flow</keyword>
 <keyword>Prince William Sound</keyword>
 <keyword>Ecosystem</keyword>
 <keyword>Alaska</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet><keyword>EVOSTC</keyword>
 <keyword>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council</keyword>
 <keyword>Oil Spill</keyword>
 <keyword>Exxon Valdez</keyword>
 <keyword>Fish</keyword>
 <keyword>Oil and Contaminants</keyword>
 <keyword>Environmental Drivers</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>Gulf Watch Alaska Thesaurus</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <intellectualRights> <para>This material is based upon work funded by the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council under Project No. (320-I).  Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed herein are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views or positions of the Trustee Council.

Additional funding sources:
Sound Ecosystem Assessment (SEA),
Global Ocean Ecosystem Dynamics (GLOBEC)

Standard scientific norms for attribution and credit to the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council and any additional funding agencies should be followed when using this data. Please let the Owner know when this data is used.

This data is licensed under CC0. The person who associated a work with this deed has dedicated the work to the public domain by waiving all of his or her rights to the work worldwide under copyright law, including all related and neighboring rights, to the extent allowed by law. You can copy, modify, distribute and perform the work, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</para>
 </intellectualRights>
 <coverage scope="document"> <temporalCoverage scope="document"> <rangeOfDates> <beginDate> <calendarDate>1994-04-26</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate> <calendarDate>1998-03-19</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 <taxonomicCoverage scope="document"> <taxonomicClassification> <taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Clupea</taxonRankValue>
 <taxonomicClassification> <taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>pallasii</taxonRankValue>
 <commonName>Pacific Herring</commonName>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicCoverage>
 <geographicCoverage scope="document"> <geographicDescription>Prince William Sound, Alaska, USA</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates> <westBoundingCoordinate>-149.125</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>-144.125</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>61.875</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>58.375</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact scope="document"> <references>1352251165373</references>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><title>Herring collection and processing</title>
 <para>All herring sampled from April 1994 to March 1998 for which length data (standard length) were available were pooled and analyzed for trend using a scatterplot and regressed for best fit using R2 and P values. Commencing in the fall of 1995, juvenile herring - &lt; 15 cm in length were sampled at four sites within PWS at approximately 1.5 month intervals between March 1996 and October 1997 (Kline 2000). This four-bay time-series enabled assessing finer scale temporal variability in several parameters (whole-body and diet energetics, growth, diet composition) for age 0 and 1 PWS herring than had been previously examined (Norcross et al. 1996). The - N = 25 from each site-sampling that were isotopically analyzed are reported here with SD estimation. Age 0 and 1 herring were pooled for this analysis since it was not possible to split the data by age and also retain both the temporal and spatial coverage. Thus ontogenetic effects were examined using a separate data selection that also benefited by including data from additional PWS sites (Kline 1999).</para>
 <para>Kline (2001)</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Pacific Herring Collection</title>
 <para>Juvenile Pacific herring (N = 360) and walleye pollock (N = 287) were collected throughout PWS opportunistically during 1994 and from a multivessel broadscale survey (Norcross et al. 1996) conducted from October to November 1995 (Fig. 1). During the broadscale survey, a lead acoustic vessel located concentrations of fishes, which were then sampled with a purse seine (50 m diameter by 4 m deep with 3-mm mesh (stretched)). On the trailing vessel, a random sample of 200 Pacific herring (range about 70 to 150 mm standard length (ages 0 and 1)) and 200 walleye pollock (range about 70 to100 mm fork length (age 0)) were immediately frozen in seawater at each study site for paired energetic (Paul et al. 1998) and isotopic analysis (this study). Laboratory handling procedures were described by Paul et al. (1998). Following energetic analysis (Paul et al. 1998), dried fish samples were sent from Seward, Alaska, to Cordova, Alaska, for isotopic analysis preparation. For 1995 sampling, 25 Pacific herring and 25 walleye pollock were randomly selected from each sampling area, ground to a fine powder, sealed in polyethylene LSC (Wheaton) vials, and shipped to the University of Alaska Fairbanks Stable Isotope Facility for isotopic analysis. In 1994, fish samples were obtained using similar gear and analysis techniques.</para>
 <para>(Kline 1999)</para>
 <para>This data includes only Isotopic data for pacific herring.  Walleye and energetic data are not included in this data set. Similar sampling methods were used for years 1996-1998 sampling.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Stable Isotope Analysis</title>
 <para>Replicate subsamples of about 1.5 mg were taken from all samples except individual macrozooplankters, since the entire organism was required for a single analysis. Subsamples or whole zooplankters, as appropriate, were weighed to the nearest 1microgram and loaded into combustion boats for mass spectrometric analysis. Isotopic analyses were performed using a semiautomated stable isotope analyzer (Europa Scientific 20/20 equipped with a Roboprep sample combustion and purification unit). A single isotopic analysis generated the following data: C-13/C-12 and N-15/N-14 ratios expressed in standard delta units, C-13 and N-15, respectively, and %C and %N. The conventional delta notation used to express stable isotope ratios is reported relative to international standards (air for nitrogen and Vienna Peedee belemnite for carbon) By definition, the isotope standards have delta values of zero, i.e., N-15 = 0 for atmospheric N2. Typically, instrument replication is &lt;0.2ppt. The %C and %N data were used to calculate C/N atomic ratios. The data presented consist of mean C-13, N-15, and C/N for all replicated samples. Removal of lipid (DeNiro and Epstein 1977) and trophic level (see Introduction) effects from C-13 values of fish made it possible to assess carbon source (Kline 1997). C-13/C-12 content of PWS nekton was correlated with C/N (a proxy for lipid content) and N-15/N-14 content (a proxy for trophic level), thus requiring lipid and trophic level normalization (Kline 1997).</para>
 <para>(Kline 1999)</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Lipid-Normalized Stable Isotope Analysis</title>
 <para>The method of McConnaughey and McRoy (1979) was used to calculate lipid-normalized C-13/C-12, while the method of Kline (1997) was used to normalize for trophic level. Lipid normalization was based on C/N using a C/N = 4 as the base level (McConnaughey and McRoy 1979). Normalization for trophic level effects used (i) the N-15 value of the herbivore N. cristatus as the trophic level baseline (Vander Zanden et al. 1997) and (ii) an assumed constant nitrogen and carbon trophic fractionation factor ratio of 3.4:1. In general, normalization reduces sources of C-13 variability, enabling comparisons among species without the confounding effects of trophic level and lipid content (Kline 1997). Thus, normalized C-13/C-12 values of fishes could be compared directly with those of N. cristatus at a consistent lipid storage level. The expressions C-13, C-13', C-13TL, and C-13TL ' denote C-13/C-12 abundance in relation to the international standard, normalized for lipid content, normalized for trophic level, and normalized for lipid content and trophic level, respectively. Whereas C-13', C-13TL, and C-13TL' are used in accordance with a particular data analysis context, C-13 is used to reflect generic C-13/C-12 isotopic trends irrespective of normalization.</para>
 <para>(Kline 1999)</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <sampling><studyExtent><description><para>Adult and juvile Pacific Herring (Clupea pallasii) were collected from various sites in Prince William Sound in Alaska during the spring and summer months in 1994-1998.</para>
 </description>
 </studyExtent>
 <samplingDescription><para>At each site, 100 fish were randomly sampled and 25 individuals were subsampled from these for analysis.  All fish were frozen on site until being freeze dried and prepared for analysis.</para>
 </samplingDescription>
 </sampling>
 </methods>
<project><title>Sound Ecosystem Assessment (SEA):  Confirming Food Web Dependencies with SI tracers: Food webs of Fishes</title>
<personnel id="1352407804792"><individualName><givenName>Thomas C.</givenName>
<surName>Kline</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>Prince William Sound Science Center</organizationName>
<positionName>Biological Oceanographer</positionName>
<role>Principal Investigator</role>
</personnel>
<funding><para>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council project numbers 94320-I, 95320-I2, 96320-I, 97320-I, 98320-I, 98311, 99311;Prince William Sound Science Center; Global Ocean Ecosystem Dynamics (GLOBEC)</para>
</funding>
</project>
  <dataTable id="1352420964420" scope="document"> <entityName>Herring SEA Isotope.csv</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Stable Isotope and Trophic level data for Pacific Herring in Prince William Sound, 1994-1998</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1352419161741" scope="document"> <objectName>Herring SEA Isotope.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">359696</size>
 <dataFormat> <textFormat> <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited> <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution> <online> <url>ecogrid://knb/couture.10.2</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList> <attribute id="1352420964421" scope="document"> <attributeName>sampleID</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Code for Sample identification</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Alphanumeric sample identfier used to track samples; those with the format xHEy where x is a 2-digit year and y is a 1 to 3 digit number were samples initially processed by Dr. AJ Paul (U. of Alaska) who then provided Kline with the standard length and wet mass data along with the remaining sample</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <nominal> <nonNumericDomain> <textDomain> <definition>Sample identification</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964422" scope="document"> <attributeName>sampleDate</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Date sample was taken</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Calendar date when sample was collected</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <dateTime> <formatString>YYYY-MM-DD</formatString>
 <dateTimePrecision>1 day</dateTimePrecision>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964423" scope="document"> <attributeName>nominalMonth</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Month of sampling cruise</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Cruise month name when sample was collected</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <dateTime> <formatString>Month</formatString>
 <dateTimePrecision>1 month</dateTimePrecision>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964424" scope="document"> <attributeName>monthNumber</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Numeric month</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Month number (January = 1, February =2, etc.) when sample was collected</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <dateTime> <formatString>MM</formatString>
 <dateTimePrecision>1 month</dateTimePrecision>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964425" scope="document"> <attributeName>year</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Year sample was taken</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Year when sample was collected</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <dateTime> <formatString>YYYY</formatString>
 <dateTimePrecision>1 year</dateTimePrecision>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964426" scope="document"> <attributeName>trimester</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Trimester sample was taken</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Trimester of calendar year when sample was collected, Trimesters A+B = A, and Trimester C = B in Kline (2007)</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <dateTime> <formatString>YYYYx</formatString>
 <dateTimePrecision>Trimester (A, B, C)</dateTimePrecision>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964427" scope="document"> <attributeName>birthday</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Hypothetical birthdate of sampled fish</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Date agreed upon by SEA investigators as a hypothetical birthday, used to compute age in days</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <dateTime> <formatString>YYYY-MM-DD</formatString>
 <dateTimePrecision>1 day</dateTimePrecision>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964428" scope="document"> <attributeName>ageInDays</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Age of sampled fish (days)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Data used as the common independent variable to enable merging of data sets used in Norcross et al. (2001)</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <ratio> <unit> <customUnit>Age</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain> <numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964429" scope="document"> <attributeName>agePerBobFoy</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Adjusted age (per Bob Foy)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Herring age in years per instructions from Bob Foy (at the time a Ph. D. sudent of Dr. Brenda Norcross, U. of Alaska ), 0 or 1, otherwise A (putative adults)</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <interval> <unit> <customUnit>Age</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain> <numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </interval>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964430" scope="document"> <attributeName>cnMassRatio</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>C/N mass ratio</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Carbon/Nitrogen mass ratio, three significant figures</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <ratio> <unit> <customUnit>Ratio</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain> <numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964431" scope="document"> <attributeName>Lparameter</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>L parameter calculated from C/N atom ratio from McConnaughey and McRoy (1979), three significant figures</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <ratio> <unit> <customUnit>Ratio</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain> <numberType>natural</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964432" scope="document"> <attributeName>family</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Family</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Taxonomic family</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <nominal> <nonNumericDomain> <enumeratedDomain> <codeDefinition> <code>Clupeidae</code>
 <definition>Clupeidae</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964433" scope="document"> <attributeName>species</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Sample Genus and species</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Binomial scientific name  (genus and species)</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <nominal> <nonNumericDomain> <enumeratedDomain> <codeDefinition> <code>Clupea pallasii</code>
 <definition>Clupea pallasii</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964434" scope="document"> <attributeName>vernacular</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Common name</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Common name</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <nominal> <nonNumericDomain> <enumeratedDomain> <codeDefinition> <code>Pacific Herring</code>
 <definition>Pacific Herring</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964435" scope="document"> <attributeName>functionalGroup</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>The sample attributed functional group in the Prince William Sound Ecopath Model (Oakey and Pauly 1998)</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <nominal> <nonNumericDomain> <enumeratedDomain> <codeDefinition> <code>Herring Juvenile</code>
 <definition>Herring Juvenile</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition> <code>Herring Adult</code>
 <definition>Herring Adult</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964436" scope="document"> <attributeName>functionalGroupNumber</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Functional group number</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Number associated with functional group</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <ordinal> <nonNumericDomain> <textDomain> <definition>##</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </ordinal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964437" scope="document"> <attributeName>nitrogenStableIsotopeRatio</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Nitrogen SI ratio</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Nitrogen stable isotope ratio of the bulk sample in standard delta units relative to air to the nearest 0.1</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <ratio> <unit> <customUnit>Ratio</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain> <numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964438" scope="document"> <attributeName>carbonStableIsotopeRatio</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Carbon SI ratio</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Carbon stable isotope ratio of the bulk sample in standard delta units relative to VPDB to the nearest 0.1</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <ratio> <unit> <customUnit>Ratio</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain> <numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964439" scope="document"> <attributeName>cnAtomicRatio</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Carbon Nitrogen atomic ratio</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Carbon/Nitrogen atomic ratio calculated from mass ratio, three significant figures</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <ratio> <unit> <customUnit>Ratio</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain> <numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964440" scope="document"> <attributeName>correctedCarbonStableIsotopeLipid</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Corrected carbon SI ratio</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>d13C corrected for lipid content using the method of McConnaughey and McRoy 1979, to the nearest 0.1</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <ratio> <unit> <customUnit>Ratio</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain> <numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964441" scope="document"> <attributeName>tropohicLevelReference</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Trophic level reference</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Trophic level (TL) reference value used to TL normalize carbon stable isotpe ratio using method of Kline et al. (1998) and to calculate trophic level from nitrogen stable istope ratio using method of Kline (2001)</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <ratio> <unit> <customUnit>Ratio</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain> <numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964442" scope="document"> <attributeName>correctedStableIsotopeLipidAndTrophicLevel</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Corrected TL carbon SI ratio</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>d13C corrected for lipid content as well as TL using the methods of, respectively, McConnaughey and McRoy 1979 and Kline  et al. (1998), to the nearest 0.1</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <ratio> <unit> <customUnit>Ratio</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain> <numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964443" scope="document"> <attributeName>tropicLeve</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Trophic level</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Sample trophic level (TL) based on nitrogen stable isotope ratio, to nearest 0.1 TL (used for Kline 2001)</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <ratio> <unit> <customUnit>Ratio</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain> <numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964444" scope="document"> <attributeName>wetMass</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Wet Mass (g)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Whole fish wet mass in g in 3 significant figures</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <ratio> <unit> <customUnit>grams</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain> <numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964445" scope="document"> <attributeName>location</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Site name in PWS</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Location in Prince William Sound where sampled</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <nominal> <nonNumericDomain> <textDomain> <definition>site of collection</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1352420964446" scope="document"> <attributeName>standardLength</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Standard Length (mm)</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Standard length in mm to nearest mm</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <ratio> <unit> <customUnit>milimeters</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain> <numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>2087</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 </dataset>
 <additionalMetadata> <metadata> <unitList> <unit id="Age" name="Age" unitType="age"> <description>Age</description>
 </unit>
 </unitList>
 </metadata>
 </additionalMetadata>
 <additionalMetadata> <metadata> <unitList> <unit id="Ratio" name="Ratio" unitType="ratio"> <description>Ratio</description>
 </unit>
 </unitList>
 </metadata>
 </additionalMetadata>
 <additionalMetadata> <metadata> <unitList> <unit id="grams" name="grams" unitType="mass(g)"> <description>SI unit of mass</description>
 </unit>
 </unitList>
 </metadata>
 </additionalMetadata>
 <additionalMetadata> <metadata> <unitList> <unit id="milimeters" name="milimeters" unitType="length(mm)"> <description>SI unit of length</description>
 </unit>
 </unitList>
 </metadata>
 </additionalMetadata>
 </ns0:eml>