<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="df35b.175.3" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 eml.xsd">  <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"><allow><principal>public</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
</allow>
<allow><principal>cn=evos,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
<permission>write</permission>
<permission>changePermission</permission>
</allow>
</access>
<dataset> <title>Fish Density in Subtidal Communities of Prince William Sound, Alaska (1990, 1991, 1993, 1995)</title>
 <creator id="1385223389318"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation>
 <givenName>Thomas</givenName>
 <surName>Dean</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Coastal Resources Associates, Inc.</organizationName>
 <positionName>President</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>5190 El Arbol Dr.</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Carlsbad</city>
 <administrativeArea>CA</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>92008</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">760-207-0985</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>tomdean@coastalresources.us</electronicMailAddress>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1385223408831"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation>
 <givenName>Stephen</givenName>
 <surName>Jewett</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>School of Fisheries and Ocean Sciences, University of Alaska, Fairbanks</organizationName>
 <positionName>Professor</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>11120 Glacier Highway</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Juneau</city>
 <administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>99801</postalCode>
 </address>
 </creator>
 <associatedParty id="1385223520929"><individualName><givenName>Jessica</givenName>
 <surName>Couture</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis</organizationName>
 <positionName>Research Assistant</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis, Unversity of California, Santa Barbara</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>735 State St.</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Santa Barbara</city>
 <administrativeArea>CA</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>93101</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">805-892-2500</phone>
 <phone phonetype="fax">805-892-2510</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>couture@nceas.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Metadata Provider</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty><references>1385223389318</references>
 <role>Author</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty id="1375826455694"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation>
 <givenName>Steven</givenName>
 <surName>Jewett</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>School of Fisheries and Ocean Sciences</organizationName>
 <positionName>Research Professor</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>128 O'Neill</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 757220</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Fairbanks</city>
 <administrativeArea>AK</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>99775-7220</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">(907) 474-7841</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>scjewett@alaska.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <abstract><para>Benthic organisms associated with subtidal sediments generally represent good monitors for measuring effects of oil fluxing to the bottom. These organisms typically remain close to or at the site of larval settlement and, consequently, represent good monitoring organisms. The composition of the marine benthic fauna has been successfully used at various locations throughout the industrial world as a basis for measuring effects of pollutants on the bottom.

Shallow (&lt;20 m) subtidal studies were initiated in Prince William Sound in the fall of 1989, and continued during the summers of 1990 and 1991. Thus far, the 1989-90 sampling effort has demonstrated the presence of oil (observed as sheens) and/or injury to marine plants, invertebrates, and fishes in silted fjord, eelgrass (Zostera) and Laminaria/Agarum bay habitats (Jewett et al., 1992).

Deep (&gt;20 m) benthos studies were initiated in the Prince William Sound in July l99O. Six of the deep benthos sites sampled in l990 were adjacent to eelgrass sites sampled by the shallow benthic program. Preliminary results from the deep benthos study indicated significant differences for infauna within oiled embayments in comparison with unoiled embayments. 

The data here include only fish density data. Other data assocaited with this project can be found in additional data packages.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>evostc</keyword>
 <keyword>exxon valdez oil spill trustee council</keyword>
 <keyword>oil spill</keyword>
 <keyword>alaska</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>EVOSTC</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet><keyword>barrow's goldeneye</keyword>
 <keyword>biomarkers</keyword>
 <keyword>body mass</keyword>
 <keyword>Cepphus columba</keyword>
 <keyword>clams</keyword>
 <keyword>condition indicies</keyword>
 <keyword>cytochrome P450</keyword>
 <keyword>demography</keyword>
 <keyword>diet</keyword>
 <keyword>ecosystem</keyword>
 <keyword>emigration</keyword>
 <keyword>Enhydra lutris</keyword>
 <keyword>food limitation</keyword>
 <keyword>habitat selection</keyword>
 <keyword>harlequin ducks</keyword>
 <keyword>health</keyword>
 <keyword>hematology</keyword>
 <keyword>Histrionicus histrionicus</keyword>
 <keyword>home range</keyword>
 <keyword>hydrocarbons</keyword>
 <keyword>immigration</keyword>
 <keyword>intertidal</keyword>
 <keyword>Lontra canadensis</keyword>
 <keyword>masked greenlings</keyword>
 <keyword>mortality</keyword>
 <keyword>mussles</keyword>
 <keyword>nearshore</keyword>
 <keyword>pigeon guillemots</keyword>
 <keyword>plasma biochemistry</keyword>
 <keyword>pollution</keyword>
 <keyword>population recovery</keyword>
 <keyword>predator-prey interaction</keyword>
 <keyword>prey</keyword>
 <keyword>prey availability</keyword>
 <keyword>prey consumption rate</keyword>
 <keyword>prey demography</keyword>
 <keyword>Prince William Sound</keyword>
 <keyword>reproduction</keyword>
 <keyword>river otters</keyword>
 <keyword>sea otters</keyword>
 <keyword>sea urchins</keyword>
 <keyword>serum chemistry</keyword>
 <keyword>sex-ratio</keyword>
 <keyword>subtidal</keyword>
 <keyword>surveys</keyword>
 <keyword>survival</keyword>
 <keyword>trophic</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>project list</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <intellectualRights><para>This material is based upon work funded by the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council.  Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed herein are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views or positions of the Trustee Council.

Standard scientific norms for attribution and credit should be followed when using these data including to the Owners, Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council and other sources of funding. Please let the Owner know when these data are used.
 
These data are licensed under CC0. The person who associated a work with this deed has dedicated the work to the public domain by waiving all of his or her rights to the work worldwide under copyright law, including all related and neighboring rights, to the extent allowed by law. You can copy, modify, distribute and perform the work, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</para>
 </intellectualRights>
 <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Prince William Sound, Alaska</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-152.62762</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>-145.99754</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>61.12401</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>58.50127</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact><references>1385223389318</references>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><title>Study area</title>
 <para>Prince William Sound is a large (approximately 9000 km^2) sheltered sound in south central Alaska. It is largely protected from oceanic swells in the neighboring northern Gulf of Alaska by a series of islands. These islands and numerous fjordic embayments create an extensive coastline. Our studies were conducted in the southwestern portion and encompassed about one-third of the Sound. The nearshore subtidal zone (&lt; 20 m depth) is a mixture of rock and soft substrata and most is heavily vegetated. On rock substrata in sheltered bays and less exposed coastlines, the kelps Agarum cribrosum and Laminaria saccharina are the dominant vegetation (Dean et al. 1996). Eelgrass, Zostera marina, dominates on softer substrata in bays (McRoy 1968, 1970, Dean et al. 1998). More exposed points, especially those nearer entrances to the Gulf of Alaska, are rocky reefs with a canopy of bull kelp, Nereocystis luetkeana, and the understory of Laminaria bongardiana (formerly called L. groenlandica in Dean et al. 1996). Most of the intertidal region is dominated by Fucus gardneri and a mixture of red and green algae (Gilfillan et al. 1995, Stekoll et al. 1996). Nearshore gradients range from near vertical walls to broad plains with slopes of only a few degrees. Surface water temperatures range from 4 to 15C (Norcross &amp; Frandsen 1996), and while mostly ice free, sheltered embayments are sometimes ice covered in winter. Salinities to depths of 20 m generally range from 15 to 32 ppt, but can be substantially lower in the top 1 or 2 m, especially at stream mouths after heavy snow melt (Armstrong et al. 1995, Norcross &amp; Frandsen 1996). The principal predators of nearshore fishes are diving seabirds, sea lions, harbor seals, river otters, and other fishes (Pitcher 1980, 1981, Rosenthal 1983, Bowyer et al. 1994, Oakley &amp; Kuletz 1996). Salmon, Oncorhynchus spp., and Pacific herring, Clupea pallasi, are taken commercially from the Sound, but the dominant nearshore resident species are of little commercial or sport interest.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Dive Surveys</title>
 <para>Diver surveys were conducted in the summers of 1990, and 1991-1995. In 1990, we sampled at 25 sites in western Prince William Sound. Each site extended offshore from a 200 m long segment of shoreline. The 1990 sampling was conducted between 23 May and 8 August. Eelgrass sites were sampled in July and August, Laminaria Agarum (A-L) bays in May and June, A-L points in July and August, and Nereocystis beds in June and July. Three to six 30-m long transects, running parallel to shore, were sampled at each site. In eelgrass and Nereocystis habitats, three (and in one case, five) transects were placed on the middle of the depth range of vegetation at a random distance along the shore. At A-L bay and point sites, three transects were placed at each of two depth strata: 2 to 10 and 11 to 20 m below MLLW. Positions along the shore and depths were randomly selected.</para>
 <para>Fishes were counted by species along a 2 m wide swath and within 3 m of the bottom on each transect. Pacific cod were counted in two size classes: juvenile (YOY) that were generally less than 8 cm total length (TL), and larger individuals (adults). Fishes were also counted in a 2 m wide by 3 m deep transect at the surface. However, nearly all the fish observed there were schooling fishes, with large numbers (100's to 1000's) of individuals that were impossible to count accurately. As a result, we rely only on presence/absence data for schooling fishes. On each transect, divers also noted the dominant substratum type and estimated average slope. Substratum types were visually categorized by divers as rock outcrop, boulder, cobble, gravel, sand, or mud. These are as defined by the U.S. Bureau of Soils scale (Shepard 1973). The mud category includes silt and clay. Grain size analyses indicate that sediments classified as mud were mostly silt (S.C. Jewett &amp; T.A. Dean unpublished data). Slopes were estimated to the nearest degree by divers, but later categorized as low ( &lt;15), medium (15 to 30), or high ( &gt;30). While there were likely inaccuracies in absolute estimates of slope made by divers, relative estimates in low, medium, and high categories appear reasonable. Most transects in the high category (68%) had slopes estimated at 40 or greater, and most in the low category (69%) had estimated slopes of 5 or less. Thus, for most transects, misclassification of slope categories was unlikely. The dominant vegetation type (in terms of biomass) and total biomass of vegetation were determined from four 0.25 m^2 quadrats on each transect (see Dean et al. 1996, 1998 for details). In most cases, there was a clear dominant vegetation type. On over 95% of the transects sampled, a single species contributed over 50% of the biomass, and on the majority of transects, a single species contributed over 80%.</para>
 <para>At each site, divers sampled along two transects running perpendicular to shore and spaced at about 50 m to either side of the selected sampling point on the shore. The transects extended 50 m from shore, or in cases of steeply sloped shorelines, to a maximum depth of 20 m Fish within 3 m of the bottom were counted within a 1 m wide swath on each transect. All counts were standardized to the number 100/m^2 to account for variation in transect lengths. At each site, divers also estimated the dominant vegetation type, substratum type, slope, and relative index of exposure to waves (exposed, partially exposed, or not exposed).</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Justification for taxonomic grouping</title>
 <para>Species were grouped for the purposes of our analyses (Table 1) because we were unable to unequivocally identify some individuals to species, and because some individual taxa within groups were too rare to analyze individually. In most instances, analysis groups were equivalent to families, and there were one or two dominant species which comprised over 90% of the individuals in the group. Exceptions were greenlings and sculpins, which were represented by several relatively abundant species.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 <project><title>Effects of EVOS on Shallow Subtidal Communities in PWS</title>
 <personnel><references>1375826455694</references>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </personnel>
 <funding><para>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council restoration project numbers 96106; 95106; 93047-A; 93047-2; 93047-1; 93047; ST02; ST02-A</para>
 </funding>
 </project>
 <dataTable id="1386355543852"><entityName>fishData90.csv</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Fish count data 1990</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1386353891386"><objectName>fishData90.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">55499</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/df35b.170.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1386355543853"><attributeName>siteCode</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Site Code</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Site Number/Code based on sites in the Sites Table.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><entityCodeList><entityReference>1386357912772</entityReference>
 <valueAttributeReference>1386357912773</valueAttributeReference>
 <definitionAttributeReference>1386357912774</definitionAttributeReference>
 </entityCodeList>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1386355543854"><attributeName>rep</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Replicate</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Replicate sample number.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>rep</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1386355543855"><attributeName>dateTime</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Date &amp; Time</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Date and time for sample collection. Time in Alaska daylight time,</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>YYYY-MM-DD hh:mm:ss</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1386355543856"><attributeName>depthStrata</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Depth Strata</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>The depth strata associated with each transect.  1= deep (11 to 20 m MLLW), 2= shallow (2 to 11 m MLLW), and 3 (within an eelgrass bed at depths from 1.7 to 4.2 m MLLW).</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>1</code>
 <definition>Deep (11 - 20 m MLLW)</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>2</code>
 <definition>Shallow (2 - 11m MLLW)</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>3</code>
 <definition>Eelgrass Beds (1.7 - 4.2m MLLW)</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1386355543857"><attributeName>area</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Area Surveyed</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Square meters of bottom over which observations of fish were made.  All observations were made from 3 m above bottom.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>squareMeter</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1386355543858"><attributeName>fishDepth</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Fish Depth</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Depth where fish were observed relative to bottom: BOT = near bottom, generally within 1 m, COL=above bottom, generally greater than 1 m.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>Bot</code>
 <definition>Near Bottom (within 1m from bottom)</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>Col</code>
 <definition>Above Bottom (greater than 1m from bottom)</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1386355543859"><attributeName>spCode</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Species code</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Code for species observed.  Codes and associated species can be found in attached Species Codes table.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><entityCodeList><entityReference>1386359100439</entityReference>
 <valueAttributeReference>1386359100443</valueAttributeReference>
 <definitionAttributeReference>1386359100441</definitionAttributeReference>
 </entityCodeList>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1386355543860"><attributeName>age</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Age code</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Age code based on size and varies by species. A= Adult, J=Juvenile</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>A</code>
 <definition>Adult</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>J</code>
 <definition>Juvenile</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1386355543861"><attributeName>count</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Count</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Number of individuals observed</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1386355543862"><attributeName>notes</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Notes</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Various notes made by divers</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Diver notes</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>841</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 <dataTable id="1386357912772"><entityName>siteCodes.csv</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Sampled site codes</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1386357233416"><objectName>siteCodes.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">1881</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/df35b.172.2</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1386357912773"><attributeName>siteID</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Site Number Identifier</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Site number refers sites to other data tables</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>site ID</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1386357912774"><attributeName>site</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Site Name</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Site name</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>site name</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1386357912775"><attributeName>treatment</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Oil Treatment</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Defines if the site was oiled in the EVOS or remained clean and used as a control</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>Control</code>
 <definition>Site did not receive oil in the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>Oiled</code>
 <definition>Site received oil from the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1386357912776"><attributeName>habitat</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Algal Habitat</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Macro alga/plant that defines the habitat at the given site as well as other habitat differentiators</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>LaminariaAgarumBays</code>
 <definition>Bay dominated by Laminaria agarum</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>Nereocystis</code>
 <definition>Nareocystis dominated habitat</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>Zostera</code>
 <definition>Zostera dominated habitat</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>LaminariaAragumPoints</code>
 <definition>Exposed point dominated by Laminaria Agarum</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>SilledFjords</code>
 <definition>Silled Fjords</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1386357912777"><attributeName>lat</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Latitude</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Latitude for given site in decimal degrees</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1386357912778"><attributeName>lon</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Longitude</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Longitude for the given site in decimal degrees</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>degree</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>34</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 <dataTable id="1386359100439"><entityName>origSpList.csv</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Species List with codes</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1386358585008"><objectName>origSpList.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">4237</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/df35b.173.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1386359100440"><attributeName>family</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Family</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Taxonomic family</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>family</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1386359100441"><attributeName>common</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Common Name</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Common name for given species</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>common name</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1386359100442"><attributeName>species</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Genus and Species</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Genus and species of given speciman</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Genus species</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1386359100443"><attributeName>spcode</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Species Code</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Species Code referenced in fish counts tables</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>spCode</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1386359100444"><attributeName>group</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Group</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Taxonomic Group</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>group</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>65</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 <dataTable id="1386359936727"><entityName>fishData9195.csv</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Fish count data 1991 - 1995</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1386359206671"><objectName>fishData9195.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">29253</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/df35b.174.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1386359936728"><attributeName>siteCode</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Site Code</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Site Number/Code based on sites in the Sites Table</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>site code</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1386359936729"><attributeName>rep</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>replicate</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Number of 1 to 3 replicate transects randomly placed within each site.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1386359936730"><attributeName>dateTime</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Date &amp; Time</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Date and time in Alaksa daylight time.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>YYYY-MM-DD hh:mm:ss</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1386359936731"><attributeName>spCode</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Species Code</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Code for species observed. Codes and associated species can be found in attached origSpeciesList table.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><entityCodeList><entityReference>1386359100439</entityReference>
 <valueAttributeReference>1386359100443</valueAttributeReference>
 <definitionAttributeReference>1386359100441</definitionAttributeReference>
 </entityCodeList>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1386359936732"><attributeName>age</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Age Code</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Age code based on size and varies by species. A= Adult, J=Juvenile, H=Half-grown, Y=Young of the Year</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>Y</code>
 <definition>Young-of-the-Year</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>H</code>
 <definition>Half Grown</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>A</code>
 <definition>Adult</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>nA</code>
 <definition>Not applicable, not recorded</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>J</code>
 <definition>Juvenile</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1386359936733"><attributeName>count</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Count</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Number of individuals observed.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1386359936734"><attributeName>notes</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Notes</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Notes</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>notes</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>756</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>