<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="df35b.21.6" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"><allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow><principal>cn=evos,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 <permission>write</permission>
 <permission>changePermission</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset scope="document"> <title>GAK1 Mooring Timeseries data, Seward, Alaska (1970-2012)</title>
 <creator id="1354302626646" scope="document"> <individualName> <givenName>Thomas J. (Tom)</givenName>
 <surName>Weingartner</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>University of Alaska Fairbanks</organizationName>
 <positionName>Professor of Physical Oceanography</positionName>
 <address scope="document"> <deliveryPoint>Institute of Marine Science, 115 O'Neill</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 757220</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Fairbanks</city>
 <administrativeArea>Alaska</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>99775-7220</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">(907) 474-7993</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>tjweingartener@alaska.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <onlineUrl>http://www.ims.uaf.edu/gak1/</onlineUrl>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1359148173703" scope="document"> <individualName> <givenName>Thomas C.</givenName>
 <surName>Royer</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Center for Coastal Physical Oceanography</organizationName>
 <positionName>Eminent Professor of Oceanography, retired</positionName>
 <address scope="document"> <deliveryPoint>Old Domninion university, Crittenton Hall</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>768 West 52nd St.</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Norfolk</city>
 <administrativeArea>VA</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>23529</postalCode>
 </address>
 <electronicMailAddress>royer@ccpo.odu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 </creator>
 <associatedParty id="1370027933330" scope="document"> <individualName> <givenName>Jessica</givenName>
 <surName>Couture</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis</organizationName>
 <positionName>Research Assistant</positionName>
 <address scope="document"> <deliveryPoint>735 State St.</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Santa Barbara</city>
 <administrativeArea>CA</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>93101</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <electronicMailAddress>couture@nceas.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Metadata Provider</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <abstract><para>This program continues a 40(+) year time series of temperature and salinity measurements at hydrographic station GAK 1. The data set, which began in 1970, now consists of monthly CTDs and a mooring with 6 - 7 temperature/conductivity recorders throughout the water column, a fluorometer and nitrate sensor at 20 m depth and a nitrate sensor at 150 m depth. The project monitors five important Alaska Coastal Current ecosystem parameters and to quantify and understand interannual and longer period variability in: 

1. Temperature and salinity throughout the 250 m deep water column, 2. Near surface stratification, 3. Near and subsurface nitrate supply on the inner shelf, 4. Fluorescence as an index of phytoplankton biomass, and 5. Atmosphere-ocean heat fluxes. 

In aggregate these variables are basic descriptors of the Alaska Coastal Current, an important habitat and migratory corridor for organisms inhabiting the northern Gulf of Alaska, including Prince William Sound. 

Data here spans 1970 - 2012. ON GOING DATA CAN BE ACCESSED AT THE UAF GAK1 WEBSITE: http://www.ims.uaf.edu/gak1/

*****Publications which have cited this data: 

--Janout, M. A., T. J. Weingartner, T. C. Royer, and S. L. Danielson, 2010, On the nature of winter cooling and the recent temperature shift on the northern Gulf of Alaska shelf, J. Geophys. Res., 115, C05023, doi:10.1029/2009JC005774. 

--Bechtol, W.R., 2009. Abundance, recruitment, and environmental forcing of Kodiak red king crab. University of Alaska Fairbanks, Doctoral dissertation, 205 p 

--Tribuzio, C.A.,. 2009. Life history, demography and ecology of the spiny dogfish (Squalus acanthias) in the Gulf of Alaska: Critical information for aiding management. University of Alaska Fairbanks, Doctoral dissertation, in prep. 

--Ebbesmeyer, C. C., W. J. Ingraham, T. C. Royer, and C. E. Grosch, 2007, Tub Toys Orbit the Pacific Subarctic Gyre, Eos Trans. AGU, 88(1), 1. 

--Sarkar, N., 2007, Mixed layer dynamics along the Seward Line in the northern Gulf of Alaska, Ph.D. dissertation, Old Dominion University, Norfolk, VA, 71p. 

--Schroeder, I. D., 2007, Annual and interannual variability in the wind field and hydrography along the Seward Line in the northern Gulf of Alaska, Ph.D. dissertation, Old Dominion University, Norfolk, VA, 81p. 

--Royer, T. C. and C. E. Grosch, 2006, Ocean warming and freshening in the northern Gulf of Alaska, Geophysical Research Letters, 33 (16), L16605,doi:10.1029/2006GL026767 

--Capotondi, A., M. A. Alexander, C. Deser and A. J. Miller, 2005, Low-Frequency Pycnocline Variability in the Northeast Pacific, Journal of Physical Oceanography, V. 35, 8, 1403-1420 

--Ingolfsson, A., 2005, Community structure and zonation patterns of rocky shores at high latitudes: an interocean comparison, Journal of Biogeography, 32(1), 169-182, doi:10.1111/j.1365-2699.2004.01150.x 

--Royer, T.C., 2005, Hydrographic responses at a coastal site in the northern Gulf of Alaska to seasonal and interannual forcing, Deep-Sea Research Part II-Topical Studies in Oceanography, 52 (1-2): 267-288 

--Sarkar, N, T. C. Royer and C. E. Grosch, 2005. Hydrographic and mixed layer depth variability on the shelf in the northern Gulf of Alaska, 1974-1998. Cont. Shelf. Res. 25: 2147 - 2162. 

--Weingartner, T.J., Danielson, S.L. and Royer, T.C., 2005, Freshwater variability and predictability in the Alaska Coastal Current, Deep-Sea Research Part II-Topical Studies in Oceanography, 52 (1-2): 169-191

--Mueter, F.J., 2004, Gulf of Alaska - Marine Ecosystems of the North Pacific, Vol. PICES Special Publication 1 (pp. 153-175): PICES Special Publication 1.

--Stabeno, P.J., N.A. Bond, A.J. Hermann, N.B. Kachel, C.W. Mordy and J.E. Overland, 2004, Meteorology and oceanography of the Northern Gulf of Alaska, Continental Shelf Research, 24, 859-879

--PICES, 2004. Marine Ecosystems of the North Pacific. PICES Special Publication 1, 280p.

--Committee to Review the Gulf of Alaska Ecosystem Monitoring Program, National Research Council, 2002, A Century of Ecosystem Science - Planning Long-Term Research in the Gulf of Alaska, National Research Council, National Academy Press, Washington, D.C.

--Boldt, J. L. and L. J. Haldorson, 2002 A Bioenergetics Approach to Estimating Consumption of Zooplankton by Juvenile Pink Salmn in Prince William Sound, Alaska, Alaska Fishery Research Bulletin, V9 No. 2, Winter 2002

--Royer, T.C., Grosch, C.E., and Mysak, L.A., 2001, Interdecadal variability of Northeast Pacific coastal freshwater and its implications on biological productivity, Progress in Oceanography, 49 (1-4): 95-111 Sp. Iss. SI

--Mueter, F.J., 1999, Spatial and temporal patterns in the Gulf of Alaska groundfish community in relation to the environments, Doctoral dissertation

--Parker, K.S., T.C. Royer, and R.B. Deriso, 1995. High latitude climate forcing by the 18.6 year lunar nodal cycle and historical recruitment trends in Pacific halibut, Can. Spec. Publ. Fish. Aquat. Sci., 121:447-459.

--Muter, F.J., B.L. Norcross and T.C. Royer, 1994. Do cyclic temperatures cause cyclic fisheries?, Can. Spec. Publ. Fish. Aquat. Sci., 121:119-129.

--Royer, T.C. 1993. High-latitude oceanic variability associated with the 18.6-year nodal tide. J. Geop. Res., 98:4639-4644.

--Royer, T.C. 1989. Upper ocean temperature variability in the Northeast Pacific Ocean: Is it an indicator of global warming? J. Geop. Res., 94:18175-18183.

--Xiong, Q. and T.C. Royer. 1984. Coastal temperature and salinity in the northern Gulf of Alaska, J. Geop. Res., 89:8061-8066.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>Climate</keyword>
 <keyword>atmosphere</keyword>
 <keyword>Management &amp; Policy</keyword>
 <keyword>Oceanography</keyword>
 <keyword>Physics</keyword>
 <keyword>chemical oceanography</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet><keyword>Modeling</keyword>
 <keyword>moored observing array</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet><keyword>EVOSTC</keyword>
 <keyword>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council</keyword>
 <keyword>EVOS Gulf Watch Projects</keyword>
 <keyword>Oil Spill</keyword>
 <keyword>Exxon Valdez</keyword>
 <keyword>Environmental Drivers</keyword>
 <keyword>Ocean and Atmosphere</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>Gulf Watch Alaska Thesaurus</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet><keyword>Marine-Nearshore</keyword>
 <keyword>Marine-Pelagic</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet><keyword>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council</keyword>
 <keyword>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill</keyword>
 <keyword>EVOSTC</keyword>
 <keyword>Oil Spill</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet><keyword>Gulf of Alaska</keyword>
 <keyword>Seward</keyword>
 <keyword>Alaska</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <intellectualRights> <para>This material is based upon work funded by the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council under Project No. (340).  Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed herein are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views or positions of the Trustee Council.

Standard scientific norms for attribution and credit to the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council and any additional funding agencies should be followed when using this data. Please let the Owner know when this data is used.

This data is licensed under CC0. The person who associated a work with this deed has dedicated the work to the public domain by waiving all of his or her rights to the work worldwide under copyright law, including all related and neighboring rights, to the extent allowed by law. You can copy, modify, distribute and perform the work, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</para>
 </intellectualRights>
 <coverage scope="document"> <geographicCoverage scope="document"> <geographicDescription>GAK1 Mooring off of Seward, Alaska</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates> <westBoundingCoordinate>-149.466667</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>-149.466667</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>59.835278</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>59.835278</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1970</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate><calendarDate>2012</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1931</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate><calendarDate>2008</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact scope="document"> <references>1354302626646</references>
 </contact>
 <methods> <methodStep> <description> <section> <title>Mooring Procedural and Scientific Methods</title>
 <para>Data was collected at both monthly CTD measurements and year-long and continuous measurements from a subsurface mooring with temperature and conductivity (T/C) recorders placed at nominal depths of 20, 30, 60, 100, 150, 200, and 250 m. A (Wetlabs, Inc.) fluorometer is included at 20 m, to determine timing and duration of the spring and summer blooms. GLOBEC measurements show that the spring bloom extends from the surface to at least 20 m depth, but by early summer, the chlorophyll maximum is at ~20 m depth (Childers et al., 2005). The fluorometer emits an illuminated beam of light (at 470 nm) that stimulates chlorophyll in the beam path. The absorbed light excites the chlorophyll molecules, which emit light (fluoresce) at a 695 nm. The emitted light is detected by the fluorometer and the intensity of the fluorescence is proportional to chlorophyll biomass. (Note that fluorescence is only a relative measure of chlorophyll concentration. Absolute values would require systematic water sample measurements over time and additional laboratory analyses to convert the fluorometer data to absolute chlorophyll concentrations. We believe that this extra effort and cost is not essential to our particular goals.) We also include 1 - 2 ISUS (In Situ Ultraviolet Sensor) sensors at 20 m and at 150 m depth (if the instrument is available). These instruments optically determine nitrate based on the nitrate UV-absorption spectrum. This spectrum is unique for nitrate and it is resolved by the 256-channel ISUS spectrometer and interpreted by an algorithm developed by the Monterey Bay Aquarium Research Institute. The 20 m ISUS is within the euphotic zone and complements the fluorometer data. The 150 m ISUS will gauge the annual re-supply of nitrate to this shelf (and also Prince William Sound) through the annual exchange between deep shelf and slope waters (Royer, 1975; Weingartner et al., 2005). The deep water (and nitrate) is mixed to the surface in winter and is thereby available to phytoplankton at the onset of the spring bloom. ISUS sensors appear to provide sufficiently reliable data (+ 2 micronM) for a whole year [Whitledge, 2006]. The ISUS sensors are provided at no cost to this project because they were provided (and will be maintained) with support from the Alaska Ocean Observing System.</para>
 <para>The moored T/C recorders are Microcats (at depths greater than 20 m) and a SeaCat (at 20 m depth to incorporate the fluorometer) both manufactured by Seabird, Inc. Seabird performs pre- and post-calibrations upon which we determine sensor drift (typically ~0.01 degC /yr and ~0.03, or better, Practical Salinity Unit/yr).  Bio-fouling will gradually degrade the signal quality of the fluorometer so we strive to deploy the mooring in March or early April (depending upon weather) in order to minimize fouling potential prior to the spring bloom in April or May. Temperature and salinity data are sampled at 15-minute intervals except at 20 m depth where power supply considerations for the fluorometer and ISUS dictate hourly sampling.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 <instrumentation>-Subsurface mooring with temperature and conductivity (T/C) recorders placed at nominal depths of 20, 30, 60, 100, 150, 200, and 250 m</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>-Wetlabs, Inc. fluorometer at ~20m</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>-1 - 2 ISUS (In Situ Ultraviolet Sensor) sensors at 20 m and at 150 m</instrumentation>
 <instrumentation>-Microcats at depths greater than 20 m and a SeaCat at 20 m depth, both manufactured by Seabird, Inc. Seabird performs pre- and post-calibrations upon which we determine sensor drift (typically ~0.01 degC/yr and ~0.03, or better, Practical Salinity Unit/yr).</instrumentation>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep> <description> <section> <title>CTD Protocol and Scietific Methods</title>
 <para>The moored instruments and monthly CTD sampling schemes are complementary; one provides high vertical resolution at monthly time scales and the other provides high temporal resolution, but at coarser vertical spacing. The monthly CTDs provide redundancy in the event an instrument fails on the mooring. The GAK 1 monthly temperature and salinity are statistically significant predictors of monthly anomalies of the alongshelf baroclinic transport in the ACC (from November- August; Weingartner et al. [2005]) so ACC transport anomalies are monitored indirectly from the GAK 1 data.</para>
 <para>The monthly CTD casts are collected from a chartered fishing vessel resident in Seward using a portable CTD (Seabird SBE-25). The SBE 25 has an accuracy ~0.01 or better for salinity and .005degC for temperature. Bio-fouling will gradually degrade the signal quality of the fluorometer so we strive to deploy the mooring in March or early April (depending upon weather) in order to minimize fouling potential prior to the spring bloom in April or May.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 <instrumentation>-Portable CTD (Seabird SBE-25)</instrumentation>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep> <description> <section> <title>Data Analysis and Statistical Methods</title>
 <para>The temperature and salinity data analyses are straightforward. We compute standard statistical estimates for each month and depth and compare these with historical data since the thrust of this effort is to quantify interannual variability. We continue to incorporate Royer's (1982) discharge time series (provided courtesy of Royer through no cost to this project) and air-sea heat fluxes derived from Middleton Island data (which begins in 1948) in our analyses of salinity and temperature variability. We have generated the historical heat flux calculations which show that winter heat losses (from the ocean to the atmosphere) are more variable both interannually and at longer periods than summer heat gains. For example, winter heat loss has decreased by nearly 20% since the mid-1970s and this change was reflected in the warming at GAK 1 through 2005 (Royer, 2005). Since that time winter heat loss has increased substantially and returned to values that occurred in the early 1970s. Winter heat loss, in conjunction, with runoof, affects the ocean temperature distribution through spring when many young larvae are emerging to feed. On the other hand summer heat gains appear to be relatively consistent from year to year because this is primarily a function of cloud cover. Royer et al. (2006) contend that summer surface temperatures over the shelf and in Prince William Sound are primarily a function of the stratification. They suggest that stronger stratification traps heat in the surface layer and elevates surface temperatures, whereas weaker stratification allows the solar energy to diffuse to greater depths. Within the ACC, stratification is primarily a function of the vertical salinity gradients that we are measuring at GAK 1. We have lately expanded our assessment of heating and cooling rates for comparison with the long-term values derived from Middleton Island. These data are being assembled from a variety of meteorological buoys distributed around the GOA shelf. We are finding that there is considerable spatial variability in these heat fluxes and that the winter air-sea heat derived from Middleton Island (on the outer shelf) tend to underestimate those closer to shore, especially those within Prince William Sound and Cook Inlet. We are continuing to quantify the spatial variability in heat fluxes as part of this project and anticipate completing this analysis and submitting a publication by 2010. Our approach is to construct linear regressions between Middleton Island heat fluxes and those elsewhere in order to re-construct a historical time series of GOA heat fluxes and sea surface temperatures.</para>
 <para>We will also quantify spring and summer phytoplankton blooms in relation to changes in stratification, runoff, and winds. Stratification estimates will be made from the 3 uppermost instruments and the monthly CTD surveys. The fluorescence data will provide an estimate of the number of blooms and bloom duration observed in spring and summer. This approach is necessarily subjective since a bloom event is defined with reference to a base line, which may drift over time because of bio-fouling. However, when present, biofouling develops after the spring bloom, so our qualitative descriptions are primarily valuable in describing year-to-year variability of the spring bloom. GLOBEC measurements, as well as those by Eslinger et al. (2001) from Prince William Sound, indicate that the timing of the spring bloom varies considerably from year-to-year perhaps by as much as several weeks. Weingartner et al. (2003) show that the onset of the spring bloom on the Gulf of Alaska shelf is tied to the quantity and phasing of winter and early spring runoff because freshwater is the principal stratifying agent in the ACC in both seasons. For example, the spring bloom in the ACC was delayed until May in 2007 and 2008 because of the weak stratification; in contrast it occurred between early to mid-April during the GLOBEC years when winters were wetter and warmer.</para>
 <para>Climate model predictions for this region (Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change [IPCC, 2001]) indicate that winters will become warmer and wetter over the Gulf. Based on the GAK 1 time series this was the trend since the late 1970s (Royer, 2005; Royer et al., 2006; Janout et al., in prep.). If the IPCC predictions are correct, then we might expect that the onset of the spring bloom will occur earlier in the year (Weingartner et al., 2003; Weingartner et al., 2005) as stratification develops earlier. Such changes could alter the lower trophic structures in the Gulf of Alaska and/or create a mismatch in timing between the phytoplankton bloom and zooplankton hatch. Such changes could have substantial consequences for higher trophic components.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <sampling> <studyExtent> <description> <para>The fieldwork was conducted at Station GAK1 at the mouth of Resurrection Bay (Figure 3). The station is at ~59deg 51'N, 149deg 28'W and is located on the inner edge of the ACC midway between Prince William Sound and Cook Inlet in approximately 265 m water depth. Because much of the ACC flows through the sound (Niebauer et al., 1994), GAK 1 characterizes salinity and temperature properties of Prince William Sound waters.</para>
 </description>
 </studyExtent>
 <samplingDescription> <para>Monthly CTD measurements and year-long, continuous measurements from a subsurface mooring with temperature and conductivity (T/C) recorders placed at nominal depths of 20, 30, 60, 100, 150, 200, and 250 m.  The moored instruments and monthly CTD sampling schemes are complementary; one provides high vertical resolution at monthly time scales and the other provides high temporal resolution, but at coarser vertical spacing.</para>
 </samplingDescription>
 </sampling>
 </methods>
 <project scope="document"> <title>Gulf Ecosystem Monitoring: Toward long-term oceanographic monitoring of the GOA ecosystem</title>
 <personnel scope="document"> <references>1354302626646</references>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </personnel>
 <funding> <para>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council Project Numbers 98340, 99340, 00340, 01340, 02340, 030340. 040340, 070340. 10100340; North Pacific Globec; North Pacific Research Board</para>
 </funding>
 </project>
 <dataTable id="1370029778529" scope="document"> <entityName>timeSeries19702012gak1.csv</entityName>
 <entityDescription>CTD data</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1370028645171" scope="document"> <objectName>timeSeries19702012gak1.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">294849</size>
 <dataFormat> <textFormat> <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited> <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
  <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/df35b.11.4</url>
</online>
</distribution>
</physical>
 <attributeList> <attribute id="1370029778530" scope="document"> <attributeName>cruiseName</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Cruise Name</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>platform abbreviation and cruise number</attributeDefinition>
 <storageType>text code</storageType>
 <measurementScale> <nominal> <nonNumericDomain> <textDomain> <definition>cruise name code</definition>
 <source>original</source>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1370029778531" scope="document"> <attributeName>stationNumber</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Station Number</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Consecutive station number of the GAK1 cast, a unique identifing number within the ensemble of all casts for the cruise</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <nominal> <nonNumericDomain> <textDomain> <definition>station codes</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1370029778532" scope="document"><attributeName>yearDecimal</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Decimal year</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>(year.fraction of year) Fractions Begin Jan 1 of given year.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><interval><unit><customUnit>decimal day</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </interval>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1370029778533" scope="document"> <attributeName>year</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Year</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Year sample was taken</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <dateTime> <formatString>YYYY</formatString>
 <dateTimePrecision>1 year</dateTimePrecision>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1370029778534" scope="document"> <attributeName>dayOfTheYear</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Day of the year</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Consecutive day of the year, derived from decimal year. Leap years contain 366 days. (Ex: 32 would be 02/01 or Feb 01)</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <interval> <unit> <standardUnit>nominalDay</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain> <numberType>natural</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </interval>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1370029778535" scope="document"><attributeName>depthMeters</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Depth</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Depth sample was taken in meters</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1370029778536" scope="document"> <attributeName>tempCelcius</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Temperature</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Temperature at given depth in celcius</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <interval> <unit> <standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain> <numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </interval>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1370029778537" scope="document"> <attributeName>salinityPSU</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Salinity</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Salinity measured in Practical Salinity Units</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <ratio> <unit> <customUnit>PSU</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain> <numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1370029778538" scope="document"> <attributeName>sigmaT</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Density</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>Density of seawater at a given temperature. Measured in kilograms per meter cubed.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <interval> <unit> <standardUnit>numberPerMeterCubed</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain> <numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </interval>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1370029778539" scope="document"> <attributeName>deltaD</attributeName>
 <attributeLabel>Dynamic height</attributeLabel>
 <attributeDefinition>measured in meters</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <interval> <unit> <standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain> <numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </interval>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1370029778541" scope="document"> <attributeName>empty</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>empty</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale> <nominal> <nonNumericDomain> <textDomain> <definition>empty</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>4842</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 </dataset>
 <additionalMetadata> <metadata> <unitList> <unit id="PSU" name="PSU" parentSI="numberPerMeterCubed" unitType="volumetricDensity"> <description>Practical salinity unit</description>
 </unit>
 </unitList>
 </metadata>
 </additionalMetadata>
 <additionalMetadata> <metadata> <unitList> <unit id="decimal day" name="decimal day" parentSI="number" unitType="date"> <description>day of year defined by fraction of year starting at a given point</description>
 </unit>
 </unitList>
 </metadata>
 </additionalMetadata>
 </ns0:eml>