<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="df35d.372.10" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"><allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow><principal>cn=evos,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>all</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset>  <title>Smolt surveying for the restoration of sockeye salmon at Coghill Lake, Alaska 1989-1998</title>
<creator id="1379378243973"><individualName><givenName>Jim</givenName>
 <surName>Edmundson</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Alaska Department of Fish and Game</organizationName>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1382482826203"><individualName><givenName>Mark</givenName>
 <surName>Willette</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Alaska Department of Fish and Game</organizationName>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1382482881710"><individualName><givenName>Greg</givenName>
 <surName>Carpenter</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Alaska Department of Fish and Game</organizationName>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1379378308965"><individualName><givenName>Gary</givenName>
 <surName>Kyle</surName>
 </individualName>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1379378317016"><individualName><givenName>Stan</givenName>
 <surName>Carlson</surName>
 </individualName>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1379378326051"><individualName><givenName>Patrick</givenName>
 <surName>Shields</surName>
 </individualName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>43961 Kalifornsky, Ste B</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Soldotna</city>
 <administrativeArea>Alaska</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>99669-8276</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">(907)260-2941</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>pat.shields@alaska.gov</electronicMailAddress>
 </creator>
 <associatedParty id="1379378570578"><individualName><givenName>Sarah</givenName>
 <surName>Clark</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis</organizationName>
 <positionName>Projects Data Coordinator</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>735 State Street, Suite 300</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Santa Barbara</city>
 <administrativeArea>California</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>93101</postalCode>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">805-892-2500</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>sclark@nceas.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Metadata Provider</role>
 </associatedParty>
<abstract><para>Study History: Following the 1989 Exxon Valdez oil spill off Bligh Reef in Prince William Sound, Coghill Lake was selected as a system for sockeye salmon restoration to replace fishery stocks damaged by the oil spill. Edmundson et al. (1992) suggested that a decrease in macrozooplankton from excessive foraging by high densities of rearing fry produced from large escapements caused the decline in returns of Coghill Lake sockeye salmon. In 1993, a planned 5-year nutrient enrichment and evaluation continued in 1994 (Restoration Project 94259), 1995 (Restoration Project 95259) and 1996 (Restoration Project 96259). The fifth year of nutrient enrichment (1997) was not funded and this report summarizes results from the 4 years of treatment. 

Abstract: Prior to the recent run decline, Coghill Lake consistently produced the highest runs of sockeye salmon Oncorhynchus nerka in Prince William Sound. Although limnological and juvenile fisheries data are not available before the run decline, it is believed that sockeye salmon fry produced from consecutive years of high escapements overgrazed the forage base (zooplankton) and reduced the lake's rearing capacity. In 1993, the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council approved a stock restoration project (nutrient enrichment) for Coghill Lake as mitigation for damaged fishery resources. During 4 years of nutrient enrichment (1993 to 1996), the seasonal mean phosphorous concentration increased 220 percent, and the standing stock (density) of the prevalent zooplankton (Cyclops) increased 117 percent compared to pre-enrichment years. The sockeye salmon smolt population abundance averaged 263,604 before enrichment compared to 940,411 during treatment. This increased smolt production is attributed to increases in primary and secondary production because the number of smolts produced per spawner also increased during enrichment. The trophic level responses to nutrient enrichment in this meromictic, glacial were similar to those observed for other holomictic and meromictic (clear-water) lakes treated in Alaska. 

Publications:
Edmundson, J.A., G.B. Kyle, S.R. Carlson, and P.A. Shields. 1997. Trophic-level responses to nutrient treatment of meromictic and glacially influenced Coghill Lake, Exxon Vuldez Oil Spill Restoration Project Final Report (Restoration Project 96259), Alaska Department of Fish and Game, Division of Commercial Fisheries, Soldotna, Alaska.</para>
</abstract>
<keywordSet><keyword>salmon restoration</keyword>
<keyword>sockeye salmon</keyword>
<keyword>Prince William Sound</keyword>
<keyword>Oncorhynchus nerka</keyword>
<keyword>meromictic</keyword>
<keyword>smolt</keyword>
</keywordSet>
<keywordSet><keyword>EVOSTC</keyword>
<keyword>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council</keyword>
<keyword>Oil Spill</keyword>
<keyword>Exxon Valdez</keyword>
<keyword>Alaska</keyword>
<keyword>Pelagic</keyword>
<keyword>Fish</keyword>
<keywordThesaurus>Gulf Watch Alaska Thesaurus</keywordThesaurus>
</keywordSet>
   <intellectualRights><para>This material is based upon work funded by the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council. Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed herein are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views or positions of the Trustee Council. Standard scientific norms for attribution and credit should be followed when using these data including to the Owners, Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council and USGS. Please let the Owner know when these data are used. These data are licensed under CC0. The person who associated a work with this deed has dedicated the work to the public domain by waiving all of his or her rights to the work worldwide under copyright law, including all related and neighboring rights, to the extent allowed by law. You can copy, modify, distribute and perform the work, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</para>
 </intellectualRights>
 <coverage> <geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Coghill Lake, Prince William Sound, Alaska</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-148.375</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>-147.25</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>61.625</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>60.5</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1989</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate><calendarDate>1998</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 <taxonomicCoverage><taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Oncorhynchus</taxonRankValue>
 <taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>nerka</taxonRankValue>
 <commonName>Sockeye salmon</commonName>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact><references>1379378326051</references>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><title>Study Area</title>
 <para>At an elevation of 18 m, Coghill Lake (61 4'N, 147 54'W) is located about 130 km northwest of Cordova, has a surface area of 12.7 km2, a mean depth of 46 m, and a total volume of 587,000,000 m3. Its monimolimnion starts at about 30 m and composes approximately 45 percent of the total lake volume. A watershed area of 128 km2, combined with a high precipitation (mean annual 330 cm) of the coastal region, produces a large annual runoff to Coghill Lake. Much of this runoff occurs in the form of silt-laden meltwaters from several surrounding glaciers, which impart seasonally variable turbidity. Coghill Lake is a fast-flushing system, the estimated annual water retention being 0.9 years. To supplement production, sockeye salmon fingerlings were planted in the fall: 330,000 in 1994 and 865,000 in 1995. However, in both years lake stocking occurred in early November. This is near the end of the growing season, which minimized competition with wild fry for food resources and prevented overgrazing of the forage base.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Smolt Sampling</title>
 <para>We used 3 inclined-plane traps (Todd 1994) to estimate the population of sockeye salmon smolts emigrating from Coghill Lake and to collect smolt size and age information. Trap efficiencies were estimated by marking smolts with a Bismarck Brown dye. Dyed smolts were released at an upstream site after assessing handling mortality and were subsequently recaptured in the traps, enumerated, and released. Trap efficiency trials were conducted approximately weekly, and the results were used to estimate smolt abundance for each trial period. We used Chapman's (1951) modification of the Peterson mark-recapture estimate following methods described by Seber (1982). In 1993-1995 trap captures were counted prior to marking; therefore, the estimate was for the unmarked population. In 1996 the composition of hatchery and wild smolts was estimated by scale patterns. Total smolt abundance and variance were estimated by summing the weekly estimates. During the trapping operation all smolts were individually enumerated, and a random sample of 20-40 smolts per day were collected for age, weight, and length information. Stratified random sampling methods (Cochran 1977; Scheaffer et al. 1986) were used to estimate age-class proportions, mean lengths and weights, and variances. Daily strata were established and stratum weights were based on smolt abundance estimates.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep><description><section><title>Hydroacoustic Sampling</title>
 <para>Hydroacoustic surveys were conducted in August and September of 1994 to estimate juvenile sockeye salmon abundance and distribution. These surveys were conducted and analyzed by the Prince William Sound Science Center under a State of Alaska contract (Number 94009). Methods for the 1994 surveys are provided in the contract report (Thomas and Kirsch 1995). The survey was conducted at night when the fry are uniformly dispersed using a 420 khz dual-beam echo sounder. The data were collected along randomly selected transects.</para>
 <para>In 1995, hydroacoustic surveys were done on 14 August, 14 September, and 10 October by ADF&amp;G staff using sampling procedures described in Kyle (1990). A 420 kHz BioSonics dual-beam echosounder (model 105) with a model-171 tape recorder interface and a 6/15 transducer was used. Fish signals were recorded electronically with a Sony digital audio tape recorder (model TCD-D10) and on chart paper using a BioSonics model-115 chart recorder. In 1995, fish signals (downlooking data) were recorded along 12 transects. In addition, side-scanning data were recorded along diagonal transects to obtain a mean fish density near the surface of the lake (0-2 m) which is not possible in the down-looking mode.</para>
 <para>The recorded 1995 hydroacoustic data were processed by Dr. Richard Thorne of BioSonics, Inc. under a State of Alaska contract. For the downlooking data, a lake abundance estimate for each transect was calculated as the product of the transect density and the lake surface area. The total fish abundance estimate was then calculated as the mean of the individual transect estimates. The estimated variance was calculated as the sample variance divided by the number of transects (n = 12), and the standard error (S. E.) was calculated as the square root of the variance. Confidence intervals (95%) are reported as +/-2.2 (S.E.) , where 2.2 is the t-value for p = 0.05 with 11 degrees of freedom. The side-looking data (near surface density) was estimated as the mean density of the transects, weighted by the number of minutes towed in each transect. Fish abundance was then calculated as the product of the mean density and the surface area of the lake. Because the sampling was non-random, we did not compute a variance estimate or confidence interval for the near-surface population.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 <project><title>Trophic Level Responses to Nutrient Treatment of  Meromictic and Glacially Influenced Coghill Lake</title>
 <personnel><references>1379378243973</references>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </personnel>
 <personnel><references>1379378308965</references>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </personnel>
 <personnel><references>1379378326051</references>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </personnel>
 <personnel><references>1379378317016</references>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </personnel>
 <funding><para>Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council project numbers 93024, 94259, 95259, 96259, 97259</para>
 </funding>
 </project>
 <dataTable id="1379715439624"><entityName>trapCounts_1989_1995.csv</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Counts of fish species caught in smolt traps from 1989 to 1995. No information on pre-1994 methods.</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1379713317084"><objectName>ageLengthWeight_trapData_1995_1998.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">203810</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/df35d.373.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1379715439625"><attributeName>date</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>date retrieved trap? Unsure</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>MM/DD/YYYY</formatString>
 <dateTimePrecision>0</dateTimePrecision>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379715439626"><attributeName>sample</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Sample ID, no further information</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Sample ID</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379715439627"><attributeName>expn</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Unsure, batch ID?</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Unsure</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379715439628"><attributeName>time</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Time</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>HHMM</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379715439629"><attributeName>trapNumber</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Trap number the sample came from in the set of traps</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379715439630"><attributeName>tpcd</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Unsure</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379715439631"><attributeName>forkLength_mm</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Fork length of smolt</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>millimeter</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379715439632"><attributeName>weight_g</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Weight of smolt (unsure, dry or wet?)</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379715439633"><attributeName>patsAge</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Pat's age of smolt. Letter codes seem to indicate either a hatchery (H) or wild fish</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>nominalYear</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379715439634"><attributeName>terrysAge</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Terry's age of smolt. Letter codes seem to indicate either a hatchery (H) or wild fish</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>nominalYear</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379715439635"><attributeName>age</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Unspecified age</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>nominalYear</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379715439636"><attributeName>comments</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Comments, unsure of definition for TPUS code</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Comments</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>4831</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 <dataTable id="1379718068659"><entityName>markRecapture_trapData_1989_1995.csv</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Trap efficiency (mark/recapture) data for smolt traps 1989 to 1995.</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1379717912731"><objectName>markRecapture_trapData_1989_1995.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">16278</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/df35d.378.2</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1379718068660"><attributeName>date</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Date</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>MM/DD/YYYY</formatString>
 <dateTimePrecision>0</dateTimePrecision>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379718068661"><attributeName>sample</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Sample ID</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Sample ID</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379718068662"><attributeName>expn</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Unsure, sample batch ID?</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>ID</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379718068663"><attributeName>time</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Time</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>HHMM</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379718068664"><attributeName>trapNumber</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Trap number within a set of traps</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379718068665"><attributeName>markedCount</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Count of fish from a trap that were marked with dye</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379718068666"><attributeName>markedReleased</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Original number of dyed fish that were released</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379718068667"><attributeName>mktp</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Unsure</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379718068668"><attributeName>lcrl</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Unsure</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>414</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 <dataTable id="1379718236463"><entityName>markRecapture_trapData_1996_1998.csv</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Mark/recapture counts and smolt migration estimates for traps set from 1996 to 1998.</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1379718137508"><objectName>markRecapture_trapData_1996_1998.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">5228</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/df35d.379.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1379718236464"><attributeName>date</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Date</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>MM/DD/YYYY</formatString>
 <dateTimePrecision>0</dateTimePrecision>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379718236465"><attributeName>markedReleased</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Original number of dyed fish that were released</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379718236466"><attributeName>markedCount</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Count of fish from a trap that were marked with dye</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379718236467"><attributeName>fishCaught</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Number of unmarked fish caught</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379718236468"><attributeName>estimatedMigration</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Estimated fish migration</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379718236469"><attributeName>periodTotal</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Sum of unmarked fish caught for defined time period</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>161</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 <dataTable id="1379719283663"><entityName>ageLengthWeight_trapData_1995_1998.csv</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Age, weight and fork length data from sample smolt caught in traps, 1995 - 1998.</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1379719082503"><objectName>ageLengthWeight_trapData_1995_1998.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">203810</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/df35d.380.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1379719283664"><attributeName>year</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Year</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>YYYY</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379719283665"><attributeName>date</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Specific date where available</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>MM/DD/YYYY</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379719283666"><attributeName>SampleNumber</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Sample ID</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Sample ID</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379719283667"><attributeName>fishNumber</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Index for fish caught in traps</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379719283668"><attributeName>slideNumber</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Unsure, presumably ID for slide used in scale analysis</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>ID</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379719283669"><attributeName>scaleNumber</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Unsure</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379719283670"><attributeName>forkLength_mm</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Fork length of sample smolt</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>millimeter</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379719283671"><attributeName>weight_g</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Fish's weight, unsure if it is wet or dry weight</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>gram</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379719283672"><attributeName>patsAge</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Pat's age of fish, when given</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>nominalYear</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379719283673"><attributeName>terrysAge</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Terry's age of fish, when given</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>nominalYear</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379719283674"><attributeName>age</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Unspecified age of fish</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>nominalYear</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379719283675"><attributeName>comments</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Comments, unsure what TPUS stands for</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Comments</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>4831</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 <dataTable id="1379720551970"><entityName>partialTow_AgeWeightLength_1995_1996.csv</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Fish age, weight and length data from boat townetting, with data salvaged only for 1995 and 1996. Cannot locate other years.</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1379720256207"><objectName>partialTow_AgeWeightLength_1995_1996.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">26966</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/df35d.381.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1379720551971"><attributeName>year</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Year of tow</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>YYYY</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379720551972"><attributeName>date</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Specific date when available</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>MM/DD/YYYY</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379720551973"><attributeName>number</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Assuming this is indexed fish number for each smolt caught</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379720551974"><attributeName>length</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Lenght of smolt, assuming millimeters based on other data tables</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>millimeter</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379720551975"><attributeName>weight</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Fish weight, unsure if it is wet or dry. Assuming milligrams.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>milligram</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379720551976"><attributeName>age</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Age of fish</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>nominalYear</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>1195</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 <dataTable id="1379720727084"><entityName>towTripsAndFishCounts_1995.csv</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Boat trip information for 1995 townetting sampling with fish counts; missing all other years.</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1379720613445"><objectName>towTripsAndFishCounts_1995.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">810</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/df35d.382.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1379720727085"><attributeName>Date</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Date of boat trip</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>MM/DD/YYYY</formatString>
 <dateTimePrecision>0</dateTimePrecision>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379720727086"><attributeName>towNumber</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Two trip number</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379720727087"><attributeName>beginTime</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>beginning time of tow</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>HH:MM</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379720727088"><attributeName>endTime</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>End time of tow</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>HH"MM</formatString>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379720727089"><attributeName>Depth</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Depth of townet</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>S</code>
 <definition>surface</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 <codeDefinition><code>10m</code>
 <definition>10 meters</definition>
 </codeDefinition>
 </enumeratedDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379720727090"><attributeName>Sockeye</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Count of sockeye salmon caught in townet</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379720727091"><attributeName>Stickleback</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Count of stickleback caught in townet</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379720727092"><attributeName>Preservative</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Preservative used to keep fish sample</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Preservative name</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>20</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 <dataTable id="1379721305288"><entityName>hydroacousticFishDensity_1995.csv</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Hydroacoustice fish survey data for 1995, all other years missing.</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1379720767155"><objectName>hydroacousticFishDensity_1995.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">2933</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/df35d.383.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1379721305289"><attributeName>date</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Date of survey</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>MM/DD/YYYY</formatString>
 <dateTimePrecision>0</dateTimePrecision>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379721305290"><attributeName>transect</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Survey transect ID</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Transect ID</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379721305291"><attributeName>fishDensity</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Fish density on the transect (number of fish per 1000 m2)</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>numberPer1000MeterSquared</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379721305292"><attributeName>areaTransect</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Are of the survey transect. Column header states: 'X 103 m2'.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>squareMeter</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>108</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 <dataTable id="1379721555162"><entityName>hydroacousticPopEstimate_1995.csv</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Lake estimates for juvenile salmon population based on hydroacoustic surveys in 1995.</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1379721402351"><objectName>hydroacousticPopEstimate_1995.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">1082</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/df35d.384.2</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1379721555163"><attributeName>date</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Date of survey</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><dateTime><formatString>MM/DD/YYYY</formatString>
 <dateTimePrecision>0</dateTimePrecision>
 </dateTime>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379721555164"><attributeName>totalArea</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Total area covered by a transect</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>squareMeter</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379721555165"><attributeName>weightedMeanFishDensity</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Mean fish density for a transect</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>numberPer1000MeterSquared</customUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1379721555166"><attributeName>lakeEstimate</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Estimate of juvenile salmon population for Coghill Lake</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>37</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 </dataset>
 <additionalMetadata><metadata><unitList><unit id="numberPer1000MeterSquared" multiplierToSI="0.001" name="numberPer1000MeterSquared" parentSI="numberPerMeterSquared" unitType="arealDensity"><description>numberPer1000MeterSquared</description>
 </unit>
 </unitList>
 </metadata>
 </additionalMetadata>
 </ns0:eml>