<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-ntl.25.8" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0  http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
  <access authSystem="https://pasta.lternet.edu/authentication" order="allowFirst" scope="document" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=NTL,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <alternateIdentifier system="NTL-DEIMS">5717</alternateIdentifier>
    <shortName>NTLMP05</shortName>
    <title>North Temperate Lakes LTER: Macrophyte Biomass in Trout Lake Summary 1983 -
			current</title>
    <creator>
      <positionName>NTL LTER Lead PI</positionName>
      <organizationName>Center for Limnology</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <organizationName>NTL LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <metadataProvider>
      <organizationName>North Temperate Lakes LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Center for Limnology, UW Madison</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </metadataProvider>
    <pubDate>2010</pubDate>
    <language>english</language>
    <abstract>
      <para>These data are collected to document and characterize the submersed macrophytes of Trout
				Lake, to evaluate the long-term stability of this component, and to interface with
				investigations of other compartments of the ecosystem. Four sites along the shoreline of
				Trout Lake have been sampled annually in August along permanent line transects. This dataset
				includes biomass per m2 for individual species summarized by depth along the transect.
				Derived data include the mean and standard deviation of macrophyte biomass. These data are
				useful in determining the annual variability of the submersed macrophytes and providing
				information on the effects of the invasion of an introduced crayfish. Sampling Frequency:
				annually during summer Number of sites: 4 </para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>biomass</keyword>
      <keyword>primary production</keyword>
      <keyword>species composition</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>LTER Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>NTL LTER</keyword>
      <keyword>North Temperate Lakes - LTER</keyword>
      <keyword>aquatic macroflora</keyword>
      <keyword>aquatic plant</keyword>
      <keyword>littoral zone</keyword>
      <keyword>macrophytes</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>NTL Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <section>
        <title>Data Policies</title>
        <para>Copyright Board of Regents, University of Wisconsin, Madison. This information is
					released to the public and may be used for academic, educational, or commercial purposes
					subject to the following restrictions: The Data User must realize that these data sets are
					being actively used by others for ongoing research and that coordination may be necessary
					to prevent duplicate publication. The Data User is urged to contact the NTL lead Principal
					Investigator, leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu, to check on other uses of the data. Where
					appropriate, the Data User may be encouraged to consider collaboration and/or
					co-authorship with original investigators.</para>
        <para>The Data User must realize that the data may be misinterpreted if taken out of
					context. We request that you provide the NTL lead Principal Investigator, ATTN: Data
					Access, Center for Limnology, University of Wisconsin-Madison, 680 North Park St.,
					Madison, WI 53706 with a copy of any manuscript using the data so that it may be reviewed
					and comments provided on the presentation of our data.</para>
        <para>The Data User must acknowledge use of the data by an appropriate citation (see
					Citation) of the NTL-LTER database. A generic citation for our databases is: name of data
					set, North Temperate Lakes Long Term Ecological Research program, NSF, contact person for
					data set, Center for Limnology, University of Wisconsin-Madison. The data set name and
					contact person for each data set can be found in the metadata header of the online data
					sets.</para>
        <para>The Data User must send two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the
					data to the address above. We would like to include such manuscripts in our LTER
					publications list.</para>
        <para>The Data User must not redistribute original data and documentation without permission
					from Emily Stanley, lead Principal Investigator, (ehstanley@wisc.edu).</para>
        <para>While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation,
					complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is".
					The North Temperate Lakes LTER shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or
					misinterpretation of data sets. Data users should be aware that we periodically update
					data sets.</para>
        <para>Our goal is to release all long term data associated with core research areas within 2
					years of collection. These data and accompanying metadata will be available for download
					from the NTL-LTER web site.</para>
        <para>By using these data, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement.
					Thank you for your cooperation. </para>
      </section>
    </intellectualRights>
    <distribution>
      <online>
        <url function="information">http://lter.limnology.wisc.edu/node/5717</url>
      </online>
    </distribution>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Trout Lake, Vilas County, WI, USA </geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-89.704</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.647</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>46.079</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>46.013</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1983-08-01</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2009-12-31</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <maintenance>
      <description>
        <para>ongoing </para>
      </description>
    </maintenance>
    <contact>
      <organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName>
      <positionName>LNO Information Manager</positionName>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <positionName>NTL LTER Information Manager</positionName>
      <organizationName>University of Wisconsin</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Street</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <positionName>NTL LTER Lead PI</positionName>
      <organizationName>Center for Limnology</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    <publisher>
      <organizationName>North Temperate Lakes LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Center for Limnology, UW Madison</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>infomgr@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </publisher>
    <pubPlace>North Temperate Lakes</pubPlace>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <para>I Site Locations Sites are designated according to the LTER numbering scheme
							established for the shoreline of the south basin of Trout Lake and its islands (see
							fig. 1). The four sites used by the macrophyte component are also used in the LTER
							fish and crayfish sampling and the descriptions that follow make reference to the
							shore stakes set for the fish sampling crews. Appendix A details their placement. In
							addition, photos have been included to identify the landmarks used. Each site
							establishes a transect line from a proximal shore landmark to a distal shore landmark
							on a specified compass heading. Site 7 Rocky Reef Bay: Landmarks: Proximal - Large
							birch with a spike nailed one foot above the base. Also at fish sampling stake D.
							Distal - The Rocky Reef Resort main building located in line with the north end of
							Rocky Reef Island. Compass Heading: 280degree Site 31 Channel Mouth Island: Landmarks:
							Proximal - White Birch at fish sampling stake B Distal - A distant pine (approx. 1
							mi.) standing above the canopy in the skyline facing east. Pine is at peak where the
							landscape shows a rise. Compass Heading: 83degree Site 50 - Southwest Bay of South
							Trout: Landmarks: Proximal - Large White Pine in clearing between fish sampling stake
							C and D. About 9 meters east of stake D. Distal - The west tip of Haunted Island.
							Compass Heading: 13degree Site 56 - Mouth of Mann Creek: Landmarks: Proximal - Large
							White Cedar with spike nailed 1 foot above base. Distal - The west tip of Millers
							Island. Compass Heading: 41degree. II Line Transects The site descriptions specify a
							transect line along which presenceorabsence data is recorded for all macrophyte
							species. A 0.25 M2 ring placed at 1 meter intervals (except site 7 - 0.5 to 1 M depth
							where the ring is placed at 2 meter intervals) along transect designates the sampling
							quadrat. Using SCUBA, species data are recorded along with the total number of
							quadrats encountered between the following depth intervals: 0.5-1 M, 1-2 M, 2-3 M and
							3-5 M. These depth intervals have been permanently established with markers consisting
							of a commercial Earth Anchor set in the lake bottom with 2 floats secured to it near
							the bottom. Large boat bumpers are used on the anchors at 3 and 5 meters. The other
							floats are small polybottles. Between 28 and 52 quadrats are examined within each
							depth interval at each site. The paths over which the quadrats are laid are shown on
							the site maps (Figs. 2-5). A species list is given in appendix B. III Biomass
							Harvesting. Five replicate quadrats (0.25 M2) are harvested for all above ground
							biomass at each site at each of three nominal depths: 1.5 M, 2.5 M and 4 M. Samples
							are removed along a line parallel to shore - located midway between each of the 1, 2,
							3 and 5 M anchors. Figures 2-5 show the distribution of the replicates. Four sites
							with 3 depths and 5 replicates yields 60 samples. A sample may be empty. In the lab,
							samples are separated by species, placed in labeled paper bags (LABEL:
							SpeciesorSiteorDepthorRepnumber ), oven dried, and weights recorded. Paper bags used
							for drying should be purchased in groups to allow the plant weights to be determined
							by difference using an average tare for a group of bags. Paper bags for determining
							average tare should be wetted and oven dried in the same manor as the bags containing
							plant samples. IV Additional Comments. A. Pre-1987 Data. In 1987, permanent line
							transects were established at each of the sites. Biomass samples and line transects
							observed before 1987 were set by more general descriptions at the site and were not
							identical year to year. B. Biomass Weights. Starting in 1989, biomass weights were
							determined by weighing dried plants in paper bags and using an average tare for the
							bags. Consequently, values in the data base can be negative and should be considered
							as present in very small amounts. </para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <project>
      <title>North Temperate Lakes LTER</title>
      <personnel>
        <positionName>NTL LTER Lead PI</positionName>
        <organizationName>Center for Limnology</organizationName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>680 North Park Str.</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Madison</city>
          <administrativeArea>WI</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>53706</postalCode>
          <country>United States</country>
        </address>
        <electronicMailAddress>leadpi@lter.limnology.wisc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <role>project personnel</role>
      </personnel>
      <abstract>
        <para>North Temperate Lakes Long Term Ecological Research studies the ecology of lakes as
					one of a network of sites established by the National Science Foundation. We are
					interested in how biophysical setting, climate, and changing land use and cover interact
					to shape lake characteristics and dynamics over time (past, present, future). Our primary
					study sites include a set of seven northern Wisconsin and four southern Wisconsin lakes
					and their surrounding landscapes. The project, which started in 1981, is administered by
					the Center for Limnology at the University of Wisconsin-Madison. Perception of Long-Term
					Change: How and why have the lake districts changed, and how will they change in the
					future? Climatic Forcing of Change: What are the major ecological and social responses of
					lake districts to climate change? Interacting Drivers, Scales of Space and Time, and
					Regional Change: How do multiple interacting drivers affect regional change in lake
					districts at multiple scales? Ecosystem Services: Past, Present and Future: What are the
					magnitudes, interactions and potential future flows of ecosystem services in lake
					districts? </para>
      </abstract>
    </project>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>macrophyte_biomass_tr_sumview</entityName>
      <entityDescription>North Temperate Lakes LTER: Macrophyte Biomass in Trout Lake
				Summary</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>macrophytebiomasstrsumview</objectName>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
              <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url function="download">https://pasta.lternet.edu/package/data/eml/knb-lter-ntl/25/8/eb346bf6bc41f73dcdece85b7ce98cdd</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <coverage>
        <geographicCoverage>
          <geographicDescription>Location: Trout Lake is located within the Northern
						Highland-American Legion State Forest, Vilas County. It is a drainage lake with
						predominantly gravel and sand substrate. It has a surface area of 1607.9 hectare, 25.9
						kilometers of mostly undeveloped shoreline and a maximum depth of 35.7 meters. </geographicDescription>
          <boundingCoordinates>
            <westBoundingCoordinate>-89.665017</westBoundingCoordinate>
            <eastBoundingCoordinate>-89.665017</eastBoundingCoordinate>
            <northBoundingCoordinate>46.029267</northBoundingCoordinate>
            <southBoundingCoordinate>46.029267</southBoundingCoordinate>
          </boundingCoordinates>
        </geographicCoverage>
      </coverage>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>lakeid</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>lake name abbreviation</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>lake name abbreviation</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>TR</code>
                    <definition>Trout Lake</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>year4</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>year</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>year</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>nominalYear</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>site</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>site</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>site</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>site</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>depth</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>sample depth meter</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>depth at which the sample or measurement was
						taken</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>meter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>species_name</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>species of macrophyte</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>species of macrophyte</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>species of macrophyte</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>nreps</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>number of replicate samples</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>number of replicate samples</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>avg_dryweight_g</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>mean of dryweight from reps</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>mean of dryweight from replicate samples</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>gramPer_pt25MeterSquared</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>stdev_dryweight_g</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>stdev of dryweights from reps</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>standard deviation of dryweight from replicate
						samples</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>gramPer_pt25MeterSquared</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1     http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
        <ns2:unit id="gramPer_pt25MeterSquared" />
      </ns2:unitList>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
</ns0:eml>