<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="ecotrends.12458.2" scope="system" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/eml/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
  <access authSystem="https://pasta.lternet.edu/authentication" order="allowFirst" scope="document" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=ECT,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=SBC,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>write</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <shortName>sbc_SBC-CARP_density-animal-TSN169751_noperm2_yearly</shortName>
    <title>Santa Barbara Coastal site, station Carpinteria Reef, Santa Barbara Channel, study of animal density of Phanerodon furcatus in units of numberPerMeterSquared on a yearly timescale</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Dan</givenName>
        <surName>Reed</surName>
      </individualName>
      <positionName>Research Biologist</positionName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Marine Science Institute, University of California</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Santa Barbara</city>
        <administrativeArea>CA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>93106</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">805-893-8363</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>reed@lifesci.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://sbc.lternet.edu/~reed</onlineUrl>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <organizationName>Santa Barbara Coastal</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Marine Science Institute, University of California</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Santa Barbara</city>
        <administrativeArea>CA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>93106-6150</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">805-893-2071</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>sbc_help@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://sbc.lternet.edu/</onlineUrl>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <organizationName>EcoTrends Project</organizationName>
      <positionName>EcoTrends Project Coordinator</positionName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>USDA-ARS Jornada Experimental Range</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>New Mexico State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Las Cruces</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>88003</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>ecotrend@nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.ecotrends.info</onlineUrl>
    </creator>
    <metadataProvider>
      <organizationName>EcoTrends Project</organizationName>
      <positionName>EcoTrends Project Coordinator</positionName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>USDA-ARS Jornada Experimental Range</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>New Mexico State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Las Cruces</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>88003</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>ecotrend@nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.ecotrends.info</onlineUrl>
    </metadataProvider>
    <metadataProvider>
      <organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Long Term Ecological Research - Network Office</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>UNM Biology Department, MSC03-2020</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131-0001</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </metadataProvider>
    <pubDate>2013</pubDate>
    <abstract>
      <para>
The EcoTrends project was established in 2004 by Dr. Debra Peters 
(Jornada Basin LTER, USDA-ARS Jornada Experimental Range) and 
Dr. Ariel Lugo (Luquillo  LTER, USDA-FS Luquillo Experimental Forest) 
to support the collection and analysis of long-term ecological datasets. 
The project is a large synthesis effort focused on improving the accessibility 
and use of long-term data.  At present, there are ~50 state and federally funded 
research sites that are participating and contributing to the EcoTrends project, 
including all 26 Long-Term Ecological Research (LTER) sites and sites funded by 
the USDA Agriculture Research Service (ARS), USDA Forest Service, 
US Department of Energy, US Geological Survey (USGS) and numerous universities. 
      </para>
      <para>
Data from the EcoTrends project are available through an exploratory web portal 
(http://www.ecotrends.info). This web portal enables the continuation of data
compilation and accessibility by users through an interactive web application.
Ongoing data compilation is updated through both manual and automatic
processing as part of the LTER Provenance Aware Synthesis Tracking
Architecture (PASTA). The web portal is a collaboration between the Jornada LTER 
and the LTER Network Office. 
      </para>
      <para>
The following dataset from Santa Barbara Coastal (SBC)
contains animal density of Phanerodon furcatus measurements in numberPerMeterSquared units
and were aggregated to a yearly timescale.
      </para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">EcoTrends</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">long term</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">ecological</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">ecology</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">trends</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">synthesis</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="place">Santa Barbara Coastal</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="place">Carpinteria Reef, Santa Barbara Channel</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">animal density of Phanerodon furcatus</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Biotic structure</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Animal abundance, cover, and density</keyword>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <section>
        <title>EcoTrends Data Access Policy, Data Access Requirements, and General Data Use Agreement</title>
        <para>
          <emphasis>April 10, 2007</emphasis>
        </para>
        <section>
          <title>EcoTrends Data Access Policy</title>
          <para>
The EcoTrends data policy follows the LTER data policy by including three specific 
sections designed to express shared network policies regarding the release of 
EcoTrends data products, user registration for accessing data, and the licensing 
agreements specifying the conditions for data use.
    </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>EcoTrends Data Release Policy</title>
          <para>
Data and information made available to the EcoTrends project are accessible online 
with as few restrictions as possible, on a nondiscriminatory basis. EcoTrends 
participating scientists should make every effort to release data with attention 
to accurate and complete metadata. 
    </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Data</title>
          <para>
All data made available to the public via the EcoTrends website are to be released 
to the general public according to the terms of the general data use agreement below.
    </para>
          <para>
While the spirit of this document is to promote maximum availability for ecological data, 
there are criteria by which priority for data release may be determined. Aggregated 
or otherwise processed data with complete metadata have highest priority. Other types 
of data including student thesis data or legacy data that already suffer from inadequate 
documentation or format obsolescence may be ranked a lower priority by a site with 
justifications provided in their data management policy. Finally, some data may be 
determined of lowest priority for archiving on the grounds that they are interim data 
that led to final products that carry the scientific value. These might include data 
files created during stages within an analytic workflow, raw or replicate data values 
that were subsequently aggregated or processed for release, or individual outputs from 
stochastic models. EcoTrends does not store or distribute datasets with distribution or 
use restrictions imposed by the data owner(s). 
    </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Metadata</title>
          <para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
          1. Metadata documenting archived/online data sets of all types listed above 
             will be made available when, or before, the dataset itself is released 
             according to the terms above.
          </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
          2. All metadata will be publicly available.
          </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
          3. All metadata will follow Long-Term Ecological Research (LTER) Network 
             recommended standards and will minimally contain adequate information on 
             proper citation, access, contact information, and discovery. 
             Complete information including methods, structure, semantics, and quality 
             control/assurance is expected for most datasets and is strongly encouraged.
          </para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>EcoTrends Data Access Requirements</title>
          <para>
The access to all EcoTrends data is subject to requirements set forth by this 
policy document to enable data providers to track usage, evaluate its impact in 
the community, and confirm users' acceptance of the terms of acceptable use. 
These requirements are standardized to provide contractual exchange of data 
between Site Data Providers, Network Data Providers, and Data Users that can be 
encoded into electronic form and exchanged between computers. This will allow 
direct access to data via a common portal once these requirements have been 
fulfilled. The following information may be required directly or by proxy 
prior to the transference of any data object:
      <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Registration</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <orderedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>1. Name</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>2. Affiliation</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>3. Email Address</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>4. Full Contact Information</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Acceptance of the General Public Use Agreement</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
          A Statement of Intended Use that is compliant with the above 
          agreements. Such statements may be made submitted explicitly or made 
          implicitly via the data access portal interface.
          </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Data Use Agreements</title>
          <para>
Datasets released by EcoTrends will be accompanied by the General Data Use 
Agreement (see below). This document specifies general roles and the obligations 
and rights enjoyed by each regarding the use of most dataset released for 
general public use. This document may be updated as the LTER data policy is 
updated in the future to ensure compliance with the LTER policy.
    </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>General Data Use Agreement</title>
          <section>
            <title>Definitions</title>
            <para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <emphasis>Dataset</emphasis> - Digital data and its metadata derived 
              from any research activity such as field observations, collections, 
              laboratory analysis, experiments, or the post-processing of existing 
              data and identified by a unique identifier issued by a recognized 
              cataloging authority such as a site, university, agency, or other 
              organization.
            </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <emphasis>Data User</emphasis> - individual to whom access has 
              been granted to this Dataset, including his or her immediate 
              collaboration sphere, defined here as the institutions, partners, 
              students and staff with whom the Data User collaborates, and with 
              whom access must be granted, in order to fulfill the Data User's 
              intended use of the Dataset
            </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <emphasis>Dataset Creator</emphasis> - individual or institution that 
              produced the Dataset
            </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <emphasis>Dataset Owner</emphasis> - individual or institution 
              that holds intellectual property rights to the dataset. Note that 
              this may or may not be defined as a legal copyright. If no other 
              party is designated in the metadata as Dataset Owner, it may be 
              presumed that these rights are held by the Dataset Creator.
            </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <emphasis>Dataset Distributor</emphasis> - individual or 
              institution providing access to the Datasets.
            </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <emphasis>Dataset Contact</emphasis> - party designated in the 
              accompanying metadata of the Dataset as the primary contact for 
              the Dataset.
            </para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Conditions of Use</title>
            <para>
The re-use of scientific data has the potential to greatly increase communication, 
collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines, and thus is fostered, 
supported and encouraged. Permission to use this dataset is granted to the 
Data User free of charge subject to the following terms:
      </para>
            <para>
              <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
              1) <emphasis>Acceptable use</emphasis>. Use of the dataset will be 
              restricted to academic, research, educational, government, 
              recreational, or other not-for-profit professional purposes. The 
              Data User is permitted to produce and distribute derived works 
              from this dataset provided that they are released under the same 
              license terms as those accompanying this Dataset. Any other uses 
              for the Dataset or its derived products will require explicit 
              permission from the dataset owner.
            </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
              2 ) <emphasis>Redistribution</emphasis>. The data are provided for 
              use by the Data User. The metadata and this license must accompany 
              all copies made and be available to all users of this Dataset. The 
              Data User will not redistribute the original Dataset beyond this 
              collaboration sphere.
            </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
              3 ) <emphasis>Citation</emphasis>. It is considered a matter of 
              professional ethics to acknowledge the work of other scientists. 
              Thus, the Data User will properly cite the Dataset in any 
              publications or in the metadata of any derived data products that 
              were produced using the Dataset. Citation should take the following 
              general form: <emphasis>Creator, Year of Data Publication, Title 
              of Dataset, Publisher, Dataset identifier.</emphasis>
                  </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
              4 ) <emphasis>Acknowledgement</emphasis>. The Data User should 
              acknowledge any institutional support or specific funding awards 
              referenced in the metadata accompanying this dataset in any 
              publications where the Dataset contributed significantly to its 
              content. Acknowledgements should identify the supporting party, 
              the party that received the support, and any identifying information 
              such as grant numbers.
            </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
              5 ) <emphasis>Notification</emphasis>. The Data User will notify 
              the Dataset Contact when any derivative work or publication based 
              on or derived from the Dataset is distributed. The Data User will 
              provide the data contact with two reprints of any publications 
              resulting from use of the Dataset and will provide copies, or 
              on-line access to, any derived digital products. Notification will 
              include an explanation of how the Dataset was used to produce the 
              derived work.
            </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
              6 ) <emphasis>Collaboration</emphasis>. The Dataset has been 
              released in the spirit of open scientific collaboration. Data Users 
              are thus strongly encouraged to consider consultation, collaboration 
              and/or co-authorship with the Dataset Creator.
            </para>
                </listitem>
              </orderedlist>
            </para>
            <para>
      By accepting this Dataset, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of 
      this agreement. The Data Owner shall have the right to terminate this 
      agreement immediately by written notice upon the Data User's breach of, 
      or non-compliance with, any of its terms. The Data User may be held 
      responsible for any misuse that is caused or encouraged by the Data User's 
      failure to abide by the terms of this agreement.
      </para>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Disclaimer</title>
          <para>
    While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and 
    documentation contained in the datasets discovered on the EcoTrends website, 
    complete accuracy of data and metadata cannot be guaranteed. All data and 
    metadata are made available as is. The Data User holds all parties 
    involved in the production or distribution of the Dataset harmless for 
    damages resulting from its use or interpretation.
    </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>
      Forward comments to:
      EcoTrends Project Coordinator
      Jornada Basin LTER
      New Mexico State University
      Box 30003, MSC 3JER
      Las Cruces, NM 88003
      chrlaney@nmsu.edu
      </literalLayout>
          </para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </intellectualRights>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Santa Barbara Coastal</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-119.5399000</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-119.5399000</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3902000</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3902000</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>2000</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2007</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <contact>
      <positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
      <organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>UNM Biology Department, MSC03-2020</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131-0001</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">505 277-2535</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">505 277-2541</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>tech-support@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <organizationName>EcoTrends Project</organizationName>
      <positionName>EcoTrends Project Coordinator</positionName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>USDA-ARS Jornada Experimental Range</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 30003, MSC 3JER</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>New Mexico State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Las Cruces</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>88003</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>ecotrend@nmsu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.ecotrends.info</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <publisher>
      <organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>UNM Biology Department, MSC03-2020</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131-0001</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>tech-support@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://lno.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </publisher>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>
        The source data used to generate this dataset were provided by Santa Barbara Coastal, 
	and transformed into a derived product by EcoTrends. Please read and agree 
	to the data policy of Santa Barbara Coastal and the EcoTrends Data Policy before using 
	these data in any analyses and/or publications. Metadata describing these 
	derived data were provided by the LTER Network Office and EcoTrends.
          </para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>
	These data are produced as part of the EcoTrends project. This phase of the
	EcoTrends project produces derived data through a manual process of inputing
	raw (site) data through an R (the R statistical programming language)
	script, which converts input data from the raw schema to the global schema.
          </para>
          <para>
	This process produces a file that uses a canonical naming convention that
	contains keyword nomenclature used to generate attribute level metadata.
	The proposed and agreed upon file naming convention used for derived data
	products encodes the following information into the name: (1) site(s) code,
	(2) station(s) code, (3) variable, (4) unit, and (5) timescale. In addition,
	the symbols NA and UNK may be used to signify a field that has nothing
	applicable or a field where the content is unknown, respectively. Each field
	is joined in the file name by the underscore _ character. The site,
	station, and variable fields may contain multiple codes that are joined with
	the hyphen or dash - character. All derived data product file names end
	with the .trends.csv extension. The file name is case sensitive so as to
	avoid confusion between similar codes (e.g., c for Celsius and C for
	carbon). This convention results in a file name that looks like:
          </para>
          <para>
	SITE_STATION_VARIABLE_UNIT_TIMESCALE.trends.csv
          </para>
          <para>
	An example of a real file name is and_OR10_smax-10cm_c_monthly.trends.csv,
	which decodes to maximum soil temperature recorded in degrees Celsius
	subsurface at 10cm located at the Andrews LTER, using soil sensor station
	OR10, and with data aggregated to a monthly average.
          </para>
          <para>
	Data are converted from the raw (site) schema to a global schema that
	includes: (1) Date stamp for either the year (YYYY), and if the month exists
	(MM); (2) Observation value, (3) Number of raw observations used in
	aggregate, (4) Standard Deviation of Aggregate population, (5) Standard
	Error of Aggregate population, (6) Proportion Missing of Aggregate
	population, (7) Proportion Questionable of Aggregate population, (8)
	Proportion Estimated of Aggregate population, (9) Proportion Trace
	Measurement of Aggregate population (precipation data only), (10) Proportion
	Ivalid of Aggregate population, and (11) Comments for the Aggregate
	population.
          </para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>ecotrends_12458_1</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Santa Barbara Coastal site, station Carpinteria Reef, Santa Barbara Channel, study of animal density of Phanerodon furcatus in units of numberPerMeterSquared on a yearly timescale</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>sbc_SBC-CARP_density-animal-TSN169751_noperm2_yearly.csv</objectName>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url function="download">https://pasta.lternet.edu/package/data/eml/ecotrends/12458/2/c8777c04e463859b2b074e5c8f70bac2</url>
          </online>
          <access authSystem="https://pasta.lternet.edu/authentication" order="allowFirst" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu">
            <allow>
              <principal>uid=ECT,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
              <permission>all</permission>
            </allow>
            <allow>
              <principal>uid=SBC,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
              <permission>write</permission>
            </allow>
            <allow>
              <principal>public</principal>
              <permission>read</permission>
            </allow>
          </access>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>ID_OBS</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>ID number for the observation</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>integer as text</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>YEAR</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>year range of data collection</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">date</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>YYYY</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>OBSERVATION</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>animal density of Phanerodon furcatus</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>numberPerMeterSquared</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>value is not applicable or does not exist</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>OBSERVATION_EST</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>an estimation of the observation based on a sampling average of similar data for computing missing values</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>numberPerMeterSquared</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>value is not applicable or does not exist</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>S_DEV</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>sample standard deviation</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>numberPerMeterSquared</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>value is not applicable or does not exist</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>S_ERR</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>sample standard error</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>numberPerMeterSquared</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>value is not applicable or does not exist</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>N_EXPECTED</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>number of observations expected to make a summary statistic (e.g., number of days in a month)</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>integer</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>value is not applicable or does not exist</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>N_OBSERVED</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>number of observations actually observed in a sample</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>integer</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>value is not applicable or does not exist</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>N_MISSING</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>the number of values in a sampling period (year or month), given the intended sampling frequency (e.g., every 15 minutes, every day, etc.), that were not available for calculating statistics. This includes the number of values that were flagged as missing (reported missing values), and the number of values that were expected to be in the dataset given the overall sampling frequency but were not present in the dataset (unreported missing values)</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>integer</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>value is not applicable or does not exist</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>N_QUESTIONABLE</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>the number of values in a sampling period (year or month) that were flagged as questionable</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>integer</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>value is not applicable or does not exist</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>N_ESTIMATED</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>the number of values in a sampling period (year or month) that were flagged as estimated</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>integer</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>value is not applicable or does not exist</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>N_TRACE</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>the number of values in a sampling period (year or month) that were flagged as trace values (this is only used for precipitation data)</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>integer</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>value is not applicable or does not exist</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>N_INVALID</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>according to some testing criteria outlined in the summarization script (e.g., temp &gt; 75 degrees C)</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>integer</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NA</code>
            <codeExplanation>value is not applicable or does not exist</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
      <numberOfRecords>8</numberOfRecords>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <site>SBC</site>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <stations>
        <station>SBC-CARP</station>
      </stations>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <stationNames>
        <stationName>Carpinteria Reef, Santa Barbara Channel</stationName>
      </stationNames>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <variableName>animal density of Phanerodon furcatus</variableName>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <unitName>numberPerMeterSquared</unitName>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <timescale>yearly</timescale>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <topic>Biotic structure</topic>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <subtopic>Animal abundance, cover, and density</subtopic>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <sourceMetadataURLs>
        <sourceMetadataURL>http://jornada-www.nmsu.edu/ims/trends/cvs/Trends/metadata/knb-lter-sbc.17.5.xml</sourceMetadataURL>
      </sourceMetadataURLs>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
</ns0:eml>