<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.204.154830" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
  <access authSystem="https://pasta.lternet.edu/authentication" order="allowFirst" scope="document" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=SEV,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <title>Tree Mast Production in  Pinyon-Juniper-Oak Forests at the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico (1997- )</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Roman</givenName>
        <surName>Zlotin</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Department of Geography, Indiana University, Student Building 120</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Bloomington</city>
        <administrativeArea>IN</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>47405</postalCode>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>rzlotin@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">12227</userId>
    </creator>
    <pubDate>2011</pubDate>
    <language>english</language>
    <abstract>
      <section>
        <para>The purpose of this study is to monitor the fruit production of three   woody tree  species  that occur on the Sevilleta National Wildlife   Refuge (NWR).  Two monoecious species, Pinus edulis and Quercus  turbinella, are assessed, as is a dioecious species, Juniperus  monosperma.  In August, fruit production is estimated for  the three species at five  sites within the Sevilleta NWR.  For each of the species different  protocols are used for estimating fruit  production:  P. edulis estimates are made using the number of cones per mature tree,  Q. turbinellla estimates utilize the number of acorns per 0.1m2 of canopy surface area, and J. monosperma estimates use the number of  berries per twig on female trees.  In  addition, the age and/or size of each  individual tree was assessed at  the beginning of the study. For P. edulis and J. monosperma, distinctions continue to be made between young,  medium, old, and very old trees; for Q. turbinella, canopy  surface area is estimated.</para>
      </section>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>populations</keyword>
      <keyword>primary production</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>species</keyword>
      <keyword>ecosystem properties</keyword>
      <keyword>productivity</keyword>
      <keyword>population and community properties</keyword>
      <keyword>diversity</keyword>
      <keyword>riparian</keyword>
      <keyword>growth</keyword>
      <keyword>plant growth</keyword>
      <keyword>tree growth</keyword>
      <keyword>production</keyword>
      <keyword>aboveground production</keyword>
      <keyword>reproduction</keyword>
      <keyword>canopies</keyword>
      <keyword>plants</keyword>
      <keyword>seeds</keyword>
      <keyword>trees</keyword>
      <keyword>vegetation</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <additionalInfo>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>Data collection began in 1997 and is ongoing.</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </additionalInfo>
    <intellectualRights>
      <section>
        <title>Data Policies</title>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated Contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER.  Datasets must be cited as in the example below.

Muldavin, E. 2004. Sevilleta LTER Fertilizer NPP Study Dataset. Albuquerque, NM: Sevilleta Long Term Ecological Research Site Database: SEV155.  (Date of download)

A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.  
 </literalLayout>
        </para>
      </section>
    </intellectualRights>
    <distribution>
      <online>
        <url function="information">http://sev.lternet.edu/node/2048</url>
      </online>
    </distribution>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Location: The Cerro Montosa Pinyon-Juniper site has been the location of major Sevilleta LTER research since 1989. Meteorological trends, net primary productivity, rodent and ground-dwelling arthropod populations, mycorrhizal responses to fertilizer, pinyon-juniper fruit and nut production, and pinyon mortality are all being investigated at this site. Previous studies have included analyses of pinyon tree rings for regional climate reconstruction.Vegetation: The vegetation is New Mexico Pinyon-Juniper Woodland, dominated by Colorado pinyon (Pinus edulis) and one-seed juniper (Juniperus monosperma), and accompanied by gray oak (Quercus grisea).  There is a diverse shrub component, including scrub live oak (Q. turbinella), mountain mahogany (Cercocarpus montanus), broom snakeweed (Gutierrezia sarothrae), sacahuista (Nolina microcarpa), red barberry (Mahonia haematocarpa), Apache plume (Fallugia paradoxa), tree cholla (Opuntia imbricata), skunkbush (Rhus trilobata), and banana yucca (Yucca baccata).  Grass diversity is also high, and open spaces between trees are dominated by blue grama (Bouteloua gracilis), with hairy and sideoats grama (B. hirsuta and B. curtipendula) and black grama (B. eriopoda) also being significant. Other common grasses include purple threeawn (Aristida purpurea), wolftail (Lycurus phleoides), mountain and ring muhly (M. montanus and M. torreyi), and New Mexican porcupinegrass (Heterostipa neomexicana). Common forbs include small-flowered milkvetch (Astragalus nuttallianus), white sagebrush (Artemesia ludoviciana), Fendler&#8217;s arabis (Arabis fendleri), Fendler&#8217;s sandmat (Chamaesyce fendleri), New Mexico thistle (Cirsium neomexicanum), false pennyroyal (Hedeoma oblongifolia), bastard sage (Eriogonum wrightii), ping&#252;e rubberweed (Hymenoxys richardsonii), large four o&#8217;clock (Mirabilis multiflora), Fendler's penstemon (Penstemon fendleri), and globemallows (Sphaeralcea hastulata and S. wrightii). , </geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.535</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.535</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>34.368</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>34.368</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>1976</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>1976</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Location: The UNM Field Station and USFandWS Headquarters are the primary support facilities for all research conducted on the Sevilleta NWR. As such the area has also been important as a research site - especially as regards meteorology and monitoring of rodent populations for Hantavirus. While the breaks above and behind are characterized as black grama dominated desert grassland, the immediate area around the Field Station is best described as an ecotonal mixture of Plains-Mesa Sand Scrub and Great Basin Scrub vegetaion greatly influenced by honey mesquite (Prosopis glandulosa) and the drainages which bisect the area at regular intervals and support many one-seed Junipers (Juniperus monosperma). Dominant grasses include 4 species of dropseed (Sporobolis contractus, S. cryptandrus, S. flexuosus and S. airoides) and indian rice grass (Oryzopsis hymenoides)</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.885</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.885</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>34.356</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>34.356</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>1466</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>1466</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Location: The Goat Draw Juniper Savanna Core Site was established in 1998 in order to provide data at the lower end of the transition from the Pinon-Juniper Woodland habitat at the Cerro Montoso site to Juniper Savanna.Vegetation: While the site is positioned between two ridgelines, the vegetation is best characterized as Juniper Savanna, dominated by one-seed juniper (Juniperus monosperma), scrub liveoak (Quercus turbinella), and grama grasses (Bouteloua curtipendula, B. gracilis, B. eriopoda, and B. hirsuta), with scattered Colorado pinyon pine trees (Pinus edulis) in the upper reaches. There is also a significant influence of Arroyo Riparian vegetation in the main arroyo, Goat Draw, and its tributaries., siteid: 39</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.5228246</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.5228246</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>34.41464054</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>34.41464054</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>1790</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>1790</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1997-01-01</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2015-12-31</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <purpose>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>This study is designed to monitor the fruit production of three woody tree species that occur on the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge (NWR).</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </purpose>
    <maintenance>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>Data were compiled into a single file for all years.  In addition, a year column was added. Cells that had a period (.) or were blank were changed to NA.  Abbreviations were given for sites and   Kartez codes assigned for juniper, pine, and oak.  File was saved  as CSV.   TK. 6 February 2009. Data were qa/qc'd for obivous errors and metadata was  updated.  Added West Mesa site. 11 January 2010. tlk. Changed the  order of variables so that "year" is first and "site" is second.  The order of the other variables has  not been changed, only shifted.  Added information to West Mesa site.  Added Biome Transition Area  site, replacing previous name,  McKenzie Flats. 8 March 2010, tlk. Kristin updated  Roman's personal information. 12 March 2010, tlk.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </maintenance>
    <contact>
      <positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
      <organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>UNM Biology Department, MSC03-2020</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131-0001</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">505 277-2535</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">505 277-2541</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>tech-support@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Information Manager</givenName>
        <surName>Sevilleta LTER</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint> 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">(505) 277.5355</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <para>
              <literalLayout>Site information:At each study site, four 1 ha plots were established.  Each plot was divided into four subplots.Spatial structure of juniper, pinon pine and oak populations:All trees and shrubs within the 1 ha plots were tagged and mapped using either GPS cordinates or compass headings. Height, canopy diameter (in both north-south and west-east directions) and diameter-at-breast-height (DBH) of trunk were measured for all woody plants, including those that died during the drought of the 1950's. Juniper and pinon trees were subdivided into four age/size groups based upon mean canopy radius for juniper and DBH for pinon. For oak trees, the canopy surface area of all individual trees was measured.Measuring mast production:Berry, cone, and acorn production is measured in August when fruits are ripening. Three different methods were developed to estimate annual production.For juniper, the percent of twigs with berries and the quantity of berries per twig are determined every year for all trees in each plot. The average twig has a length of 45 cm and trunk diameter of 12 mm.  Estimates of berry production are made separately for the upper and lower halves of the crown, and for the northwestern, northeastern, and southern sectors and the mean number of berries per  twig calculated.To determine berry production per tree and per hectare, the average number of twigs on trees of different size groups is estimated. Samples of 500-800 berries from a plot are taken randomly each year to determine the percentage of developed and underdeveloped berries, as well as berries with the pericarp damaged by insects.The absolute number of third-year, ripened, green cones is estimated on all trees within the 1 hectare plots. Young brown cones of the second year are also counted to predict the yield of cones the following year. Cones are counted with binoculars. &#160;The unit of pinon mast production is  cones/seeds per mature tree.To estimate cone predation in the spring, the number of damaged female stems and the mortality of conelets are estimated. Then, in August of the following year, samples of 100 green ripened cones are collected randomly on 30-40 trees at each of three pinon sites, and the ratio of filled seeds to empty seeds, as well as the percentage of cones damaged by predatory insects, estimated.Several hundred ripened cones and filled ripen seeds were initially measured to determine their average weight. The average dry weight of a ripened cone consisting of filled seeds was 3.5 g. The weight of a cone with no seeds was 2.1 g, representing 62% of total weight. The average number of filled seeds in a cone was six and the average dry weight of a filled seed 0.22 g, consisting of a seed shell of 0.13 g (59% of seed weight) and a seed core of 0.09 g (41% of seed weight).A different method is used to estimate acorn production. First, the canopy surface area of each oak tree is determined. The number of acorns is counted separately for well-developed, undeveloped, and those damaged by Curculionidae beetle larvae within a 31 cm x 32 cm frame projected onto the crown surface of each oak tree in 3-5 repetitions. Acorns are subdivided into three size groups, small, medium, and large. Medium acorns are most common. To determine the weight of acorns, 100 acorns of each small, medium and large size were collected from 50 different trees.A comparison of production of the three woody species was done on the basis of fruit biomass per unit of measure: well-developed, undamaged berries per twig for juniper, filled seeds per mature tree for pinon  pine, and well-developed, undamaged acorns per 0.1 m2 of canopy surface for oak. Additionally, biomass of  berries, pinon seeds and acorns per hectare was estimated in order to compare production at the five sites and quantify  annual fluctuations.Site abbreviations are as follows:CM=Cerro MontosaGD=Goat DrawFS=Field StationMF=McKenzie Flats222=222/Red TankWM=West MesaPlot:Plot refers to the 1 ha area and associated subplots where data is collected. Values range from I1-I4, II1-II4, III1-III4, IV1-IV4.</literalLayout>
            </para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <qualityControl>
        <description>
          <para>
            <literalLayout>&#160;Datasheets were visually assessed for any errors.</literalLayout>
          </para>
        </description>
      </qualityControl>
    </methods>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>sev204_mastproductionall_20150114.txt</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Data for SEV204</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>sev204_mastproductionall_20150114.txt</objectName>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>https://pasta.lternet.edu/package/data/eml/knb-lter-sev/204/154830/a081e7948e345daa847a1b2ecb4ef2d7</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <coverage>
        <temporalCoverage>
          <rangeOfDates>
            <beginDate>
              <calendarDate>1997-01-01</calendarDate>
            </beginDate>
            <endDate>
              <calendarDate>2014-01-01</calendarDate>
            </endDate>
          </rangeOfDates>
        </temporalCoverage>
      </coverage>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Year</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Year</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The year in which the data were collected.  </attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>date</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>YYYY</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Site</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Site</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The site at which data was collected</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>CM</code>
                    <definition> Cerro Montosa</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>GD</code>
                    <definition> Goat Draw</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>FS</code>
                    <definition> Field Station</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>MF</code>
                    <definition> McKenzie Flats</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>222</code>
                    <definition> Two-22</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>WM</code>
                    <definition> West Mesa</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Species</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Species</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Kartez code for species being sampled based on the USDA plants database.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Kartez code for species being sampled based on the USDA plants database.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Plot</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Plot</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>This is the plot and subplot, if any, where the data were collected.  The format is Plot.subplot, e.g., II.1 refers to Plot II, subplot 1.  </attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>This is the plot and subplot, if any, where the data were collected.  The format is Plot.subplot, e.g., II.1 refers to Plot II, subplot 1.  </definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Field Identification number</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Field-ID#</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Tag number on a tree. An '*' means tree is near arroyo.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Tag number on a tree. An '*' means tree is near arroyo.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Age or Size</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Age/Size</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The age of pinon or juniper and size of oak</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>Y</code>
                    <definition>Young tree</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>M</code>
                    <definition>Medium sized tree </definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>O</code>
                    <definition>Old tree</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>VO</code>
                    <definition>Very old tree </definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>#</code>
                    <definition>size of an oak tree</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Tree location</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Location</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Location of tree, often described relative to other trees</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Location of tree, often described relative to other trees</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Dead Canopy (%)</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>D.Canopy</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Percentage of dead canopy</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>percent</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>5</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">95</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Fruit/Count</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Fruit/Count</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Number of fruits for each individual tree. For JUMO, # berries per twig of female tree; for PIED, # cones per mature tree; for QUTU2, # acorns per 0.1m2 of canopy surface area. </attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>number</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">1100</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
        <ns2:unit abbreviation="%" constantToSI="0" id="percent" multiplierToSI="100" name="percent" parentSI="numberPerNumber" unitType="dimensionless">
          <ns2:description>ratio of two quantities as percent composition (1:100)</ns2:description>
        </ns2:unit>
      </ns2:unitList>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
</ns0:eml>