<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-sev.65.154595" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
  <access authSystem="https://pasta.lternet.edu/authentication" order="allowFirst" scope="document" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=SEV,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <title>Soil Surface Dynamics in the Chihuahuan Desert at the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge, New Mexico (1994- )</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Carleton</givenName>
        <surName>White</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Sevilleta LTER, 167 Castetter Hall, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>cswhite@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">9443</userId>
    </creator>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>John</givenName>
        <surName>Craig</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Department of Biology, MSC03 2020, University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>jcraig@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="http://sev.lternet.edu/">10424</userId>
      <role>data manager</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <pubDate>2010</pubDate>
    <language>english</language>
    <abstract>
      <section>
        <para>Observations of the soil surface on the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge indicate that the surface is very dynamic.  During collections of decomposition bags it has been noted that the bags are frequently resting on pedestals of soil, often 2-3cm above the surrounding surface. This study will attempt to measure the dynamics of the soil surface using a specially designed soil bridge.  The soil bridge will allow for repeated measurements of the relative height of the soil surface at several sites on the Sevilleta. These measurements will be used to assess the impact of the changing soil surface on nutrient cycling.</para>
      </section>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>disturbance</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>measurements</keyword>
      <keyword>canopies</keyword>
      <keyword>roads</keyword>
      <keyword>soil</keyword>
      <keyword>deserts</keyword>
      <keyword>grasslands</keyword>
      <keyword>plants</keyword>
      <keyword>grasses</keyword>
      <keyword>shrubs</keyword>
      <keyword>vegetation</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <additionalInfo>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>&#160;This research project measures soil microtopography of 5 bridges at 4 sites: Deep Well, Cerro Montosa, Red Tank, and Rio Salado. Deep Well site includes soil collections from under grass and open patches for N mineralization. Five additional sites installed on Deb Coffin's experimental plots: 6 bridges at 3 sites, 9 bridges at 2 sites&#160;</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </additionalInfo>
    <intellectualRights>
      <section>
        <title>Data Policies</title>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>This dataset is released to the public and may be freely downloaded. Please keep the designated Contact person informed of any plans to use the dataset. Consultation or collaboration with the original investigators is strongly encouraged. Publications and data products that make use of the dataset must include proper acknowledgement of the Sevilleta LTER.  Datasets must be cited as in the example below.

Muldavin, E. 2004. Sevilleta LTER Fertilizer NPP Study Dataset. Albuquerque, NM: Sevilleta Long Term Ecological Research Site Database: SEV155.  (Date of download)

A copy of any publications using these data must be supplied to the Sevilleta LTER Information Manager.  
 </literalLayout>
        </para>
      </section>
    </intellectualRights>
    <distribution>
      <online>
        <url function="information">http://sev.lternet.edu/node/3090</url>
      </online>
    </distribution>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Location: Five Points is the area which encompasses the Five Points Black Grama and Five Points Creosote Core study sites and falls along the transition between Chihuahuan Desert Scrub and Desert Grassland habitats. Both sites are subject to intensive research activity, including NPP measurement, phenology observation, pollinator diversity studies, and ground dwelling arthropod and rodent population assessments. There are drought rain-out shelters in both the Black Grama and Creosote sites, as well as the mixed-ecotone, with co-located ET Towers.Vegetation: The Five Points Creosote site is characterized as Chihuahuan Desert Scrub, dominated by a creosotebush overstory with broom snakeweed, purple pricklypear (O. macrocentra) and soapweed yucca as notable shrubs. The site is also characterized by numerous dense grass dominated patches, reflecting proximity to the Five Points Black Grama site and the relatively recent appearance of creosotebush. Dominant grasses are black grama, fluffgrass (Dasyochloa pulchellum), burrograss (Scleropogon brevifolia), bush muhly (M. porteri), and galleta (Pleuraphis jamesii). Notable forb species include field bahia (Bahia absinthifolia), baby aster (Chaetopappa ericoides), plains hiddenflower (Cryptantha crassisepala), Indian rushpea (Hoffmannseggia glauca), Fendlers bladderpod (Lesquerella fendleri), and globemallow (Sphaeralcea spp.).  Five Points Black Grama habitat is ecotonal in nature, bordering Chihuahuan Desert Scrub at its southern extent and Plains-Mesa Grassland at its northern, more mesic boundary.  There is also a significant presence of shrubs, particularly broom snakeweed (Gutierrezia sarothrae), along with less abundant fourwing saltbush (Atriplex canescens), Mormon tea (Ephedra torreyana), winterfat (Krascheninnikovia lanata), tree cholla (Opuntia imbricata), club cholla (O. clavata), desert pricklypear (O. phaeacantha), soapweed yucca (Yucca glauca), and what are presumed to be encroaching, yet sparsely distributed, creosotebush (Larrea tridentata).  Characteristically, the dominant grass is black grama (Bouteloua eriopoda). Spike, sand, and mesa dropseed grasses (Sporobolus contractus, S. cryptandrus, S. flexuosus) and sand muhly (Muhlenbergia arenicola) could be considered co-dominant throughout, along with blue grama (B. gracilis) in a more mesic, shallow swale on the site.  Notable forb species include trailing four o&#8217;clock (Allionia incarnata), horn loco milkvetch (Astragalus missouriensis), sawtooth spurge (Chamaesyce serrula), plains hiddenflower (Cryptantha crassisepala), blunt tansymustard (Descarania obtusa), wooly plaintain (Plantago patagonica), globemallow (Sphaeralcea wrightii), and mouse ear (Tidestromia lanuginosa)., siteid: 2</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>106.717</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>106.717</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>34.3381</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>34.3381</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>1615</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>1615</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Location: The Cerro Montosa Pinyon-Juniper site has been the location of major Sevilleta LTER research since 1989. Meteorological trends, net primary productivity, rodent and ground-dwelling arthropod populations, mycorrhizal responses to fertilizer, pinyon-juniper fruit and nut production, and pinyon mortality are all being investigated at this site. Previous studies have included analyses of pinyon tree rings for regional climate reconstruction.Vegetation: The vegetation is New Mexico Pinyon-Juniper Woodland, dominated by Colorado pinyon (Pinus edulis) and one-seed juniper (Juniperus monosperma), and accompanied by gray oak (Quercus grisea).  There is a diverse shrub component, including scrub live oak (Q. turbinella), mountain mahogany (Cercocarpus montanus), broom snakeweed (Gutierrezia sarothrae), sacahuista (Nolina microcarpa), red barberry (Mahonia haematocarpa), Apache plume (Fallugia paradoxa), tree cholla (Opuntia imbricata), skunkbush (Rhus trilobata), and banana yucca (Yucca baccata).  Grass diversity is also high, and open spaces between trees are dominated by blue grama (Bouteloua gracilis), with hairy and sideoats grama (B. hirsuta and B. curtipendula) and black grama (B. eriopoda) also being significant. Other common grasses include purple threeawn (Aristida purpurea), wolftail (Lycurus phleoides), mountain and ring muhly (M. montanus and M. torreyi), and New Mexican porcupinegrass (Heterostipa neomexicana). Common forbs include small-flowered milkvetch (Astragalus nuttallianus), white sagebrush (Artemesia ludoviciana), Fendler&#8217;s arabis (Arabis fendleri), Fendler&#8217;s sandmat (Chamaesyce fendleri), New Mexico thistle (Cirsium neomexicanum), false pennyroyal (Hedeoma oblongifolia), bastard sage (Eriogonum wrightii), ping&#252;e rubberweed (Hymenoxys richardsonii), large four o&#8217;clock (Mirabilis multiflora), Fendler's penstemon (Penstemon fendleri), and globemallows (Sphaeralcea hastulata and S. wrightii). , </geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.535</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.535</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>34.368</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>34.368</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>1976</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>1976</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Location: This site is located in the foothills of the Sierra Ladrones on the west side of the Sevilleta NWR. Red Tank is a man-made earthen drainage pool and is the location of Met Station 43.  Research conducted at the site includes soil moisture and erosion studies  related to the Sierra Ladrone watershed project.Vegetation: The woody vegetation in this stream bed includes juniper (Juniperus monosperma), Brickellia californica, Apache plume (Fallugia paradoxa).  On the hills are Junipers and shrubs such as cane cholla (Opuntia imbricata), beargrass (Nolina microcarpa), and Oreganillo (Aloysia wrightii). The herbs in the washes include Lesquerella ovalifolia, and Mirabilis multiflora.  The grasses found at this site include three-awn (Aristida sp.), fluff-grass Erioneuron pulchellum, and  four species of grama grass (Bouteloua spp.).
, siteid: 12</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>107.036806</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>107.036806</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>34.398</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>34.398</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>1766</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>1766</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Location: The Rio Salado is an ephemeral tributary of the Rio Grande on the west side of the Sevilleta NWR, flowing west by northwest to east by southeast. Rio Salado Grassland and Rio Salado Larrea are two study sites established in 1989. These sites were established&#160;as counterparts to sites at Five Points. Between 1989 and 1998, vegetation, litter decomposition, and ground dwelling arthropod and rodent populations were studied at both sites. Core studies at these sites were largely terminated in 1998, although rodent populations are still monitored at the Rio Salado Larrea site as the Small Mammal Exclosure Study's Larrea plots are co-located there. Rio Salado Grassland is the location of Met Station 44. The Rio Salado study sites are accessed by taking the San Acacia exit, going west and then taking the frontage road back north to the Sevilleta NWR gate.&#160; After entering the refuge turn left after 0.2 mi and take this road 1.4 mi to a "T" in the road at the power lines.&#160; An earthen berm stops road travel here and the met station is located about 300 m west on the blocked road. &#160; Vegetation: The Rio Salado Grassland site is Plains-Mesa Sand Scrub habitat characterized by
stabilized deep-sand dominated by coppice dunes of honey mesquite (Prosopis
glandulosa). Co-dominant shrubs are sand sagebrush (Artemesia filifolia) and
fourwing saltbush (Atriplex canescens), with winterfat (Krascheninnikovia
lanata), Mormon tea (Ephedra torreyana), broom indigobush (Psorothamnus
scoparius), soapweed yucca (Yucca glauca), and broom snakeweed (Gutierrezia
sarothrae) as other notable shrubs. One-seed juniper (Juniperus monosperma) is
present as well, especially along shallow washes. Compared to the Black Grama
Core Site, grass cover is sparse and dominated by poverty threeawn (Aristida
divaricata), Indian ricegrass (Oryzopsis hymenoides), mesa and spike dropseed
(Sporobolus cryptandrus and S. contractus), as well as patches of black grama
(Bouteloua eriopoda). Notable forbs included spectaclepod (Dimorphocarpa
wislizenii), tansy aster (Machaeranthera tanacetifolia), desert marigold
(Baileya multiradiata), Abert buckwheat (Eriogonum abertianum), dwarf gilia
(Ipomopsis pumila), rattlesnake weed (Chamaesyce albomarginata), blunt
tansymustard (Descarania obtusa), plains hiddenflower (Cryptantha crassisepala),
and Rocky Mountain zinnia (Zinnia grandiflora)., siteid: 13</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-106.9267</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-106.9267</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>34.269</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>34.269</southBoundingCoordinate>
          <boundingAltitudes>
            <altitudeMinimum>1503</altitudeMinimum>
            <altitudeMaximum>1503</altitudeMaximum>
            <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
          </boundingAltitudes>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1994-11-16</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2009-10-14</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <maintenance>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>&#160;9/12/94  Project approved by Sevilleta LTER PCP
9/20/94  File initiated by John A. Craig
10/21/94 Wrote initial abstract - JAC
12/18/95 appended initial data (analyzed for Sevilleta Symposium Jan. 1996)
9/26/96  Added description of variables
2/14/00  Appended data through 1998
2/25/05  Appended data through 2005
4/21/09  Appended data through 2008 -- Carl White
10/29/09 Appended data through 2009 -- Carl White</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </maintenance>
    <contact>
      <positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
      <organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>UNM Biology Department, MSC03-2020</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131-0001</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">505 277-2535</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">505 277-2541</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>tech-support@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Information Manager</givenName>
        <surName>Sevilleta LTER</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>SEV LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint> 1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <postalCode>87131</postalCode>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(505) 277-2109</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">(505) 277.5355</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>data-use@sevilleta.unm.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    <pubPlace>Sevilleta LTER</pubPlace>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <para>
              <literalLayout>Experimental Design:The purpose of this experiment was to determine the magnitude of change in the soil surface at certain locations around the Sevilleta. The locations chosen were thought to be characteristic of the vegetation types in which they occurred, but this experiment was NOT designed to test whether or not certain vegetation types had more dynamic soil surfaces. To address that question, replication of the vegetation types would be necessary. The locations are not&#160;standardized for parent material (underlying geology), slope, aspect, or geomorphic position, although the sites were selected to minimize differences in these characteristics. &#160;Each site has a total of 5 bridges that are about 75 m apart and covers a total of about 300 m. along an approximate contour at site 1 and 4 and perpendicular to the approximate contours over an elevational range at sites 2 and 3. &#160;Installation of the bridge began by randomly selecting the spot for the first rebar after the approximate location was determined. The first rebar (24 in.) was driven in until about 15 to 20 mm extended above the soil surface. The bridge was then placed over the rebar and the location for the second rebar was determined by the position of the hole in the other end of the bridge. &#160;The second rebar was driven to the proper depth to level the bridge (determined by the bubble level permanently mounted on the bridge). When the bridge was level, wood shims were inserted into the end of the bridge to secure the bridge around the rebar and to make the bridge more rigid. &#160;A pointed aluminum pin (60 cm) was inserted through hole #16 (the middle hole) and lowered to the soil&#160;surface to indicate placement of the spike (with depression in head). The bridge was removed and the spike driven until the head was flush with the soil surface. &#160;The bridge was replaced, the middle pin inserted through the bridge into the depression in the head of the spike and shims inserted into the end of the bridge. &#160;Pins were inserted through the holes in the bridge and lowered to the soil surface. &#160;If the pin struck vegetation while being inserted, canopy&#160;coverage was recorded for that pin (indicated by a '1' in cover column; '0' indicates no cover). &#160;If the pin struck plant basal coverage at the soil surface, basal cover was recorded (indicated by a '1' in basal cover column; '0' indicates no basal cover). &#160;If the soil surface was not hard enough to support the pin, the pin was secured by a clothespin at the top of the bridge. &#160;The height of each pin above the bridge was recorded only to the nearest mm (or last mm mark to be&#160;seen above the pin). &#160;After heights of all 31 pins (including #16, the middle reference pin above the spike) and their canopy or basal intercept were recorded, the bridge was removed, leaving the two end rebar pieces and the middle spike for permanent reference.Sites:Bridges 1.1, 1.2, 1.3, 1.4, and 1.5 are located east of the original fertilizer plots south of deep well. Bridges 2.1, 2.2, 2.3, 2.4, and 2.5 are located at the top of Goat Draw on the east side of the Los Pinos Mountains. Bridge 2.6 is a special bridge that was set at the top of an arroyo head-cut to measure dynamics in arroyo formations. Bridge 2.7 was set at an apparent nick on the slope where a rill formation may occur (the beginning of a potential arroyo).Embedded Study:Bridges 1.1 through 1.5 were identified within an area to be burned in the summer of 2003. &#160;In June of 2003, 5 new bridges were established&#160;at about 200 m to the west of the original bridges to serve as controls to maintain the long-term untreated measurements at that site. The original bridges (1.1 through 1.5) were measured on 11 June 2003 and the new bridges (identified as 7196, 7197, 7198, 7199, and 7200) were established on 13 June 2003. The new bridges were essentially the same with respect to plant cover, basal cover, and variation in microtopography as the original bridges. The original&#160;bridge sites were burned by prescribed fire on 19 June 2003, with the initial post-fire sampling occurring on 23 June 2003.&#160;Instrumentation:The soil bridge consists of a 6 ft. length of 1.5 in. (OD) aluminum square bar or tubing. &#160;Beginning at ---, brass bushings were set in the tubing at 5 cm intervals (31 each). &#160;A bubble level was secured to the top of the bridge (the bubble level was always on the left side of the bridge, hole #1 the closest to the level). &#160;A hole approximately --- from the end of the bridge was made in the bottom of the bar to fit over the rebar that is driven into the ground. The bridge is removed after each measurement and stored at the Biology Annex.Data Collection Methods:Data collected are date of sampling, location, height of each pin above the bar, and an indication of canopy and basal intercept for each pin. &#160;Data are recorded in a surveyor's book and then transcribed to computer spreadsheets for data management.NOTE: Beginning on 19 April 2004, two additional data columns were initiated. These columns were cover and basal cover by annual herbaceous plants. These new data were collected in response to the large increase in annual herbaceous plants on the burned plots (1.1 through 1.5)&#160; This information has been collected an all sites following 19 April 2005.</literalLayout>
            </para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>sev065_bridges_03012012.txt</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Data for SEV065</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>sev065_bridges_03012012.txt</objectName>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url>https://pasta.lternet.edu/package/data/eml/knb-lter-sev/65/154595/469fe000950adce77eb0e662aeb47300</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <coverage>
        <temporalCoverage>
          <rangeOfDates>
            <beginDate>
              <calendarDate>1994-11-16</calendarDate>
            </beginDate>
            <endDate>
              <calendarDate>2011-10-13</calendarDate>
            </endDate>
          </rangeOfDates>
        </temporalCoverage>
      </coverage>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>date</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>date</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The date in which data were collected.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>date</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>YYYYMMDD</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>site</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>site</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The site at which data was collected.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>1.1-1.5 </code>
                    <definition> East of original fertilizer plots, south of Deep Well</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>2.1-2.7 </code>
                    <definition> Goat Draw</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>3.1-3.5 </code>
                    <definition> unknown</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>4.1-4.5 </code>
                    <definition> unknown</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>7016-7050 </code>
                    <definition> unknown</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>7100 </code>
                    <definition> unknown</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>7196-7200 </code>
                    <definition> Same as 1.1-1.5, but installed in June 2003</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>pin</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>pin</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>The pin number.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>The pin number.</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>height</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>height</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Height of pin above bridge.</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <customUnit>millimeters</customUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>canopy</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>canopy</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Indicates whether pin strikes vegetation above the ground</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>1 </code>
                    <definition> indicates plant canopy present at that pin location</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>0 </code>
                    <definition> indicates canopy absent</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>basal</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>basal</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Indicates if pin rests on basal part of plant.</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>1 </code>
                    <definition> indicates plant basal cover present</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>0 </code>
                    <definition> indicates no basal cover</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>hcanopy</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>hcanopy</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Indicates if pin strikes herbaceous canopy</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>1 </code>
                    <definition> canopy of annual herbaceous plants present</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>0 </code>
                    <definition> if abscent</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>hbasal</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>hbasal</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Indicates if pin rests on herbaceous basal area (as opposed to grass basal area).</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <enumeratedDomain>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>1 </code>
                    <definition> indicates basal cover of annual herbaceous plants present</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                  <codeDefinition>
                    <code>0 </code>
                    <definition> if abscent</definition>
                  </codeDefinition>
                </enumeratedDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <ns2:unitList xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/stmml.xsd">
        <ns2:unit abbreviation="" constantToSI="0" id="millimeters" multiplierToSI="0.001" name="millimeters" parentSI="meter" unitType="length">
          <ns2:description>millimeter</ns2:description>
        </ns2:unit>
      </ns2:unitList>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
</ns0:eml>