<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-cdr.154.1" scope="system" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd">
  <access authSystem="https://pasta.lternet.edu/authentication" order="allowFirst" scope="document" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=CDR,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <alternateIdentifier>knb-lter-cdr.154.1</alternateIdentifier>
    <shortName>hte052</shortName>
    <title>Maximum plant height along transects: Interactive Effects of Fertility and Distribution on Plant Community Diversity and Structure</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Scott</givenName>
        <surName>Wilson</surName>
      </individualName>
    </creator>
    <metadataProvider>
      <organizationName>Cedar Creek LTER</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Cedar Creek Ecosystem Science Reserve</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>100 Ecology Building</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>1987 Upper Buford Circle</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Saint Paul</city>
        <administrativeArea>MN</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>55108</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">612-625-5740</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">612-624-6777</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>webmaster@cedarcreek.umn.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.cedarcreek.umn.edu/</onlineUrl>
    </metadataProvider>
    <pubDate>2013-07-16</pubDate>
    <abstract>
      <para>There are four levels of nitrogen, corresponding to treatments A, C, E and G in E001, applied at the same time as in that experiment. For a description of fertilizer added to E052, see file fertilization details. There are four levels of soil disturbance designated 1, 2, 3 and 4.

Level 1: undisturbed
Level 2: 1 pass with a 7 HP Honda rear-tined rototiller with the elevator set to till to a depth of 9 inches
Level 3: 2 passes or however many required to produce about 50% bare ground
Level 4: 3 passes or however many required to produce 100% bare ground. This requires 3 passes in some plots but 5 or 6 in others. In addition, all woody vegetation not destroyed by tilling is cut at the base.

Rototilling is applied in late April.

Each fertilization treatment receives each disturbance treatment, for a total of sixteen treatments. There are four replicates of each of the sixteen treatments. In addition, the four extreme ends (lowest N, lowest disturbance; highest N, lowest disturbance, etc. ) are replicated an additional ten times. Treatments are applied in a completely randomized design. Each of the 104 plots is 5m x 5m.

Measurements taken at E052 will include: 1) species abundances, 2) community biomass allocation to leaves/roots/stems/flowers, 3) above and below ground net primary production and 4) rates of nitrogen mineralization. For a list of treatments, see the treatment layouts in file trmte52.

The plots in E052 are enclosed by a fence to exclude mammalian herbivores. Galvanized welded-wire hardware cloth with 6mm x 6mm openings was buried to a depth of 50cm. Additional hardware cloth extends 60cm above the ground and poultry netting extends to 2m above the ground.

In 1990, ten plots of each of four treatments (N1D1, N1D4, N4D1, N4D4, where N is the level of nitrogen added and D is the disturbance treatment) were randomly selected for the competition experiment. The above and belowground effects of neighbors on transplanted grass seedlings were measured using three competition treatments: transplants were grown in 50cm diameter subplots 1) with no neighbors, 2) with the roots but not shoots of neighbors, 3) with all above and belowground parts of neighbors present. One transplant was grown in the center of each subplot. Competition treatments were applied to subplots within the main plots during 14-18 May, 1990. Competition treatments were replicated three times in each of the ten replicate plots for each of the four combinations of nitrogen supply rate and disturbance. Thus, the 40 plots of the nitrogen and disturbance combinations (2 nitrogen levels x 2 disturbance levels x 10 replicates) each contained 9 subplots (3 competition treatments x 3 replicates), each subplot comprising one transplant in one competition treatment. A total of 360 seedlings were transplanted. Competition treatments were assigned randomly to subplots within each plot.

In 1991, three species of contrasting sizes, life histories, growth rates and positions along gradients of nitrogen and disturbance in the experiment were used: Schizachyrium scoparium, Agropyron repens, and Setaria viridis. Transplants were grown individually in subplots, with 1) all neighbors and 2) no neighbors. The experiment was conducted in high and low nutrient environments to test for the interaction between the environment, the size and the species. There were ten replicate plots of each of the two environments, one receiving no additional nitrogen and the second receiving nitrogen at 17g/m2/yr. In total, there were 32 transplants (3 species x 3 size classes x 2 competition treatments x 1, 2 or 3 replicates) in each plot, and 20 plots (2 environments x 10 replicates), or 640 transplants. Seedlings were transplanted into the field during 3-6 June, 1991.</para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Biodiversity</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Climatic Variation</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Disturbance Patterns</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Ecology</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Ecosystem functioning</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Fire Frequency</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Long Term</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Nitrogen limitation</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Nutrient Budgets</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Nutrient Cycles</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Plant Competition</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Primary Productivity</keyword>
      <keyword keywordType="theme">Successional dynamics</keyword>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <section>
        <title>Code of Ethics and Rules for Use of Cedar Creek LTER and Related Data</title>
        <para>As a condition for access to data provided by researchers of the Cedar Creek LTER, I agree to abide by the following code of ethics.</para>
        <para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>A. I agree to notify the Cedar Creek LTER scientists who gathered data if I would like to use those data in any publication. I acknowledge that these data were gathered by Cedar Creek scientists because they had already perceived the importance of these data for a variety of scientific and societal issues. I will provide them with formal recognition that, at their discretion, may include co-authorship or acknowledgements on publications.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>B. I realize that the researchers who gathered these data may be using them for scientific analyses, papers or publications that are currently planned or in preparation, and that such activities have precedence over any that I might wish to prepare. In this case, my preparation of any work may be delayed, at the option of the Cedar Creek researchers involved, until their work is completed.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>C. Because it may be possible to misinterpret a data set if it is taken out of context, I will seek the assistance and opinion of those Cedar Creek researchers involved in the design of a study and the collection of the data as I analyze the data. Moreover, I realize that this computer data set is not complete, and it may contain errors. The complete data set includes extensive written documentation, which should be referenced to reduce the chance of errors in data and errors of interpretation.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para>
      </section>
    </intellectualRights>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage id="geoReferenceID">
        <geographicDescription> The Cedar Creek Ecosystem Science Reserve is located in Anoka and Isanti counties, approximately 30 miles north of Saint Paul, MN. CCNHA lies at the boundary between prairie and forest. It is a mosaic of uplands dominated by oak savanna, prairie, hardwood forest, pine forests,and abandoned agricultural fields and of lowlands comprised of ash and cedar swamps, acid bogs, marshes, and sedge meadows. Large tracts of the pre-agricultural ecosystems of the region are preserved within its boundaries, as is a successional chronosequence of more than 80 old fields of known history.</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-93.22445</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-93.16289</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>45.44138</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>45.384865</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1990</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>1990</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <contact>
      <positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
      <organizationName>LTER Network Office</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>UNM Biology Department, MSC03-2020</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>1 University of New Mexico</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <administrativeArea>NM</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>87131-0001</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">505 277-2535</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">505 277-2541</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>tech-support@lternet.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Dan</givenName>
        <surName>Bahauddin</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Cedar Creek Ecosystem Science Reserve</organizationName>
      <positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Ecology Evolution and Behaviour Dept. University Of Minnesota</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>100 Ecology Building</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>1987 Upper Buford Circle</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Saint Paul</city>
        <administrativeArea>MN</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>55108</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">612-625-5740</phone>
      <phone phonetype="fax">612-624-6777</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>webmaster@cedarcreek.umn.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>"Microplot" Fertilization Treatments</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>The "microplot" fertilization treatments are used in experiments 1, 2, 4, 8, 9, 11, 23, 25, and 52. Experiments 5, 6, 28, 36,53,97, 98 and 100 are conducted within plots that are fertilized and should be treated as part of the fertilized plot.  There are nine treatment levels, assigned a letter A through I. This is also equivalent to the numeric labels 1 to 9. Treatment levels A through H differ in the amount of NH4NO3 added. Treatment I is a true control and receives no nutrients. The nutrients are applied twice a year, once in early May and once in late June. An exception is experiment 25 where time of application is experimentally manipulated. Not all experiments  use all possible treatments. Nutrients are given in g/m2 for each fertilization; plot area and treatments used follow the nutrient lists.

Treatment A to H receive the following base nutrients:
	 	 	
Rate  	Volume  	Element
10 g/m2  	150 ml  	P2O5 (0-46-0)
10 g/m2  	150 ml  	K2O (0-0-61)
20 g/m2  	200 ml  	CaCO3 (lime)
15m2  	200 ml  	MgSO4 (Epsom Salts)
0.0625 ml/m2  	trace mineral solution in 1 ml to 10 ml sand	 	 	

The description for making trace mineral sand is at the end of this section.

The amount of NH4NO3 fertilizer added at the different treatment levels is:
	 	 	
Treatment  	Rate  	Volume
A  	0.0 g/m2  	0 ml
B  	1.5 g/m2  	25 ml
C  	3.0 g/m2  	50 ml
D  	5.0 g/m2  	90 ml
E  	8.0 g/m2  	140 ml
F  	14.0 g/m2  	250 ml
G  	25.0 g/m2  	445 ml
H  	40.0 g/m2  	710 ml
I  	0.0 g/m2  	0 ml	 	 	

These rates are added twice a year. Actual annual N addition is calculated as:

0.34%N * rate (g/m2) * 2 times/year

The trace mineral stock solutions are made by adding the following grams of reagent to 1000 ml of water:

CuSO4*5H2O 9.8 g
ZnSO4*7H2O 22.0 g
or
ZnCl2 10.5 g
CoCl2*6H2O 10.0 g
MnCl2*4H2O 180.0 g
Na2MoO4*2H2O 6.3 g
H3BO3 6.0 g

The trace metal solution is made by combining 120ml of each stock solution, adding 67.2g of citric acid dissolved in deionized water and adding deionized water to bring the volume to a total of 2 liters. The working solution is then autoclaved to chelate the trace metals.

The size of the plots and treatments used for each experiment are:
	 	 	
Experiment  	Treatments  	Plot size (m2)
Experiment 1 except Field D  	A thru I  	16
Experiment 1 Field D  	A thru I  	6
Experiment 2  	A thru I  	16
Experiment 4  	E, G, I  	1000
Experiment 8  	C, F, H, I  	16
Experiment 9  	C, F, H, I  	16
Experiment 11  	E, G, I  	16
Experiment 24  	E, G, I  	16
Experiment 25  	E, G, I  	5.25
Experiment 52  	A, C, F, G  	25</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Field Operations: Fencing</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>The plots in experiment E052 are enclosed by a fence to exclude mammalian herbivores. Galvanized welded-wire hardware cloth with 6mm x 6mm openings was buried to a depth of 84cm. Additional hardware cloth extends 60cm above the ground, and poultry netting extends to 1.8m above the ground.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Field Operations: Fertilization</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Fertilizer is mixed and spread by hand twice a year, once in early May and once in late June. Each plot gets the fertilizer mixture specified by its fertilizer treatment code</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Field Operations: Mammal Trapping</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Pocket gophers are trapped out of the fields as soon as they appear. Gopher mounds are then removed and vegetation is unburied.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Field Operations: Rototilling</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Rototilling is done in April. Each plot receives the amount of rototilling it should get according to the disturbance treatment each plot is assigned.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Field Operations: Neighbor Exclusion</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>1990: The no neighbors treatment was imposed by severing all roots at the perimeter of a subplot to a depth of 15cm once each sample period. All plants in the subplots were sprayed with a systemic, rapidly decomposing herbicide (Roundup). Any resprouting neighbor biomass was severed at the soil surface and removed by hand. Transplants were grown with only the roots of neighbors by using plastic netting to pull back the shoots (50x50cm;mesh:1x2cm) was fastened to the soil surface at the center of the subplot using four steel pins each 8cm long. The center portion (5x5cm) of the net was cut out to allow transplanting. The outer corners of the net were held 10cm above the soil using pins 20cm long. The all neighbors treatment comprised a transplant grown in the center of a 50x50cm subplot containing the existing, undisturbed vegetation of the plot. 1991:The no neighbor treatment was imposed by driving a tube 10cm deep and 11cm in diameter into the soil and killing all neighbor material inside with Roundup. Each tube was surrounded by garden netting (50 x50cm) to ensure that transplants in no neighbor treatments received an equal and constant amount of light. Transplants in all neighbor treatments also had tubes installed around them in order to make a comparable amount of environmental space available to transplants in both the neighbor and no neighbor treatments.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Field Operations: Additional notes</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>On May 5, 1995, a wildfire burned all of the plots in experiment 52 in field B.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Light Penetration</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Light meter readings for E052 are taken in the same way as in E001 except that only one set of readings (one above and one below the vegetation) is taken in each plot.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Light Penetration Measurements Methods</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>From 1982 to 1988, light meter readings were taken using a Li-Cor, Inc. Integrating Quantum/Radiometer/Photometer, model LI-188B. Two people were needed to take light readings with this system. One would hold the control box and record data and the other would hold the light sensor. The batteries would be checked before starting each session. If the batteries were OK, they would proceed to take readings. The sensor was connected to the control box by a relatively short cord, so the two people taking readings were required to stay close together. When taking readings, it was necessary to get a range value for each light value entered. If the integrating time of 1 second was not sufficient, it was increased to 10 seconds. This was also recorded.

In 1989, two new light meters were acquired. These are SF Sunfleck Ceptometers, model SF-40 (40cm probe). They were purchased from Decagon Devices, Inc., P.O. Box 835, Pullman, WA 99163. One person can easily handle a ceptometer alone. This makes is possible for three people to get the readings done more quickly and easily. One person records data while the other two take readings from the plots simultaneously. No range values are needed. To take readings a person needs to select function #1 (PAR readings), position the probe (see below) and press ``A' (read value). More than one reading can be taken and then averaged by pressing a certain sequence of letters (A, A, B, B, A).

Measurements are taken within a 4 hour period, 2 hours on either side of solar noon. (Solar noon is half way between sunrise and sunset; it is not 1200 hours). Solar noon is at 1315 hours, Central Daylight Time. Samples are taken between 1115 hours and 1515 hours. Measurements are not taken when the plot being sampled is shaded. Light readings are done when the sky is clear, whenever possible. If a cloud passes over the plot being sampled, assistants wait for the cloud to pass before taking the readings. If the sky is mostly cloudy, light meter readings are not taken.

Two measurements are taken in each plot. Each measurement consists of one reading above the vegetation and a second reading at ground level. Both values are taken to get the percent of sunlight above the vegetation that reaches ground level. In taking the above vegetation reading, the sensor must be kept level, held high above all vegetation, kept out of the shade (of plants and people) and it must be clean. When taking the below vegetation reading, at ground level, the sensor must be kept level, out of the soil and out of the shade created by people.

In 1991, light meter readings were only taken in E026 and E055. Light profiles were taken using an A-shaped frame made of aluminum. Wires were strung across the frame at 10cm intervals. The frame was placed over the subplot being metered. A reading was taken over the top of the frame, and then at each 10cm level, by placing the light meter across the wires, starting at 90cm above the ground. Readings were taken every 10cm down the frame and again at ground level.
Light Data Transformations:
Light readings are transformed to obtain percent light penetration which represents the percent of light above the vegetation that reaches the ground surface. In cases where the experiment involves shading, another variable is computed to reflect the percent of sun light that reaches above the canopy. This variable is called light available. In the case of absence of artificial shades, the latter is set to 1.

percent light penetration = ( Light below canopy / Light above canopy ).

percent light available = ( Light below shade / Light above shade ).</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Animal Sampling Methods</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Small mammal trapping in E052 consists of gopher trapping only. This is done the same way as in E001.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Treatment layout : trmte52</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>@@
Field Identification 	Experiment Number 	Plot Number 	Nitrogen Treatment 	Ammonium Nitrate(34-0-0) addition(g/m2/yr) 	Soil Disturbance Treatment
B	52	1	3	6	2
B	52	2	7	50	4
B	52	3	6	28	2
B	52	4	7	50	4
B	52	5	1	0	1
B	52	6	1	0	1
B	52	7	7	50	1
B	52	8	7	50	1
B	52	9	3	6	1
B	52	10	7	50	4
B	52	11	6	28	3
B	52	12	1	0	4
B	52	13	1	0	4
B	52	14	3	6	1
B	52	15	1	0	1
B	52	16	1	0	2
B	52	17	7	50	4
B	52	18	1	0	1
B	52	19	3	6	4
B	52	20	7	50	2
B	52	21	1	0	4
B	52	22	7	50	1
B	52	23	7	50	3
B	52	24	1	0	2
B	52	25	6	28	2
B	52	26	1	0	1
B	52	27	3	6	2
B	52	28	1	0	4
B	52	29	1	0	3
B	52	30	6	28	1
B	52	31	6	28	4
B	52	32	1	0	1
B	52	33	7	50	1
B	52	34	1	0	4
B	52	35	7	50	4
B	52	36	7	50	1
B	52	37	3	6	3
B	52	38	7	50	4
B	52	39	7	50	1
B	52	40	3	6	4
B	52	41	1	0	1
B	52	42	1	0	4
B	52	43	1	0	2
B	52	44	1	0	3
B	52	45	6	28	3
B	52	46	1	0	1
B	52	47	3	6	4
B	52	48	6	28	1
B	52	49	1	0	4
B	52	50	7	50	4
B	52	51	7	50	4
B	52	52	3	6	2
B	52	53	7	50	4
B	52	54	3	6	1
B	52	55	1	0	4
B	52	56	3	6	3
B	52	57	7	50	1
B	52	58	1	0	1
B	52	59	1	0	4
B	52	60	1	0	4
B	52	61	7	50	3
B	52	62	7	50	1
B	52	63	7	50	1
B	52	64	1	0	2
B	52	65	3	6	4
B	52	66	6	28	1
B	52	67	3	6	2
B	52	68	1	0	1
B	52	69	6	28	2
B	52	70	7	50	1
B	52	71	1	0	4
B	52	72	7	50	4
B	52	73	6	28	4
B	52	74	7	50	2
B	52	75	1	0	1
B	52	76	3	6	1
B	52	77	7	50	3
B	52	78	7	50	3
B	52	79	7	50	2
B	52	80	1	0	3
B	52	81	6	28	3
B	52	82	1	0	1
B	52	83	3	6	3
B	52	84	1	0	4
B	52	85	1	0	4
B	52	86	6	28	2
B	52	87	6	28	3
B	52	88	1	0	4
B	52	89	7	50	1
B	52	90	7	50	4
B	52	91	6	28	4
B	52	92	7	50	4
B	52	93	7	50	1
B	52	94	7	50	4
B	52	95	1	0	3
B	52	96	7	50	2
B	52	97	1	0	1
B	52	98	6	28	4
B	52	99	7	50	1
B	52	100	7	50	4
B	52	101	1	0	1
B	52	102	3	6	3
B	52	103	7	50	1
B	52	104	6	28	1@@</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Vegetation Sampling Methods</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>E052 is in field B. Plots in this experiment are sampled on an annual basis. Each time it is sampled, the sample strip is located in a different place.

Documentation on where the strips are located for each year can be found in the clipping maps.

Species composition of all plots was measured on August 22, 1990 along a transect that ran diagonally across each plot. Two quadrats were placed along the transect, each 1.5m towards the center of the plot from each end of the transect. Thus, there were two quadrats per plot. The cover of each species was recorded using Daubenmire's scale (Mueller-Dombois and Ellenberg 1974).

Standing crop was measured by clipping all aboveground plant material within a 10cm x 1m quadrat in each of the ten plots used for the competition experiment. Different quadrats were clipped in each plot on May 3, May 22, June 15, July 3, July 24, August 23, September 24 and November 1, 1990. The first quadrat was 1m inside the SW corner of each plot, and each subsequent quadrat was 30cm N from, and parallel to, the previous quadrat.

Sampling methods are the same as described in above ground vegetation sampling methods except for the use of a meter stick instead of the 3m aluminum pole because the sample strips are only 1m long.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Sampling Map</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Sampling map for e052 is not currently available

1988: Clipped in the SW corner of each plot, 10cm x 1m

1989: Clipped at 1m in from the right side.

1990: First quadrat was clipped at 1m in from the SW corner of each plot. Each subsequent quadrat was 30cm N from and parallel to the previous quadrat. Vegetation was sampled on May 3, May 22, June 15, July 3, July 24, August 23, September 24 and November 1. Vegetation species composition of all plots was measured on August 22, along a transect that ran diagonally across each plot. Two quadrats, each 0.5 x 1m, were placed along the transect, each 1.5m from one end. The cover of each species was recorded using Daubenmire's scale of six classes. Root biomass was measured in each plot on May 3 and August 23 by taking four soil cores (each 3cm diameter, 10cm deep), evenly spaced along a transect 1m inside the west edge of each plot, and pooling them. The above-ground parts of transplants were harvested during 10-14 Sept. , sorted to dead pieces, flowering tillers and other live portions. All above ground plant material, live and dead, within 15cm of each transplant grown with all neighbors was harvested immediately after the transplant was harvested.

1991: Above-ground biomass was measured by clipping all above-ground plant material within a 10cm x 100cm quadrat in each plot during August 12-16. Four cores were also taken from each plot, combined and rinsed for root biomass. These cores were taken along a transect 1m inside the west edge of each plot. Species composition of all plots was measured on August 13-14 along a transect that ran diagonally across each plot. Two quadrats, each 0.5 x 1m, were placed along the transect, each 1.5m from one end. The cover of each species was recorded using Daubenmire's scale of six classes (Mueller-Dombois and Ellenberg 1974). Transplants were harvested during September 9-12 by removing the tubes which contained the transplants. Transplant and neighbor biomass were determined.

1993: Starting at the SE corner, we measured 2m north and 1m west. Then, sample was clipped in a quadrat 1m long and 10cm wide running west from their point. (See sheet for 1993).</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>e052_Maximum plant height along transects</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Maximum plant height along transects: Interactive Effects of Fertility and Distribution on Plant Community Diversity and Structure</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>e052_Maximum plant height along transects.txt</objectName>
        <size unit="rows">104</size>
        <characterEncoding>ASCCII</characterEncoding>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <numFooterLines>0</numFooterLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>\t</fieldDelimiter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url function="download">https://pasta.lternet.edu/package/data/eml/knb-lter-cdr/154/1/ddd43f3384977624a47603c5cc4a9e75</url>
          </online>
          <access authSystem="https://pasta.lternet.edu/authentication" order="allowFirst" scope="document" system="https://pasta.lternet.edu">
            <allow>
              <principal>uid=CDR,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
              <permission>all</permission>
            </allow>
            <allow>
              <principal>public</principal>
              <permission>read</permission>
            </allow>
          </access>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Field number/letter</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Field number/letter</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Field number/letter</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Experiment number</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Experiment number</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Experiment number</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Plot number</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Plot number</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Plot number</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Sampling date</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Sampling date</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>YYMMDD
</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Plant height (cm) #1</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Plant height (cm) #1</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Plant height (cm) #2</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Plant height (cm) #2</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Plant height (cm) #3</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Plant height (cm) #3</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Plant height (cm) #4</attributeName>
          <attributeDefinition>Plant height (cm) #4</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
      <numberOfRecords>104</numberOfRecords>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <ns2:unitList />
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
</ns0:eml>