<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-europe-deims.13193.13487" system="knb-lter-europe-deims" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 https://code.ecoinformatics.org/code/eml/tags/RELEASE_EML_2_1_1/eml.xsd">

<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
  <allow>
  <principal>uid=Lithuania,o=LTER-Europe,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
  <permission>all</permission>
</allow>
  <allow>
    <principal>public</principal>
    <permission>read</permission>
  </allow>
</access>
<dataset id="knb-lter-europe-deims.13193.13487" system="knb-lter-europe-deims">
<alternateIdentifier>40cbbaa6-9866-11e2-b534-005056ab003f</alternateIdentifier>
<title>Forest ecosystems of Aukstaitija national park</title>
<creator>
<individualName>
<surName>Lithuania</surName>
</individualName>
</creator>
<metadataProvider>
<individualName>
<givenName>Algirdas</givenName>
<surName>Augustaitis</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>Aleksandras Stulginskis University, Forest Monitoring Laboratory, Kaunas dstr., Lithuania</organizationName>
<electronicMailAddress>algirdas.augustaitis@asu.lt</electronicMailAddress>
</metadataProvider>
<language>eng</language><abstract>
<section>
<para>Data on forest structure, condition, increment ans well as LAI, Leaf and soil chemistry are presented.

Data on 20 permanant observation pine stands are presented. Investigations are carried out since the 1986. Presented data: dendrometric parameters, condition, defoliation, tree ring width series, FAR/LAI, primary productivity, dead wood, meteorology, soil and needle chemistry</para>
</section>
</abstract>
<keywordSet>
<keyword>climate change</keyword>
<keyword>forest ecology</keyword>
<keyword>soil chemistry</keyword>
<keyword>dendrochronology</keyword>
<keyword>biogeochemistry</keyword>
<keywordThesaurus>EnvEurope Thesaurus;2012-08-13;version 3.0;http://vocabs.lter-europe.net/EnvThes3.html</keywordThesaurus>
</keywordSet>
<additionalInfo>
<section>
<title>Metadata date</title>
<para>2013-05-19 00:00:00</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Dataset access and use constraints</title>
<para>Principal:Research has granted a permission of type:Other restrictions according to rules defined in itellectual rights</para>
</section>
</additionalInfo>
<intellectualRights>
<section>
<para>The first four</para>
</section>
</intellectualRights>
<distribution>
<online>
<url>www.asu.lt</url>
</online>
</distribution>
<coverage>
<temporalCoverage>
<rangeOfDates>
<beginDate>
<calendarDate>2010-01-01</calendarDate>
</beginDate>
<endDate>
<calendarDate>2013-01-01</calendarDate>
</endDate>
</rangeOfDates>
</temporalCoverage>
</coverage>
<contact>
<individualName>
<givenName>Algirdas</givenName>
<surName>Augustaitis</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>Aleksandras Stulginskis University, Forest Monitoring Laboratory, Kaunas dstr., Lithuania</organizationName>
<electronicMailAddress>algirdas.augustaitis@asu.lt</electronicMailAddress>
</contact>
<methods>
<methodStep>
<description>
<section>
<para>
<literalLayout>20 stands were located in the surroundings of Integrated monitoring stations (IMS) established there, and were selected according to stand maturity: 4 sapling stands (45&#8211;50 years), 4 middle aged stands (61&#8211;80 years), 4 premature stands (81&#8211;100 years), 3 mature stands (101&#8211; 120 years) and 5 over mature stands  more than121 years). Data on tree and stand parameters (mean diameter and height of trees, tree density, basal area and tree volume per hectare) as well as crown defoliation were available from the permanent observation stands. A three-stage sampling pattern was used for the collection of the field material: (i)&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; sampling of the research stands; (ii)&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; sampling of the circular plots within each research stand; (iii) &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; sampling of the trees for more detailed measurements of tree crown parameters and tree ring analysis. Each pine stand included 12 circular sample plots distributed systematically in a grid system with on average 15-20 trees in each plot, i.e.; about 150-250 sample trees per stand. There, tree stem diameter was permanently measured and crown defoliation assessed for all sample trees annually. In addition three closest to the centre of sampling plot trees were sampled for measurement of crown parameters (height, diameter and length) and analysis of annual radial increment (tree ring width). Standard dendrochronological technique was used to assess tree growth rates. Radial growth was assessed by measuring the width of annual rings in stem cores. Each ring was measured to the closest 0.01 mm using an electronic transducer and binocular scope fixed over the moving stage. Based on the ring widths and measured diameter we computed stem basal area increment (BAI). For each of the POS a BAI chronology was computed by averaging the BAI for each year across all trees sampled at POS. Crown defoliation was assessed at the end of August. Forest monitoring methodology was employed to assess tree defoliation: healthy trees &#8211; (defoliation up to 10%); slightly damaged trees (defoliation ranging from 11 to 25%); moderately damaged trees (defoliation 26&#8211;60%); severely damaged trees (defoliation 61&#8211;99%); dead trees (defoliation 100%) (UN-ECE, 1994).&#160;</literalLayout>
</para>
</section>
</description>
<instrumentation>Instruments for estimation of the tree dendromentric parameters</instrumentation>
</methodStep>
<sampling>
<studyExtent>
<description>
<section>
<para>UN-ECE. Manual on methods and Criteria for Harmonised Sampling, Assessment, Monitoring and Analysis of the Effects of Air Pollution on Forests. ICP, 1994.</para>
</section>
</description>
</studyExtent>
<samplingDescription>annually</samplingDescription>
</sampling>
</methods>
</dataset>
</ns0:eml>