<ns0:metadata xmlns:ns0="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0 http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0/onedcx_v1.0.xsd">
  <ns0:simpleDc>
    <ns2:type>package</ns2:type>
    <ns2:creator>Minnesota Population Center</ns2:creator>
    <ns2:title>IPUMS-International: Fiji 1996 Census</ns2:title>
    <ns2:identifier>ipumsi_6.3_fj_1996_DC.xml</ns2:identifier>
    <ns2:subject>Census</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Group Quarters Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Economic Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Utilities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Appliances, Mechanicals, Other Amenities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Dwelling Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Constructed Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Technical Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Constructed Family Interrelationship Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Demographic Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Fertility and Mortality Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Nativity and Birthplace Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Ethnicity and Language Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Education Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Migration Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Disability Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work: Occupation Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work: Industry Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
  </ns0:simpleDc>
  <ns0:dcTerms>
    <ns2:dateSubmitted>2014-09-15</ns2:dateSubmitted>
    <ns2:available>2014-07-01</ns2:available>
    <ns2:abstract>IPUMS-International is an effort to inventory, preserve, harmonize, and disseminate census microdata from around the world. The project has collected the world's largest archive of publicly available census samples. The data are coded and documented consistently across countries and over time to facilitate comparative research. IPUMS-International makes these data available to qualified researchers free of charge through a web dissemination system. The IPUMS project is a collaboration of the Minnesota Population Center, National Statistical Offices, and international data archives. Major funding is provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation and the Demographic and Behavioral Sciences Branch of the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development. Additional support is provided by the University of Minnesota Office of the Vice President for Research, the Minnesota Population Center, and Sun Microsystems. Detailed metadata will be found in ipumsi_6.3_fj_1996_ddic.html within the Data Package. The related metadata describes the content of the extraction of the specified sample from the IPUMS International on-line extraction system.</ns2:abstract>
    <ns2:tableOfContents>Record type; Country; Year; IPUMS sample identifier; Household serial number; Number of person records in the household; Household weight; Subsample number; Group quarters status; Number of unrelated persons; Continent and region of country; 1st subnational geographic level, world [consistent boundaries over time]; Province, Fiji [Level 1; consistent boundaries over time]; Province, Fiji [Level 1; inconsistent boundaries, harmonized by name]; Division, Fiji; Ownership of dwelling [general version]; Ownership of dwelling [detailed version]; Land ownership; Electricity; Cooking fuel; Telephone availability; Trash disposal; Automobiles available; Clothes washing machine; Refrigerator; Television set; Number of rooms; Toilet; Wall or building material; Household classification; Number of families in household; Number of married couples in household; Number of mothers in household; Number of fathers in household; Dwelling number; Number of persons in household; Dwelling created by splitting apart a large dwelling or household; Division; Province; Batch number; Living quarters; Wall materials; Number of rooms; Water supply; Water supply dries up; Electricity; Electricity supplier; Source of lighting; Source of cooking fuel; Toilet facilities; Septic tank; Living quarters tenure; Land tenure; Dwelling adequacy; Waste collected by local authority; Waste buried; Waste burned; Waste disposed into rivers; Waste disposed in backyard; Other waste disposal; Household has car; Household has carrier/truck; Household has refrigerator; Household has video/television; Household has washing machine; Household has gas/electric stove; Household has telephone; Household has outboard motor; Household has water pump; Any crop production in 1996; Crop production in 1996: vegetables; Crop production in 1996: root crops; Crop production in 1996: copra; Crop production in 1996: other crops and grain; Raise any livestock in 1996; Raise livestock in 1996: cattle; Raise livestockin 1996: pigs; Raise livestock in 1996: poultry; Catch any seafood in 1996; Catch seafood in 1996: fish; Catch seafood in 1996: crabs and lobsters; Catch seafood in 1996: shells; Catch seafood in 1996: sea cucumber; Run any a business  in 1996; Run a business  in 1996: store, bakery; Run a business  in 1996: truck, taxi, carrier; Run a business  in 1996: boat; Any craft production in 1996; Craft production in 1996: boat/canoes; Craft production in 1996: wooden handicraft; Craft production in 1996: mats, baskets; Craft production in 1996: thatching materials; Craft production in 1996: houses; Other business or activity in 1996; Record type [person version]; Country [person version]; Year [person version]; IPUMS sample identifier [person version]; Household serial number [person version]; Person number; Person weight; Mother's location in household; Father's location in household; Spouse's location in household; Rule for linking parent; Rule for linking spouse; Probable stepmother; Probable stepfather; Man with more than one wife linked; Woman is second or higher order wife; Family unit membership; Number of own family members in household; Number of own children in household; Number of own children under age 5 in household; Age of eldest own child in household; Age of youngest own child in household; Relationship to household head [general version]; Relationship to household head [detailed version]; Age; Sex; Marital status [general version]; Marital status [detailed version]; Year of birth; Month of birth; Month of last birth; Year of last birth; Number of children dead; Number of female children dead; Number of male children dead; Mortality status of last birth; Mortality status of mother; Mortality status of father; Number of own children in household; Number of own female children in household; Number of own male children in household; Number of own children living elsewhere; Number of own female children living elsewhere; Number of own male children living elsewhere; Nativity status; Country of birth; Province of birth, Fiji; Religion [general version]; Religion [detailed version]; Ethnicity, Fiji; School attendance; Educational attainment, international recode [general version]; Educational attainment, international recode [detailed version]; Years of schooling; Educational attainment, Fiji; Employment status [general version]; Employment status [detailed version]; Occupation, ISCO general; Occupation, unrecoded; Industry, general recode; Industry, unrecoded; Days worked last week; Migration status, 5 years; Country of residence 5 years ago; Province of residence 5 years ago, Fiji; Disability status; Employment disability; Person number (within household); Relationship to head of household; Sex; Month of birth; Year of birth; Age; Ethnicity; Marital status; Father alive; Mother alive; Mother's person number; Mother's age; Religion; Province or country of birth; Town, village or settlement of birth; Province or country of residence in 1991; Town, village or settlement of residence 5 years ago; School enrollment status; Educational attainment; Activity in the past week; Days working for money in the past week; Subsistence; Economic activity; Occupation (3 digits); Major occupation; Industry (2 digits); Major industry; Employment status; Male children born alive living here; Female children born alive living here; Male children born alive living elsewhere; Female children born alive living elsewhere; Male children dead; Female children dead; Month of last birth; Year of last birth; Last child still alive; Any disability; Any difficulties with daily activities; </ns2:tableOfContents>
    <ns2:spatial>Fiji</ns2:spatial>
    <ns2:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:Box">northlimit=-12.461784; eastlimit=180.000000; southlimit=-21.042326; westlimit=-179.984726; name=Fiji;</ns2:spatial>
    <ns2:temporal>1996</ns2:temporal>
    <ns2:references>http://international.ipums.org</ns2:references>
    <ns2:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_fj_1996_ddic.xml</ns2:hasPart>
    <ns2:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_fj_1996_ddic_xml.html</ns2:hasPart>
    <ns2:accessRights>IPUMS-International distributes integrated microdata of individuals and households only by agreement of collaborating national statistical offices and under the strictest of confidence. Before data may be distributed to an individual researcher, an electronic license agreement must be signed and approved. (see http://international.ipums.org)</ns2:accessRights>
    <ns2:modified>2014-12-10T00:00:00</ns2:modified>
  </ns0:dcTerms>  
</ns0:metadata>