<ns0:metadata xmlns:ns0="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0 http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0/onedcx_v1.0.xsd">
  <ns0:simpleDc>
    <ns2:type>package</ns2:type>
    <ns2:creator>Minnesota Population Center</ns2:creator>
    <ns2:title>IPUMS-International: Egypt 2006 Census</ns2:title>
    <ns2:identifier>ipumsi_6.3_eg_2006_DC.xml</ns2:identifier>
    <ns2:subject>Census</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Group Quarters Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Economic Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Utilities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Appliances, Mechanicals, Other Amenities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Dwelling Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Constructed Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Technical Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Constructed Family Interrelationship Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Demographic Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Nativity and Birthplace Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Ethnicity and Language Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Education Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Migration Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Disability Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work: Occupation Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work: Industry Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Other Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
  </ns0:simpleDc>
  <ns0:dcTerms>
    <ns2:dateSubmitted>2014-09-15</ns2:dateSubmitted>
    <ns2:available>2014-07-01</ns2:available>
    <ns2:abstract>IPUMS-International is an effort to inventory, preserve, harmonize, and disseminate census microdata from around the world. The project has collected the world's largest archive of publicly available census samples. The data are coded and documented consistently across countries and over time to facilitate comparative research. IPUMS-International makes these data available to qualified researchers free of charge through a web dissemination system. The IPUMS project is a collaboration of the Minnesota Population Center, National Statistical Offices, and international data archives. Major funding is provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation and the Demographic and Behavioral Sciences Branch of the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development. Additional support is provided by the University of Minnesota Office of the Vice President for Research, the Minnesota Population Center, and Sun Microsystems. Detailed metadata will be found in ipumsi_6.3_eg_2006_ddic.html within the Data Package. The related metadata describes the content of the extraction of the specified sample from the IPUMS International on-line extraction system.</ns2:abstract>
    <ns2:tableOfContents>Record type; Country; Year; IPUMS sample identifier; Household serial number; Number of person records in the household; Household weight; Subsample number; Group quarters status; Number of unrelated persons; Urban-rural status; Continent and region of country; 1st subnational geographic level, world [consistent boundaries over time]; Governorate, Egypt [Level 1; consistent boundaries over time]; District (20,000 and over), Egypt [Level 2; inconsistent boundaries, harmonized by name]; Ownership of dwelling [general version]; Ownership of dwelling [detailed version]; Electricity; Water supply; Sewage; Cooking fuel; Telephone availability; Cellular phone availability; Internet access; Automobiles available; Air conditioning; Computer; Clothes washing machine; Food freezer; Refrigerator; Television set; Videocassette recorder; Radio in household; Number of rooms; Kitchen or cooking facilities; Toilet; Bathing facilities; Household classification; Number of families in household; Number of married couples in household; Number of mothers in household; Number of fathers in household; Head's location in household; Dwelling number; Number of persons in household; Dwelling created by splitting apart a large dwelling or household; Number of persons in large household before it was split; Governorate; Urban/rural; Public housing type; Number of household members (males); Number of household members (females); Number of household members (total); Dwelling type; Ownership status; Source of water; Access to water; Lighting; Sewage; Number of rooms; Monthly rent in Egyptian pounds; Kitchen; Separate bathroom; Bathroom with toilet; Separate toilet; Fuel and energy used: propane; Fuel and energy used: natural gas; Fuel and energy used: kerosene; Fuel and energy used: electricity; Fuel and energy used: other; Number of private cars owned; Number of motorcycles owned; Number of bicycles owned; Number of other means of transportation owned; No means of transportation; Number of radios; Number of televisions; Number of video players; Number of satellite dishes; Number of refrigerators; Number of deep freezers; Number of non-automatic washing machines; Number of automatic washing machines; Number of dishwashers; Number of stoves; Number of water heaters; Number of vacuum cleaners; Number of air conditioners; Number of computers; Number of fans; Number of internet connections; Number of land-line phones; Number of cellular phones; No household appliances; Record type [person version]; Country [person version]; Year [person version]; IPUMS sample identifier [person version]; Household serial number [person version]; Person number; Person weight; Mother's location in household; Father's location in household; Spouse's location in household; Rule for linking parent; Rule for linking spouse; Probable stepmother; Probable stepfather; Man with more than one wife linked; Woman is second or higher order wife; Family unit membership; Number of own family members in household; Number of own children in household; Number of own children under age 5 in household; Age of eldest own child in household; Age of youngest own child in household; Relationship to household head [general version]; Relationship to household head [detailed version]; Age; Age, grouped into intervals; Sex; Marital status [general version]; Marital status [detailed version]; Polygamous union; Nativity status; Governorate of birth, Egypt; Citizenship; Country of citizenship; Religion [general version]; Religion [detailed version]; School attendance; Literacy; Educational attainment, international recode [general version]; Educational attainment, international recode [detailed version]; Educational attainment, Egypt; Employment status [general version]; Employment status [detailed version]; Occupation, ISCO general; Occupation, unrecoded; Occupation, ISCO-1988, 3-digit; Industry, general recode; Industry, unrecoded; Class of worker [general version]; Class of worker [detailed version]; Sector of employment; Migration status, previous residence; Years residing in current locality; Reason for migration; Governorate of previous residence, Egypt; Disability status; Employment disability; Person number (within household); Relationship to household head; Age; Sex; Religion; Nationality; Nationality in detail; Marital status; Number of wives; Educational level (main code); School enrollment; School drop out (stage); School drop out (grade); Employment status; Place of work; Sector; Primary occupation, 3-digit; Industry, 3-digit; Job stability; Disability status; Governorate of birth; District of birth; Place of birth: urban/rural; Duration of stay at place of residence, in years; Previous governorate of residence; Previous district of residence; Previous place of residence: urban-rural; Reason of changing place of residence; Governorate of residence for guests and/or visitors; Urban/ rural status of residence for guests and/or visitors; </ns2:tableOfContents>
    <ns2:spatial>Egypt</ns2:spatial>
    <ns2:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:Box">northlimit=31.646945; eastlimit=36.895827; southlimit=21.994164; westlimit=24.706800; name=Egypt;</ns2:spatial>
    <ns2:temporal>2006</ns2:temporal>
    <ns2:references>http://international.ipums.org</ns2:references>
    <ns2:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_eg_2006_ddic.xml</ns2:hasPart>
    <ns2:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_eg_2006_ddic_xml.html</ns2:hasPart>
    <ns2:accessRights>IPUMS-International distributes integrated microdata of individuals and households only by agreement of collaborating national statistical offices and under the strictest of confidence. Before data may be distributed to an individual researcher, an electronic license agreement must be signed and approved. (see http://international.ipums.org)</ns2:accessRights>
    <ns2:modified>2014-12-10T00:00:00</ns2:modified>
  </ns0:dcTerms>  
</ns0:metadata>