<ns0:metadata xmlns:ns0="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0 http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0/onedcx_v1.0.xsd">
  <ns0:simpleDc>
    <ns2:type>package</ns2:type>
    <ns2:creator>Minnesota Population Center</ns2:creator>
    <ns2:title>IPUMS-International: Rwanda 2002 Census</ns2:title>
    <ns2:identifier>ipumsi_6.3_rw_2002_DC.xml</ns2:identifier>
    <ns2:subject>Census</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Group Quarters Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Economic Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Utilities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Appliances, Mechanicals, Other Amenities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Dwelling Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Other Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Constructed Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Technical Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Constructed Family Interrelationship Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Demographic Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Fertility and Mortality Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Nativity and Birthplace Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Ethnicity and Language Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Education Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Migration Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Disability Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work: Occupation Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work: Industry Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
  </ns0:simpleDc>
  <ns0:dcTerms>
    <ns2:dateSubmitted>2014-09-15</ns2:dateSubmitted>
    <ns2:available>2014-07-01</ns2:available>
    <ns2:abstract>IPUMS-International is an effort to inventory, preserve, harmonize, and disseminate census microdata from around the world. The project has collected the world's largest archive of publicly available census samples. The data are coded and documented consistently across countries and over time to facilitate comparative research. IPUMS-International makes these data available to qualified researchers free of charge through a web dissemination system. The IPUMS project is a collaboration of the Minnesota Population Center, National Statistical Offices, and international data archives. Major funding is provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation and the Demographic and Behavioral Sciences Branch of the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development. Additional support is provided by the University of Minnesota Office of the Vice President for Research, the Minnesota Population Center, and Sun Microsystems. Detailed metadata will be found in ipumsi_6.3_rw_2002_ddic.html within the Data Package. The related metadata describes the content of the extraction of the specified sample from the IPUMS International on-line extraction system.</ns2:abstract>
    <ns2:tableOfContents>Record type; Country; Year; IPUMS sample identifier; Household serial number; Number of person records in the household; Household weight; Subsample number; Group quarters status; Number of unrelated persons; Urban-rural status; Continent and region of country; 1st subnational geographic level, world [consistent boundaries over time]; Province, Rwanda [Level 1; consistent boundaries over time]; Province, Rwanda [Level 1; inconsistent boundaries, harmonized by name]; Ownership of dwelling [general version]; Ownership of dwelling [detailed version]; Electricity; Water supply; Cooking fuel; Telephone availability; Cellular phone availability; Internet access; Trash disposal; Automobiles available; Computer; Television set; Radio in household; Number of rooms; Toilet; Floor material; Wall or building material; Roof material; Number of deaths in household last year; Any deaths in household last year; Household classification; Number of families in household; Number of married couples in household; Number of mothers in household; Number of fathers in household; Head's location in household; Dwelling number; Number of persons in household; Dwelling created by splitting apart a large dwelling or household; Province; District / Township; Urban/rural; Household type; Number of absent male residents; Number of absent female residents; Number of absent residents; Type of settlement; Type of dwelling unit / type of building; Main roof material; Main walls material; Main floor material; Number of rooms; Source of water; Type of lighting; Cooking fuel; Type of toilet facility; Type of garbage disposal; Home ownership status; Ownership of a radio and TV; Ownership of a fixed or mobile telephone; Ownership of a computer or internet; Ownership of motor vehicle(s); Ownership of motorcycle; Ownership of bicycle; Any death in past 12 months; Total number of deaths in past12 months; Main type of household; Type of institutional household; Number of mortality records in input data; Record type [person version]; Country [person version]; Year [person version]; IPUMS sample identifier [person version]; Household serial number [person version]; Person number; Person weight; Residence status: de facto, de jure; Mother's location in household; Father's location in household; Spouse's location in household; Rule for linking parent; Rule for linking spouse; Probable stepmother; Probable stepfather; Man with more than one wife linked; Woman is second or higher order wife; Family unit membership; Number of own family members in household; Number of own children in household; Number of own children under age 5 in household; Age of eldest own child in household; Age of youngest own child in household; Relationship to household head [general version]; Relationship to household head [detailed version]; Age; Age, grouped into intervals; Sex; Marital status [general version]; Marital status [detailed version]; Consensual union; Polygamous union; Year of birth; Month of birth; Children ever born; Children surviving; Number of female children ever born; Number of male children ever born; Number of female children surviving; Number of male children surviving; Number of births last year; Children surviving from births last year; Mortality status of mother; Mortality status of father; Nativity status; Country of birth; Province of birth, Rwanda; Citizenship; Country of citizenship; Religion [general version]; Religion [detailed version]; Foreign language spoken, Rwanda; School attendance; Literacy; Educational attainment, international recode [general version]; Educational attainment, international recode [detailed version]; Years of schooling; Educational attainment, Rwanda; Employment status [general version]; Employment status [detailed version]; Occupation, ISCO general; Occupation, unrecoded; Occupation, ISCO-1988, 3-digit; Industry, general recode; Industry, unrecoded; Class of worker [general version]; Class of worker [detailed version]; Sector of employment; Years residing in current locality; Disability status; Blind or vision-impaired; Deaf or hearing-impaired; Mute; Disability affecting lower extremities; Disability affecting upper extremities; Mental disability; Origin of disability; Person number (within household); Relationship to household head; Residence status; Sex; Month of birth; Year of birth; Age; Nationality/country of citizenship; Country of birth/district of birth; Duration of residence; Country or district of previous residence; Language spoken; Religion; Major handicap / disability; Cause of the handicap or disability; Survival ofparents; School attendance; Level of education; Field of education or training; Highest diploma received; Literacy; Employment status (situation in economic activity); Occupation; Work status; Industry; Sector of economic activity; Marital status; Male children ever born alive; Female children ever born alive; Male children still alive; Female children still alive; Male children born in the past 12 months; Female children born in the past 12 months; Male children born in the past 12 months still alive; Female children born in the past 12 months still alive; Residence status (large groups); </ns2:tableOfContents>
    <ns2:spatial>Rwanda</ns2:spatial>
    <ns2:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:Box">northlimit=-1.054446; eastlimit=30.893263; southlimit=-2.825491; westlimit=28.854445; name=Rwanda;</ns2:spatial>
    <ns2:temporal>2002</ns2:temporal>
    <ns2:references>http://international.ipums.org</ns2:references>
    <ns2:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_rw_2002_ddic.xml</ns2:hasPart>
    <ns2:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_rw_2002_ddic_xml.html</ns2:hasPart>
    <ns2:accessRights>IPUMS-International distributes integrated microdata of individuals and households only by agreement of collaborating national statistical offices and under the strictest of confidence. Before data may be distributed to an individual researcher, an electronic license agreement must be signed and approved. (see http://international.ipums.org)</ns2:accessRights>
    <ns2:modified>2014-12-10T00:00:00</ns2:modified>
  </ns0:dcTerms>  
</ns0:metadata>