<ns0:metadata xmlns:ns0="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0 http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0/onedcx_v1.0.xsd">
  <ns0:simpleDc>
    <ns2:type>package</ns2:type>
    <ns2:creator>Minnesota Population Center</ns2:creator>
    <ns2:title>IPUMS-International: Kenya 1989 Census</ns2:title>
    <ns2:identifier>ipumsi_6.3_ke_1989_DC.xml</ns2:identifier>
    <ns2:subject>Census</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Group Quarters Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Economic Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Utilities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Dwelling Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Constructed Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Technical Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Constructed Family Interrelationship Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Demographic Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Fertility and Mortality Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Nativity and Birthplace Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Education Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Migration Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Disability Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work: Occupation Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
  </ns0:simpleDc>
  <ns0:dcTerms>
    <ns2:dateSubmitted>2014-09-15</ns2:dateSubmitted>
    <ns2:available>2014-07-01</ns2:available>
    <ns2:abstract>IPUMS-International is an effort to inventory, preserve, harmonize, and disseminate census microdata from around the world. The project has collected the world's largest archive of publicly available census samples. The data are coded and documented consistently across countries and over time to facilitate comparative research. IPUMS-International makes these data available to qualified researchers free of charge through a web dissemination system. The IPUMS project is a collaboration of the Minnesota Population Center, National Statistical Offices, and international data archives. Major funding is provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation and the Demographic and Behavioral Sciences Branch of the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development. Additional support is provided by the University of Minnesota Office of the Vice President for Research, the Minnesota Population Center, and Sun Microsystems. Detailed metadata will be found in ipumsi_6.3_ke_1989_ddic.html within the Data Package. The related metadata describes the content of the extraction of the specified sample from the IPUMS International on-line extraction system.</ns2:abstract>
    <ns2:tableOfContents>Record type; Country; Year; IPUMS sample identifier; Household serial number; Number of person records in the household; Household weight; Subsample number; Group quarters status; Number of unrelated persons; Urban-rural status; Continent and region of country; 1st subnational geographic level, world [consistent boundaries over time]; Province, Kenya [Level 1; consistent boundaries over time]; Province, Kenya [Level 1; inconsistent boundaries, harmonized by name]; District, Kenya [Level 2; inconsistent boundaries, harmonized by name]; Ownership of dwelling [general version]; Ownership of dwelling [detailed version]; Electricity; Water supply; Sewage; Cooking fuel; Toilet; Floor material; Wall or building material; Roof material; Household classification; Number of families in household; Number of married couples in household; Number of mothers in household; Number of fathers in household; Head's location in household; Province; District; Enumeration area type; Record type; Tenure; Roof; Wall; Floor; Water source; Sewage; Fuel; Light; Record type [person version]; Country [person version]; Year [person version]; IPUMS sample identifier [person version]; Household serial number [person version]; Person number; Person weight; Mother's location in household; Father's location in household; Spouse's location in household; Rule for linking parent; Rule for linking spouse; Probable stepmother; Probable stepfather; Man with more than one wife linked; Woman is second or higher order wife; Family unit membership; Number of own family members in household; Number of own children in household; Number of own children under age 5 in household; Age of eldest own child in household; Age of youngest own child in household; Relationship to household head [general version]; Relationship to household head [detailed version]; Age; Age, grouped into intervals; Sex; Marital status [general version]; Marital status [detailed version]; Polygamous union; Children ever born; Children surviving; Number of female children ever born; Number of male children ever born; Number of female children surviving; Number of male children surviving; Month of last birth; Year of last birth; Sex of last birth; Number of children dead; Number of female children dead; Number of male children dead; Mortality status of last birth; Year of death of the last child born; Month of death of the last child born; Mortality status of mother; Mortality status of father; Number of own children in household; Number of own female children in household; Number of own male children in household; Number of own children living elsewhere; Number of own female children living elsewhere; Number of own male children living elsewhere; Nativity status; Country of birth; District of birth, Kenya; School attendance; Literacy; Educational attainment, international recode [general version]; Educational attainment, international recode [detailed version]; Years of schooling; Educational attainment, Kenya; Employment status [general version]; Employment status [detailed version]; Occupation, ISCO general; Occupation, unrecoded; Migration status, 1 year; Country of residence 1 year ago; District of residence 1 year ago, Kenya; Employment disability; Relationship to head; Sex; Age; Marital status; Birthplace; Previous residence; Father alive; Mother alive; Literacy; School attendance; Educational attainment; Activity status; Occupation, 2 digits; Occupation, 4 digits; Class of worker; Male children living at home; Female children living at home; Male children living away; Female children living away; Male children who have died; Female children who have died; Last birth, month; Last birth, year; Sex of last birth; Last birth alive; Month of death of last birth; Year of death of last birth; Number of children ever born; </ns2:tableOfContents>
    <ns2:spatial>Kenya</ns2:spatial>
    <ns2:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:Box">northlimit=4.622500; eastlimit=41.905163; southlimit=-4.669618; westlimit=33.907218; name=Kenya;</ns2:spatial>
    <ns2:temporal>1989</ns2:temporal>
    <ns2:references>http://international.ipums.org</ns2:references>
    <ns2:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_ke_1989_ddic.xml</ns2:hasPart>
    <ns2:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_ke_1989_ddic_xml.html</ns2:hasPart>
    <ns2:accessRights>IPUMS-International distributes integrated microdata of individuals and households only by agreement of collaborating national statistical offices and under the strictest of confidence. Before data may be distributed to an individual researcher, an electronic license agreement must be signed and approved. (see http://international.ipums.org)</ns2:accessRights>
    <ns2:modified>2014-12-10T00:00:00</ns2:modified>
  </ns0:dcTerms>  
</ns0:metadata>