<ns0:metadata xmlns:ns0="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0 http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0/onedcx_v1.0.xsd">
  <ns0:simpleDc>
    <ns2:type>package</ns2:type>
    <ns2:creator>Minnesota Population Center</ns2:creator>
    <ns2:title>IPUMS-International: Venezuela 2001 Census</ns2:title>
    <ns2:identifier>ipumsi_6.3_ve_2001_DC.xml</ns2:identifier>
    <ns2:subject>Census</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Group Quarters Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Economic Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Utilities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Appliances, Mechanicals, Other Amenities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Dwelling Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Constructed Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Other Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Technical Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Constructed Family Interrelationship Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Demographic Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Fertility and Mortality Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Nativity and Birthplace Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Ethnicity and Language Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Education Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Income Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Migration Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Disability Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work: Occupation Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work: Industry Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Other Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
  </ns0:simpleDc>
  <ns0:dcTerms>
    <ns2:dateSubmitted>2014-09-15</ns2:dateSubmitted>
    <ns2:available>2014-07-01</ns2:available>
    <ns2:abstract>IPUMS-International is an effort to inventory, preserve, harmonize, and disseminate census microdata from around the world. The project has collected the world's largest archive of publicly available census samples. The data are coded and documented consistently across countries and over time to facilitate comparative research. IPUMS-International makes these data available to qualified researchers free of charge through a web dissemination system. The IPUMS project is a collaboration of the Minnesota Population Center, National Statistical Offices, and international data archives. Major funding is provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation and the Demographic and Behavioral Sciences Branch of the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development. Additional support is provided by the University of Minnesota Office of the Vice President for Research, the Minnesota Population Center, and Sun Microsystems. Detailed metadata will be found in ipumsi_6.3_ve_2001_ddic.html within the Data Package. The related metadata describes the content of the extraction of the specified sample from the IPUMS International on-line extraction system.</ns2:abstract>
    <ns2:tableOfContents>Record type; Country; Year; IPUMS sample identifier; Household serial number; Number of person records in the household; Household weight; Subsample number; Group quarters status; Number of unrelated persons; Urban-rural status; Continent and region of country; 1st subnational geographic level, world [consistent boundaries over time]; State, Venezuela [Level 1; consistent boundaries over time]; State, Venezuela [Level 1; inconsistent boundaries, harmonized by name]; Municipality (20,000 and over), Venezuela [Level 2; inconsistent boundaries, harmonized by name]; Ownership of dwelling [general version]; Ownership of dwelling [detailed version]; Electricity; Water supply; Sewage; Cooking fuel; Telephone availability; Internet access; Trash disposal; Automobiles available; Hot water heater; Air conditioning; Computer; Clothes washing machine; Refrigerator; Television set; Radio in household; Number of rooms; Number of bedrooms; Kitchen or cooking facilities; Toilet; Number of bathrooms; Bathing facilities; Floor material; Wall or building material; Roof material; Household classification; Number of families in household; Number of married couples in household; Number of mothers in household; Number of fathers in household; Head's location in household; Dwelling number; Household number (within dwelling); Number of households in dwelling; Number of persons in dwelling; Number of persons in household; Dwelling created by splitting apart a large dwelling or household; State; Urban or rural area; Type of dwelling; Occupancy status of the dwelling; Predominant construction material of walls; Predominant construction material of roof(s); Predominant construction material of floors; Location of kitchen; Fuel used for cooking; Water supply; Number of rooms with showers in the dwelling; Removal of excretion; Telephone (landline); Trash collection; Number of rooms in the dwelling; Electrical service; Ownership of the dwelling; Monthly mortgage and rent payment; Number of rooms for sleeping; Household head has a companion; Number of rooms with a tub or shower in the household; Has a bicycle; Has a motorcycle; Has a car; Have any vehicle; Number of cars; Has a refrigerator; Has a water filter; Has a radio; Has a television; Has a washing machine; Has a dryer; Has a water heater; Has air conditioning; Has a microwave; Has a cell phone; Has cable television; Has a computer; Has internet access; Type of household; Critical crowding; Household in inadequate dwelling; Basic services in household; Households by economic dependency; Number of unsatisfied basic needs; Poverty according to NBI; Record type [person version]; Country [person version]; Year [person version]; IPUMS sample identifier [person version]; Household serial number [person version]; Person number; Person weight; Mother's location in household; Father's location in household; Spouse's location in household; Rule for linking parent; Rule for linking spouse; Probable stepmother; Probable stepfather; Man with more than one wife linked; Woman is second or higher order wife; Family unit membership; Number of own family members in household; Number of own children in household; Number of own children under age 5 in household; Age of eldest own child in household; Age of youngest own child in household; Relationship to household head [general version]; Relationship to household head [detailed version]; Age; Age, grouped into intervals; Sex; Marital status [general version]; Marital status [detailed version]; Consensual union; Children ever born; Children surviving; Month of last birth; Year of last birth; Nativity status; Country of birth; State of birth, Venezuela; Citizenship; Speaks indigenous language; School attendance; Literacy; Educational attainment, international recode [general version]; Educational attainment, international recode [detailed version]; Years of schooling; Educational attainment, Venezuela; Employment status [general version]; Employment status [detailed version]; Occupation, ISCO general; Occupation, unrecoded; Occupation, ISCO-1988, 3-digit; Industry, general recode; Industry, unrecoded; Class of worker [general version]; Class of worker [detailed version]; Sector of employment; Size of work establishment; Hours worked per week; Hours worked per week, categorized; Total income; Earned income; Retirement or pension income; State of residence 5 years ago, Venezuela; Disability status; Employment disability; Blind or vision-impaired; Deaf or hearing-impaired; Disability affecting lower extremities; Disability affecting upper extremities; Mental disability; Person number (within household); Relationship to head of household; Sex; Type of age; Age (in years or months); State or country of birth; Year of arrival in country; Nationality; Indigenous identity; Speaks an indigenous language; Blindness; Hearing disability; Mental disability; Disability in an upper extremity; Disability in a lower extremity; Other disability; No disability; Uses a wheelchair; State or country of residence in October 1996; Knows how to read and write; School attendance; Type of school; Educational level; Last grade or year passed/completed; Educational level attained; Last semester passed/completed; Degree obtained; Graduate degree; Marital status; Employment status; Carries out other paid activity; Occupation; Industry; Size of business where person works; Employment sector; Mercantile registry; Class of worker; Place of work; Occupational training; Hours worked; Labor income; Terms of income; Income from rent or bank interest; Income from pensions; Income from retirement; Income from public or private grants; Public or private assistance; Unemployment insurance; Alimony; Other income; Has non-labor income; Number of children born alive; Month of birth of last child born alive; Year of birth of last child born alive; Number of children currently alive; Age (in completed years); </ns2:tableOfContents>
    <ns2:spatial>Venezuela</ns2:spatial>
    <ns2:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:Box">northlimit=12.197826; eastlimit=-59.802612; southlimit=0.649532; westlimit=-73.377570; name=Venezuela;</ns2:spatial>
    <ns2:temporal>2001</ns2:temporal>
    <ns2:references>http://international.ipums.org</ns2:references>
    <ns2:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_ve_2001_ddic.xml</ns2:hasPart>
    <ns2:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_ve_2001_ddic_xml.html</ns2:hasPart>
    <ns2:accessRights>IPUMS-International distributes integrated microdata of individuals and households only by agreement of collaborating national statistical offices and under the strictest of confidence. Before data may be distributed to an individual researcher, an electronic license agreement must be signed and approved. (see http://international.ipums.org)</ns2:accessRights>
    <ns2:modified>2014-12-10T00:00:00</ns2:modified>
  </ns0:dcTerms>  
</ns0:metadata>