<ns0:metadata xmlns:ns0="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0 http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0/onedcx_v1.0.xsd">
  <ns0:simpleDc>
    <ns2:type>package</ns2:type>
    <ns2:creator>Minnesota Population Center</ns2:creator>
    <ns2:title>IPUMS-International: Romania 1992 Census</ns2:title>
    <ns2:identifier>ipumsi_6.3_ro_1992_DC.xml</ns2:identifier>
    <ns2:subject>Census</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Group Quarters Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Utilities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Appliances, Mechanicals, Other Amenities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Dwelling Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Constructed Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Economic Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Technical Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Constructed Family Interrelationship Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Demographic Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Fertility and Mortality Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Nativity and Birthplace Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Ethnicity and Language Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Education Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Migration Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work: Occupation Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work: Industry Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Other Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
  </ns0:simpleDc>
  <ns0:dcTerms>
    <ns2:dateSubmitted>2014-09-15</ns2:dateSubmitted>
    <ns2:available>2014-07-01</ns2:available>
    <ns2:abstract>IPUMS-International is an effort to inventory, preserve, harmonize, and disseminate census microdata from around the world. The project has collected the world's largest archive of publicly available census samples. The data are coded and documented consistently across countries and over time to facilitate comparative research. IPUMS-International makes these data available to qualified researchers free of charge through a web dissemination system. The IPUMS project is a collaboration of the Minnesota Population Center, National Statistical Offices, and international data archives. Major funding is provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation and the Demographic and Behavioral Sciences Branch of the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development. Additional support is provided by the University of Minnesota Office of the Vice President for Research, the Minnesota Population Center, and Sun Microsystems. Detailed metadata will be found in ipumsi_6.3_ro_1992_ddic.html within the Data Package. The related metadata describes the content of the extraction of the specified sample from the IPUMS International on-line extraction system.</ns2:abstract>
    <ns2:tableOfContents>Record type; Country; Year; IPUMS sample identifier; Household serial number; Number of person records in the household; Household weight; Subsample number; Group quarters status; Number of unrelated persons; Urban-rural status; Continent and region of country; 1st subnational geographic level, world [consistent boundaries over time]; NUTS1 Region, Europe; NUTS2 Region, Europe; NUTS3 Region, Europe; County, Romania [Level 1; consistent boundaries over time]; County, Romania [Level 1; inconsistent boundaries, harmonized by name]; Region, Romania; Electricity; Water supply; Sewage; Fuel for heating; Hot water heater; Central heating; Number of rooms; Kitchen or cooking facilities; Toilet; Bathing facilities; Wall or building material; Living area in square meters; Household classification; Number of families in household; Number of married couples in household; Number of mothers in household; Number of fathers in household; Head's location in household; Dwelling number; Number of persons in household; Urban/rural; County; Order number of the household in the dwelling; Designation of the building; Year of construction; Material used for outer walls; Type of building; Top floor of the building; Type of ownership, building; Water supply system, building; Sewage system, building; Electricity, building; Gas for cooking, building; Main type of heating, building; Installed utilities in building; Occupancy status of dwellings in building; Number of the households in dwelling; Type of dwelling; Type of ownership; Floor where dwelling is located; Water supply system; Hot water supply installation; Sewage installation; Electrical installation; Gas for cooking; Main type of heating; Rooms in dwelling, excluding kitchen; Living area of dwelling, excluding kitchen; Kitchen; Bathroom; Flush toilet; Tenure status of dwelling by tenure status of households; Persons in dwelling; Number of rooms in dwelling, including kitchen; Total persons in household; Number of children in household; Number of economically active persons in household; Number of supported persons in household; Number of supported children in household; Number of employees in household; Number and type of generations in household; Relationship of household members; Record type [person version]; Country [person version]; Year [person version]; IPUMS sample identifier [person version]; Household serial number [person version]; Person number; Person weight; Mother's location in household; Father's location in household; Spouse's location in household; Rule for linking parent; Rule for linking spouse; Probable stepmother; Probable stepfather; Man with more than one wife linked; Woman is second or higher order wife; Family unit membership; Number of own family members in household; Number of own children in household; Number of own children under age 5 in household; Age of eldest own child in household; Age of youngest own child in household; Relationship to household head [general version]; Relationship to household head [detailed version]; Relationship to head, Europe; Age; Age, grouped into intervals; Sex; Marital status [general version]; Marital status [detailed version]; Marital status, Europe; Age at first marriage or union; Year of first marriage; Year of birth; Month of birth; Children ever born; Nativity status; Country of birth; County of birth, Romania; Region of birth, Europe, NUTS1; Region of birth, Europe, NUTS2; Region of birth, Europe, NUTS3; Citizenship; Religion [general version]; Religion [detailed version]; Ethnicity, Romania; Mother tongue, Romania; School attendance; Literacy; Educational attainment, international recode [general version]; Educational attainment, international recode [detailed version]; Educational attainment, Romania; Educational attainment, Europe; Employment status [general version]; Employment status [detailed version]; Employment status, Europe; Occupation, ISCO general; Occupation, unrecoded; Industry, general recode; Industry, unrecoded; Class of worker [general version]; Class of worker [detailed version]; Class of worker, Europe; Migration status, previous residence; Years residing in current locality; County of previous residence, Romania; Person number (within household); Order number of the person in the household; Relationship to household head; Situation at the census moment; Person belongs to a household in other locality; County of previous residence; Place of previous residence; Year of establishing legal residence; Year of establishing actual residence; Person number of the father; Person number of the mother; Person number of the spouse; Sex; Month of birth; County or country of birth; Place of birth in other locality; Marital status; Ethnicity; Mother tongue; Religion; Highest level of school completed; Level of educational institution attended; Economic status in reference week; Year of first marriage; Number of children born alive; Occupation, 1 digit; Occupation; Class of worker; Industry; Ownership structure of workplace; Tenure status of the household in dwelling; Number of the family nucleus; Type of the family nucleus; Relationship to the nucleus head; </ns2:tableOfContents>
    <ns2:spatial>Romania</ns2:spatial>
    <ns2:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:Box">northlimit=48.263882; eastlimit=29.672218; southlimit=43.623309; westlimit=20.261027; name=Romania;</ns2:spatial>
    <ns2:temporal>1992</ns2:temporal>
    <ns2:references>http://international.ipums.org</ns2:references>
    <ns2:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_ro_1992_ddic.xml</ns2:hasPart>
    <ns2:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_ro_1992_ddic_xml.html</ns2:hasPart>
    <ns2:accessRights>IPUMS-International distributes integrated microdata of individuals and households only by agreement of collaborating national statistical offices and under the strictest of confidence. Before data may be distributed to an individual researcher, an electronic license agreement must be signed and approved. (see http://international.ipums.org)</ns2:accessRights>
    <ns2:modified>2014-12-10T00:00:00</ns2:modified>
  </ns0:dcTerms>  
</ns0:metadata>