<ns0:metadata xmlns:ns0="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0 http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0/onedcx_v1.0.xsd">
  <ns0:simpleDc>
    <ns2:type>package</ns2:type>
    <ns2:creator>Minnesota Population Center</ns2:creator>
    <ns2:title>IPUMS-International: Panama 1990 Census</ns2:title>
    <ns2:identifier>ipumsi_6.3_pa_1990_DC.xml</ns2:identifier>
    <ns2:subject>Census</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Group Quarters Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Economic Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Utilities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Appliances, Mechanicals, Other Amenities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Dwelling Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Constructed Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Other Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Technical Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Constructed Family Interrelationship Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Demographic Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Fertility and Mortality Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Nativity and Birthplace Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Ethnicity and Language Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Education Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Income Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Disability Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Other Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work: Occupation Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work: Industry Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
  </ns0:simpleDc>
  <ns0:dcTerms>
    <ns2:dateSubmitted>2014-09-15</ns2:dateSubmitted>
    <ns2:available>2014-07-01</ns2:available>
    <ns2:abstract>IPUMS-International is an effort to inventory, preserve, harmonize, and disseminate census microdata from around the world. The project has collected the world's largest archive of publicly available census samples. The data are coded and documented consistently across countries and over time to facilitate comparative research. IPUMS-International makes these data available to qualified researchers free of charge through a web dissemination system. The IPUMS project is a collaboration of the Minnesota Population Center, National Statistical Offices, and international data archives. Major funding is provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation and the Demographic and Behavioral Sciences Branch of the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development. Additional support is provided by the University of Minnesota Office of the Vice President for Research, the Minnesota Population Center, and Sun Microsystems. Detailed metadata will be found in ipumsi_6.3_pa_1990_ddic.html within the Data Package. The related metadata describes the content of the extraction of the specified sample from the IPUMS International on-line extraction system.</ns2:abstract>
    <ns2:tableOfContents>Record type; Country; Year; IPUMS sample identifier; Household serial number; Number of person records in the household; Household weight; Subsample number; Donated household; Group quarters status; Number of unrelated persons; Continent and region of country; 1st subnational geographic level, world [consistent boundaries over time]; Province, Panama [Level 1; consistent boundaries over time]; Province, Panama [Level 1; inconsistent boundaries, harmonized by name]; District, Panama [Level 2; inconsistent boundaries, harmonized by name]; Ownership of dwelling [general version]; Ownership of dwelling [detailed version]; Number of international migrants; Electricity; Water supply; Sewage; Cooking fuel; Telephone availability; Air conditioning; Clothes washing machine; Refrigerator; Television set; Radio in household; Number of rooms; Number of bedrooms; Floor material; Wall or building material; Roof material; Year structure was built; Age of structure, coded from intervals; Household classification; Number of families in household; Number of married couples in household; Number of mothers in household; Number of fathers in household; Head's location in household; Dwelling number; Dwelling created by splitting apart a large dwelling or household; Province; Electric fan; Potable water source; Air conditioner; Lighting; Year of departure for first member; Year of departure for second member; Year of departure for third member; Year of departure for fourth member; Fuel for cooking; Condition of the dwelling; Year of the building of the dwelling; Number of rooms in the dwelling; Number of sleeping rooms in the dwelling; Age at departure of first member who left Panama; Age at departure of second member who left Panama; Age at departure of third member who left Panama; Age at departure of fourth member who left Panama; Household income; Washing machine; Sewing machine; Monthly payment for mortgage or rent; Country of departure for first member who left Panama; Country of departure for second member who left Panama; Country of departure for third member who left Panama; Country of departure for fourth member who leftPanama; Wall material; Floor material; Radio; Refrigerator; Have a member who left the country during the last 10 years; Sewer facilities; Sex of the first member who left Panama; Sex of the second member who left Panama; Sex of the third member who left Panama; Sex of the fourth member who left Panama; Roof material; Telephone; Television; Tenure of the dwelling; Type of dwelling; Type of dwelling (recoded); Tenure of the dwelling (recoded); Water source and system (recoded); Fuel for cooking (recoded); Electricity and sewage; Number of individuals within dwelling; Number of individuals the person lives with; Record type [person version]; Country [person version]; Year [person version]; IPUMS sample identifier [person version]; Household serial number [person version]; Person number; Person weight; Mother's location in household; Father's location in household; Spouse's location in household; Rule for linking parent; Rule for linking spouse; Probable stepmother; Probable stepfather; Man with more than one wife linked; Woman is second or higher order wife; Family unit membership; Number of own family members in household; Number of own children in household; Number of own children under age 5 in household; Age of eldest own child in household; Age of youngest own child in household; Relationship to household head [general version]; Relationship to household head [detailed version]; Age; Age, grouped into intervals; Sex; Marital status [general version]; Marital status [detailed version]; Consensual union; Children ever born; Children surviving; Number of births last year; Mortality status of mother; Nativity status; Member of an indigenous group; Ethnicity (indigenous group) for Panama; School attendance; Literacy; Educational attainment, international recode [general version]; Educational attainment, international recode [detailed version]; Years of schooling; Educational attainment, Panama; Employment status [general version]; Employment status [detailed version]; Occupation, ISCO general; Occupation, unrecoded; Industry, general recode; Industry, unrecoded; Class of worker [general version]; Class of worker [detailed version]; Sector of employment; Total income; Earned income; Wage and salary income; Self-employment income; Disability status; Blind or vision-impaired; Deaf or hearing-impaired; Mute; Mental disability; Person number (within household); Principal economic activity; Year of birth, since May 1989; Attends school; Working Status; Number of children still alive; Monthly income from own-account work; Age; Employment status; Survival of a child; Marital status; Level of education attained; Indigenous group; Number of children ever born alive; Disability; Monthly income from retirement, pensions, scholarships, family assistance, rental and rents incomes, or subsidies; Year arrived in Panama; Mother alive; Family nucleus; Occupation; Relationship; Industry - 3 Digits; Industry; Ability to read and write; Sex; Without income; Monthly income from wage or salary; Employment sector; Child born since May 14, 1989; Monthly income from agricultural sales; Age groups for older population; Marital status recoded; Relationship to head of household recoded; Number of children alive recoded; Possession of title; Economically active; Looked for work last week; Reason for not looking for work; Employment status; Monthly income from work; Monthly income from work recoded; Other monthly income in category; Total monthly income; Occupation recoded; Industries recoded; </ns2:tableOfContents>
    <ns2:spatial>Panama</ns2:spatial>
    <ns2:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:Box">northlimit=9.620136; eastlimit=-77.198336; southlimit=7.206110; westlimit=-83.030291; name=Panama;</ns2:spatial>
    <ns2:temporal>1990</ns2:temporal>
    <ns2:references>http://international.ipums.org</ns2:references>
    <ns2:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_pa_1990_ddic.xml</ns2:hasPart>
    <ns2:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_pa_1990_ddic_xml.html</ns2:hasPart>
    <ns2:accessRights>IPUMS-International distributes integrated microdata of individuals and households only by agreement of collaborating national statistical offices and under the strictest of confidence. Before data may be distributed to an individual researcher, an electronic license agreement must be signed and approved. (see http://international.ipums.org)</ns2:accessRights>
    <ns2:modified>2014-12-10T00:00:00</ns2:modified>
  </ns0:dcTerms>  
</ns0:metadata>