<ns0:metadata xmlns:ns0="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0 http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0/onedcx_v1.0.xsd">
  <ns0:simpleDc>
    <ns2:type>package</ns2:type>
    <ns2:creator>Minnesota Population Center</ns2:creator>
    <ns2:title>IPUMS-International: France 1968 Census</ns2:title>
    <ns2:identifier>ipumsi_6.3_fr_1968_DC.xml</ns2:identifier>
    <ns2:subject>Census</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Group Quarters Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Economic Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Utilities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Appliances, Mechanicals, Other Amenities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Dwelling Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Constructed Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Technical Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Constructed Family Interrelationship Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Demographic Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Nativity and Birthplace Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Education Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Migration Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work: Industry Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work: Occupation Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Other Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
  </ns0:simpleDc>
  <ns0:dcTerms>
    <ns2:dateSubmitted>2014-09-15</ns2:dateSubmitted>
    <ns2:available>2014-07-01</ns2:available>
    <ns2:abstract>IPUMS-International is an effort to inventory, preserve, harmonize, and disseminate census microdata from around the world. The project has collected the world's largest archive of publicly available census samples. The data are coded and documented consistently across countries and over time to facilitate comparative research. IPUMS-International makes these data available to qualified researchers free of charge through a web dissemination system. The IPUMS project is a collaboration of the Minnesota Population Center, National Statistical Offices, and international data archives. Major funding is provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation and the Demographic and Behavioral Sciences Branch of the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development. Additional support is provided by the University of Minnesota Office of the Vice President for Research, the Minnesota Population Center, and Sun Microsystems. Detailed metadata will be found in ipumsi_6.3_fr_1968_ddic.html within the Data Package. The related metadata describes the content of the extraction of the specified sample from the IPUMS International on-line extraction system.</ns2:abstract>
    <ns2:tableOfContents>Record type; Country; Year; IPUMS sample identifier; Household serial number; Number of person records in the household; Household weight; Subsample number; Group quarters status; Number of unrelated persons; Urban-rural status; Continent and region of country; 1st subnational geographic level, world [consistent boundaries over time]; NUTS1 Region, Europe; NUTS2 Region, Europe; Region, France [Level 1; consistent boundaries over time]; Ownership of dwelling [general version]; Ownership of dwelling [detailed version]; Electricity; Sewage; Fuel for heating; Telephone availability; Automobiles available; Central heating; Number of rooms; Number of bedrooms; Kitchen or cooking facilities; Bathing facilities; Year structure was built; Age of structure, coded from intervals; Stories in structure; Elevator in structure; Household classification; Number of families in household; Number of married couples in household; Number of mothers in household; Number of fathers in household; Head's location in household; Region; Year the building was completed; Presence of an elevator in the building; Heating source of the dwelling (and the building); Heating fuel in the building; Means of heating in the dwelling; Central heating in the building; Household category; Type of cooking facilities; Electrical supply for the building; Drainage of toilets; Drainage of domestic water; Number of floors in a building; Gas supply to the dwelling; Supply of gas to the building; Number of rooms in a dwelling (kitchen not included); Number of rooms in a dwelling; Density of dwelling; Bathing facilities; Dwelling number in the building; Primary materials in the walls; Primary materials in the roof; Primary materials for the walls and roof; Number of children in the dwelling; Number of agricultural units in the dwelling; Number of families in the household; Primary family in the household; Number of secondary households in the household; Number of people in the dwelling; Number of people in the restricted dwelling; Number of dwellings in the building; Number of dwellings in the building in the sample; Number of rooms in the dwelling; Number of people in the dwelling; Number of farms belonging to a household in the dwelling; Water supply in the dwelling; Water source for domestic use; Spouse of the head of household present; Weight of the building; First dwelling in the building; Ownership; Number of basements in the building; Farmland assigned to dwelling; Size of the first farm; Size of the second farm; Telephone connection in the dwelling; Type of dwelling; Farm status; Number of dwellings and building type; Number of cars available to the household; Toilet facilities; Number of people in the family; Number of rooms occupied by the family; Saphir region; Urban-rural; Record type [person version]; Country [person version]; Year [person version]; IPUMS sample identifier [person version]; Household serial number [person version]; Person number; Person weight; Mother's location in household; Father's location in household; Spouse's location in household; Rule for linking parent; Rule for linking spouse; Probable stepmother; Probable stepfather; Man with more than one wife linked; Woman is second or higher order wife; Family unit membership; Number of own family members in household; Number of own children in household; Number of own children under age 5 in household; Age of eldest own child in household; Age of youngest own child in household; Relationship to household head [general version]; Relationship to household head [detailed version]; Relationship to head, Europe; Age; Age, grouped into intervals; Sex; Marital status [general version]; Marital status [detailed version]; Marital status, Europe; Year of birth; Nativity status; Region of birth, France; Region of birth, Europe, NUTS1; Region of birth, Europe, NUTS2; Citizenship; Country of citizenship; School attendance; Educational attainment, international recode [general version]; Educational attainment, international recode [detailed version]; Educational attainment, France; Educational attainment, Europe; Age when completed education; Employment status [general version]; Employment status [detailed version]; Employment status, Europe; Occupation, ISCO general; Occupation, unrecoded; Industry, general recode; Industry, unrecoded; Class of worker [general version]; Class of worker [detailed version]; Class of worker, Europe; Number of employees; Period seeking work; Region of work, France; Means of transportation to work or school; Migration status, last census; Region of residence at last census, France; Head of family relationship to head of the household; Industry (nomenclature of the UN); Belonging to a family; Age completed schooling; Category of the population in detail; Occupation; Class of worker; Diploma; Unemployment duration; General education diploma; Technical education degree or general education degree; Citizenship; Age; Age in calendar year; Industry, 41 categories; Region of birth; Region of previous residence; Relationship to head of family; Relationship to head of household; Marital status; Main form of transportation; Second means of transportation; Third means of transportation; Nationality; Number of forms of transportation; Number of paid workers; Number of corrections made for the individual; Region of workplace; Sex; Qualification; Employment status; SAPHIR region of birthplace; SAPHIR region of previous residence; SAPHIR region of workplace; SAPHIR citizenship; SAPHIR nationality; SAPHIR diploma; SAPHIR type of activity; SAPHIR class of worker; SAPHIR occupation; Migration; </ns2:tableOfContents>
    <ns2:spatial>France</ns2:spatial>
    <ns2:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:Box">northlimit=51.091109; eastlimit=9.562218; southlimit=41.364927; westlimit=-4.790282; name=France;</ns2:spatial>
    <ns2:temporal>1968</ns2:temporal>
    <ns2:references>http://international.ipums.org</ns2:references>
    <ns2:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_fr_1968_ddic.xml</ns2:hasPart>
    <ns2:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_fr_1968_ddic_xml.html</ns2:hasPart>
    <ns2:accessRights>IPUMS-International distributes integrated microdata of individuals and households only by agreement of collaborating national statistical offices and under the strictest of confidence. Before data may be distributed to an individual researcher, an electronic license agreement must be signed and approved. (see http://international.ipums.org)</ns2:accessRights>
    <ns2:modified>2014-12-10T00:00:00</ns2:modified>
  </ns0:dcTerms>  
</ns0:metadata>