<ns0:metadata xmlns:ns0="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0 http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0/onedcx_v1.0.xsd">
  <ns0:simpleDc>
    <ns2:type>package</ns2:type>
    <ns2:creator>Minnesota Population Center</ns2:creator>
    <ns2:title>IPUMS-International: Indonesia 1985 Census</ns2:title>
    <ns2:identifier>ipumsi_6.3_id_1985_DC.xml</ns2:identifier>
    <ns2:subject>Census</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Group Quarters Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Geography Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Economic Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Utilities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Appliances, Mechanicals, Other Amenities Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Dwelling Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Other Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Constructed Household Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Technical Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Constructed Family Interrelationship Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Demographic Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Nativity and Birthplace Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Ethnicity and Language Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Education Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Migration Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Disability Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Other Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work: Occupation Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
    <ns2:subject>Work: Industry Variables -- PERSON</ns2:subject>
  </ns0:simpleDc>
  <ns0:dcTerms>
    <ns2:dateSubmitted>2014-09-15</ns2:dateSubmitted>
    <ns2:available>2014-07-01</ns2:available>
    <ns2:abstract>IPUMS-International is an effort to inventory, preserve, harmonize, and disseminate census microdata from around the world. The project has collected the world's largest archive of publicly available census samples. The data are coded and documented consistently across countries and over time to facilitate comparative research. IPUMS-International makes these data available to qualified researchers free of charge through a web dissemination system. The IPUMS project is a collaboration of the Minnesota Population Center, National Statistical Offices, and international data archives. Major funding is provided by the U.S. National Science Foundation and the Demographic and Behavioral Sciences Branch of the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development. Additional support is provided by the University of Minnesota Office of the Vice President for Research, the Minnesota Population Center, and Sun Microsystems. Detailed metadata will be found in ipumsi_6.3_id_1985_ddic.html within the Data Package. The related metadata describes the content of the extraction of the specified sample from the IPUMS International on-line extraction system.</ns2:abstract>
    <ns2:tableOfContents>Record type; Country; Year; IPUMS sample identifier; Household serial number; Number of person records in the household; Household weight; Subsample number; Group quarters status; Number of unrelated persons; Urban-rural status; Continent and region of country; 1st subnational geographic level, world [consistent boundaries over time]; Province, Indonesia [Level 1; consistent boundaries over time]; Province, Indonesia [Level 1; inconsistent boundaries, harmonized by name]; Regency, Indonesia [Level 2; inconsistent boundaries, harmonized by name]; Ownership of dwelling [general version]; Ownership of dwelling [detailed version]; Land ownership; Main source of livelihood; Electricity; Water supply; Sewage; Cooking fuel; Television set; Radio in household; Bathing facilities; Floor material; Wall or building material; Roof material; Stories in structure; Living area in square meters; Number of deaths in household last year; Any deaths in household last year; Household classification; Number of families in household; Number of married couples in household; Number of mothers in household; Number of fathers in household; Head's location in household; Dwelling number; Number of persons in household; Province; Regency/municipality; Urban/rural; Source of household income; Household owned farmland; Area (in hectares) of the farm land owned; Average monthly expenditure (thousands of Rp); Physical building type; Multifloor building; Number of census units in building; Number of households in census unit; Ownership status of living quarters; Ownership status of land; Type of material of roof; Type of material of wall; Type of material of floor; Floor area (in square meters) of living quarters; Total area (in square meters) of land including living quarters; Type of energy used for lighting; Type of energy used for cooking; Source of drinking water; Distance between well and septic tank/sewage disposal; Source of water for bathing; Bathing facilities; Toilet facilities; Cupboard; Stove; Bicycle; Radio/cassette tape player; Television; Household weight; Total number of household members; Total number of births last year; Total number of infant deaths last year; Total number of deaths last year; Record type [person version]; Country [person version]; Year [person version]; IPUMS sample identifier [person version]; Household serial number [person version]; Person number; Person weight; Mother's location in household; Father's location in household; Spouse's location in household; Rule for linking parent; Rule for linking spouse; Probable stepmother; Probable stepfather; Man with more than one wife linked; Woman is second or higher order wife; Family unit membership; Number of own family members in household; Number of own children in household; Number of own children under age 5 in household; Age of eldest own child in household; Age of youngest own child in household; Relationship to household head [general version]; Relationship to household head [detailed version]; Age; Age, grouped into intervals; Sex; Marital status [general version]; Marital status [detailed version]; Nativity status; Province of birth, Indonesia; Citizenship; Country of citizenship; Religion [general version]; Religion [detailed version]; School attendance; Literacy; Educational attainment, international recode [general version]; Educational attainment, international recode [detailed version]; Years of schooling; Educational attainment, Indonesia; Employment status [general version]; Employment status [detailed version]; Occupation, ISCO general; Occupation, unrecoded; Occupation, ISCO-1968, 3-digit; Industry, general recode; Industry, unrecoded; Class of worker [general version]; Class of worker [detailed version]; Days worked last week; Hours worked per week; Hours worked per week, categorized; Hours worked in main occupation; Period seeking work; Migration status, 5 years; Migration status, previous residence; Years residing in current locality; Reason for migration; Province of previous residence, Indonesia; Province of residence 5 years ago, Indonesia; Employment disability; Person number (within household); Person number; Relationship to head of household; Sex; Age; Marital status; Religion; Citizenship; Province of birth; Regency/municipality of birth; Ever lived in another regency/municipality; Length of time lived in current regency/municipality; Province of previous residence; Regency/municipality of previous residence; Reason for moving; Own mother living in household; Serial number of own mother; Province lived in October 1980; Regency/municipality lived in October 1980; Current school attendance; Highest level of school attended; Highest grade attended; Highest grade attending/attended; Highest level of education completed; Ability to read/write; Primary activity last week; Worked at least 1 hour last week; Temporarily not working last week; Ever worked before; Looked for work last week; Total number of days worked lastweek; Total number of hours worked last week; Primary occupation; Status in primary occupation; Number of hours worked at primary occupation; Industry of primary occupation; Secondary job last week; Number of hours worked at additional job; Industry of secondary occupation; Have another additional job; Looked for work last week; Months looking for work; Type of work desired; Effort made to look for work - acquaintances and family; Effort made to look for work - advertisement; Effort made to look for work - companies/offices; Effort made to look for work - register at Ministry of Manpower; Effort made to look for work - other; Reason for not looking for work last week; Willing to accept any type of employment; Worked last year; Industry during the last year; Person weight; </ns2:tableOfContents>
    <ns2:spatial>Indonesia</ns2:spatial>
    <ns2:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:Box">northlimit=5.913473; eastlimit=141.007021; southlimit=-10.929655; westlimit=95.210945; name=Indonesia;</ns2:spatial>
    <ns2:temporal>1985</ns2:temporal>
    <ns2:references>http://international.ipums.org</ns2:references>
    <ns2:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_id_1985_ddic.xml</ns2:hasPart>
    <ns2:hasPart>ipumsi_6.3_id_1985_ddic_xml.html</ns2:hasPart>
    <ns2:accessRights>IPUMS-International distributes integrated microdata of individuals and households only by agreement of collaborating national statistical offices and under the strictest of confidence. Before data may be distributed to an individual researcher, an electronic license agreement must be signed and approved. (see http://international.ipums.org)</ns2:accessRights>
    <ns2:modified>2014-12-10T00:00:00</ns2:modified>
  </ns0:dcTerms>  
</ns0:metadata>