<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb-lter-cwt.1070.4" scope="system" system="cwt-lter" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 http://gce-lter.marsci.uga.edu/lter/files/schemas/eml-201/eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><title>Measuring forest canopy structure and aboveground biomass with a 3-D laser scanner.</title><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Philip</givenName><surName>Radtke</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Virginia Tech Department of Forestry</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>Virginia Tech</deliveryPoint><city>Blacksburg</city><administrativeArea>Virginia</administrativeArea><postalCode>24061</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(540) 231-8863</phone><electronicMailAddress>pradtke@vt.edu</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://coweeta.ecology.uga.edu</onlineUrl></creator><creator scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Britt</givenName><surName>Boucher</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Foresters Incorporated</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>P.O. Box 11750</deliveryPoint><city>Blacksburg</city><administrativeArea>Virginia</administrativeArea><postalCode>24062-1750</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(540) 951-0223</phone><electronicMailAddress>britt@foresters-inc.com</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>http://coweeta.ecology.uga.edu</onlineUrl></creator><abstract><para>Improvement in techniques for measuring forest canopy structure and aboveground biomass is needed for the advancement of carbon sequestration monitoring and prediction. Methods that increase the accuracy of aboveground biomass measurements and facilitate integration of data from forest inventory, remote sensing and Ameriflux collection methods are particularly needed. Rapid, accurate measurements of aboveground biomass and canopy structure would greatly improve efforts to assess and model carbon sequestration in forest canopies. | Methods for measuring 3-D canopy structure with a commercially available scanning laser instrument will be developed and tested for feasibility on a commercial scale. The methods will allow for the estimation of the amount and spatial distribution of foliage surface area and mass in forested canopies. In addition, the methods will allow for the estimation of wood volume and biomass in tree boles and large branches. | A laser-scanning instrument will be used to measure 3-D canopy structure in broadleaved, deciduous forests at existing research sites in the eastern United States. Estimates of leaf area index (LAI) and its spatial arrangement in the canopy, and the biomass of leaves, boles and large branches will be estimated for comparison to existing measurements made with traditional methods at the research sites.</para><para>Work at Coweeta will proceed during the winter season 2001-02 under leafless canopies. A tripod-mounted 3D-Laser Scanner (Riegl LMS-Z210) will be used to acquire high-resolution laser range, intensity and color (RGB) measurements of the underside of the canopy. Data acquisition is nondestructive. The class 1 laser scanner is considered eye safe. Multiple scans will be made over a sampling grid on study plots. Grid resolution will be varied from 1 x 1 m on subsections of the research plots, up to a coarser resolution of 10 x 10 m over the entire 20 x 40 m research plots. Tree x, y coordinates with respect to the plot corner will be recorded along with dbh unless these data have been measured recently and are made available to us.</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>Coweeta</keyword><keyword>LTER</keyword><keyword>laser scanner</keyword><keyword>foliage height profile</keyword><keyword>LAI</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><para>Must adhere to the Coweeta LTER Data Policy (See http://coweeta.uga.edu/policies/data).</para></intellectualRights><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://coweeta.uga.edu/summaries/Csummary1070_b.html</url></online></distribution><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Terrestrial gradient plots: 118, 218, 318, 427 and 527</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate /><eastBoundingCoordinate /><northBoundingCoordinate /><southBoundingCoordinate /></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2001-08-01</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2002-08-01</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><positionName>Coweeta LTER Information Manager</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University of Georgia</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>Georgia</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">(828) 524-2128</phone></contact><project scope="document"><title>Coweeta Long Term Ecological Research</title><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Ted</givenName><surName>Gragson</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University of Georgia</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>Georgia</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><electronicMailAddress>tgragson@earthlink.net</electronicMailAddress><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>James</givenName><surName>Vose</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University of Georgia</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>Georgia</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><electronicMailAddress>jvose@fs.fed.us</electronicMailAddress><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><personnel scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Brian</givenName><surName>Kloeppel</surName></individualName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Ecology</deliveryPoint><deliveryPoint>University of Georgia</deliveryPoint><city>Athens</city><administrativeArea>Georgia</administrativeArea><postalCode>30602</postalCode><country>USA</country></address><electronicMailAddress>kloeppel@sparc.ecology.uga.edu</electronicMailAddress><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><abstract><para>The Coweeta LTER Research Program has evolved since 1980 from a site-based to a site- and region-based project examining the effects of disturbance

and environmental gradients on biogeochemical cycling, and the underlying

watershed ecosystem processes that regulate and respond to those cycles. 

The objective for the 2002-2008 research is to advance scientific

understanding of the spatial, temporal, and decision-making components of

land use and land-use change in the southern Appalachian Mountains over the

last 200 years, and forecast patterns into the future 30 years.  This will

be accomplished by addressing ecological and socioeconomic aspects of

land-use change while continuing long-term studies of environmental

gradients and natural disturbance regimes.  The result will be a more

complete understanding of ecological dynamics in the southern Appalachian

Mountains that makes possible the development of reasonable forecasts of

its future ecological state. | The guiding hypothesis for the proposed research is that the frequency, intensity, and extent of land use represents human decision-making in

response to socioeconomic and bio-geophysical conditions with consequences

that cascade through ecosystems.  The research activities are organized

into three initiatives: (1) Characterization of the Socio-Natural Template,

(2) Ecosystem Responses to the Socio-Natural Template, and (3) Forecasting

Ecosystem Responses to Changes in the Socio-Natural Template.  The

integrated scientific research will provide both a description as well as

an explanation of the underlying causes of land use and the consequences of

land-use change for southern Appalachian ecosystems and society.  It thus

recognizes the complexity of land use as a process and the research needs

as defined in the LTER Program and the broader scientific community.</para></abstract><funding><para>National Science Foundation. Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed in the material are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation.</para></funding></project><access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>uid=cwt,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission></allow><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access></dataset></ns0:eml>