<metadata><Source>http://www1.usgs.gov/metadata/mdata/vip/metapaisbdy.xml</Source>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>National Park Service</origin>
        <pubdate>2009</pubdate>
        <title>Padre Island National Seashore Vegetation Mapping Project - Park Boundary</title>
        <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
        <onlink>http://www1.usgs.gov/vip/pais/paisgeodata.zip</onlink>
        <onlink>doi:10.5066/F7S180GD</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>National Park or National Monument boundary used to delineate project area. This is a vector polygon file showing the Boundary at Padre Island National Seashore. The coordinates for the dataset were were digitized off of a 1:24000 USGS Topographic map. The file was originally digitized into EPPL7 and then converted to ArcView on a PC.</abstract>
      <purpose>To assist with the development of vegetation maps for the National Park Service.</purpose>
      <supplinf>Boundary data were downloaded by the Colorado Natural Heritage Program/Colorado State University on 12/04/2009 from https://irma.nps.gov/App/Reference/Search and imported to the file geodatabase.

Padre Island National Seashore was established by Congress on September 28, 1962 (16 U.S.C. 459d, et seq.), "In order to save and preserve, for purposes of public recreation, benefit, and inspiration, a portion of the diminishing seashore of the United States that remains undeveloped..." Padre Island National Seashore is located on a largely undeveloped barrier island in southern Texas, on the Gulf of Mexico. The National Seashore consists of 130,454 acres of land and water, is approximately 70 miles in length, and varies from one-half to three miles in width. The seashore is bordered on the east by the Gulf of Mexico and is separated from the Texas mainland, to the west, by the Laguna Madre, a shallow, hypersaline body of water. Padre Island National Seashore is the longest stretch of undeveloped barrier island in the world, providing primitive beach recreation, wildlife viewing, and scenic solitude. The barrier island is a dynamic system subject to many geologic forces and climatic events. The barrier island was formed, and is continually being reshaped, by the actions of wind, gulf currents, and waves. The seashore's landscape changes from broad, white, fine-sand beaches on the Gulf side, to ridges of fore-island sand dunes, to grassy interior upland flats dotted with smaller dunes, and ephemeral ponds and freshwater wetlands. The western portion of the Seashore is defined by the Laguna Madre and the back-island dunes and wind tidal flats that merge with the waters of the Laguna Madre. There are also two natural and 20 man-made spoil islands in the Laguna that lie within the National Seashore. The park encompasses thousands of acres of wetlands that are important habitat for numerous aquatic species. Approximately 60 percent (78,000 ac.) of the area between the gulf dune line and the Laguna Madre is comprised of a rich variety of wetlands, including estuarine emergent wetlands, freshwater ponds, wind tidal algal flats, Laguna Madre intertidal zone, lagoonal seagrass beds, and marshes. The remaining 40 percent (55,000 ac.) includes Gulf of Mexico waters to the two-fathom line, Gulf beach, coastal prairie grassland, and sparsely vegetated dunes. Park cultural resources include shipwrecks, Native American sites, and the last remaining examples of barrier island ranching structures along the Gulf coast.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>2003</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>None planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Padre Island National Seashore</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-97.426247</westbc>
        <eastbc>-97.254414</eastbc>
        <northbc>27.539657</northbc>
        <southbc>26.560716</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>National Park Boundary</themekey>
        <themekey>National Monument Boundary</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from U.S. Geological Survey and National Park Service servers and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way.</accconst>
    <useconst>The National Park Service shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.  These data and related tables are not legal documents and are not intended to be used as such. The information contained in these data is dynamic and may change over time.  The data are not better than the original sources from which they were derived.  It is the responsibility of the data user to use the data appropriately and consistent within the limitations of geospatial data in general and these data in particular.

The National Park Service gives no warranty, expressed or implied, as to the accuracy, reliability, or completeness of these data.  Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the utility of the data on another system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data. Mention of trade names or commercial products in this metadata report does not constitute endorsement or recommendation for use by the U. S. Department of the Interior, U. S. Geological Survey and National Park Service.</useconst>
    <native>Microsoft Windows Vista Version 6.0 (Build 6002) Service Pack 2; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.1.1850</native>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>The correctness of the dataset was verified by the Resource Management Specialist at Padre Island National Seashore during the time of development.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>There are no duplicate features present. Polygon features end and start at the same point.</logic>
    <complete>This dataset is complete to the specifications of Park personnel at the time of collection. At this time there is no need for any more data collection of the pipeline area, but this dataset may be changed or be added to in the future.</complete>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Unknown</procdesc>
        <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Vector</direct>
    <ptvctinf>
      <sdtsterm>
        <sdtstype>G-polygon</sdtstype>
        <ptvctcnt>1</ptvctcnt>
      </sdtsterm>
    </ptvctinf>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>14</utmzone>
            <transmer>
              <sfctrmer>0.999600</sfctrmer>
              <longcm>-99.000000</longcm>
              <latprjo>0.000000</latprjo>
              <feast>500000.000000</feast>
              <fnorth>0.000000</fnorth>
            </transmer>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
          <coordrep>
            <absres>0.000100</absres>
            <ordres>0.000100</ordres>
          </coordrep>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
        <ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.000000</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257222</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>PAIS_Park_Boundary</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Feature class attribute table</enttypd>
        <enttypds>National Park Service</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>OBJECTID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SHAPE</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Park_Code</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>NPS Park Code</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>NPS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Park acronym name (PAIS).</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Park_Name</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>NPS Park Name</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>NPS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Park name (Padre Island National Seashore)</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>State</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>2-letter abbreviation of state in which park occurs (or mostly occurs if park spans more than one state)</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>NPS</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>State acronym name (TX).</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Acres</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Area (unknown units)</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Hectares</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Perimeter (unknown units)</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SHAPE_Length</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Length of feature in internal units.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>SHAPE_Area</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Area of feature in internal units squared.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>USGS/CSS/Core Science Analytics and Synthesis</cntorg>
          <cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Characterization Program Coordinator</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, MS 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>Colorado</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>303-202-4219</cntfax>
        <cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
    <distliab>The U.S. Geological Survey and the National Park Service shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.  These data and related graphics (if available) are not legal documents and are not intended to be used as such.

The information contained in these data is dynamic and may change over time.  The data are not better than the original sources from which they were derived.  It is the responsibility of the data user to use the data appropriately and consistent within the limitations of geospatial data in general and these data in particular.  Any related graphics (if available) are intended to aid the data user in acquiring relevant data; it is not approriate to use the related graphics as data.

The U.S. Geological Survey and the National Park Service gives no warranty, expressed or implied, as to the accuracy, reliability, or completeness of these data.  It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from an U.S. Geological Survey and National Park Service servers and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way.  Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the utility of the data on another system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data. Mention of trade names or commercial products in this metadata report does not constitute endorsement or recommendation for use by the U. S. Department of the Interior, U. S. Geological Survey and National Park Service.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>HTML</formname>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>http://www.usgs.gov/core_science_systems/csas/vip/parks/pais.html</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
            <accinstr>Internet Access</accinstr>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20091208</metd>
    <metrd>20100710</metrd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>USGS/CSS/Core Science Analytics and Synthesis</cntorg>
          <cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Characterization Program Coordinator</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, MS 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>Colorado</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>303-202-4219</cntfax>
        <cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.usgs.gov/core_science_systems/csas/metadata/index.html</onlink>
    </metextns>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>