<metadata><Source>http://www1.usgs.gov/metadata/mdata/vip/metatumaspatial.xml</Source>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Sonoran Desert Network, Inventory and Monitoring Program</origin>
<origin>Sarah Studd, NPS Vegetation Ecologist</origin>
<pubdate>20090201</pubdate>
<title>Tumacacori National Historic Park Vegetation Inventory and Mapping Project - Spatial Vegetation Data</title>
<geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>NPS-USGS Vegetation Mapping Program</sername>
<issue>Tumacacori National Historic Park</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
<publish>USGS, Biological Resources Discipline, Center for Biological Informatics</publish>
</pubinfo>
<onlink>http://www1.usgs.gov/vip/tuma/tumageodata.zip</onlink>
<onlink>doi:10.5066/F7GQ6VPS</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>This polygon feature class represents vegetation communities mapped at Tumacacori National Historic Park to an alliance or association level. landscape feature as a guide. d to develop the polygons, such as shape, size, pattern, tone, texture, color, and shadow. Additional data layers were used in aiding the interpretation, such as slope, hydrology, geography, and ground-collected vegetation information. The draft polygons were printed out and taken into the field; Field crews modified boundaires and merged or split delineated polygons based on field observations. All edits were made on paper maqps and transferred into GIS later. The minimum mapping unit was 1/2 hectare. The attributed vegetation classes were subjected to an accuracy assessment, following which final adjustments were made to the vegetation classes. As with any digital layer, this layer is a representation of what is actually occurring on the ground. Errors are inherent in any interpretation of ground qualities. Due to the "snapshot" nature of the imagery, this vegetation layer reflects conditions that existed when the imagery was collected.</abstract>
<purpose>This polygon layer represents vegetation communities found in all three management units of Tumacacori National Historic Park. The intended use of all data in the park's GIS library is to support diverse park activities including planning, management, maintenance, research, and interpretation.</purpose>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>20060827</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>Source photography date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>As needed</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<descgeog>Tumacacori National Historic Park</descgeog>
<bounding>
<westbc>-111.052598</westbc>
<eastbc>-110.899160</eastbc>
<northbc>31.583563</northbc>
<southbc>31.405847</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>None</themekt>
<themekey>Vegetation Classification</themekey>
<themekey>Standardized National Vegetation Classification</themekey>
<themekey>SNVCS</themekey>
<themekey>NVCS</themekey>
<themekey>Alliance</themekey>
<themekey>Community Association</themekey>
<themekey>Vegetation Map</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>National Park Service Theme Category Thesaurus</themekt>
<themekey>Vegetation</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
<themekey>biota</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>None</placekt>
<placekey>Tumacacori National Historic Park</placekey>
<placekey>TUMA</placekey>
<placekey>Santa Cruz County</placekey>
<placekey>Arizona</placekey>
<placekey>AZ</placekey>
<placekey>Sonoran Desert</placekey>
<placekey>National Park Service</placekey>
<placekey>NPS</placekey>
<placekey>USA</placekey>
</place>
<place>
<placekt>National Park System Unit Name Thesaurus</placekt>
<placekey>Tumacacori National Historic Park</placekey>
</place>
<place>
<placekt>National Park System Unit Code Thesaurus</placekt>
<placekey>TUMA</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<taxonomy>
<keywtax>
<taxonkt>None</taxonkt>
<taxonkey>Standardized National Vegetation Classification System</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>vegetation classification</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>alliance</taxonkey>
<taxonkey>community association</taxonkey>
</keywtax>
<taxoncl>
<taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
<taxonrv>Plantae</taxonrv>
<common>plants</common>
</taxoncl>
</taxonomy>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>Acknowledgment of the National Park Service would be appreciated in products derived from these data. Any person using the information presented here should fully understand the data collection and compilation process before beginning their analysis/use. The burden of determining fitness for use lies with the user.</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>Sonoran Desert Network, Inventory and Monitoring Program</cntorg>
<cntper>Sarah Studd</cntper>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Vegetation Ecologist</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing</addrtype>
<address>12661 E Broadway Blvd</address>
<city>Tucson</city>
<state>AZ</state>
<postal>85748</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>520-343-8845</cntvoice>
<cntemail>sarah_studd@nps.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
<datacred>NPS, TUMA &amp; SODN</datacred>
<native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 2; ESRI ArcCatalog 10.1</native>
<crossref>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Drake, S., S. Buckley, M. Villarreal, S. Studd, and J. A. Hubbard. 2009.</origin>
<pubdate>20090901</pubdate>
<title>Vegetation classification, distribution, and mapping report: Tumac&#225;cori National Historical Park.Natural Resource Report NPS/SODN/NRR&#151;2009/148. National Park Service, Fort Collins, Colorado</title>
<geoform>report</geoform>
<onlink>http://science.nature.nps.gov/im/Units/SODN/</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</crossref>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<attracc>
<attraccr>Network staff have ground checked and verified all features to the best of their knowledge. GIS personnel verified all features and attributes.</attraccr>
</attracc>
<logic>All polygon features are checked for topology using the ArcGIS software.  There are no duplicate features present.  The tests for logical consistency are performed in ArcGIS.  All attribute codes and attributes have been checked for typographical and logical errors.</logic>
<complete>This data contains all the polygons mapped both in and surrounding Tumacacori National Nistoric park. All data in the project area were classified and digitized. This includes alliances/community association classes, density classes, height classes and unvegetated/landuse. All data with a minimum mapping unit of 1/2 hectare that could be interpreted from the aerial photographs are entered into the digital database. Road and utility corridors and streams/canals wider than 10 meters are included as polygons in this vegetation coverage.</complete>
<posacc>
<horizpa>
<horizpar>The vegetation spatial data meets National Map Accuracy Standards.</horizpar>
</horizpa>
<vertacc>
<vertaccr>Not applicable</vertaccr>
</vertacc>
</posacc>
<lineage>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Arizona Remote Sensing Center, University of Arizona</origin>
<pubdate>varies</pubdate>
<title>qb_pansharp_tumm_sub.img</title>
<geoform>remote-sensing image</geoform>
<onlink>\\SIND\D$\NPS_VegMapping\TUMA\Imagery\qb_pansharp_tumm_sub.img</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<typesrc>unknown</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>20060827</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>Imagery date</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>DRG</srccitea>
<srccontr>Printed copies of the pan-sharpened image were used for field maps.</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>USGS/BRD, Center for Biological Informatics</origin>
<pubdate>19941101</pubdate>
<title>Accuracy Assessment Procedures, NBS/NPS Vegetation Mapping</title>
<geoform>document</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>USGS-NPS Vegetation Mapping Program</sername>
<issue>Tumacacori National Historic Park</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
<publish>USGS/BRD, Center for Biological Informatics</publish>
</pubinfo>
<othercit>This report was prepared by Environmental Systems Research Institute+ADs- Redlands, CA,  National Center for Geographic Information and Analysis,  University of California, Santa Barbara, CA and The Nature Conservancy, Arlington, VA under contract from the U.S. Department of Interior National Biological Survey and National Park Service.</othercit>
<onlink>http://www.usgs.gov/core_science_systems/</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<typesrc>electronic document</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>19941101</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>Accuracy Assessment Procedures Documents</srccitea>
<srccontr>This document was used to guide the accuracy assessment process for this project. However, a census method was chosen for Tumacacori NHP as outlined in the Small Park Alternative Guidelines document (3/25/2008).</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<procstep>
<procdesc>Imagery collection and publication.  Original imagery was acquired on August 27, 2006 by DigitalGlobe, Inc.'s Quickbird satellite. Its 4 multispectral bands (blue, green, red, near-infrared), together with the concurrently-collected panchromatic data, were orthorectified with ERDAS (Leica) software, using a USGS National Elevation Dataset digital elevation model, ground control points from digital orthophoto quarter quadrangles (DOQQs) and the Quickbird rational polynomial coefficient model. Following orthorectification, the multispectral imagery, collected at 2.4-m pixel resolution, was sharpened with the 0.6-m panchromatic data, producing a 4-band image with 0.6-m resolution.</procdesc>
<procdate>2007</procdate>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>Polygon creation.  Using the pan-sharpened Quickbird imagery as a base layer, lines delineating vegetation boundaries were digitized on-screen. Polygons were attributed with a formation type representative of the structural characterisitcs (i.e. forest versus woodland versus savanna) when drawn.</procdesc>
<procdate>2007</procdate>
<proccont>
<cntinfo>
<cntperp>
<cntper>Sam Drake</cntper>
<cntorg>Arizona Remote Sensing Center, University of Arizona</cntorg>
</cntperp>
<cntpos>Research Scientist</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>unknown</address>
<city>Tucson</city>
<state>AZ</state>
<postal>85721</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>520-621-4501</cntvoice>
<cntemail>sdrake@email.arizona.edu</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</proccont>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>Accuracy assessment.  An accuracy assessment was conducted using a census method akin to that in which the polygons were attributed and modified. It followed the guidelines in the Small Park Alternative Guidelines document. The accuracy assessment was conducted primarily by the Chief of Resources at Tumacacori NHP.</procdesc>
<procdate>2008-2009</procdate>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>Revision and publication.  Following the accuracy assessment, specialists examined analyzed the thematic accuracy of the vegetation layer.  Adjustments were made to the data layer according to those assessments.  Data was migrated to a personal file-based geodatabase.</procdesc>
<procdate>2009</procdate>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spdoinfo>
<direct>Vector</direct>
<ptvctinf>
<sdtsterm>
<sdtstype>G-polygon</sdtstype>
<ptvctcnt>59</ptvctcnt>
</sdtsterm>
<sdtsterm>
<sdtstype>Entity point photo points</sdtstype>
<ptvctcnt>40</ptvctcnt>
</sdtsterm>
</ptvctinf>
</spdoinfo>
<spref>
<horizsys>
<planar>
<gridsys>
<gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
<utm>
<utmzone>12</utmzone>
<transmer>
<sfctrmer>0.999600</sfctrmer>
<longcm>-111.000000</longcm>
<latprjo>0.000000</latprjo>
<feast>500000.000000</feast>
<fnorth>0.000000</fnorth>
</transmer>
</utm>
</gridsys>
<planci>
<plance>coordinate pair</plance>
<coordrep>
<absres>0.000100</absres>
<ordres>0.000100</ordres>
</coordrep>
<plandu>meters</plandu>
</planci>
</planar>
<geodetic>
<horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
<ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
<semiaxis>6378137.000000</semiaxis>
<denflat>298.257222</denflat>
</geodetic>
</horizsys>
</spref>
<eainfo>
<detailed>
<enttyp>
<enttypl>fcl_Veg_Polys</enttypl>
<enttypd>Feature Class</enttypd>
<enttypds>National Park Service</enttypds>
</enttyp>
<attr>
<attrlabl>OBJECTID</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SHAPE</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Poly_ID</attrlabl>
<attrdef>unique polygon ID</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ALphanumeric identifier</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>unique polygon ID</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Poly_Code</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Map class unique identifier</attrdef>
<attrdefs>SODN</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Code delineating the Map Unit for TUMA.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Unit_Code</attrlabl>
<attrdef>4 letter NPS code for each management unit</attrdef>
<attrdefs>NPS park codes</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Four letter codes for each park unit.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Map_Code</attrlabl>
<attrdef>NVC codes for each map unit</attrdef>
<attrdefs>NVC or SODN</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Codes representing NVC community types.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Formation</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Structural type of vegetation</attrdef>
<attrdefs>SODN</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Descriptive label for vegetation structure.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Veg_Type</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Full scientific name of each vegetation alliance or association</attrdef>
<attrdefs>NPS - SODN</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Full type name.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>PDF_Path</attrlabl>
<attrdef>File name of pdf</attrdef>
<attrdefs>SODN</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Entered as attachment path name.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SHAPE_Length</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Length of feature in internal units.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SHAPE_Area</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Area of feature in internal units squared.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Poly_Symbol</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Poly Symbol Name</attrdef>
<attrdefs>NPS</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Textual poly symbol name.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Override</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Unknown field created by originator but not documented.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>NPS</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Blob.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
</detailed>
<detailed>
<enttyp>
<enttypl>fcl_VegPoly_Photopoints</enttypl>
<enttypd>Feature Class</enttypd>
<enttypds>National Park Service</enttypds>
</enttyp>
<attr>
<attrlabl>OBJECTID</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SHAPE</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Poly_ID</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Unique number polygon ID showing which polygon photos were taken in. ID is followed by photo point number (pp2) where applicable.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ALphanumeric identifier</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>polygon idenifier</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Unit_Code</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Four letter park unit code</attrdef>
<attrdefs>NPS</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>FOur letter codes for each park management unit.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
</detailed>
<detailed>
<enttyp>
<enttypl>rc_VegPolys_VegMapInfo</enttypl>
<enttypd>Relationship</enttypd>
<enttypds>National Park Service</enttypds>
</enttyp>
</detailed>
<detailed>
<enttyp>
<enttypl>rc_VegPolys_tVegAssociation</enttypl>
<enttypd>Relationship</enttypd>
<enttypds>National Park Service</enttypds>
</enttyp>
</detailed>
<overview>
<eaover>
The National Vegetation Classification Standard is organized hierarchically to support conservation and resource stewardship applications across multiple scales. The upper levels of the hierarchy are based on the physical form or structure of the vegetation (physiognomy) and have been refined from the international standards developed by the United Nations Educational, Scientific, and Cultural Organization (UNESCO). The two most detailed levels of the hierarchy are based on the species composition of existing vegetation (floristics) and reflect the phyto-sociological standards that were originally developed by European ecologists. The vegetation classification is continually advanced through the collection and analysis of new field data and will be greatly strengthened during the course of the USGS/NPS mapping efforts. Data file attributes include vegetation height, density, species, alliance, community element, and land cover.
OBJECTID - ObjectID - Sequential unique whole numbers automatically generated.
SHAPE - Geometry - Feature geometry, ESRI autogenerated.
Poly_ID- Text - Unique polygon identifier created for relationship purposes.
Poly_Code - Text - Map class unique identifier
Unit_Code - Text - 4 letter NPS code for each management unit
Map_Code - Text - NVC codes for each map unit
Formation - Text - Structural type of vegetation
Veg_Type - Text - Full scientific name of each vegetation alliance or association
PDF_Path - Text - File name of pdf
SHAPE_Length - Double - Length of feature in internal units.
SHAPE_Area - Double - Area of feature in internal units squared.
</eaover>
<eadetcit>Unknown.</eadetcit>
</overview>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS/CSS/Core Science Analytics and Synthesis</cntorg>
<cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Characterization Program Coordinator</cntper>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, MS 302</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>303-202-4219</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
<distliab>
The U.S. Geological Survey and the National Park Service shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.  These data and related graphics (if available) are not legal documents and are not intended to be used as such.

The information contained in these data is dynamic and may change over time.  The data are not better than the original sources from which they were derived.  It is the responsibility of the data user to use the data appropriately and consistent within the limitations of geospatial data in general and these data in particular.  Any related graphics (if available) are intended to aid the data user in acquiring relevant data; it is not approriate to use the related graphics as data.

The U.S. Geological Survey and the National Park Service gives no warranty, expressed or implied, as to the accuracy, reliability, or completeness of these data.  It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from an U.S. Geological Survey and National Park Service servers and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way.  Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the utility of the data on another system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data. Mention of trade names or commercial products in this metadata report does not constitute endorsement or recommendation for use by the U. S. Department of the Interior, U. S. Geological Survey and National Park Service.
</distliab>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<formname>HTML</formname>
</digtinfo>
<digtopt>
<onlinopt>
<computer>
<networka>
<networkr>http://www.usgs.gov/core_science_systems/csas/vip/parks/tuma.html</networkr>
</networka>
</computer>
<accinstr>Internet Access</accinstr>
</onlinopt>
</digtopt>
</digform>
<fees>None</fees>
</stdorder>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20130117</metd>
<metrd>20130128</metrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>USGS/CSS/Core Science Analytics and Synthesis</cntorg>
<cntper>USGS-NPS Vegetation Characterization Program Coordinator</cntper>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, MS 302</address>
<city>Denver</city>
<state>Colorado</state>
<postal>80225</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(303) 202-4220</cntvoice>
<cntfax>303-202-4219</cntfax>
<cntemail>gs-b-npsveg@usgs.gov</cntemail>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
<metextns>
<onlink>http://www.usgs.gov/core_science_systems/csas/metadata/index.html</onlink>
</metextns>
</metainfo>
</metadata>