<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="esa.1.4" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 eml.xsd"> <dataset scope="document"> <alternateIdentifier system="ESA">E081-011-D1</alternateIdentifier>
 <title>Osnabr&#252;ck net primary productivity data set</title>
 <creator scope="document"> <organizationName>ESA</organizationName>
 </creator>
 <creator scope="document"> <organizationName>Ecological Society of America</organizationName>
 </creator>
 <creator scope="document"> <individualName> <givenName>Gerd</givenName>
 <surName>Esser</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Institute for Plant Ecology,  Justus-Liebig University</organizationName>
 <address scope="document"> <deliveryPoint>Justus-Liebig University,
Heinrich-Buff Ring 38
D-35392</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Giessen</city>
 <administrativeArea>Select state or territory here.</administrativeArea>
 <country>Germany</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">49 (641) 99 35310</phone>
 <phone phonetype="Fax">49 (641) 99 35309</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>gerd.esser@bot2.bio.uni-giessen.de</electronicMailAddress>
 </creator>
 <metadataProvider scope="document"> <individualName> <givenName>Callie</givenName>
 <surName>Bowdish</surName>
 </individualName>
 </metadataProvider>
 <associatedParty scope="document"> <individualName> <givenName>H. F. H.</givenName>
 <surName>Lieth</surName>
 </individualName>
 <role>Co-owner</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty scope="document"> <individualName> <givenName>Jonathan M. O.</givenName>
 <surName>Scurlock</surName>
 </individualName>
 <role>Co-owner</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty scope="document"> <individualName> <givenName>R. J.</givenName>
 <surName>Olson</surName>
 </individualName>
 <role>Co-owner</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <pubDate>2006-03-28</pubDate>
 <abstract> <para>An extensive compilation of nearly 700 field estimates of net primary productivity of natural and agricultural ecosystems worldwide was synthesized in Ger
many in the 1970s and early 1980s. The literature cited dates from 1869 to 1982, with the majority of references from the 1960s and 1970s. Although the Osnabr&#252;ck data
set has not been updated since the 1980s, it represents a wealth of information for use in model development and validation. This data paper documents the development of th
is data set, its contents, and its recent availability on the Internet, both in Ecological Archives on the Ecological Society of America's web site, and in a "mirror" copy
at the Oak Ridge National Laboratory Distributed Active Archive Center for Biogeochemical Dynamics. The version presented here (version 2.0) incorporates amendments suggest
ed by data users over the past two years. Caution is advised in using these data, which necessarily include assumptions that may not be universally applicable to all study
sites and records. Nevertheless, we consider these "Class III" data to be useful, even though they may not meet the "Gold Standards" which are being developed for this type
 of data (mainly because the documentation may be incomplete, not because the numbers themselves are of poor quality).</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>net primary productivity</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>agricultural ecosystems</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>Crop/Plant Yields</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>Soil Productivity</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <additionalInfo> <para>In addition to the data files described here, version 1.0 of the NPP estimates is also available from the ORNL DAAC as a single spreadsheet file (od
s_xls.bin, Excel 4.0; ods_wk1.bin, Lotus 1-2-3 Version 2.0), or as two separate but complementary ASCII files (ods_npp1.txt and ods_npp2.txt), which may be linked by the NP
P_ID identification number in the two files.

The bibliography of 855 original-source references (856 in version 2.0) is also available from the ORNL DAAC in a number of file formats (odsr_doc.bin, Word 7.0; odsr_wp5.b
in, WordPerfect 5.1) as well as ASCII text. A downloadable binary file (odsTMdoc.bin, Word 7.0) is available (excluding the data and bibliography), or the complete document
 (Esser et al., 1997) may be ordered from the User Services Office at the ORNL DAAC.</para>
 </additionalInfo>
 <intellectualRights> <para>no restrictions</para>
 </intellectualRights>
 <distribution scope="document"> <online> <url function="download">http://www.esapubs.org/archive/ecol/E081/011/</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 <distribution scope="document"> <offline> <mediumName>digital</mediumName>
 </offline>
 </distribution>
 <coverage scope="document"> <temporalCoverage scope="document"> <rangeOfDates> <beginDate> <calendarDate>1869</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate> <calendarDate>1982</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
  </coverage>
 <contact scope="document"> <individualName> <givenName>Gerd</givenName>
 <surName>Esser</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Institute for Plant Ecology</organizationName>
 <address scope="document"> <deliveryPoint>Justus-Liebig University
Heinrich-Buff Ring 38
D-35392</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Giessen</city>
 <administrativeArea>Select state or territory here.</administrativeArea>
 <country>Germany</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">49 (641) 99 35310</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>gerd.esser@bot2.bio.uni-giessen.de</electronicMailAddress>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><title>Data acquisition</title>
 <para>Several different versions of the Osnabr&#252;ck data set were exchanged between Esser, Scurlock and Olson between 1988 and 1995. Starting with an October 1995 version and eliminating duplicates, these have been condensed into a list of 683 unique records by Scurlock and Olson. Most of these records (about 90%) were matched to a list of references from the primary literature. However, this bibliography contains more references than records, including multiple sources for the same author and study, as well as additional references to data on standing biomass, soils, and so forth. Since this is a useful resource in its own right, an edited and corrected compilation of these 856 references is provided here as an accompanying file.</para>
 <para>Where the geographical coordinates of the experimental site were not included in the original paper, Lieth, Esser and co-workers selected the coordinates from maps or based them on site descriptions. Operational navigation charts (Defense Mapping Agency Aerospace Center, St. Louis Air Force Base, Missouri 63118, USA) and other regional</para>
 <para>and local maps were used for this purpose.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <sampling><studyExtent><description><para>The NPP study sites represent primarily natural ecosystems; however, unusual sites, such as very young or very old forest stands, crops, fertilized pastures, and plantations are also included (and have been flagged where possible). The data set includes NPP data based on measurements collected over the past 100 years by investigators using a variety of methods and algorithms to estimate NPP. The scientific literature considered for inclusion in the data set was selected through a review of collections such as Biological Abstracts, Chemical Abstracts, Agricola, and Current Contents, as well as of a number of textbooks and monographs. Lieth, Esser and co-workers extracted data predominantly from primary publications, that is, those papers that described the original work. The minimum requirements for data to be considered were the following: * at least a vague geographical reference to the site of measurement (data related to vegetation types only were not considered) and  * the use of one of the commonly accepted methods of assessing terrestrial NPP (Whittaker and Marks, 1975).</para>
 </description>
 </studyExtent>
 <samplingDescription><para>QA/QC procedures

The quality assessment process performed recently on these data by Scurlock and Olson consisted of selecting those records for which consistent information was available on
 (1) NPP, (2) latitude/longitude (corresponding to known land masses), (3) biome or vegetation type, and, as far as possible, (4) at least one literature reference. The criteria for consistency included the use of common systems of names, units, and so on. Names of countries and other data categories were translated from a mixture of English
and German to English only. By sorting and re-sorting the records in order of each variable, it was possible to check for out-of-range values and to cross-check many suspect records against the original primary literature (or at least against the titles of the primary literature references). In certain cases where the primary literature was readily available (e.g., Ecology, Journal of Ecology, Oecologia, etc.), data, vegetation type, and geographical coordinates were checked more thoroughly (see also below). Further duplicates or near-duplicates were eliminated at this stage. Sites were re-mapped using Geographical Information System software, and suspect sites that were located in oceans or other unlikely areas were identified. Suspect data were checked against original records and corrected in the data set where necessary.

The bibliography of original-source references in the Appendix is provided as a separate file. The references can be linked to the site records by the Author combined with the Year; we have found that only the first four characters of Author are generally needed (the data file usually contains the name of the first author, whereas the file of source references contains the full list of authors). The list of 856 references has been edited by Scurlock and Olson for consistency of citation style, since it was originally compiled by a number of individuals using different forms of abbreviations. Journal and book titles were checked against citation indexes and major libraries and are given in full where available. Duplicates, errors, and spelling and typographical mistakes have been eliminated as far as possible, as have obvious mismatches between journal volume numbers and years. A number of missing references described in the original data set have been restored. Literature that is not directly cross-referenced to NPP records is marked with an asterisk (*).

disclaimer: Some of the sites in the data set are agricultural sites, and others may represent natural systems with management treatments such as fertilizer, irrigation, grazing, burning, or thinning. Caution is advised in using these data, which necessarily include assumptions that may not be universally applicable to all sites.</para>
 </samplingDescription>
 </sampling>
 </methods>
 <access authSystem="knb" order="denyFirst" scope="document"> <allow> <principal>uid=esaadmin,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>all</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow> <principal>cn=knb-prod,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>all</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow> <principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>