<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="esa.35.3" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 eml.xsd"> <dataset scope="document"> <alternateIdentifier system="ESA">Ecological Archives E087-132-D1</alternateIdentifier>
  <title>Tree growth, mortality, physical condition, and microsite in an old-growth lowland tropical rain forest</title>
<creator scope="document"> <organizationName>ESA</organizationName>
 </creator>
 <creator scope="document"> <organizationName>Ecological Society of America</organizationName>
 </creator>
 <creator scope="document"> <individualName> <givenName>David B.</givenName>
 <surName>Clark</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Department of Biology,    University of Missouri-St. Louis, Missouri, USA and  La Selva Biological Station  Puerto Viejo de Sarapiqu&#237;, Costa Rica</organizationName>
 <address scope="document"> <administrativeArea>Missouri</administrativeArea>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <electronicMailAddress>dbclark@sloth.ots.ac.cr</electronicMailAddress>
 </creator>
 <metadataProvider scope="document"> <individualName> <givenName>Callie</givenName>
 <surName>Bowdish</surName>
 </individualName>
 </metadataProvider>
 <associatedParty scope="document"> <individualName> <givenName>Deborah A.</givenName>
 <surName>Clark</surName>
 </individualName>
 <role>Co-owner</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <pubDate>2006-12-14</pubDate>
<abstract><para>Tree species richness in tropical rain forest typically exceeds several hundred species over mesoscale landscapes. There is no generally accepted ecological theory that accounts for the coexistence of so many species with the same general morphologies and the same basic requirements of light, nutrients, water,  and physical space. In part, this lack of theory rests on the lack of understanding of the post-establishment ecology for the vast majority of tropical tree species. Of even more immediate concern is the lack of data on tree performance in relation to climate; such data are critical to project effects of global climate change on tropical forests.

Here we present data from a project designed to examine the post-establishment ecology of 10 species of tropical wet forest trees selected to span a range of predicted life history patterns. The study site was terra firme old-growth tropical wet forest at the La Selva Biological Station in Costa Rica. Particular emphasis has been placed on evaluating the precision of measurements, metadata development, and annual measurements of all individuals. Because the climates of all forest environments show significant interannual variation, the annual time interval is a powerful scale at which to study the relation of tree performance to climate variation. It is also a temporal interval that captures the scale of microhabitat variations and the responses of trees to this variation in tropical rain forest.</para>
</abstract>
  <keywordSet> <keyword keywordType="theme">tropical trees</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword keywordType="place">Costa Rica</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>emergents</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword keywordType="place">La Selva</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>life history strategies</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>physical damage</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>tree demography</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>tropical rain forest</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <additionalInfo> <para>LS_trees_1983_2000.txt
file is 3381 records, not including header row, Ascii text, tab delimited. No compression schemes were used.</para>
 </additionalInfo>
 <intellectualRights> <para>no restrictions</para>
 </intellectualRights>
 <distribution scope="document"> <online> <url function="download">http://www.esapubs.org/archive/ecol/E087/132/default.htm</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 <distribution scope="document"> <offline> <mediumName>digital</mediumName>
 </offline>
 </distribution>
 <coverage scope="document"> <temporalCoverage scope="document"> <rangeOfDates> <beginDate> <calendarDate>1983</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate> <calendarDate>2000</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 <geographicCoverage scope="document"> <geographicDescription>La Selva, situated at the confluence of two major rivers in the Caribbean lowlands of northern Costa Rica (10&#176; 26' N, 83&#176; 59' W), comprises 1,600 hectares (3,900 acres) of tropical wet forests and disturbed lands. The study was carried out in terra firme old-growth tropical wet forest at the La Selva Biological Station, Costa Rica. A detailed site description is given in McDade et al. 1994. Site and area maps, many GIS coverages, meterological data and lists of publications are available on the La Selva web site (http://www.ots.duke.edu/en/laselva/).</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates> <westBoundingCoordinate>-83.9833</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>-83.9833</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>10.4333</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>10.4333</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <taxonomicCoverage scope="document"> <generalTaxonomicCoverage>Species studied since 1983 (family) [representative voucher specimen]:

Minquartia guianensis Aubl. (Olacaceae) [G.Herrera 2250],

Lecythis ampla Miers (Lecythidaceae) [R.Robles 2208],

Hymenolobium mesoamericanum H.C. Lima (Papilionoideae) [R.Aguilar 19],

Dipteryx panamensis (Pittier) Record &amp; Mell (Papilionoideae) [R.Robles 1199],

Balizia elegans elegans (Ducke) Barneby &amp; J. W. Grimes (Mimosoideae)

[B.Hammel 17319] (before 1999 = Pithecellobium elegans),

Hyeronima alchorneoides Allemao (Euphorbiaceae) [Chacon 751],

Species studied since 1988 (family) [representative voucher specimen]:

Cecropia insignis Liebm. (Cecropiaceae) [W. Burger 11135],

Cecropia obtusifolia Bertol. (Cecropiaceae) [R. Robles 1446],

Simarouba amara Aubl. (Simaroubaceae) [R. Robles 1670],

Species studied since 1998 (family) [representative voucher specimen]:

Pentaclethra macroloba (Willd.) Kuntze (Mimosoideae) [B. Hammel 8440]</generalTaxonomicCoverage>
 <taxonomicClassification> <taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Minquartia guianensis</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification> <taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Lecythis ampla</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification> <taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Hymenolobium mesoamericanum</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification> <taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Dipteryx panamensis</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification> <taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Balizia elegans elegans</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification> <taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Pithecellobium elegans</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification> <taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Hyeronima alchorneoides</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification> <taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Cecropia insignis</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification> <taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Cecropia obtusifolia</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification> <taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Simarouba amara</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification> <taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Pentaclethra macroloba</taxonRankValue>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact scope="document"> <individualName> <givenName>David B.</givenName>
 <surName>Clark</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Department of Biology,    University of Missouri-St. Louis, Missouri, USA and  La Selva Biological Station  Puerto Viejo de Sarapiqu&#237;, Costa Rica</organizationName>
 <address scope="document"> <administrativeArea>Missouri</administrativeArea>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <electronicMailAddress>dbclark@sloth.ots.ac.cr</electronicMailAddress>
 </contact>
 <methods> <methodStep> <description> <section> <title>Experimental or sampling design</title>
 <para>In 1982 we selected six non-pioneer species of canopy and emergent trees (see list below) as focal species for this study. We chose them to represent a broad gradient of shade tolerance based on existing knowledge or hypotheses. All six species were also commercial timber species. In 1988 we added three species that were reported to be pioneers or high-light-demanding at other sites (two Cecropia species and Simarouba amara). In 1998 we added the most common canopy species at La Selva, Pentaclethra macroloba.</para>
 <para>The list of study species is given below. Referenced voucher specimens are in the Herbario Nacional de Costa Rica, San Jos&#233;, Costa Rica (except for the voucher for Hyeronima, which is at the Instituto Nacional de Biodiversidad de Costa Rica, Santo Domingo de Heredia, Costa Rica, and for Pentaclethra, which is in the Duke Herbarium, Duke University, Durham, North Carolina, USA).</para>
 <para>We present data on survivorship, growth, and microhabitat for 3381 individuals from greater than or equal to 50 cm tall to canopy-level individuals measured annually between 1983 and 2000 (the study is ongoing and complete through 2005), thus adding seven years' data and the dominant canopy species at La Selva to the data set we published in 2000. The data set is unique in its scope (number of years of continuous annual measurements, number of monitored individuals) as well as in the degree of metadata documentation and unrestricted access to the raw data. The data have been used to study life history patterns, relations with microhabitats including edaphic factors and crown light environments, relations among ecophysiology, morphology, and performance, and the relation of tree performance to climate variation both at local and global scales. The data have also been used in a diversity of remote sensing studies.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <sampling> <studyExtent> <description> <para>From time to time we have extended our study area (e.g., by crossing a creek). In newly included areas of forest we followed the same procedure for adding new species/size combinations (i.e. nothing on the current "add" list is ever rejected, unless it is across some new natural boundary where we choose not to extend the study area). All individuals in our study sample have been marked and mapped with respect to trail locations and to each other (copies of these maps are stored at La Selva and off-site, under the Clarks' control). Each individual is censused annually for growth, survival, physical condition and microsite, until they are determined in at least two consecutive censuses to be dead, or the stem is substantially decomposed at the first census where death is observed. In order to maintain very close to 1 yr intervals between censuses of each tree, we have maintained the same spatiotemporal order of working through the study area (for 1993/4, inter-census intervals were 365   plus or minus 16 d for 94% of the 2011 trees; Clark and Clark 1999).</para>
 </description>
 </studyExtent>
 <samplingDescription> <para>Our sampling protocol was designed to accumulate an unbiased sample of all post-establishment size classes for each study species using objective and consistent criteria. To do this we selected the original sample of study individuals in 1982-83 by walking transects on compass bearings from trails to natural boundaries such as creeks, attempting to completely cover specific areas of old growth; transects were spaced approximately 20 m apart. In this sampling we included included without exception all live individuals greater than or equal to 50 cm tall of our original six study species that were encountered, regardless of condition or microsite. In addition, for Lecythis ampla, Hyeronima alchorneiodes, and Hymenolobium mesoamericanum, in every census we included all encountered individuals less than 50 cm tall (new seedlings in the main). In each subsequent year, prior to each annual census, we evaluated the dataset and decided for which species-size classes increased sample sizes were needed (we sought to maintain a minimum of greater than 20 live individuals/species-size class based on the size classes analyzed in Clark and Clark 1992). For those species-size classes, we then added to the study sample all untagged individuals encountered during the course of the annual census following the same all-inclusive criteria: no individual of the target species/size-classes that was sighted within our study area was ever rejected. Note that this sample is not a complete sample for the area searched, at least for the small size classes. We were interested in assessing the long-term ecology of all post-establishment size classes of focal species, and to get useful sample sizes for these species involved searching greater than 200 ha. Complete samples are only possible by examining every stem above a minimum size limit, which would have been logistically impractical in an area this size and with the size classes used here. The sample in this study is rather a sample assembled using unbiased search and inclusion protocols based on the same basic criteria for the entire study period.</para>
 </samplingDescription>
 </sampling>
 </methods>
 <access authSystem="knb" order="denyFirst" scope="document">
<allow>
<principal>uid=esaadmin,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
<permission>all</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
<principal>cn=knb-prod,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
<permission>all</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
<principal>public</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
</allow>
</access>
</dataset>
</ns0:eml>