<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="esa.7.8" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 eml.xsd"> <dataset scope="document"> <alternateIdentifier system="ESA">E081-004</alternateIdentifier>
 <title>National land-cover pattern data</title>
 <creator scope="document"> <organizationName>ESA</organizationName>
 </creator>
 <creator scope="document"> <organizationName>Ecological Society of America</organizationName>
 </creator>
 <creator scope="document"> <individualName> <givenName>Kurt H.</givenName>
 <surName>Riitters</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>US Geological Survey,  Biological Resources Division</organizationName>
 <address scope="document"> <deliveryPoint>Campus Box 8002
North Carolina State University</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Raleigh</city>
 <administrativeArea>North Carolina</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>27695</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <electronicMailAddress>kurt@usgs.gov</electronicMailAddress>
 </creator>
 <metadataProvider scope="document"> <individualName> <givenName>Callie</givenName>
 <surName>Bowdish</surName>
 </individualName>
 </metadataProvider>
 <associatedParty scope="document"> <individualName> <givenName>James D.</givenName>
 <surName>Wickham</surName>
 </individualName>
 <role>Co-owner</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty scope="document"> <individualName> <givenName>James E.</givenName>
 <surName>Vogelmann</surName>
 </individualName>
 <role>Co-owner</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty scope="document"> <individualName> <givenName>K. Bruce</givenName>
 <surName>Jones</surName>
 </individualName>
 <role>Co-owner</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <pubDate>2006-03-29</pubDate>
 <abstract> <para>Land cover and its spatial patterns are key ingredients in ecological studies that consider large regions and the impacts of human activities. Because land-cover maps show only cover types and their locations, further processing is needed to extract pattern information and to characterize its spatial variability. We are producing a nationally consistent spatial database of six land-cover pattern indices: forest area density, forest connectivity, the U index (a measure of general land-use pressure by humans), land-cover connectivity, land-cover diversity, and landscape pattern types. We use the land-cover maps produced by the Multi-resolution Land Characteristics Consortium for the conterminous United States at 30-m resolution. The goal of this paper is to encourage use of the pattern data as: contextual information and independent variables for studies involving a set of field sites; indicators of landscape conditions for ecological assessments; and dependent variables in biogeographic and socioeconomic models. The new maps will be most useful in studies that require consistent and comparable land-cover pattern measurements over large regions and can be combined with the original land-cover maps and other data.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>Forests</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>Agricultural Lands</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>Grasslands</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>Wetlands</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>Vegetation Cover</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>Habitat Conversion/Fragmentation</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>Land-cover connectivity</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>Land-cover diversity</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>Forest connectivity</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>land-cover maps</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>Urbanization</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <additionalInfo> <para>National Land Cover Pattern Database, This location has a partial list of the coverage maps.  This data was created as part of a national analysis of land cover pattern. A series of derived maps (different indices, different window sizes) is available. They are proposed for consideration by landscape analysts, as independent variables (e.g., covariates, stratification rules), and as "context" information for finer-scale investigations, for example field plots.</para>
 </additionalInfo>
 <intellectualRights> <para>other</para>
 <para>Partial list available online</para>
 </intellectualRights>
 <distribution scope="document"> <online> <url function="download">http://www.esapubs.org/archive/ecol/E081/004/default.htm</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 <distribution scope="document"> <online> <url function="download">http://www.lsc.usgs.gov/gis/nlpd/asp/index.htm</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 <distribution scope="document"> <offline> <mediumName>digital</mediumName>
 </offline>
 </distribution>
 <coverage scope="document"> <temporalCoverage scope="document"> <singleDateTime> <calendarDate>2000</calendarDate>
 </singleDateTime>
 </temporalCoverage>
 <geographicCoverage scope="document"> <geographicDescription>Conterminous United States</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates> <westBoundingCoordinate>-124.7333</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>-66.625</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>49.875</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>24.947</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact scope="document"> <individualName> <givenName>Kurt H.</givenName>
 <surName>Riitters</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>US Geological Survey,  Biological Resources Division</organizationName>
 <address scope="document"> <deliveryPoint>Campus Box 8002
North Carolina State University</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Raleigh</city>
 <administrativeArea>North Carolina</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>27695</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <electronicMailAddress>kurt@usgs.gov</electronicMailAddress>
 </contact>
 <methods> <methodStep> <description> <section> <title>Methods</title>
 <para>We use the land-cover maps from the Multi-Resolution Land Characteristics (MRLC) Consortium (Loveland and Shaw 1996). The MRLC Consortium is a federal initiative with a principal objective to collect and process Landsat Thematic Mapper (TM) data for the lower 48 states. As part of the MRLC Consortium activities, a land-cover data set is being developed for the conterminous United States at 30 m resolution. The primary source of data for this effort is 1991-1993 vintage TM data. Other sources of spatial data are being used, including elevation, population, soils, and available land-cover information derived by other programs (e.g., National Wetlands Inventory data, State land-cover data sets). In general, leaf-on and leaf-off TM mosaics are classified by using a combination of unsupervised and supervised classification methods, and the ancillary data are then used to resolve conflicts and to refine the classification (Vogelmann et al. 1998a,b). Twenty-three land-cover ! types approximating the Level II thematic detail of Anderson et al. (1976) are labeled (Table 1).</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <sampling> <studyExtent> <description> <para>Table 1. The MRLC land-cover types that are the basis for the land-cover pattern indices described in this paper. Types are grouped by major category such as "water" and "developed." Water; Open water, Perennial ice / snow, Developed  Low intensity residential, High intensity residential  High intensity commercial /industrial/transportation  Barren; Bare rock / sand / clay, Quarries / strip mines / gravel pits, Transitional  Natural forested upland; Deciduous forest, Evergreen forest, Mixed forest, Natural shrubland Deciduous shrubland, Mixed shrubland, Evergreen shrubland, Non-natural woody,  Planted / cultivated; Herbaceous upland natural / semi-natural, Grassland / herbaceous, Herbaceous planted / cultivated, Pasture / hay, Row crops, Small grains, Bare soil, Urban / recreational grasses, Wetlands; Woody, Emergent herbaceous</para>
 </description>
 </studyExtent>
 <samplingDescription> <para>We apply a series of spatial filters to the land-cover maps, to derive new maps of pattern indicators. A convolution filter (e.g., Pratt 1978, Schowengerdt 1983, Gonzalez and Woods 1992) places a "window" (support region, or kernel) on each pixel of land cover, calculates the pattern index within the window, and puts the result on a new map at the same location. Thus, the value of a pixel in one of the new maps represents an index of land-cover pattern for the surrounding window in the original land-cover map. Six pattern indices are mapped: forest connectivity, forest area density, land-cover connectivity, land-cover diversity, the U-index (O'Neill et al. 1988), and landscape pattern types (Wickham and Norton 1994).</para>
 <para>The pattern indices are calculated from the frequencies of land-cover types, and from the tendencies of a given land-cover type to be spatially autocorrelated (i.e., to appear in clumps as opposed to isolated pixels). Consider a window placed somewhere on a land-cover map. Let t be the number of land-cover types, after any aggregation of land-cover types that is particular to a given pattern index. Let Pi (i = 1 to t) be the proportion of non-missing pixels in the window of the ith type. The Pi values are used in four of the six indices as follows.</para>
 <para>Forest area density, an index of forest amount, is the proportion of forest in the window, as determined from a map with all forest types aggregated into one. The index is continuous over [0,1], and is available for three window sizes (9 x 9 pixels, 27 x 27 pixels, and 81 x 81 pixels; roughly equivalent to 7, 66, and 590 ha). The U-index (after O'Neill et al. 1988) is the proportion of agriculture plus developed land-cover types in the window, and it measures general land use pressure by humans. This index is also continuous over [0,1], and is available for a window size of 66 ha.</para>
 <para>Landscape pattern types (LPT's; after Wickham and Norton 1994) provide geographic strata for identifying differences in landscape characteristics (e.g., forest patch size, amount of edge). They are motivated by the prevailing tendency for land cover to be spatially autocorrelated. The LPT's are evaluated within 590-ha windows, and 19 categorical values are identified based on the local proportions of aggregated forest, developed, and agriculture land-cover types. The proportions are compared to each other, and to the critical values of 0.1 and 0.6, to yield categories indicating general land use themes. Landscapes dominated by one land cover appear to be qualitatively different from landscapes with a more even distribution of land-cover types (Wickham and Norton 1994). As a practical matter, where Pi greater than 0.6 the i^th land-cover type appears as the "background" upon which other land-cover types are superimposed. Igno! ring relatively minor amounts (i.e., Pi less than 0.1) of the ith land-cover type helps to clarify regional patterns.</para>
 <para>Land-cover diversity is analogous to Simpson's (1949) index; land-cover type proportions here replace the species proportions in the original equation, 1 - &#931; i Pi2. The index is continuous over [0,1] for 66-ha windows and higher values are taken to indicate greater diversity. While no single diversity measure can be definitive (e.g., Hurlbert 1971), at least one must be selected if we are to make a measurement of land-cover diversity. Simpson's index is easy to visualize and its properties are understood by many ecologists (e.g., Magurran 1988). Compared to most other diversity indices, Simpson's index is relatively more sensitive to changes in abundant land-cover types and less sensitive to changes in rare types (and thus, to classification errors in the land-cover maps).</para>
 <para>The other two indices are texture measures derived from an attribute adjacency table (e.g., Musick and Grover 1991), in which Fij (i,j = 1 to t) is the frequency of adjacent pixel pairs with land-cover types {i,j}. When forming the attribute adjacency table, adjacency is evaluated in the four cardinal directions, each edge is counted once, the order of pixels in pairs is not preserved, and pairs involving a missing pixel are not included (Riitters et al. 1996b). Define Gi = &#931; j Fij and Wi = Fii / &#931; i,j Fij for the ith land-cover type.</para>
 <para>Forest connectivity was measured by the conditional probability that two adjacent pixels in a given window are forest, given that the first is forest. The index is calculated as Fii / Gi where i refers to all forest types aggregated into one. It is continuous over [0,1], and is derived for three window sizes (7, 66, 590 ha). The index is of interest because of concern regarding forest "fragmentation," which can be estimated as one minus the connectivity index.</para>
 <para>Land-cover connectivity (Wickham and Riitters 1995) was measured as &#931;i Wi, i.e., as the overall probability that adjacent pixels had the same land-cover type. The index is continuous over [0,1] and is available for a 66-ha window size. It is similar to contagion (O'Neill et al. 1988, Li and Reynolds 1993), which measures the overall tendency for land cover to appear in non-random pairings. Larger connectivity values indicate relatively less overall fragmentation in the window.</para>
 <para>For computer storage, the continuous indices (all except landscape pattern types) are converted to discrete values in the range [1,255], with zero reserved for missing values. All pixels labeled as water or missing in the land-cover map are labeled as missing in the derived maps. In addition, some other land-cover types are labeled as missing for some indices, and these locations will have missing values for those cases. For example, the "barren, transitional" land-cover type could represent either forest or agriculture when calculating the LPT index and was treated as a missing value.</para>
 <para>The maps are distributed in a generic binary format that is suitable for use with most image processing and geographic information systems. The map projection is Albers conical equal area, with the same geographic references as the land-cover maps. The documentation complies with the Federal Geospatial Data Committee (FGDC) standard and provides additional procedural information.</para>
 </samplingDescription>
 </sampling>
 </methods>
 <access authSystem="knb" order="denyFirst" scope="document"> <allow> <principal>uid=esaadmin,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>all</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow> <principal>cn=knb-prod,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>all</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow> <principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>