<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<response>
<lst name="responseHeader"><int name="status">0</int><int name="QTime">238</int><lst name="params"><str name="facet.range">dateUploaded</str><str name="q">*:* -obsoletedBy:* formatType:METADATA</str><str name="facet.limit">-1</str><str name="facet.range.gap">+1YEAR</str><str name="facet.missing">true</str><str name="fq">datasource:"urn:node:NKN"</str><str name="sort">dateUploaded asc</str><str name="rows">1</str><str name="facet">true</str><str name="wt">xml</str><str name="facet.range.start">2001-01-01T00:00:00Z</str><str name="facet.range.end">2017-12-31T23:59:59.999Z</str></lst></lst><result name="response" numFound="11" start="0"><doc><str name="id">3bbdbc1b-efa5-4198-af95-37342a5e6559</str><str name="identifier">3bbdbc1b-efa5-4198-af95-37342a5e6559</str><str name="formatId">eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0</str><str name="formatType">METADATA</str><long name="size">34189</long><str name="checksum">9f66ceb9af724f5952ed474bdc4d5452</str><str name="submitter">CN=urn:node:NKN,DC=dataone,DC=org</str><str name="checksumAlgorithm">MD5</str><str name="rightsHolder">CN=Edward Flathers,O=Google,C=US,DC=cilogon,DC=org</str><bool name="replicationAllowed">true</bool><int name="numberReplicas">3</int><date name="dateUploaded">2015-05-28T16:45:07.624Z</date><date name="updateDate">2015-05-28T16:45:07.624Z</date><date name="dateModified">2015-05-30T21:41:28.072Z</date><str name="datasource">urn:node:NKN</str><str name="authoritativeMN">urn:node:NKN</str><arr name="replicaMN"><str>urn:node:NKN</str><str>urn:node:CN</str><str>urn:node:TFRI</str><str>urn:node:mnUNM1</str><str>urn:node:mnORC1</str></arr><arr name="replicaVerifiedDate"><date>2015-05-28T16:57:01.396Z</date><date>2015-05-28T16:57:01.508Z</date><date>2015-05-30T21:34:20.151Z</date><date>2015-05-30T21:34:29.017Z</date><date>2015-05-30T21:34:30.685Z</date></arr><arr name="readPermission"><str>public</str></arr><bool name="isPublic">true</bool><str name="dataUrl">https://cn.dataone.org/cn/v2/resolve/3bbdbc1b-efa5-4198-af95-37342a5e6559</str><str name="abstract">The data presented here represent the benthic macroinvertebrate data collected in 1976 and 1977 along the Salmon River mainstem.  These data were part of the original river continuum concept (RCC) project.  Seven sites were sampled seasonally over the two year period.  Four sites on the upper Salmon River mainstem (i.e., Camp, Smiley, Obsidian, and Casino) were sampled in March and July of 1976.  Four sites on the mid to lower Salmon River were sampled in March/April, July, and September/October of 1977 (i.e., Casino, Deadman's hole, Shoup, and Slate).  However, only Shoup and Slate were processed during the July 1977 sampling trip.  Additional samples (i.e., transport and benthic organic matter) were sampled during other trips, but the data presented here are the only seasonal samples that were processed for invertebrates.  Samples were collected either via a 'dustpan-kicknet' (1976) or a dome sampler (1977).  Invertebrates were identified and counted.  As the methods differ between years, interannual differences can only be compared based on relative abundance.

These data are the basis for the following manuscripts.

Minshall, G. W., J. T. Brock, and T. W. Lapoint. 1982. Characterization and dynamics of benthic organic-matter and invertebrate functional feeding group relationships in the upper Salmon River, Idaho (USA). Internationale Revue der Gesamten Hydrobiologie 67:793-820.
Minshall, G. W., R. C. Petersen, T. L. Bott, C. E. Cushing, K. W. Cummins, R. L. Vannote, and J. R. Sedell. 1992. Stream ecosystem dynamics of the Salmon River, Idaho: An 8th order system. Journal of the North American Benthological Society 11:111-137.
Minshall, G. W., R. C. Petersen, K. W. Cummins, T. L. Bott, J. R. Sedell, C. E. Cushing, and R. L. Vannote. 1983. Interbiome comparison of stream ecosystem dynamics. Ecological Monographs 53:1-25.</str><arr name="keywords"><str>Salmon River, river continuum concept, RCC, macroinvertebrate, insect, invertebrate, benthic, functional feeding group, abundance, aquatic</str></arr><str name="title">Salmon River RCC Benthic Invertebrate Data</str><float name="southBoundCoord">43.88333</float><float name="northBoundCoord">45.641666</float><float name="westBoundCoord">-116.291664</float><float name="eastBoundCoord">-114.25361</float><arr name="site"><str>Salmon River mainstem</str></arr><date name="beginDate">1976-03-01T00:00:00Z</date><date name="endDate">1977-10-05T00:00:00Z</date><str name="author">Colden Baxter</str><str name="authorGivenName">Colden</str><str name="authorSurName">Baxter</str><str name="authorSurNameSort">Baxter</str><arr name="authorLastName"><str>Baxter</str></arr><arr name="investigator"><str>Baxter</str></arr><arr name="origin"><str>Colden Baxter</str></arr><arr name="contactOrganization"><str>Stream Ecology Center, Idaho State University</str></arr><arr name="attributeName"><str>Station</str><str>Lat Dec</str><str>Long Dec</str><str>Nearby feature</str><str>Site</str><str>Year</str><str>Month</str><str>Day</str><str>Date</str><str>Sample ID</str><str>Sample Type</str><str>Sampler type</str><str>Habitat</str><str>Order</str><str>Family</str><str>Genus</str><str>Species</str><str>Stage</str><str># in Size Fraction  ≥1mm or  ≥500um (# per sample)</str><str># in Size Fraction &lt;1mm and ≥100µm (# per sample)</str><str>Area sampled (cm^2)</str><str>Habitat Notes</str><str>ID notes</str><str>Sample Date</str><str>Sample processing notes</str></arr><arr name="attributeLabel"><str>Study Site Location Names</str><str>Latitude of Study Site</str><str>Longitude of the study site</str><str>Geographic reference point for each study site.</str><str>Name of the study site</str><str>This is the year that the sample was collected.</str><str>This is the month that a sample was collected.</str><str>This is the day of the month that a sample was collected.</str><str>This is the date that a sample was collected.</str><str>This is the unique identifier for each sample.</str><str>This the sample type of the specific sample</str><str>This is the type of sample instrument used</str><str>Habitat type where the sample was taken.</str><str>Taxonomic order</str><str>Taxonomic family</str><str>Taxonomic genus</str><str>Taxomic species designation</str><str>Development stage</str><str>Abundance of individuals in the large size fraction</str><str># in the smaller size fraction</str><str>The sample area</str><str>Notes on the substrate and habitat of a particular sample</str><str>Notes about the old taxonomic name for a particular organism</str><str>The date a sample was taken</str><str>Study site name</str><str>Notes on how and which samples were size fractionated</str></arr><arr name="attributeDescription"><str>These are the actual study site locations.</str><str>These are the latitude measurements for the study site.</str><str>Longitude of the study site</str><str>This provides a nearby reference point for each study reach.</str><str>This is the name of the study site.</str><str>This is the specific year that a sample was collected.</str><str>This is the particular month that a sample was collected.</str><str>This is the day of the month that a particular sample was collected.</str><str>This is the specific date that a sample was collected.</str><str>These are the sample identifications that were recorded off of the lab datasheets. Note that some sites and year do not exhibit consecutive sampling numbers.  When a detrital depletion sample was taken, the first number in the column is the dome sample number.  The second number is the detrital sample number. The samples with the 'a' designation are the samples used for invertebrate calculations.  The samples with the 'b' or 'c' designation are the detrital depletion samples that were not used in the invertebrate calculations.</str><str>Two types of samples were identified.  Invert samples are the ones that were used for the invertebrate assemblage calculations.  The detrital depletion are replicate samples at the dome sampling sites, which were not used in the invertebrate calculations.</str><str>This is the type of instrument used to collect the sample.  In 1976, a modified kicknet was used.  In 1977, a dome sampler was used.</str><str>This is the habitat type where a specific sample was taken.</str><str>This is the taxonomic order that a particular individual belonged to</str><str>This is the taxonomic family that an individual was classified as</str><str>This is the genus that an individual was classified as</str><str>This is the species name of the particular organism</str><str>This is the development stage that an individual was classified as.
adult, nymph, larvae, or pupae</str><str>This is the number of individuals per sample.  In 1976, this was defined as individuals  ≥ 1mm.  In 1977, this was defined as individuals  ≥ 500micrometers.</str><str>This is the total number of individuals of a particular taxonomic group that was found in the smaller size fraction of that sample.  In 1977, this was defined as &lt;500micrometer and ≥100micrometer.  This size fraction was not collected during 1976.</str><str>This is the area of the benthos that was sampled for a given sample.</str><str>This reports the dominant substrate or habitat that was present at a given sampling location.  Also, this indicates which invert sample that a detrital depletion sample was coupled with.</str><str>Between the 1970s and the present, taxonomic names have changed.  The name reported here is the name originally reported in the RCC publications, which has been updated in the genus column.</str><str>This is the date that sample was collected</str><str>This is the RCC study site</str><str>This describes the sampling method used.  It also indicates which samples were size fractionated and picked.</str></arr><arr name="attributeUnit"><str>degree</str><str>number per sample</str><str>squareCentimeters</str></arr><arr name="attribute"><str>Station Study Site Location Names These are the actual study site locations.</str><str>Lat Dec Latitude of Study Site These are the latitude measurements for the study site. degree</str><str>Long Dec Longitude of the study site Longitude of the study site degree</str><str>Nearby feature Geographic reference point for each study site. This provides a nearby reference point for each study reach.</str><str>Site Name of the study site This is the name of the study site.</str><str>Year This is the year that the sample was collected. This is the specific year that a sample was collected.</str><str>Month This is the month that a sample was collected. This is the particular month that a sample was collected.</str><str>Day This is the day of the month that a sample was collected. This is the day of the month that a particular sample was collected.</str><str>Date This is the date that a sample was collected. This is the specific date that a sample was collected.</str><str>Sample ID This is the unique identifier for each sample. These are the sample identifications that were recorded off of the lab datasheets. Note that some sites and year do not exhibit consecutive sampling numbers.  When a detrital depletion sample was taken, the first number in the column is the dome sample number.  The second number is the detrital sample number. The samples with the 'a' designation are the samples used for invertebrate calculations.  The samples with the 'b' or 'c' designation are the detrital depletion samples that were not used in the invertebrate calculations.</str><str>Sample Type This the sample type of the specific sample Two types of samples were identified.  Invert samples are the ones that were used for the invertebrate assemblage calculations.  The detrital depletion are replicate samples at the dome sampling sites, which were not used in the invertebrate calculations.</str><str>Sampler type This is the type of sample instrument used This is the type of instrument used to collect the sample.  In 1976, a modified kicknet was used.  In 1977, a dome sampler was used.</str><str>Habitat Habitat type where the sample was taken. This is the habitat type where a specific sample was taken.</str><str>Order Taxonomic order This is the taxonomic order that a particular individual belonged to</str><str>Family Taxonomic family This is the taxonomic family that an individual was classified as</str><str>Genus Taxonomic genus This is the genus that an individual was classified as</str><str>Species Taxomic species designation This is the species name of the particular organism</str><str>Stage Development stage This is the development stage that an individual was classified as.
adult, nymph, larvae, or pupae</str><str># in Size Fraction  ≥1mm or  ≥500um (# per sample) Abundance of individuals in the large size fraction This is the number of individuals per sample.  In 1976, this was defined as individuals  ≥ 1mm.  In 1977, this was defined as individuals  ≥ 500micrometers. number per sample</str><str># in Size Fraction &lt;1mm and ≥100µm (# per sample) # in the smaller size fraction This is the total number of individuals of a particular taxonomic group that was found in the smaller size fraction of that sample.  In 1977, this was defined as &lt;500micrometer and ≥100micrometer.  This size fraction was not collected during 1976. number per sample</str><str>Area sampled (cm^2) The sample area This is the area of the benthos that was sampled for a given sample. squareCentimeters</str><str>Habitat Notes Notes on the substrate and habitat of a particular sample This reports the dominant substrate or habitat that was present at a given sampling location.  Also, this indicates which invert sample that a detrital depletion sample was coupled with.</str><str>ID notes Notes about the old taxonomic name for a particular organism Between the 1970s and the present, taxonomic names have changed.  The name reported here is the name originally reported in the RCC publications, which has been updated in the genus column.</str><str>Sample Date The date a sample was taken This is the date that sample was collected</str><str>Site Study site name This is the RCC study site</str><str>Sample processing notes Notes on how and which samples were size fractionated This describes the sampling method used.  It also indicates which samples were size fractionated and picked.</str></arr><str name="fileID">https://cn.dataone.org/cn/v2/resolve/3bbdbc1b-efa5-4198-af95-37342a5e6559</str><arr name="geohash_1"><str>9</str></arr><arr name="geohash_2"><str>9r</str></arr><arr name="geohash_3"><str>9ry</str></arr><arr name="geohash_4"><str>9ryn</str></arr><arr name="geohash_5"><str>9ryn8</str></arr><arr name="geohash_6"><str>9ryn8u</str></arr><arr name="geohash_7"><str>9ryn8uv</str></arr><arr name="geohash_8"><str>9ryn8uv0</str></arr><arr name="geohash_9"><str>9ryn8uv02</str></arr><bool name="isService">false</bool><arr name="documents"><str>3c4b03cf-9c84-4ff4-be99-01e892f43ec6</str><str>771defdb-baba-4300-a8fe-f68abf826a38</str><str>f1db466b-233a-4da6-8e6f-ef72a4861230</str><str>a7a2e5b6-1445-4374-8ed1-d9ee5b04907f</str><str>22e58d84-b03a-4f18-94ed-d1b45f14a834</str><str>05e23cd9-fbeb-4f53-bc98-882c6fe601ba</str><str>7acf8e2b-d935-44ad-afaf-7317bff6d799</str><str>46566cc1-2ad6-4841-b90d-aa4e563a775e</str><str>be75ae93-350e-49fc-8a9d-0b85ca0aba9c</str><str>2cb802db-9adf-41dc-855e-97192f6d27e7</str></arr><arr name="resourceMap"><str>e7ef8b9b-9d95-425c-b076-a03dddb3e129</str><str>0058dd2e-552d-4c89-80e6-b26003d5f428</str></arr><str name="serviceCoupling">false</str></doc></result><lst name="facet_counts"><lst name="facet_queries"/><lst name="facet_fields"/><lst name="facet_dates"/><lst name="facet_ranges"><lst name="dateUploaded"><lst name="counts"><int name="2001-01-01T00:00:00Z">0</int><int name="2002-01-01T00:00:00Z">0</int><int name="2003-01-01T00:00:00Z">0</int><int name="2004-01-01T00:00:00Z">0</int><int name="2005-01-01T00:00:00Z">0</int><int name="2006-01-01T00:00:00Z">0</int><int name="2007-01-01T00:00:00Z">0</int><int name="2008-01-01T00:00:00Z">0</int><int name="2009-01-01T00:00:00Z">0</int><int name="2010-01-01T00:00:00Z">0</int><int name="2011-01-01T00:00:00Z">0</int><int name="2012-01-01T00:00:00Z">0</int><int name="2013-01-01T00:00:00Z">0</int><int name="2014-01-01T00:00:00Z">0</int><int name="2015-01-01T00:00:00Z">1</int><int name="2016-01-01T00:00:00Z">10</int><int name="2017-01-01T00:00:00Z">0</int></lst><str name="gap">+1YEAR</str><date name="start">2001-01-01T00:00:00Z</date><date name="end">2018-01-01T00:00:00Z</date></lst></lst><lst name="facet_intervals"/><lst name="facet_heatmaps"/></lst>
</response>
