<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<response>
<lst name="responseHeader"><int name="status">0</int><int name="QTime">150</int><lst name="params"><str name="facet.range">dateUploaded</str><str name="q">*:* -obsoletedBy:* formatType:METADATA</str><str name="facet.limit">-1</str><str name="facet.range.gap">+1YEAR</str><str name="facet.missing">true</str><str name="fq">datasource:"urn:node:PISCO"</str><str name="sort">dateUploaded asc</str><str name="rows">1</str><str name="facet">true</str><str name="wt">xml</str><str name="facet.range.start">2001-01-01T00:00:00Z</str><str name="facet.range.end">2017-12-31T23:59:59.999Z</str></lst></lst><result name="response" numFound="19820" start="0"><doc><str name="id">doi:10.6085/AA/PTSXXX_015ADCP015R00_20030902.50.5</str><str name="identifier">doi:10.6085/AA/PTSXXX_015ADCP015R00_20030902.50.5</str><str name="formatId">eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1</str><str name="formatType">METADATA</str><long name="size">21859</long><str name="checksum">263ecf5dcffb2f3cf39569cdefa9b39b</str><str name="submitter">uid=cjones,o=PISCO,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</str><str name="checksumAlgorithm">MD5</str><str name="rightsHolder">uid=cjones,o=PISCO,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</str><bool name="replicationAllowed">true</bool><int name="numberReplicas">1</int><arr name="preferredReplicationMN"><str>urn:node:KNB</str></arr><str name="obsoletes">doi:10.6085/AA/PTSXXX_015ADCP015R00_20030902.50.4</str><date name="dateUploaded">2005-09-14T23:00:00Z</date><date name="updateDate">2005-09-14T23:00:00Z</date><date name="dateModified">2013-11-14T23:28:34.788Z</date><str name="datasource">urn:node:PISCO</str><str name="authoritativeMN">urn:node:PISCO</str><arr name="replicaMN"><str>urn:node:CN</str><str>urn:node:PISCO</str><str>urn:node:KNB</str></arr><arr name="replicaVerifiedDate"><date>2016-01-04T22:14:28.572Z</date><date>2016-03-11T23:23:12.728Z</date><date>2016-03-11T23:24:16.7Z</date></arr><arr name="readPermission"><str>public</str><str>cn=data-managers,o=PISCOGROUPS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</str></arr><arr name="writePermission"><str>cn=data-managers,o=PISCOGROUPS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</str></arr><arr name="changePermission"><str>cn=data-managers,o=PISCOGROUPS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</str></arr><bool name="isPublic">true</bool><str name="dataUrl">https://cn.dataone.org/cn/v2/resolve/doi%3A10.6085%2FAA%2FPTSXXX_015ADCP015R00_20030902.50.5</str><str name="abstract">This metadata record describes bottom-mounted ADCP data collected at Point Sal, California, USA, by PISCO. Measurements were collected using an RDI 600 kHz Workhorse Sentinel ADCP beginning 2003-09-02.  The instrument depth was 015 meters, in an overall water depth of 15 meters (both relative to Mean Sea Level, MSL).  The instrument was programmed with a sampling interval of 2.0 minutes and a vertical resolution of 1 meter.</str><arr name="keywords"><str>EARTH SCIENCE: Oceans: Ocean Circulation: Ocean Currents</str><str>EARTH SCIENCE: Oceans: Ocean Temperature: Water Temperature</str><str>EARTH SCIENCE: Oceans: Ocean Pressure: Pressure</str><str>Temperature</str><str>Integrated Ocean Observing System</str><str>IOOS</str><str>Oceanographic Sensor Data</str><str>Bottom-mounted ADCP Current Profile Data</str><str>continental shelf</str><str>currents</str><str>ADCP</str><str>PISCO</str><str>California</str><str>United States of America</str></arr><str name="title">PISCO: Physical Oceanography: bottom-mounted ADCP data: Point Sal, California, USA (PTS)</str><str name="project">Partnership for Interdisciplinary Studies of Coastal Oceans (PISCO)</str><float name="southBoundCoord">34.86919</float><float name="northBoundCoord">34.86919</float><float name="westBoundCoord">-120.63583</float><float name="eastBoundCoord">-120.63583</float><arr name="site"><str>Point Sal: PTS: The nearshore mooring is located approximately 5 km Southeast of Point Sal, California, USA.  The base of the mooring is in 15 meters of water below Mean Sea Level (MSL), and it extends up to 4 meters below MSL.  The altitudeMinimum and altitudeMaximum tags in this initial coverage section refer to the ADCP measurement range and are also referenced to MSL.  They do not represent the overall water depth.  Note the nominal range of the ADCP may extend from near-bottom (a depth expressed as a negative altitude) to slightly above MSL (a height expressed as a positive altitude).</str></arr><date name="beginDate">2003-09-02T00:00:00Z</date><date name="endDate">2003-11-06T00:00:00Z</date><str name="author">Libe Washburn</str><arr name="authorLastName"><str>Washburn</str></arr><arr name="investigator"><str>Washburn</str></arr><arr name="origin"><str>Partnership for Interdisciplinary Studies of Coastal Oceans (PISCO)</str><str>Libe Washburn</str></arr><arr name="contactOrganization"><str>Partnership for Interdisciplinary Studies of Coastal Oceans (PISCO)</str></arr><arr name="attributeName"><str>date</str><str>time</str><str>yearday</str><str>height</str><str>depth</str><str>waterdepth</str><str>temp_c</str><str>pressure</str><str>intensity</str><str>data_quality</str><str>eastward</str><str>northward</str><str>upwards</str><str>errorvelocity</str><str>flag</str></arr><arr name="attributeDescription"><str>Greenwich Mean Time calendar date of each ADCP measurement record, using ISO 8601 standard format YYYY-MM-DD</str><str>Greenwich Mean Time of each ADCP measurement record, to the 1/100th of a second, using ISO 8601 standard format hh:mm:ss.ssZ.  The 'Z' indicates 'Zero Meridian' (or Greenwich Mean Time) and must be included.</str><str>Greenwich Mean Time of each ADCP measurement record, expressed as fractional decimal days since Jan. 1 of the year measurement was made.  For example, 12 noon GMT on Jan. 2 is represented by yearday 1.5, NOT yearday 2.5.</str><str>The height of the velocity, temperature, or pressure measurement, in meters above the sea bottom.</str><str>The depth of the velocity, temperature, or pressure measurement, in positive meters below Mean Sea Level (MSL).  Bins above MSL are represented with negative depths.</str><str>The fluctuating water depth (sea floor to sea surface distance) at the measurement site, in meters, as determined by location of sea surface from ADCP pressure measurements, or if pressure is unavailable, the maximum in ADCP echo intensity.</str><str>seawater temperature from ADCP sensor</str><str>pressure measured at the ADCP sensor, measured in decibars with a precision defined as the effective resolution of the instrument.</str><str>ADCP echo intensity (or backscatter), in RDI counts.  This value represents the average of all 4 beams, rounded to the nearest whole number.</str><str>A post-processing quantitative data quality indicator.  Specifically, RDI percent-good #4, in earth coordinates (percentage of successful 4-beam transformations), expressed as a percentage, 50, 80, 95, etc.</str><str>True eastward velocity measurements.  Negative values represent westward velocities.</str><str>True northward velocity measurements.  Negative values represent southward velocities.</str><str>True upwards velocity measurements.  Negative values represent downward velocities.</str><str>The difference of two vertical velocities, each measured by an opposing pair of ADCP beams</str><str>data flag used to qualify data as bad, questionable, etc.</str></arr><arr name="attributeUnit"><str>nominalDay</str><str>meter</str><str>meter</str><str>meter</str><str>celsius</str><str>decibar</str><str>number</str><str>number</str><str>metersPerSecond</str><str>metersPerSecond</str><str>metersPerSecond</str><str>metersPerSecond</str></arr><arr name="attribute"><str>date  Greenwich Mean Time calendar date of each ADCP measurement record, using ISO 8601 standard format YYYY-MM-DD</str><str>time  Greenwich Mean Time of each ADCP measurement record, to the 1/100th of a second, using ISO 8601 standard format hh:mm:ss.ssZ.  The 'Z' indicates 'Zero Meridian' (or Greenwich Mean Time) and must be included.</str><str>yearday  Greenwich Mean Time of each ADCP measurement record, expressed as fractional decimal days since Jan. 1 of the year measurement was made.  For example, 12 noon GMT on Jan. 2 is represented by yearday 1.5, NOT yearday 2.5. nominalDay</str><str>height  The height of the velocity, temperature, or pressure measurement, in meters above the sea bottom. meter</str><str>depth  The depth of the velocity, temperature, or pressure measurement, in positive meters below Mean Sea Level (MSL).  Bins above MSL are represented with negative depths. meter</str><str>waterdepth  The fluctuating water depth (sea floor to sea surface distance) at the measurement site, in meters, as determined by location of sea surface from ADCP pressure measurements, or if pressure is unavailable, the maximum in ADCP echo intensity. meter</str><str>temp_c  seawater temperature from ADCP sensor celsius</str><str>pressure  pressure measured at the ADCP sensor, measured in decibars with a precision defined as the effective resolution of the instrument. decibar</str><str>intensity  ADCP echo intensity (or backscatter), in RDI counts.  This value represents the average of all 4 beams, rounded to the nearest whole number. number</str><str>data_quality  A post-processing quantitative data quality indicator.  Specifically, RDI percent-good #4, in earth coordinates (percentage of successful 4-beam transformations), expressed as a percentage, 50, 80, 95, etc. number</str><str>eastward  True eastward velocity measurements.  Negative values represent westward velocities. metersPerSecond</str><str>northward  True northward velocity measurements.  Negative values represent southward velocities. metersPerSecond</str><str>upwards  True upwards velocity measurements.  Negative values represent downward velocities. metersPerSecond</str><str>errorvelocity  The difference of two vertical velocities, each measured by an opposing pair of ADCP beams metersPerSecond</str><str>flag  data flag used to qualify data as bad, questionable, etc.</str></arr><str name="fileID">https://cn.dataone.org/cn/v2/resolve/doi%3A10.6085%2FAA%2FPTSXXX_015ADCP015R00_20030902.50.5</str><arr name="geohash_1"><str>9</str></arr><arr name="geohash_2"><str>9q</str></arr><arr name="geohash_3"><str>9q4</str></arr><arr name="geohash_4"><str>9q4n</str></arr><arr name="geohash_5"><str>9q4nq</str></arr><arr name="geohash_6"><str>9q4nqg</str></arr><arr name="geohash_7"><str>9q4nqge</str></arr><arr name="geohash_8"><str>9q4nqgex</str></arr><arr name="geohash_9"><str>9q4nqgexv</str></arr><bool name="isService">false</bool><arr name="documents"><str>doi:10.6085/AA/PTSXXX_015ADCP015R00_20030902.40.2</str></arr><arr name="resourceMap"><str>resourceMap_PTSXXX_015ADCP015R00_20030902.50.5</str></arr><str name="serviceCoupling">false</str></doc></result><lst name="facet_counts"><lst name="facet_queries"/><lst name="facet_fields"/><lst name="facet_dates"/><lst name="facet_ranges"><lst name="dateUploaded"><lst name="counts"><int name="2001-01-01T00:00:00Z">0</int><int name="2002-01-01T00:00:00Z">0</int><int name="2003-01-01T00:00:00Z">0</int><int name="2004-01-01T00:00:00Z">0</int><int name="2005-01-01T00:00:00Z">5189</int><int name="2006-01-01T00:00:00Z">1170</int><int name="2007-01-01T00:00:00Z">1480</int><int name="2008-01-01T00:00:00Z">3423</int><int name="2009-01-01T00:00:00Z">1634</int><int name="2010-01-01T00:00:00Z">2215</int><int name="2011-01-01T00:00:00Z">732</int><int name="2012-01-01T00:00:00Z">1555</int><int name="2013-01-01T00:00:00Z">47</int><int name="2014-01-01T00:00:00Z">3</int><int name="2015-01-01T00:00:00Z">18</int><int name="2016-01-01T00:00:00Z">2286</int><int name="2017-01-01T00:00:00Z">68</int></lst><str name="gap">+1YEAR</str><date name="start">2001-01-01T00:00:00Z</date><date name="end">2018-01-01T00:00:00Z</date></lst></lst><lst name="facet_intervals"/><lst name="facet_heatmaps"/></lst>
</response>
