<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<response>
<lst name="responseHeader"><int name="status">0</int><int name="QTime">139</int><lst name="params"><str name="facet.range">dateUploaded</str><str name="q">*:* -obsoletedBy:* formatType:METADATA</str><str name="facet.limit">-1</str><str name="facet.range.gap">+1YEAR</str><str name="facet.missing">true</str><str name="fq">datasource:"urn:node:TFRI"</str><str name="sort">dateUploaded asc</str><str name="rows">1</str><str name="facet">true</str><str name="wt">xml</str><str name="facet.range.start">2001-01-01T00:00:00Z</str><str name="facet.range.end">2017-12-31T23:59:59.999Z</str></lst></lst><result name="response" numFound="843" start="0"><doc><str name="id">chin.1.1</str><str name="identifier">chin.1.1</str><str name="formatId">eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1</str><str name="formatType">METADATA</str><long name="size">16872</long><str name="checksum">bc6af1d7cee92f8e48d6546ab3e12b68</str><str name="submitter">uid=chin,o=TFRI,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</str><str name="checksumAlgorithm">MD5</str><str name="rightsHolder">uid=chin,o=TFRI,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</str><bool name="replicationAllowed">false</bool><date name="dateUploaded">2006-10-21T00:00:00Z</date><date name="updateDate">2006-10-21T00:00:00Z</date><date name="dateModified">2013-06-12T01:02:18.562Z</date><str name="datasource">urn:node:TFRI</str><str name="authoritativeMN">urn:node:TFRI</str><arr name="replicaMN"><str>urn:node:CN</str><str>urn:node:TFRI</str></arr><arr name="replicaVerifiedDate"><date>2017-02-24T21:01:35.86Z</date><date>2017-10-03T11:20:08.016Z</date></arr><arr name="readPermission"><str>public</str></arr><bool name="isPublic">true</bool><str name="dataUrl">https://cn.dataone.org/cn/v2/resolve/chin.1.1</str><str name="abstract">Forest fires are generally considered a destructiveand undesirable event in forest managment, because fires can lead to severe environmental damages by releasing large amount of carbon. Therefore, estimation of fire emmissions has been intensively studied by fire science community. There are several methods to estimate fire emmissions released by different researchers. Generally, fire emmissions can be estimated ushing fire and fuel properties, including area burned, fuel loading or consumption factor, emmission factor, and fuel moisture. This methodlogy is based on traditional fire science in fuel inventory and experimental design. It cases some diffiuclties when the outdated data used and lack of fuel survey data. In recent years, remote sensing is one of the new methodology for estimating carbon released by forest fire. Remote sensing has showed its powerful capacity in estimating carbon release. However, this method costs high budget on obtaining the source and high techniques on processing the data. The present seeks to collect the current methods on estimating carbon released by fires and selects a suitable one for Taiwan. The results are expect to provide useful information for objective of this project (1) to establish a method fore estimatation carbon released by forest fire to be used in Taiwan, (2) to integrate fire database for the input of calculation of carbon release, and (3) to suggest emission reductions techniques.</str><arr name="keywords"><str>forest fire</str><str>fire emissions</str><str>fuel  properties</str><str>carbon emissions</str></arr><str name="title">Carbon and Fuel Management in Taiwan Red Pine Forest</str><str name="project">The Strategy of Forest Management to Resonse Kyoto Protocol</str><float name="southBoundCoord">24.0</float><float name="northBoundCoord">24.625</float><float name="westBoundCoord">120.875</float><float name="eastBoundCoord">121.375</float><arr name="site"><str>Dajashi national forest</str></arr><date name="beginDate">2006-01-01T00:00:00Z</date><date name="endDate">2006-01-01T00:00:00Z</date><str name="author">Chau-Chin Lin</str><str name="authorGivenName">Chau-Chin</str><str name="authorSurName">Lin</str><str name="authorSurNameSort">Lin</str><arr name="authorLastName"><str>Lin</str></arr><arr name="investigator"><str>Lin</str></arr><arr name="origin"><str>Chau-Chin Lin</str></arr><arr name="contactOrganization"><str>Taiwan Forestry Research Institute</str></arr><arr name="attributeName"><str>tree number</str><str>Species</str><str>Treestat</str><str>TreeHT</str><str>DBH</str><str>Biomassw</str><str>brushid</str><str>bspecies</str><str>BrushHT</str><str>BasalD</str><str>Bcrown</str><str>Bweight</str><str>Byear</str><str>Bmonth</str><str>Bplace</str><str>burnArea</str></arr><arr name="attributeLabel"><str>each tree surveyed within the sampling plot</str><str>species with its Chinese name</str><str>each tree status surveyed</str><str>Tree Height of each tree</str><str>each tree Diameter</str><str>the weight of the survey tree</str><str>the brush surveyed within the sampling plot</str><str>species name of each surveyed brush with Chinese name</str><str>each brush height</str><str>diameter of the brush from the basal area</str><str>crown span of the surveyed brush</str><str>weight of the brush</str><str>Burn year</str><str>burn moth</str><str>fire ignition place</str><str>burned area</str></arr><arr name="attributeDescription"><str>the number is a id of the survey tree without any unit</str><str>The name of surveyed tree used Chinese common name and will be mapped to real scientific name if it is necessary</str><str>using three classes to describe tree status surveyed by live,dead standing, and broken standing</str><str>tree hight measured by tree height portable scale. Estimated the height by using traditional forest survey method</str><str>tree diameter using soft meter scale to measure. by measuring upslope and downslope two dimensions and averaged the values to indicate the diameter</str><str>the weight is the subsamples taken from the tree after cutting down and weight fhe fresh weight in the field then ovendried with 103c in the lab</str><str>the id used a number for survey recording</str><str>If necessary, the brushes were identifed and gave a scientific name</str><str>measured by using a 10 meter pole using in the fiels</str><str>this basal diameter was measured by using soft meter scale from the litter layer on the gruond</str><str>crown span was measured by two dimensions of the crown with the length and width then aversage them</str><str>the whole brush was cutt down and weight freshly in the field after cutting. Then sent to lab for drying with an oven to weight the oven dry</str><str>year ffom 200 to 2005</str><str>using digital number</str><str>the place use national forest compartement number then suing gis to identify the coordinator</str><str>the burned area using ha ad the unit</str></arr><arr name="attributeUnit"><str>dimensionless</str><str>meter</str><str>centimeter</str><str>gram</str><str>dimensionless</str><str>meter</str><str>centimeter</str><str>meter</str><str>kilogram</str><str>hectare</str></arr><arr name="attribute"><str>tree number each tree surveyed within the sampling plot the number is a id of the survey tree without any unit dimensionless</str><str>Species species with its Chinese name The name of surveyed tree used Chinese common name and will be mapped to real scientific name if it is necessary</str><str>Treestat each tree status surveyed using three classes to describe tree status surveyed by live,dead standing, and broken standing</str><str>TreeHT Tree Height of each tree tree hight measured by tree height portable scale. Estimated the height by using traditional forest survey method meter</str><str>DBH each tree Diameter tree diameter using soft meter scale to measure. by measuring upslope and downslope two dimensions and averaged the values to indicate the diameter centimeter</str><str>Biomassw the weight of the survey tree the weight is the subsamples taken from the tree after cutting down and weight fhe fresh weight in the field then ovendried with 103c in the lab gram</str><str>brushid the brush surveyed within the sampling plot the id used a number for survey recording dimensionless</str><str>bspecies species name of each surveyed brush with Chinese name If necessary, the brushes were identifed and gave a scientific name</str><str>BrushHT each brush height measured by using a 10 meter pole using in the fiels meter</str><str>BasalD diameter of the brush from the basal area this basal diameter was measured by using soft meter scale from the litter layer on the gruond centimeter</str><str>Bcrown crown span of the surveyed brush crown span was measured by two dimensions of the crown with the length and width then aversage them meter</str><str>Bweight weight of the brush the whole brush was cutt down and weight freshly in the field after cutting. Then sent to lab for drying with an oven to weight the oven dry kilogram</str><str>Byear Burn year year ffom 200 to 2005</str><str>Bmonth burn moth using digital number</str><str>Bplace fire ignition place the place use national forest compartement number then suing gis to identify the coordinator</str><str>burnArea burned area the burned area using ha ad the unit hectare</str></arr><str name="fileID">https://cn.dataone.org/cn/v2/resolve/chin.1.1</str><arr name="geohash_1"><str>w</str></arr><arr name="geohash_2"><str>ws</str></arr><arr name="geohash_3"><str>wsq</str></arr><arr name="geohash_4"><str>wsq4</str></arr><arr name="geohash_5"><str>wsq4k</str></arr><arr name="geohash_6"><str>wsq4k3</str></arr><arr name="geohash_7"><str>wsq4k3b</str></arr><arr name="geohash_8"><str>wsq4k3bw</str></arr><arr name="geohash_9"><str>wsq4k3bw9</str></arr><bool name="isService">false</bool><str name="serviceCoupling">false</str></doc></result><lst name="facet_counts"><lst name="facet_queries"/><lst name="facet_fields"/><lst name="facet_dates"/><lst name="facet_ranges"><lst name="dateUploaded"><lst name="counts"><int name="2001-01-01T00:00:00Z">0</int><int name="2002-01-01T00:00:00Z">0</int><int name="2003-01-01T00:00:00Z">0</int><int name="2004-01-01T00:00:00Z">0</int><int name="2005-01-01T00:00:00Z">0</int><int name="2006-01-01T00:00:00Z">214</int><int name="2007-01-01T00:00:00Z">230</int><int name="2008-01-01T00:00:00Z">71</int><int name="2009-01-01T00:00:00Z">90</int><int name="2010-01-01T00:00:00Z">98</int><int name="2011-01-01T00:00:00Z">9</int><int name="2012-01-01T00:00:00Z">13</int><int name="2013-01-01T00:00:00Z">2</int><int name="2014-01-01T00:00:00Z">8</int><int name="2015-01-01T00:00:00Z">42</int><int name="2016-01-01T00:00:00Z">33</int><int name="2017-01-01T00:00:00Z">33</int></lst><str name="gap">+1YEAR</str><date name="start">2001-01-01T00:00:00Z</date><date name="end">2018-01-01T00:00:00Z</date></lst></lst><lst name="facet_intervals"/><lst name="facet_heatmaps"/></lst>
</response>
