<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="esa.60.3" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 eml.xsd">


<access authSystem="knb" order="denyFirst">
<allow>
  <principal>uid=esaadmin,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
  <principal>cn=knb-prod,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
  <principal>cn=esa-moderators,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
  <principal>uid=regetz,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>read</permission>
<permission>write</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
  <principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission>
</allow>
</access>
<dataset>
<title>Data from an extensive field survey aiming to test the role of the patch-size distribution of vegetation as a suitable indicator of desertification processes</title>
<creator>
<organizationName>Universidad Rey Juan Carlos</organizationName>
</creator>
<creator>
<organizationName>Ecological Society of America</organizationName>
</creator>
<creator>
<individualName>
<givenName>Fernando T</givenName>
<surName>Maestre</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>Universidad Rey Juan Carlos</organizationName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>&#195;&#129;rea de Biodiversidad y Conservaci&#195;&#179;n
Escuela Superior de Ciencias Experimentales y Tecnolog&#195;&#173;a
C/ Tulip&#195;&#161;n s/n, M&#195;&#179;stoles, 28933</deliveryPoint>
<city>M&#195;&#179;stoles</city>
<administrativeArea>Madrid</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>28933</postalCode>
<country>Spain</country>
</address>
<phone>+34-914888511</phone>
<phone phonetype="Fax">+34-916647490</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>fernando.maestre@urjc.es</electronicMailAddress>
</creator>
<metadataProvider><individualName>
<givenName>Fernando T</givenName>
<surName>Maestre</surName>
</individualName>
</metadataProvider>
<associatedParty><individualName>
<givenName>Fernando T</givenName>
<surName>Maestre</surName>
</individualName>
<role>associatedParty</role>
</associatedParty>
<pubDate>2010-05-10</pubDate>
<abstract>
<para>Data from an extensive field study gathered in 29 semiarid Stipa tenacissima steppes located along an environmental gradient spanning from the center to the south-eastern part of Spain. The data consist of the patch-size distribution of perennial vegetation and of different soil variables used as surrogates of ecosystem functioning (soil respiration, organic carbon, total nitrogen and phosphorus, potassium, pH, water holding capacity and the activity of three enzymes related to the carbon [b-glucosidase], nitrogen [urease] and phosphorus [phosphatase] cycles). The data were gathered to: i) test if transitions from a patch-size distribution characterized by a power law function to another described by a truncated power law function occur in the more degraded sites (i.e., in those sites closer to desertification), and ii) explore how joint changes in this distribution and in total plant cover, the importance of which has often been highlighted in the study of desertification, relate to surrogates of desertification processes</para>
</abstract>
<keywordSet>
<keyword>desertification</keyword>
<keyword>spain</keyword>
<keyword>patch-size distribution</keyword>
<keyword>land degradation</keyword>
<keyword>drylands</keyword>
<keyword>power law</keyword>
<keyword>spatial pattern</keyword>
<keyword>ecosystem functioning</keyword>
<keyword>Stipa tenacissima</keyword>
<keyword>species interactions</keyword>
<keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
</keywordSet>
<additionalInfo>
<para>The data is associated with the publication: Maestre, F. T. &amp; A. Escudero. 2009. Is the patch-size distribution of vegetation a suitable indicator of desertification processes? Ecology (accepted).
The data are in Excel format</para>
</additionalInfo>
<intellectualRights>
<para>other</para>
<para>The data can be used without restrictions, but those using them should acknowledge their use in publications/synthesis carried out using these data</para>
</intellectualRights>
<distribution>
<offline>
<mediumName>digital </mediumName>
</offline>
</distribution>
<coverage>
<temporalCoverage>
<singleDateTime>
<calendarDate>2006-07-20</calendarDate>
</singleDateTime>
</temporalCoverage>
<geographicCoverage>
<geographicDescription>Our study was conducted at 29 Stipa tenacissima steppes located along an environmental gradient spanning from the center to the south-eastern part of Spain. Below are the coordinates from the northern and southern study sites, respectively.</geographicDescription>
<boundingCoordinates>
<westBoundingCoordinate>-2.8681</westBoundingCoordinate>
<eastBoundingCoordinate>-1.3039</eastBoundingCoordinate>
<northBoundingCoordinate>40.3556</northBoundingCoordinate>
<southBoundingCoordinate>37.0819</southBoundingCoordinate>
</boundingCoordinates>
</geographicCoverage>
</coverage>
<contact>
<individualName>
<givenName>Fernando T</givenName>
<surName>Maestre</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>Universidad Rey Juan Carlos</organizationName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>&#195;&#129;rea de Biodiversidad y Conservaci&#195;&#179;n
Escuela Superior de Ciencias Experimentales y Tecnolog&#195;&#173;a
C/ Tulip&#195;&#161;n s/n, M&#195;&#179;stoles, 28933</deliveryPoint>
<city>M&#195;&#179;stoles</city>
<administrativeArea>Madrid</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>28933</postalCode>
<country>Spain</country>
</address>
<phone>+34-914888511</phone>
<phone phonetype="Fax">+34-916647490</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>fernando.maestre@urjc.es</electronicMailAddress>
</contact>
<methods><methodStep><description><section>
<title>Vegetation and soil properties survey</title>
<para>At each site we established a 30 x 30 m plot for vegetation and soil measurements. Our surveys of plant communities focused on perennial vascular plants; they were conducted in four 30 m long transects per plot, separated 8 m each, using the line-intercept method and contiguous quadrats. In each transect, we collected a detailed record of all perennial plant patches intercepting the transect to estimate their sizes. </para>
<para>We measured some &#226;&#128;&#156;slow&#226;&#128;&#157; soil variables that are critical determinants of the functioning of drylands: respiration, organic carbon, total nitrogen and phosphorus, potassium, pH, water holding capacity and the activity of three enzymes related to the carbon (b-glucosidase), nitrogen (urease) and phosphorus (phosphatase) cycles. </para>
<para>Respiration rates were determined by NaOH absorption followed by titration with HCl (Froment 1972). Organic carbon was estimated using the Walkley-Black method (Nelson and Sommers 1982). Total nitrogen and phosphorus were obtained using a San++ Analyzer (Skalar, Breda, The Netherlands) after digestion in sulfuric acid. Potassium was measured with the same analyzer after shaking the soil sample with distilled water (1:5 ratio) for one hour. pH was measured with a pH meter, in a 1:2.5 mass:volume soil and water suspension. Urease, phosphatase and b-glucosidase activities were determined as described in Tabatabai (1982). Water holding capacity was measured in two of the five replicates per site as described in Forster (1995). The average values of each measured soil variable per site were used in subsequent analyses.

References

Forster, J. C. 1995. Soil physical analysis. Pages 106-111 in K. Alef and P. Nannipieri, editors. Methods in Applied Soil Microbiology and Biochemistry. Academic Press Inc, San Diego, USA.

Froment, A. 1972. Soil respiration in a mixed oak forest. Oikos 23:273-277.

Nelson, R. E. and L. E. Sommers. 1982. Total carbon, organic carbon, and organic matter. Pages 539-580 in A. L. Page, R. H. Miller and D. R. Keeney, editors. Methods of soil analysis. Part 2. Chemical and microbiological properties. American Society of Agronomy and Soil Science Society of America. Madison, USA.

Tabatabai, M. A. (1982). Soil enzimes. Pages 501&#226;&#128;&#147;538 in A. L. Page, R. H. Miller and D. R. Keeney, editors. Methods of Soil Analysis. Part 2, Second edition. American Society of Agronomy and Soil Science Society of America, Madison, USA.</para>
</section></description></methodStep>
<sampling><studyExtent><description>
<para>Our study was conducted at 29 Stipa tenacissima steppes located along an environmental gradient spanning from the center to the south-eastern part of Spain. The climate of the study area is semiarid Mediterranean, with average annual precipitation and temperatures ranging from 265 to 497 mm, and from 13 to 17&#194;&#186;C, respectively. Most sites (22) were located on soils derived from limestone, Lithic Calciorthid, while seven sites were located on gypsum-rich soils, Typic Gypsiorthid. All sites were placed on south-facing gentle slopes. Vegetation was in all cases an open steppe dominated by S. tenacissima and contained shrub species like Quercus coccifera, Rosmarinus officinalis and Thymus vulgaris in calcareous soils, and Lepidium subulatum, Gypsophila struthihum and Thymus lacaite in gypsum soils. Perennial plant cover ranged between 15 and 68%.

Soil and vegetation sampling was carried out only once in all sites.</para>
</description></studyExtent>
<samplingDescription>
<para>Soil sampling was conducted at all the sites between 20 July and 15 August 2006, when the soil was dry after at least 1.5 months of summer drought. Five 50 cm x 50 cm quadrats were randomly placed in open areas devoid of vascular vegetation. A composite sample obtained from six 145 cm3 soil cores (0-7.5 cm depth) was obtained for each quadrat, bulked and homogenized in the field (n = 5 per site). Samples were transported to the laboratory, where they were sieved by 2 mm mesh and air-dried for two months. </para>
</samplingDescription>
</sampling>
</methods>
</dataset></ns0:eml>