<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="esa.98.2" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 eml.xsd">


<access authSystem="knb" order="denyFirst">
<allow>
  <principal>uid=esaadmin,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
  <principal>cn=knb-prod,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
  <principal>cn=esa-moderators,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
  <principal>uid=regetz,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>read</permission>
<permission>write</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
  <principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission>
</allow>
</access>
<dataset>
<title>Cueva del Azufre, Tabasco State, Mexico primary producer and consumer carbon and nitrogen stable isotope data from August 2008</title>
<creator>
<organizationName>Kirk Winemiller Aquatic Ecology laboratory, Department of Wildlife and Fisheries Sciences, Texas A&amp;M University</organizationName>
</creator>
<creator>
<organizationName>Ecological Society of America</organizationName>
</creator>
<creator>
<individualName>
<givenName>Kirk</givenName>
<surName>Winemiller</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>Kirk Winemiller Aquatic Ecology laboratory</organizationName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>101 Herman Heep, 2258 TAMU, Texas A&amp;M University</deliveryPoint>
<city>College Station</city>
<administrativeArea>Texas</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>77843</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
<phone>785-766-5592</phone>
<phone phonetype="Fax">979-845-4096</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>roackat@gmail.com</electronicMailAddress>
</creator>
<metadataProvider><individualName>
<givenName>Katherine</givenName>
<surName>Roach</surName>
</individualName>
</metadataProvider>
<associatedParty><individualName>
<givenName>Kirk</givenName>
<surName>Winemiller</surName>
</individualName>
<role>associatedParty</role>
</associatedParty>
<pubDate>2011-09-29</pubDate>
<abstract>
<para>Tissues from primary producers, macroinvertebrates, and Poecilia mexicana were collected in August 2008. Tissues were preserved in salt. At the Texas A&amp;M University laboratory, tissues were soaked in deionized water for four hours, dried at 60 degrees C for 48 hours, encapsulated in tin, and sent to the W.M. Keck Paleoenvironmental and Environmental Stable Isotope Laboratory for analysis of carbon and nitrogen stable isotope ratios. The purpose of the data was to estimate % contributions of primary producers supporting consumer biomass. </para>
</abstract>
<keywordSet>
<keyword>chemoautotroph</keyword>
<keyword>cave fish</keyword>
<keyword>food web</keyword>
<keyword>hydrogen sulfide</keyword>
<keyword>cave</keyword>
<keyword>production source</keyword>
<keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
</keywordSet>
<intellectualRights>
<para>no restrictions</para>
</intellectualRights>
<distribution>
<offline>
<mediumName>digital </mediumName>
</offline>
</distribution>
<coverage>
<temporalCoverage>
<rangeOfDates>
<beginDate>
<calendarDate>2008-08-01</calendarDate>
</beginDate>
<endDate>
<calendarDate>2008-08-31</calendarDate>
</endDate>
</rangeOfDates>
</temporalCoverage>
<geographicCoverage>
<geographicDescription>Cueva del Azufre stream and cave system in Southern Tabasco State, Mexico</geographicDescription>
<boundingCoordinates>
<westBoundingCoordinate>-92.7858</westBoundingCoordinate>
<eastBoundingCoordinate>-92.7556</eastBoundingCoordinate>
<northBoundingCoordinate>17.4522</northBoundingCoordinate>
<southBoundingCoordinate>17.4344</southBoundingCoordinate>
</boundingCoordinates>
</geographicCoverage>
<taxonomicCoverage>
<generalTaxonomicCoverage>La pesca en aguas interiores (serie los pescadores de Mexico) by Arturo Argueta, A field guide to the mammals of Central Africa and Southeast Mexico by Fiona Reid</generalTaxonomicCoverage>
<taxonomicClassification>
  <taxonRankName>species</taxonRankName>
  <taxonRankValue>Poecilia mexicana</taxonRankValue>
</taxonomicClassification>
<taxonomicClassification>
  <taxonRankName>species</taxonRankName>
  <taxonRankValue>Thiobacilli spp.</taxonRankValue>
</taxonomicClassification>
<taxonomicClassification>
  <taxonRankName>species</taxonRankName>
  <taxonRankValue>Acidimicrobium ferrooxidans</taxonRankValue>
</taxonomicClassification>
<taxonomicClassification>
  <taxonRankName>species</taxonRankName>
  <taxonRankValue>Mormoops megalophylla</taxonRankValue>
</taxonomicClassification>
<taxonomicClassification>
  <taxonRankName>species</taxonRankName>
  <taxonRankValue>Belostoma sp.</taxonRankValue>
</taxonomicClassification>
<taxonomicClassification>
  <taxonRankName>species</taxonRankName>
  <taxonRankValue>Goeldichironomus fulvipilus</taxonRankValue>
</taxonomicClassification>
</taxonomicCoverage>
</coverage>
<contact>
<individualName>
<givenName>Katherine</givenName>
<surName>Roach</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>Kirk Winemiller Aquatic Ecology laboratory, Texas A&amp;M University</organizationName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>101 Herman Heep, 2258 TAMU, Texas A&amp;M University</deliveryPoint>
<city>College Station</city>
<administrativeArea>Texas</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>77843</postalCode>
<country>USA</country>
</address>
<phone>785-766-5592</phone>
<phone phonetype="Fax">979-845-4096</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>roackat@gmail.com</electronicMailAddress>
</contact>
<methods><methodStep><description><section>
<title>Carbon and nitrogen stable isotope analysis of primary producers and consumers</title>
<para>Samples of leaves from the dominant vegetation (mosses, ferns, Acacia, Heliconia, and grasses; n = 10) were collected from the riparian zone of the surface streams. Small seedlings (n = 2), which had apparently been carried in by bats and germinated in the dark, were collected from the non-sulfidic cave. Snails (n = 17) were collected by hand from each habitat as a proxy for the stable isotope signature of benthic algae or other predominant biofilms (Vander Zanden and Rasmussen 1999). Mats of sulfur-oxidizing bacteria (n = 4) were collected from the sulfidic habitats. Samples of bat feces (n = 6), a potentially important source of carbon for cave fishes (Tobler 2008), were obtained from the caves. Fishes were collected from all habitats with a seine, anesthetized with tricaine methanesulfonate, and preserved in 10% formalin for gut contents analysis after removal of a sample of muscle tissue (n = 20) from the dorso-lateral region with a scalpel. The aquatic hemipteran Belostoma sp. (n = 9) was collected from the non-sulfidic cave, and samples of dipteran larvae were taken from the non-sulfidic cave stream (n = 4) and the sulfidic surface stream (n = 5). Samples of snails and dipteran larvae were composites of several individuals to ensure adequate material for mass spectrometry. All samples were placed in plastic bags with salt, which has little influence on stable isotope signatures of tissues (Arrington and Winemiller 2002), for later processing at Texas A&amp;M University.</para>
<para>Samples of primary producers, bacteria mats, fishes, and insects were rinsed and then soaked in deionized water for four hours to remove salt. The shells were removed from snail samples by hand. All samples were subsequently dried at 65&#194;&#176;C for 48 hours and ground to a fine powder using a mortar and pestle. Subsamples were then weighed into Ultra-Pure tin capsules (Costech Analytical, Valencia, California, USA) and sent to the W.M. Keck Paleoenvironmental and Environmental Stable Isotope Laboratory, University of Kansas, Lawrence, Kansas, USA, for analysis of carbon and nitrogen isotope ratios using a ThermoFinnigan MAT 253 continuous-flow mass spectrometer. The standard was Pee Dee Belemnite limestone for carbon isotopes and atmospheric nitrogen for nitrogen isotopes.</para>
</section></description></methodStep>
<sampling><studyExtent><description>
<para>The habitats sampled include the non-sulfidic surface stream Arroyo Tacubaya, the sulfidic surface stream El Azufre, the non-sulfidic cave stream Cueva Luna Azufre, and the sulfidic cave stream Cueva del Azufre.  </para>
</description></studyExtent>
<samplingDescription>
<para>Sampling design information can be found above in method description.</para>
</samplingDescription>
</sampling>
</methods>
</dataset></ns0:eml>