<ns0:metadata xmlns:ns0="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0" xmlns:ns2="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0 http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0/onedcx_v1.0.xsd"><ns0:simpleDc><ns2:identifier>1e121697-bb78-476a-b625-ee6175c3277f</ns2:identifier><ns2:title>Global climate model (MIROC4.0) simulations for permafrost dynamics sensitivity to the subsurface and the atmosphere</ns2:title><ns2:subject>GCM (Global Climate model) simulations</ns2:subject><ns2:subject>permafrost dynamics</ns2:subject><ns2:subject>atmospheric impacts</ns2:subject><ns2:language>eng</ns2:language><ns2:format>BIN</ns2:format></ns0:simpleDc><ns0:dcTerms><ns2:modified>2011-12-08T15:19:41</ns2:modified><ns2:created>2011-04-28T00:00:00</ns2:created><ns2:abstract>A set of land-atmosphere coupled global climate model simulations were performed to investigate the sensitivity of the permafrost dynamics and the soil settings to the subsurface hydro-thermal states and to examine the impacts on the hydro-climate above the surface.
c5s0 (conventional land process scheme; conventional soil property values; 5-layer 4m soil column; no top organic layers)
c5s0o (conventional land process scheme; physically-based soil property values; 5-layer 4m soil column; no top organic layers)
p5s0 (partial refinement (no unfrozen water); physically-based soil property values; 5-layer 4m soil column; no top organic layers)
r6s1(refined permafrost dynamics; physically-based soil property values; 6-layer 14m soil column; top organic layers)
rCs0 (refined permafrost dynamics; physically-based soil property values; 12-layer 100m soil column; no top organic layers)
rCs1y (refined permafrost dynamics; physically-based soil property values; 12-layer 100m soil column; top organic layers; different hydraulic parameters)
rCs1 (refined permafrost dynamics; physically-based soil property values; 12-layer 100m soil column; top organic layers)

The work was partially supported by NSF Grant number ARC-0327664, 0652838. The MIROC GCM was developed by CCSR (Univ. Tokyo), NIES and FRCGC, Japan.  Simulations were done at the Arctic Research Supercomputing Center (ARSC).</ns2:abstract><ns2:accessRights /><ns2:accessRights /><ns2:accessRights /><ns2:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:Box">northlimit=90; southlimit=-90; eastlimit=180; westlimit=-180</ns2:spatial><ns2:temporal>Begin 0020-01-01T00:00:00; End 0079-12-31T23:59:59</ns2:temporal></ns0:dcTerms></ns0:metadata>