<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="cmchiu.9.9" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><title>Tracheid length and micofibril Taiwania grown under different thinning and pruning treatments</title><creator id="1164769051031" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Chih-Ming</givenName><surName>Chiu</surName></individualName><organizationName>Taiwan Forestry Research Institute</organizationName><positionName>Division of Forest Management</positionName><electronicMailAddress>cmchiu@tfri.gov.tw</electronicMailAddress></creator><abstract><para>The effects of different thinning and pruning methods on the tracheid length and microfibril angle of young Taiwania (Taiwania cryptomerioides Hay) were investigated. No significant differences were found for tracheid length and microfibril angle among the three thinning and pruning treatments. The tracheid length increases outwards from the pith. The radial variation in microfibril angle is high near the pith, and declines gradually towards the cambium. The tracheid length values increase with decreasing microfibril angle.</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>Thinning</keyword><keyword>Pruning</keyword><keyword>Tracheid length</keyword><keyword>Microfibril angle</keyword><keyword>Taiwania</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><para>Please inquire of the author</para></intellectualRights><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Taiwan</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>119.975</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>122.25</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>25.375</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>21.5</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><singleDateTime><calendarDate>2005</calendarDate></singleDateTime></temporalCoverage></coverage><contact id="1164767734937" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Cheng-Jung</givenName><surName>Lin</surName></individualName><organizationName>Taiwan Forestry Research Institute</organizationName><positionName>Division of Forest Utilization</positionName><electronicMailAddress>zzlin@tfri.gov.tw</electronicMailAddress></contact><methods><methodStep><description><section><para>The study site was located in the No. 12, Liukuei Experimental Forest of the Taiwan Forestry Research Institute (TFRI), Kaohsiung County, Taiwan, R.O.C. The area of the study site was about 2.0 ha, divided into 27 plots, each about 0.04 ha in area, including a buffer zone. The three types of thinning treatments were heavy thinning (basal area 28 m2/ha. at diameter breast height [DBH, about 1.3 m. above the ground]), moderate thinning (33 m2/ha.), and control (42 m2/ha.).</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><para>The heavy-thinning and moderate-thinning treatments harvested stocks from the original 42 (m2/ha) to retain 28 (m2/ha) and 33 (m2/ha), respectively. The three types of pruning treatments were heavy pruning (4.5 m), moderate pruning (3.6m), and control (non-pruning). The heavy-pruning and moderate-pruning treatments represented trees that were pruned from the root base upward to 4.5 m and 3.6 m of the tree height, respectively. The study plantation was planted at an initial density of 1750 trees/ha in 1980. Thinning and pruning treatments were implemented in 1990.</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><para>Three levels of thinning were combined with another three levels of pruning treatment. Therefore, nine silvicultural practices (3 thinning &#215; 3 pruning treatments) were used in this study. The same thinning and pruning treatment plots were repeated three times, for a total of 27 sample plots in the experimental design.</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><para>There is large tree-to-tree (inter-tree) and within-tree variation in wood properties within a species; even the trees have the same age and grow in the same condition. In this study, the diameter and height of each tree on the 27 small plots were all measured. We had studied the structure of thinning and pruning treatments of Taiwania stands and the expected and fitted Weibull distribution of diameter breast height (DBH) classes for Taiwania plantations after thinning and pruning treatments. To eliminate the variation in this study, trees (samples) were removed only from the mediate tree per plot. In other words, we sampled 3 trees (one [mediate] tree was selected from each plot) of each treatment. The data set consisted of one tree &#215; three replicas (plots) &#215; three thinning treatments &#215; three pruning treatments. In total, 27 trees were investigated for tracheid length and MFA. Each tree had more than nine trachied lengths and MFAs according to the number of rings examined, respectively.</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><para>First, the diameter and height of each tree on the 27 small plots were measured. The average DBHs and tree heights are shown in Table 1. A mean diameter from the trees was selected from each plot (3 trees per treatment), and a total of 27 sample trees were cut. These trees were harvested on February 14-15, 2001, when they were about 20 years old.</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><para>One cross-sectional disc (10 cm thick) was cut from each sample tree at the position of its DBH. A pith-to-bark strip about 1 cm wide and 1.5 cm thick was sawn along an average radius from each disk. The diametrical strip was sawn from each disc in the same direction, and each strip was subdivided into growth rings as measuring units. Matchstick-size specimens were trimmed to contain only one growth ring (earlywood and latewood), and then soaked in test tubes with a maceration solution (H2O2: CH3COOH: distilled H2O = 1: 4: 5). These then were heated at less than 40&#8451; for 72 h until the color of the specimens became transparently white. Then the specimens were removed from the test tubes and washed with distilled water. The bundles of macerated tracheids were stirred and separated with a glass rod, and then stained with Safrain-O.</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><para>Tracheid length (TL) - In order to compare tracheid length and microfibril angle (MFA) data on the ring, ring boundary positions for each sample were obtained using Resistograph. The within-ring variances of density and the ring boundaries have been reported in an earlier paper. Fortunately, the density profiles for these samples did show clear boundaries. To eliminate within-ring variance in this study, fibers were removed only from the third outermost location of earlywood and all latewood (annual ring). Three or four tangential sections, 0.2 mm in thickness, were prepared from each measuring point in the outermost annual ring. After maceration, the tracheids were then washed, dispersed, and mounted on microscope slides.</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><para>The number of measurements required was determined through a series of preliminary measurements and using formula N=t2&#945;S2/E2, where t is the student&#8217;s t value at the &#945; probability level, i.e. &#945;&lt;=0.01 in this study, S2 is the variation of preliminary sample, and E is the allowable error set at 10% of the mean earlywood/latewood tracheid length. Based on the results of the preliminary measurement, 60 earlywood and 60 latewood tracheids from a fiber slide were selected and measured, respectively. The 60 tracheids from each earlywood and latewood were measured using a light microscope with a photograph system, respectively. Therefore, there are 120 measurements per each ring (earlywood and latewood) in this study.</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><para>In this study, the difference is tracheid length between the earlywood and the latewood there are slight variation, and the mean latewood tracheid length longer than the mean earlywood. Therefore, the mean length of 60 entire earlywood and 60 entire latewood tracheids was used to represent the tracheid length for each individual ring. In other words, the average length of 120 tracheids was used as the tracheid length for each individual growth ring. Thus, more than 29,160 tracheid lengths were measured (120 replicates &#215; more than 9 rings &#215; 3 trees &#215; 3 thinning treatments &#215; 3 pruning treatments).</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><para>Micrifibril angle (MFA) - The MFA can be measured by a wide range of techniques, such as the angle of the slit pits, polarizing, fluorescent and electron microscopy, iodine staining, X-ray diffraction, soft-rot cavity method, sonication (ultrasonic treatment), light microscopy, SilviScan.</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><para>In this study, three or four tangential sections, 0.2 mm in thickness, were also prepared from each measuring point in the latewood. After maceration, the tracheids were also then washed, dispersed, and mounted on microscope slides. One MFA (the orientation of the cellulose microfibrils) was measured per tracheid utilizing the common method. The common procedure for measuring MFAs is to dry specimens rapidly. The rapid shrinkage and high drying stresses cause the cell walls to check and split along the direction of the microfibrils in the S2 layer. Subsequent staining enhances the cracks for measurement by light microscopy (observation of images). When cell-wall cracks are not present, the angle of elongated pit apertures can be measured, another technique regarded as being closely aligned with the MFA of the S2 cell-wall layer. It is agreeable to have a simple, direct, and correct method for MFA determination. Although the method has disadvantages, cracks and pit apertures cannot always be found in sufficient quantit.</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><para>We regarded the angle of pit apertures against the cell axis on tangential walls of latewood tracheids as the MFA. The angle of the pit aperture is parallel to the MFA of the S2 layer of the cell, and Taiwania usually has a lot of tangential pittings in latewood. One average MFA was measured on individual tracheids. Thereafter, the MFAs were measured in thirty tracheids from each latewood using a light microscope with a photograph system.</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><para>Thirty measurements were completed for each latewood to obtain a satisfactory estimated means each ring. Therefore, the average angle from each 30 tracheids was taken to be the angle of the ring and was used to represent the MFA in each ring. Each tree had more than 9 MFAs according to the number of rings examined. Thus, more than 7,290 tracheid lengths were measured (30 replicates &#215; more than 9 rings &#215; 3 trees &#215; 3 thinning treatments &#215; 3 pruning treatments).</para></section></description></methodStep></methods><access authSystem="knb" order="denyFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataTable id="1164705184968" scope="document"><entityName>Tracheild data</entityName><physical scope="document"><objectName>~deleteme20410.tmp</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">ecogrid://knb/cmchiu.18.1</url></online></distribution></physical><attributeList><attribute id="1164705184984" scope="document"><attributeName>sample</attributeName><attributeLabel>sample name</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>sample number</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>number</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="1164705185000" scope="document"><attributeName>DBH</attributeName><attributeLabel>Diameter at breast height</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>DBH, about 1.3m. above the ground.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>centimeter</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="1164705185015" scope="document"><attributeName>TLE</attributeName><attributeLabel>Tracheid length in earlywood</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>the tracheid from each earlywood segment were measured were measured using a light microscope with a photograph system 50X</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>millimeter</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="1164705185031" scope="document"><attributeName>TLL</attributeName><attributeLabel>Tracheid length in latewood</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>the tracheid from each latewood segment were measured were measured using a light microscope with a photograph system 50X</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>millimeter</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="1164768214125" scope="document"><attributeName>MFA</attributeName><attributeLabel>Microfibril angle</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>microfibril angle were measured by the angle of the slit pits of latewood method, the degree between slit and the axial of tracleid for latewood.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>degree</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList></dataTable></dataset></ns0:eml>