<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="hsiao.5.1" scope="system" system="NGIS" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><shortName>ctdf6190.asc</shortName><title>IPCC Climate Change Data: 1961-1990, Temperature Difference</title><creator id="1086641977080" scope="document"><organizationName>Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC)</organizationName><onlineUrl>http://www.ipcc.ch/index.html</onlineUrl></creator><associatedParty id="1086642101767" scope="document"><organizationName>SEEK</organizationName><onlineUrl>http://seek.ecoinformatics.org/</onlineUrl><role>Content Provider</role></associatedParty><abstract><para>From the IPCC website: The CRU Global Climate Dataset available through the IPCC DDC
        consists of a multi-variate 0.01&#186; latitude by 0.01&#186; longitude resolution
        mean monthly climatology for global land areas, excluding Antarctica, strictly constrained
        to the period 1961-1990. The mean 1961-1990 climatology comprises a suite of eleven surface
        variables: precipitation (PRE) and wet-day frequency (WET); mean, maximum and minimum
        temperature (TMP, TMX, TMN); diurnal temperature range (DTR); vapour pressure (VAP;) global
        radiation (RAD;) cloud cover (CLD); frost frequency (FRS); and wind speed (WND). The mean
        climate surfaces have been constructed from a new dataset of station 1961-1990
        climatological normals, numbering between 19,800 (precipitation) and 3615 (windspeed). The
        station data were interpolated as a function of latitude, longitude and elevation using
        thin-plate splines. The accuracy of the interpolations are assessed using cross-validation
        and by comparison with other climatologies. this data-set has been decsribed in: New,M.,
        Hulme,M. and Jones,P.D. (1999) Representing twentieth century space-time climate
        variability. Part 1: development of a 1961-90 mean monthly terrestrial climatology J.Climate
        12, 829-856.</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>climate</keyword><keyword>weather</keyword><keyword>temperature</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><para>1. The IPCC Data Distribution Centre permits the research results from seven climate
        modelling centres (Hadley Centre for Climate Prediction and Research, Deutsches
        Klimarechenzentrum, Canadian Centre for Climate Modelling and Analysis, Geophysical Fluids
        Dynamics Laboratory, the Commonwealth and Scientific Industrial Research Organisation, the
        National centre for Atmospheric Research and the Centre for Climate System Research) to be
        used freely for the purposes of bona fide research. (Bona fide research is deemed to be
        research which generates results that are freely and universally accessible to any
        interested party, i.e., if people use DDC data they must agree to publish results openly or
        respond willingly to requests from others for copies of the results.) 2. The climate
        modelling centres' research results should not be used for commercial exploitation,
        business use, resale or transfer to any third party. 3. No warranty is given as to the
        suitability of the climate modelling centres' research results for particular
        purposes. 4. No liability is accepted by the IPCC Data Distribution Centre and/or the
        climate modelling centres for any errors or omissions in the climate modelling
        centres' research results, associated information and/or documentation. 5. Please
        acknowledge the use of the corresponding climate modelling centres' research
        results in any publication. 6. The intellectual property rights on the climate modelling
        centres' research results remains the property of each of the climate modelling
        centres. 7. By registering with the DDC you agree to abide by this Data Statement.</para></intellectualRights><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Taiwan</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>120.0309121</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>122.0609121</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>25.5542559</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>21.8442559</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1961-01-01</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>1990-01-01</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><contact id="1086642088611" scope="document"><organizationName>IPCC</organizationName></contact><methods><methodStep><description><para>Format (ASCII) The first and second lines of the file contain information on the
            grid size, for example: grd_sz xmin ymin xmax ymax n_cols n_rows n_months missing 0.01
            120.0309121 21.8442559 122.0609121 25.5542559 371 203 12 -9999 This is followed by 12
            monthly grids that are n_cols by n_rows in size. Each record contains n_cols (=371)
            columns longitude values, format 720i5, starting at xmin (= 120.0309121 deg) and ending
            at xmax (=122.0609121 deg) The first record starts at January, ymax (=25.5542559 deg)
            and the last record is the row for December, ymin (=21.8442559 deg). Co-ordinates
            represent the centre of each grid cell. Missing values (Antarctica, oceans and major
            inland water bodies) are assigned integer values of -9999. Units: degrees K</para></description></methodStep><qualityControl><description><para>Problems have come to light through user feedback and routine quality control in the
            Climatic Research Unit (during work towards the construction of an updated version of
            the 1961-1990 climatology). These problems range from systematic errors (for example,
            due to incorrect units being assumed for a whole country) to single-station errors.
            Errors at single stations have varying importance depending on the density of the
            surrounding network. Where the network is sparse, the station error will influence a
            larger area because of its greater spatial influence during the interpolation.
            Systematic errors arise because of varying reporting methods and units adopted by
            different national meteorological agencies (and other data contributors). The methods
            used to standardise data to a common format are discussed by New et al. (1999). Some
            problems are due to shortcomings in the standardisation methods used. In addition,
            misunderstandings (or a lack of information) about the units in which data were supplied
            means that the incorrect (or no) standardisation was used. The majority of
            problems/errors identified to date are due to confusion of units and shortcomings in the
            standardisation towards the use of common units. The climate variable with the largest
            potential for confusion is wind speed. Not only do reporting units vary between metres
            per second, miles per hour and knots; anemometer heights can vary greatly from the
            desired 10m (e.g. between 2m and 20m). The following (variable) gridded files are known
            to have either systematic or significant single station errors which potential users
            need to be aware of. The errors are present in the mean-monthly 1961-90 terrestrial
            climatology files and are thus propagated into the gridded 1901-1995 monthly
            time-series. The affected part of the globe is defined where possible. * Greenland: all
            variables The interior of Greenland is poorly covered by meteorological observation.
            This coupled with the presence of the high elevation ice cap makes interpolation of
            climate normals very difficult due to the potential for unusual lapse rates. It is
            likely that significant bias may be present with all variables for the interior of the
            landmass (e.g. diurnal temperature range and precipitation too high).</para></description></qualityControl></methods><access authSystem="knb" order="denyFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><spatialRaster scope="document"><entityName>ctdf6190.asc</entityName><physical scope="document"><objectName>ctdf6190.asc</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>6</numHeaderLines><numPhysicalLinesPerRecord>371</numPhysicalLinesPerRecord><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>space</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">http://srb2.tfri.gov.tw/srb/read2.php?file=ctdf6190</url></online></distribution></physical><attributeList><attribute scope="document"><attributeName>TDF</attributeName><attributeLabel>Temperature Difference</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Temperature Difference (degrees K)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.0001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">-9999</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">100</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale><missingValueCode><code>-9999</code><codeExplanation>numberic value</codeExplanation></missingValueCode></attribute></attributeList><spatialReference scope="document"><horizCoordSysName>GCS_WGS_1984</horizCoordSysName></spatialReference><horizontalAccuracy><accuracyReport>Unknown</accuracyReport></horizontalAccuracy><verticalAccuracy><accuracyReport>Unknown</accuracyReport></verticalAccuracy><cellSizeXDirection>0.01</cellSizeXDirection><cellSizeYDirection>0.01</cellSizeYDirection><numberOfBands>1</numberOfBands><rasterOrigin>Upper Left</rasterOrigin><rows>371</rows><columns>203</columns><verticals>12</verticals><cellGeometry>pixel</cellGeometry></spatialRaster></dataset></ns0:eml>