<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="iwang.7.6" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><title>Decolorization Treatments of Paper Industry Effluents</title><creator id="1162362186317" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Wang</givenName><surName>I-Chen</surName></individualName><organizationName>Division of Wood Cellulose, Taiwan Forestry Research Institute</organizationName><positionName>research fellow</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>53 Nanhai Rd., Taipei 10066, Taiwan</deliveryPoint></address><phone phonetype="voice">02-23039978#3701</phone><phone phonetype="fax">02-23037832</phone><electronicMailAddress>iwang@tfri.gov.tw</electronicMailAddress></creator><creator id="1162364708917" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Perng</givenName><surName>Yuan-Shing</surName></individualName><organizationName>Department of Environmental Engineering, Dayeh University</organizationName><positionName>associate professor</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>112 Shanjiau Rd., Datsuen, Changhwa 51591, Taiwan</deliveryPoint></address></creator><creator id="1162455311592" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Wang</givenName><surName>Kuo-Tsai</surName></individualName><organizationName>Division of Wood Cellulose, Taiwan Forestry Research Institute, Council of Agriculture, Executive Yuan</organizationName><positionName>assistant research</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>53 Nanhai Road, Taipei 10066, Taiwan</deliveryPoint></address><phone phonetype="voice">02-23039978#3703</phone><phone phonetype="fax">02-23037832</phone></creator><creator id="1162364563987" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Ho</givenName><surName>Chen-Lung</surName></individualName><organizationName>Division of Wood Cellulose, Taiwan Forestry Research Institute</organizationName><positionName>Assistant research</positionName></creator><abstract><para>Pulp and paper mills emit effluents that are often tainted with color substances. Most often, lignin fragments form chromophores that impart a yellow-brown color to the effluent; making colored paper also causes residual dyestuffs to infuse the effluent with colors. Despite otherwise adequate effluent parameters, the color in effluents evokes a perception of uncleanness and often leads to environmental confrontations; thus this issue needs to be resolved. In this study, we explored several means of color removal from  effluents. The results indicated that the colored substances in effluent were often difficult to agglomerate due to their small particle sizes, but adsorption using activated carbon and more cheaply, fly ash, could achieve good removal. Membrane treatment using ultrafiltration (UF) films with a molecular weight cut-off of 5000 Da could effectively remove colors from pulp mill and OCC mill effluents. Certain colored paper effluents could also be treated with good effect as well. The advanced oxidation processes (AOPs) applied to various effluents achieved mixed results, with red-dyed paper effluent showing strong resistance. Reductive treatments were effective against ligneous chromophores, but this was often not so for chemical dyestuffs. Most treatments entail high costs or residual environmental concerns. Electrochemical means including dipole induction and flocculation were found to be able to decolorize dye-stained white water, but was less effective toward the decolorization of bleaching effluent.</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>paper industry effluents</keyword><keyword>decolorization</keyword><keyword>adsorption</keyword><keyword>membrane filtration</keyword><keyword>advanced oxidation process</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><para>&#27442;&#24341;&#29992;&#26412;&#25991;&#29563;&#35531;&#24501;&#27714;&#20316;&#32773;&#21516;&#24847;</para></intellectualRights><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Taiwan</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>120.0</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>122.0</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>25.375</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>21.625</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2004-01-01</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2004-12-31</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><references>1162362186317</references></contact><methods><methodStep><description><section><title>Membrane technology</title><para>An ultrafiltration lab unit made by Chao-Chun Co., Taiwan was used to decolorize the pulp and paper mill effluents. The unit consisted of a 5-cm i.d. tubular housing having a length of 100 cm and containing a spirally wound membrane cartridge with a molecular weight cut-off of 5000 Da. During the experiments, 20 L of the effluent was prefiltered using a cotton-yarn filter module to remove oversized particles. Then at an operating pressure of 7.0 MPa, filtrate was generated at a 0.4-L/min rate, and the concentrate returned to the original container. After reaching the concentration ratio of 4:1, the filtrate and concentrate were separately collected and analyzed.</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><title>Absorption/coagulation treatments</title><para>The pulp and paper mill colored effluents were treated by adding activated carbon and fly ash at various dosages. Effluent quality before and after the treatment, particularly regarding the true color (color of the turbidity-free water) and electrical conductivity were measured. Other absorbent agents, such as bentonite powder and lime were also tested. In the coagulation and precipitation tests, aliquots of the different effluents were supplemented with various polymer coagulant and flocculent solutions in jar tests. After precipitation, the clear supernatants were analyzed for color changes. We also modified the effluent pH and repeated the tests.</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><title>Oxidation and reduction treatments</title><para>1. Advanced oxidation processes (AOPs)</para><para>AOPs are often used to modify the effluent for the purpose of decolorization. The oxidizing agents used included ozone, hydroxyl free radicals, and other oxidizing agents such as peracids and potassium permanganate. Certain AOPs use UV irradiation to activate the production of oxidizing species. Aliquots of the different effluents were placed in an aeration bottle connected to an ozone generator (OREC model 03V10-0) and ozone of a known concentration and flow rate was added. Exhausts were absorbed by a KI solution in order to back-titrate ozone consumption. Caro&#226;&#128;&#153;s acid and peracetic acid were prepared by mixing a 1:1 ratio of 35% hydrogen peroxide with concentrated sulfuric acid and acetic anhydride. Potassium permanganate was applied by direct addition and stirring. Afterward, the manganese oxide precipitate was removed by filtration. The photocatalytic method entailed adding excess hydrogen peroxide and the rutile form of titanium dioxide powder and exposing the stirred suspension to 255-nm UV irradiation. Periodical sampling of the effluent color was conducted. Other water quality parameters of the treated effluent such as COD were also measured.</para><para>2. Reductive treatment</para><para>Reducing agents such as reagent grade sodium borohydride, sodium bisulfite, sodium dithionite, and formamidine sulfinic acid (FAS) were applied to the effluents at fixed dosages for the decolorization trials.</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><title>Biological treatment</title><para>Based on the Mycor process (Chang et al., 1985), we used a rotating biological contactor (RBC) unit with an inner trough capacity of ~5 L, encased in a 30&#226;&#132;&#131; circulating water bath outer trough. The rotating discs were half submerged in the inner trough and turned at a rate of 1~2 rpm. The inner trough was connected by tubing to two 10-L Erlenmeyer flasks for effluent recirculation and replacement purposes, respectively. Initially, a nutrient-rich solution was placed in the inner trough and the recirculation flask and this was inoculated with mycelia of a white rot fungus Phanerochaete chrysosporium. A plastic hood over the inner trough provided a supply of oxygen for growth enrichment.</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><title>Electrochemical treatment</title><para>After evaluating the existing technologies, we opted to apply an electro-aggregation and flotation procedure called EPN (Environmental Protection Navigator). The treatment facility was on loan from the Department of Chemical Engineering, Tamkang University, Tamshue, Taiwan. DC electricity converted from AC electricity of 100 to 250 V and between 0.8 and 4 A was fed to a ~1.5-L treatment chamber having a set of 11 cast iron electrode plates. The electrodes could be powered with different modes of electrification. Effluent was fed in with a peristaltic pump which had a hydraulic retention time typically of under 40 s, producing a ~3 L/min flow rate. In cases where the effluent had insufficient electrical conductivity, table salt was added to enhance the electrical conductivity. After treatment, the Pt-Co color and light absorbance at 510 nm (where the effluent showed maximum absorption) of the clarified effluents were measured.</para></section></description></methodStep></methods><project scope="document"><title>Pollution Control and Recyling Studies for the Forest Products Industry</title><personnel scope="document"><references>1162362186317</references><role>originator</role></personnel><funding><para>90AS-1.4.3-FI-G1,91AS-1.4.3-FI-G1,92AS-8.2.3-FI-G1</para></funding></project><access authSystem="knb" order="denyFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataTable id="1165479776414" scope="document"><entityName>Table 1. Water qualities of various colored effluent streams before and after ultrafiltration treatment</entityName><entityDescription /><physical id="1165479774070" scope="document"><objectName>Book2-1.csv</objectName><size unit="byte">722</size><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">ecogrid://knb/iwang.34.1</url></online></distribution></physical><attributeList><attribute id="1165479776430" scope="document"><attributeName>Sample</attributeName><attributeLabel>Sample</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Sample</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>Sample</code><definition>Sample</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>Pulp bleaching effluent</code><definition>Pulp bleaching effluent</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>Pulp mill effluent</code><definition>Pulp mill effluent</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>OCC mill effluent</code><definition>OCC mill effluent</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>Golden-dye colored effluent</code><definition>Golden-dye colored effluent</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>Pink-dye colored</code><definition>Pink-dye colored</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>effluent</code><definition>effluent</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="1165479776445" scope="document"><attributeName>Blank</attributeName><attributeLabel>Blank</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Blank</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain enforced="yes"><codeDefinition><code>Blank</code><definition>Blank</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>UF</code><definition>UF</definition></codeDefinition><codeDefinition><code>UF conc.</code><definition>UF conc.</definition></codeDefinition></enumeratedDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="1165479776461" scope="document"><attributeName>pH</attributeName><attributeLabel>pH</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>a mesure of acidity or alkaliuty in solution</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.01</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="false">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="false">100</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></interval></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="1165479776477" scope="document"><attributeName>TS (mg/L)</attributeName><attributeLabel>TS (mg/L)</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>a coneeutration unit, milligram substance in a liter of liquid.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>milliGramsPerMilliLiter</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType></numericDomain></interval></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="1165479776492" scope="document"><attributeName>SS (mg/L)</attributeName><attributeLabel>SS (mg/L)</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>SS (mg/L)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>milliGramsPerMilliLiter</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType></numericDomain></interval></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="1165479776508" scope="document"><attributeName>COD (mg/L)</attributeName><attributeLabel>COD (mg/L)</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>a coneentration unit, milligram substance in a liter of liquid.</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>milliGramsPerMilliLiter</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType></numericDomain></interval></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="1165479776524" scope="document"><attributeName>PCD (&#206;&#188;eq/g)*104</attributeName><attributeLabel>PCD (&#206;&#188;eq/g)*104</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>PCD (&#206;&#188;eq/g)*104</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.01</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></interval></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="1165479776539" scope="document"><attributeName>True color (Pt-Co)</attributeName><attributeLabel>True color (Pt-Co)</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>True color (Pt-Co)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>number</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList><numberOfRecords>17</numberOfRecords></dataTable></dataset></ns0:eml>