<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="huangym.23.1" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><title>Reproductive biology of three Cheilanthoid ferns in Taiwan</title><creator id="1260256520953" scope="document"><individualName><surName>Yao-Moan Huang</surName></individualName><organizationName>Division of Forest Biology, Taiwan Forestry Research Institute</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>53 Nan-Hai Rd., Taipei 100, Taiwan</deliveryPoint><city>Taipei</city><postalCode>100</postalCode><country>Taiwan</country></address></creator><creator id="1260256599234" scope="document"><individualName><surName>Sheng-Yuan Hsu</surName></individualName></creator><creator id="1260256626968" scope="document"><individualName><surName>Mei-Hsueh Huang</surName></individualName></creator><creator id="1260256634812" scope="document"><individualName><surName>Wen-Liang Chiou</surName></individualName><organizationName>Division of Forest Biology, Taiwan Forestry Research Institute</organizationName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>53 Nan-Hai Rd., Taipei 100, Taiwan</deliveryPoint></address></creator><abstract><para>Reproductive biology of Cheilanthes chusana Hook., Cheilanthes hirsute ( Poir.) Mett., and Cheilanthes tenuifolia (Burm.) Sw. native to Taiwan, were observed. Results showed that C. chusana and C. tenuifolia were diploid (2n = 60) and produced 32 spore-sporangia, whereas C. hirsute was tetraploid (2n = 120) and produces 16 spores per sporangium. The spores of C. hirsute were larger than the other two species. Spore germination was of Vittaria-type, and gametophyte development was of Adiantum-type in these three species. The gametophytes of C. chusana and C. tenuifolia produced young sporophytes sexually, whereas C. hirsute produced young sporophytes apogamously. Neutral gametophytes may be regarded as an immature individual and smaller size than other sexual gametophytes within C. chusana and C. tenuifolia. However, neutral gametophytes not only had the potential to produce sporophyte but also had the same developmental size with female and hermaphroditic gametophytes in C. hirsute. In addition, the life span may be associated with reproductive system, apogamous species had shorter gametophyte life span, e.g. 6 weeks in apogamous C. hirsute, 10 weeks in sexual C. chusana, and 12 weeks in sexual C. tenuifolia.</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>Cheilanthes chusana</keyword><keyword>Cheilanthes hirsute</keyword><keyword>Cheilanthes tenuifolia</keyword><keyword>gametophyte</keyword><keyword>reproduction</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><para>&#28961;&#20351;&#29992;&#27402;&#38480;&#21046;</para></intellectualRights><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Sporophytes were collected from Taiwan. Cilan, Ilan (Cheilanthes chusana); Nanhwa, Chiayi (C. tenuifolia) ;Fukang, Taitung (C. hirsuta)</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>119.375</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>122.5</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>25.5</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>21.375</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2007</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2008</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage><taxonomicCoverage scope="document"><taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName><taxonRankValue>hirsute</taxonRankValue></taxonomicClassification><taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName><taxonRankValue>Cheilanthes</taxonRankValue><taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName><taxonRankValue>chusana</taxonRankValue></taxonomicClassification></taxonomicClassification><taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName><taxonRankValue>Cheilanthes</taxonRankValue><taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName><taxonRankValue>tenuifolia</taxonRankValue></taxonomicClassification></taxonomicClassification></taxonomicCoverage></coverage><contact id="1260256690953" scope="document"><individualName><surName>Wen-Liang Chiou</surName></individualName></contact><methods><methodStep><description><section><title>Cytology</title><para>Sporophytes were collected from Taiwan (Table 1). They were transplanted to the fern greenhouse of the Taiwan Forestry Research Institute. After 1 month in cultivation, the root tips of sporophytes were pretreated for 3-4 h with a mixture of 70 ppm cycloheximide and 250 ppm 8-hydroxyquinoline (1:1) at about 18-20&#8451;. The root tips were fixed for 1-3 h in a mixture of 45 % acetic acid and absolute ethanol (1:3) at about 20 &#8451;, and then preserved in 70 % ethanol at 4 &#8451;. Then they were macerated for 1-3 min in 1 N HCl at 60 &#8451;, washed for 10 sec and digested for 1-2 h in 4 % pectinase. Finally, the root tips were squashed in modified Sharma&#8217;s solution (Sharma, 1982). The number of chromosomes in root-tip cells was observed with light microscopes (Leitz, Dialux 20) and photographed with a digital camera (Nikon, Coolpix 995).</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><title>Spore number and size</title><para>To determine the number of spores per sporangium, fresh fronds with mature sporangia were collected, and 10 randomly selected sporangia from each sporophyte were sampled. Fronds were air-dried for 2 days to release spores. The frequency of normal spores was determined by randomly sampling 400 spores from each sporophyte. The size (the average length of 3 equatorial axes) of 100 randomly selected normal spores from each plant was measured under a microscope (Leica, Wild M8).</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><title>Gametophyte</title><para>To observe the sexual expression of gametophytes, spores being collected from sporophytes were sown directly on medium (vermiculite: peat: perlite = 4: 4: 2). All cultures were maintained under white fluorescent illumination of ca. 24 &#956;mole m-2s-1 for 12 hd-1. The temperature ranged from 20 to 28 &#8451;.</para><para>The sexual expression, age, and size of 100 randomly selected gametophytes from each plant were recorded every two weeks.</para><para>The morphology of gametophytes of and young sporophytes was observed with naked eyes and light microscopy (Leica, Wild M8; Leitz, Dialux 20), and photographs were taken with a digital camera (Nikon, Coolpix 995).</para></section></description></methodStep></methods><access authSystem="knb" order="denyFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access></dataset></ns0:eml>