<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="cpwang.3.39" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><title>Soil respiration in a subtropical montane cloud forest in Taiwan</title><creator id="1228372789769" scope="document"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation><givenName>Shih-Chieh</givenName><surName>Chang</surName></individualName><organizationName>National Dong Hwa University</organizationName><positionName>&#21103;&#25945;&#25480;</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Natural Resources, National Dong Hwa University</deliveryPoint><city>Hualien</city><postalCode>974</postalCode><country>Taiwan</country></address><electronicMailAddress>scchang@mail.ndhu.edu.tw</electronicMailAddress></creator><creator id="1259290024221" scope="document"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation><givenName>Chiao-Ping</givenName><surName>Wang</surName></individualName><organizationName>Taiwan Forestry Research Institute</organizationName><positionName>&#21103;&#30740;&#31350;&#21729;Associate Researcher</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>&#21335;&#28023;&#36335;53&#34399;</deliveryPoint><city>&#21488;&#21271;&#24066;</city><postalCode>100</postalCode><country>Taiwan</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">+886-2-23039978=&gt;2907</phone><electronicMailAddress>cpwang@tfri.gov.tw</electronicMailAddress></creator><associatedParty id="1259290024223" scope="document"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation><givenName>Chiao-Ping</givenName><surName>Wang</surName></individualName><organizationName>Taiwan Forestry Research Institute</organizationName><positionName>&#21103;&#30740;&#31350;&#21729;Associate Researcher</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>&#21335;&#28023;&#36335;53&#34399;</deliveryPoint><city>&#21488;&#21271;&#24066;</city><postalCode>100</postalCode><country>Taiwan</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">+886-2-23039978=&gt;2907</phone><electronicMailAddress>cpwang@tfri.gov.tw</electronicMailAddress><role>Content Provider</role></associatedParty><associatedParty id="1260954581465" scope="document"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation><givenName>Shih-Chieh</givenName><surName>Chang</surName></individualName><organizationName>National Dong Hwa University</organizationName><positionName>&#21103;&#25945;&#25480;</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Institute of Natural Resources, National Dong Hwa University</deliveryPoint><city>Hualien</city><postalCode>974</postalCode><country>Taiwan</country></address><electronicMailAddress>scchang@mail.ndhu.edu.tw</electronicMailAddress><role>Principal Investigator</role></associatedParty><abstract><para>Tropical/subtropical montane cloud forests (TMCFs) are ecosystems that are less known about their carbon budgets. Especially little information is available about the soil CO2 efflux from these ecosystems, although they have been proved to have special hydrological regime which might be important in controlling soil respiration. In this study, we used an automatic chamber system to measure soil respiration rates at the Chi-Lan Mountain forest site. The half-hourly dataset was used for analyzing the controlling factors and mechanisms of soil respiration. On the other hand a manipulation experiment was conducted in the field by applying 3-fold and 1-fold aboveground litter to soil surface and the respective soil respiration rates were measured using static alkali chamber method. The results showed that soil respiration rates have a positive exponential correlation with soil temperature and a negative exponential correlation with soil water content. An empirical model relating soil respiration (Rs) to soil temperature (T) and soil water content (&#952;) is Rs = -0.095 + e(0.88+0.10T-6.99&#952;) with R2=0.83. The annual soil respiration rate calculated using this model was 176 g C m-2 y-1. This extremely low value might be caused by the permanently high soil moisture and the relative lower mean annual temperature compared to other sites that receive similar amount of precipitation. The 3-fold and 1-fold litter treatments result in significantly higher soil CO2 efflux compared to the no litter chambers. The magnitude of difference diminished to minor after six months of treatment. About 10% of the annual soil respiration was contributed by the mineralization of fresh aboveground litter. The carbon mass loss of the decomposing litter during the first six months was mainly due to leaching of dissolved organic carbon (72%) and secondly due to mineralization to CO2. From the results of this study we hypothesized that the TMCFs may be vulnerable to global warming since the drying of the soil may change the soil from carbon sink to carbon source and release the soil organic carbon that has been stored for long time.</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>soil respiration</keyword><keyword>tropical montane cloud forest</keyword><keyword>Chamaecyparis</keyword><keyword>litter decomposition</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><para>&#24341;&#29992;&#25991;&#31456;&#38656;&#35387;&#26126;&#20986;&#34389;</para></intellectualRights><coverage scope="document"><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2005</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2006</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>&#21488;&#28771;&#20840;&#23798;</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>121.5</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>121.625</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>24.125</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>24.0</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><references>1228372789769</references></contact><contact id="1259290024226" scope="document"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation><givenName>Chiao-Ping</givenName><surName>Wang</surName></individualName><organizationName>Taiwan Forestry Research Institute</organizationName><positionName>&#21103;&#30740;&#31350;&#21729;Associate Researcher</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>&#21335;&#28023;&#36335;53&#34399;</deliveryPoint><city>&#21488;&#21271;&#24066;</city><postalCode>100</postalCode><country>Taiwan</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">+886-2-23039978=&gt;2907</phone><electronicMailAddress>cpwang@tfri.gov.tw</electronicMailAddress></contact><methods><methodStep><description><section><title>Site description</title><para>The field work of this study was conducted at the Chi-Lan Mountain (CLM) site (24&#176;35&#8217;N, 121&#176;25&#8217;E).</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><title>Soil respiration measurements</title><para>Soil respiration was measured using an automated soil CO2 flux system (LI-8100, LI-COR, USA) equipped with a long-term chamber (Model 8100-101) that can be operated continuously in the field and thus may provide soil respiration data in high temporal resolution. To select an adequate plot for the placement of the long-term soil respiration chamber, the spatial variation of soil respiration rate was assessed in the preliminary test using static alkali method (Anderson, 1982).</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><title>Preliminary tests for determination of spatial variations</title><para>The static chambers for the episodic measurements of soil respiration are made of transparent acrylic (internal diameter 29 cm, height 20 cm) with removable lids. 10 chambers were randomly placed on the forest floor within a 30-m radius close to the meteorological tower. The places above fallen logs and bare rocks were avoided. The chambers were only slightly pressed into the forest floor to prevent cutting of plant roots that are densely distributed in the organic layer. The loamy texture and high moisture content of this site might minimize the error coming from lateral diffusion (Davidson et al., 2002). The border of the chamber was carefully sealed from outside with organic layer material taken from the nearby forest floor. The tightness of the chamber was checked every time before the measurements were made. The 1 N NaOH used for absorbing CO2 was placed in plastic vials that occupied 8% of soil surface within the chamber, which, might suitably prevent the underestimation indicated by Raich and Nadelhoffer (1989). The NaOH vials were further placed 2 cm above ground on a small frame such that the vials will not directly cover the soil surface. In March 2005 the static chambers were installed and left in the field without lids. The ground plants, when exist, were carefully removed with little perturbation of the soil. One month later, measurements were done in April 28, May 12, and May 26, 2005. Each time, the vials with NaOH were placed in the chamber and the lids were placed on top of the chambers. A blank test was performed in parallel with the 10 chambers using the same set-up but the chamber was closed on the bottom. The measurements usually started between 13:00 and 15:00 and lasted for 24 hr. The processing of the 11 chambers (soil respiration + blank) could be finished within 20 min. The titration of NaOH was performed in the laboratory within 24 hr and the soil respiration rates were calculated. From the results of statistical analysis of the preliminary tests, one most suitable place that represents the mean soil respiration of the site was chosen and the LI-8100 long-term chamber was set-up on it.</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><title>Long-term measurement</title><para>The LI-8100 soil respiration system measures CO2 concentration in a non-dispersive infrared (NDIR) gas analyzer. An integrated pump circulates the headspace air from the chamber to the analyzer during the closed state of the chamber and the CO2 concentration data as well as the calculated flux rates are recorded in the system. A PVC soil collar (inner diameter 20.3 cm) was installed on the soil surface. Like the static chamber, the soil collar was not much pressed into the organic layer but kept gas-tight using organic layer material. During the measurement, the moving dome covers the soil collar and the total volume of chamber is 5700 cm3. The system was operated from December 2005 to September 2006 and the soil respiration was measured every 30 min with 5-min closure of the chamber. Every 14 days the system was stopped for data collection and for the routine maintenance of the chamber system.</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><title>Meteorological data collection</title><para>As part of the monitoring parameters of the site, soil temperature (Mingguan, Taiwan) at 10 cm depth and soil water content (ML2x, Delta-T, UK) at 10 cm depth are available for the study period. Data of these sensors are recorded as 10-min averages and stored in datalogger (DL2e, Delta-T, UK).</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><title>Effect of aboveground litter on soil respiration</title><para>Since August 2003, aboveground litterfall was collected at the study site using 10 litter traps (50 * 50 cm2) that were arranged on a 100-m transect with 10-m spaces. The litterfall was collected biweekly and the samples were identified and determined for their dry mass and chemical composition. The annual leaf litterfall was 4300 kg ha-1 y-1 for the year 2004.</para></section></description></methodStep></methods><access authSystem="knb" order="denyFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataTable id="1260422371968" scope="document"><entityName>CLM_Soil_Resp_Raw.xls - Sheet1</entityName><physical scope="document"><objectName>CLM_Soil_Resp_Raw.xls - Sheet1</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution id="1260422371983" scope="document"><online><url function="download">ecogrid://knb/cpwang.73.2</url></online></distribution></physical><attributeList><attribute id="1260422371999" scope="document"><attributeName>Sampling time</attributeName><attributeDefinition>&#21462;&#27171;&#26085;&#26399;&#33287;&#26178;&#38291;</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">String</storageType><measurementScale><datetime><formatString>YYYY/MM/DD</formatString><dateTimeDomain><bounds><minimum exclusive="true">2006/07/01</minimum><maximum exclusive="true">2006/07/31</maximum></bounds></dateTimeDomain></datetime></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="1260422372014" scope="document"><attributeName>Soil Respiration</attributeName><attributeDefinition>soil respiration rate</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">String</storageType><measurementScale><interval><unit><customUnit>mgperhour</customUnit></unit><precision>0.1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></interval></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="1260422372030" scope="document"><attributeName>Soil Temperature</attributeName><attributeDefinition>soil temperature</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">String</storageType><measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></ratio></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="1260422372046" scope="document"><attributeName>Soil Water Content</attributeName><attributeDefinition>soil water content</attributeDefinition><storageType typeSystem="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">String</storageType><measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>cubicCentimetersPerCubicCentimeters</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.001</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType></numericDomain></interval></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList><numberOfRecords>1418</numberOfRecords></dataTable></dataset><additionalMetadata><unitList><unit id="mg" multiplierToSI="" name="mg" parentSI="molesPerCubicMeter" unitType="amountOfSubstanceConcentration"><description>mg</description></unit></unitList></additionalMetadata><additionalMetadata><unitList><unit id="mgperhour" multiplierToSI="0.001" name="mgperhour" parentSI="kilogramsPerSecond" unitType="massFlux"><description>mgperhour</description></unit></unitList></additionalMetadata></ns0:eml>