<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="zzlin.39.1" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><title>Application of the Fractometer for crushing strength: Juvenile-mature wood demarcation in Taiwania (Taiwania cryptomerioids Hay)</title><creator id="1167978389083" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Cheng-Jung</givenName><surName>Lin</surName></individualName><organizationName>TFRI</organizationName><positionName>Assistant Researcher</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Division of Forest Utilization, 53 Nanhei Rd., Taipei</deliveryPoint><city>Taipei</city><postalCode>100</postalCode><country>Taiwan</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">02-23039978#2604</phone><phone phonetype="fax">02-23035738</phone><electronicMailAddress>d88625002@yahoo.com.tw</electronicMailAddress></creator><associatedParty id="1165548453115" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Chih-Ming</givenName><surName>Chiu</surName></individualName><organizationName>Taiwan Forestry Research Institute</organizationName><positionName>Division of Forest Management</positionName><electronicMailAddress>cmchiu@tfri.gov.tw</electronicMailAddress><role>Associate</role></associatedParty><abstract><para>The Fractometer is a device that breaks a radial increment core along the fiber for the measurement of crushing strength which is a direct wood quality indicator for structural lumber. In this study, the crushing strength of Taiwania (Taiwania cryptomerioides Hay) trees using the Fractometer was investigated and the data were used to determine the position of demarcation between juvenile and mature wood. Segmented regression and variance component analysis were used to estimate the demarcation position. Upon increasing the distance from the age, the crushing strength of juvenile wood has been improved. Within-tree variations in wood properties are greater than tree-to-tree variations. In this experiment, the position of demarcation between juvenile and mature wood occurred at an approximate distance of 10.8 cm to 13.2 cm from the pith that was about 18-20 yeas of cambium age.</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>Crushing strength</keyword><keyword>Fractometer</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><para>please contact with authors</para></intellectualRights><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>site plantation</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>120.75</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>120.875</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>23.375</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>23.25</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2005-07-01</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2006-12-13</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage><taxonomicCoverage scope="document"><taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName><taxonRankValue>Taiwania</taxonRankValue><taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName><taxonRankValue>Taiwania</taxonRankValue><commonName>Taiwania</commonName></taxonomicClassification></taxonomicClassification></taxonomicCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><references>1167978389083</references></contact><methods><methodStep><description><section><title>materials and methods</title><para>Taiwania was selected to test the validity of the variance component and segmented regression analysis for crushing strength. The experimental plantation was located in compartment No.3, Liukuei Experimental Forest of the Taiwan Forestry Research Institute (TFRI). The mean annual temperature, relative humidity, and precipitation were 18.6 &#8451;, 81 %, and 1150 mm, respectively. The weather can be divided into a dry season and a rainy season. No silvicultural treatment is performed in sampling trees of this plot. The test samples were taken as each of the 19 trees in a study plantation established with a 2 m &#215; 2 m spacing and 2500 trees/ha in 1972.</para><para>We took different DBH (diameter at breast height) classes in order to understand the effect of different DBH on juvenile-mature wood demarcation (position). But, the data of suppressed trees are not ideal for strength analysis. 5 Therefore, the samples can be only classified into two types on the basis of DBH, namely, mean 33.6 cm (Type A: 8 trees) and 26.4 cm (Type B: 11 trees) (i.e. dominant trees and intermediate trees, respectively). The two DBH classes are suitable to be used as structural lumber.</para><para>An increment borer was used to cut cores 5 mm in diameter from Taiwania trees. From the eastern aspect of each sample tree, we extracted a pith-to-bark increment core specimen at DBH (same direction) in December 2003, when they were about 32 years old. The increment cores were conditioned in a controlled-environment (20 &#8451; and 65% relative humidity). The measurements were done on treated core (12% moisture conditioned for 2 months).</para><para>Assessment of the crushing strength of Taiwania was investigated by using a Fractometer. The Fractometer (Type II, IML, Germany) is a device that breaks a radial increment core for the measurement of fracture strength along the fiber. The commercially available Fractormeter was used to evaluate the crushing strength of increment cores from pith to bark per 12 mm. The schematic of the testing apparatus is shown in Figure 1. The cylindrical specimen is inserted into the jaws so that the fibers are parallel to the direction of load.</para><para>A total of 14 samples (distance from pith) from each tree (core of Type A) were studied (numbered 1.2 cm, 2.4 cm, 3.6 cm &#8230;. 16.8 cm outward from pith to the bark) and a total of 11 samples (distance from pith) from each tree (core of Type B) were studied (numbered 1.2 cm, 2.4 cm, 3.6 cm &#8230;. 13.2 cm outward from pith to the bark) for crushing strength.</para></section></description></methodStep></methods><access authSystem="knb" order="denyFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataTable id="1196649142765" scope="document"><entityName>Crushing strength</entityName><entityDescription>compressive strength</entityDescription><physical scope="document"><objectName>~deleteme50989.tmp</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">ecogrid://knb/zzlin.38.2</url></online></distribution></physical><attributeList><attribute id="1196649142781" scope="document"><attributeName>position</attributeName><attributeLabel>numbers</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>sampling position</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>position</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="1196649142796" scope="document"><attributeName>strength</attributeName><attributeLabel>crushung</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>compressive strength from core</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>mole</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.01</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="true">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="true">1000</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></interval></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList></dataTable></dataset></ns0:eml>