<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="zzlin.19.4" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><title>Relationships among selected wood properties of 20-year-old Taiwania (Taiwania cryptomerioides) trees</title><creator id="1167978389083" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Cheng-Jung</givenName><surName>Lin</surName></individualName><organizationName>TFRI</organizationName><positionName>Assistant Researcher</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Division of Forest Utilization, 53 Nanhei Rd., Taipei</deliveryPoint><city>Taipei</city><postalCode>100</postalCode><country>Taiwan</country></address><phone phonetype="voice">02-23039978#2604</phone><phone phonetype="fax">02-23035738</phone><electronicMailAddress>d88625002@yahoo.com.tw</electronicMailAddress></creator><creator id="1165548453115" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Chih-Ming</givenName><surName>Chiu</surName></individualName><organizationName>Taiwan Forestry Research Institute</organizationName><positionName>Division of Forest Management</positionName><electronicMailAddress>cmchiu@tfri.gov.tw</electronicMailAddress></creator><abstract><para>The relationships between bending properties, compressive strength, tracheid length, microfibril angle, and ring characteristics of 20-year-old Taiwania (Taiwania cryptomerioides Hay.) trees were examined. The trees came from different thinning and pruning treatments, but the practices showed no significant effect on the investigated properties. The results showed that based on comparison with the literature, plantation-grown immature Taiwania have noticeably lower average strength properties than mature trees of the same species. Wood density and bending and compressive strengths were not related to either tracheid length or microfibril angle in young Taiwania. There were positive relationships between bending strength and compressive strength. The wood density, ring width, earlywood width, earlywood density, and latewood percentage were the most important predictors of strength by simple linear regressions. The wood density and ring width/ earlywood width may be considered as indicators for assessing the bending strength, while wood density and latewood percentage were the best predictors of compressive strength
by multiple linear regressions.</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>Taiwania</keyword></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword>Bending strength</keyword></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword>Compressive strength</keyword></keywordSet><intellectualRights><para>contact with Dr. lin</para></intellectualRights><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>sourthern Taiwan</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>120.625</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>120.75</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>23.5</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>23.375</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><singleDateTime><calendarDate>2006-11-16</calendarDate></singleDateTime></temporalCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2006-01-03</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2006-11-29</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><references>1167978389083</references></contact><methods><methodStep><description><section><title>methods</title><para>The study plantation was planted at a rate of 1750 trees/ha</para><para>(initial spacing) in 1980. Thinning (811&#8211;1528 trees/ha) and pruning (3.6&#8211;4.5 m) treatments were implemented in 1990.</para><para>The study site is located in the no. 12 compartment of the Liukuei Experimental Forest of the Taiwan Forestry</para><para>Research Institute (TFRI), Kaohsiung Country, southern Taiwan. The diameter and height of each tree on the 27 small</para><para>plots were investigated and measured. A mean diameter from the trees was selected from each plot. In total, 27 mean</para><para>diameter trees from the stands were selected and cut for testing. The average diameter at breast height (DBH) of</para><para>test sampled trees ranged from 23.53 to 28.03 cm. The average tree heights varied from 15.2 m to 15.8 m. (Fig. 1) These trees were harvested on February 14 and 15, 2001, and were about 20 years old. One 50-cm-long log was cut from each tree where its DBH was about 80&#8211;130cm above the ground. One crosssectional disk (10 cm thick) was cut from each sample log. A diametrical strip (passing through the pith) was sawn from each disk in the same direction. The strip was cut from the disk for drilling resistance, tracheid length, and microfibril angle measurements.</para><para>In addition, a piece of cant (passing through pith) was sawn from each log (40 cm long) in an east&#8211;west direction.</para><para>Then, they were further band-sawn into specimens by the cant sawing method, as shown in Fig. 2.</para><para>Only the nine outermost growth rings (about 3 specimens and diametrical strips) near the bark of the trees were</para><para>taken and used to assess the selected wood properties. This is because the trees were sampled 9 years after thinning and pruning treatments. The cambium age of the sample specimens was 12&#8211;20 years old (from different silvicultural regimes).</para><para>All small clear specimens [32 (long) &#215; 1.5 (wide) &#215;1.5 cm (thick) and 3 (long) &#215; 1.5 (wide) &#215; 1.5 cm (thick)] were cut from the 40-cm-long cant for the bending and compressive tests. Thus, more than a total of 324 specimens were measured (27 trees &#215; more than 6 specimens &#215; 2 tests) for two strength tests. All specimens were conditioned in a</para><para>controlled environment room at 20&#176;C and 65% relative humidity such that the wood had a moisture content of 12%.</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><title>methods</title><para>A commercially available ultrasonic testing tool was  used to evaluate the ultrasonic wave velocity and dynamic</para><para>modulus of elasticity. Then, specimens [32 (long) &#215; 1.5 (wide) &#215; 1.5 cm (thick)] were also measured using an ultrasonic</para><para>wave technique for longitudinal transmission; the ultrasonic wave apparatus (Sylvatest-duo, 22kHz; Swiss Products) included a transmitting transducer and receiving transducer. The ultrasonic wave velocity (V) and the dynamic</para><para>modulus of elasticity (DMOE) were calculated in this experiment.</para><para>All diametric strips of Taiwania were subjected to the drilling resistance test, tracheid length, and microfibril angle</para><para>measurement. These strips were chosen from same product lot and experimental methods were taken from the same</para><para>techniques used in previous studies.6,17 Resistograph measurements were made on specimens (strips, at ca. 12% moisture content) in the radial direction.</para><para>The annual ring contours were marked on a chart for tree ring and control parameters, including the average tree-ring</para><para>width (RW), earlywood width (EW), latewood width (LW), tree-ring density (RD), earlywood density (EWD), latewood</para><para>density (LWD), highest density (HD), lowest density (LD), and latewood percentage (LWP) in a ring.</para><para>Bending and compressive methods for wood strength determination were in accordance with CNS 45420 and CNS</para><para>453,21 respectively. Static bending tests were conducted in accordance with the center-loading method for specimens</para><para>using a universal test machine (UH-10A; Shimadzu, Kyoto, Japan). All specimens were loaded flatwise, and the span</para><para>was 26cm in the bending tests. The proportional limit, ultimate load, and deflection were obtained from the load&#8211;</para><para>deflection curves, and the modulus of elasticity (MOE) and modulus of rupture (MOR) were calculated. Moreover, the</para><para>compressive strength in the longitudinal direction to the grain of a test specimen was evaluated.</para></section></description></methodStep></methods><access authSystem="knb" order="denyFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataTable id="1194069995765" scope="document"><entityName>coefficients</entityName><physical scope="document"><objectName>~deleteme10936.tmp</objectName><dataFormat><textFormat><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">ecogrid://knb/zzlin.18.3</url></online></distribution></physical><attributeList><attribute id="1194069995781" scope="document"><attributeName>Y</attributeName><attributeLabel>parameter 1</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Y = aX + b linear regression</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Yvalues</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="1194069995796" scope="document"><attributeName>X</attributeName><attributeLabel>parameter 2</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Y = aX + b</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>X</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="1194069995812" scope="document"><attributeName>a</attributeName><attributeLabel>contest</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Y = aX +b</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>mole</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.01</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="true">-100</minimum><maximum exclusive="true">100</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></interval></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="1194069995828" scope="document"><attributeName>b</attributeName><attributeLabel>contest 2</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Y = aX + b</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>mole</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.01</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="true">-100</minimum><maximum exclusive="true">400</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></interval></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="1194069995843" scope="document"><attributeName>R2</attributeName><attributeLabel>values</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>coefficient of determination</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>mole</standardUnit></unit><precision>0.01</precision><numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType><bounds><minimum exclusive="true">0</minimum><maximum exclusive="true">1</maximum></bounds></numericDomain></interval></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="1194069995859" scope="document"><attributeName>Fvalue</attributeName><attributeLabel>significant</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Fvalues and signifiacnt</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>measurement and significant</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList></dataTable></dataset></ns0:eml>