<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="shunyingchen.22.9" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 eml.xsd"><dataset scope="document"><title>Dormancy and germination in seeds of the medicinal Asian tree species Phellodendron amurense var. wilsonii (Rutaceae)--Effect of stratification on germination</title><creator id="1164360854796" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Ching-Te</givenName><surName>Chien</surName></individualName><organizationName>Taiwan Forestry Research Institute</organizationName><positionName>Researcher</positionName></creator><creator id="1163643518900" scope="document"><individualName><givenName>Shun-Ying</givenName><surName>Chen</surName></individualName><organizationName>Taiwan Forestry Research Institute</organizationName><positionName>Assisant Researcher</positionName><address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>53 Nan-hai. Rd., Taipei</deliveryPoint><city>Taipei</city><country>Taiwan</country></address><electronicMailAddress>sychen@tfri.gov.tw</electronicMailAddress></creator><abstract><para>The effects of alternating temperatures, cold stratification and gibberellic acid (GA3) on seed germination of Phellodendron amurense var. wilsonii were investigated. Incubation at 35/10&#176;C or stratification at 4&#176;C prior to incubation of freshly harvested seeds significantly increased germination percentages from 5% to 87%. Germination percentage was increased only slightly in intact seeds treated with up to 2000 ppm GA3. However, partial removal of the seed coat by mechanical scarification plus GA3 resulted in a drastic increase in both germination percentage and rate. Storage in liquid nitrogen for &#195;&#162;&#194;&#137;&#194;&#165; one month enhanced germination percentage, and the beneficial action was due to cracking of the seed coat. Embryos excised from their enclosing tissues and embryos surrounded by endosperm germinated to a much higher percentage than intact seeds, indicating that the water-permeable seed coat plays a mechanical role in preventing radicle protrusion in nontreated intact seeds. Seeds required three months of cold stratification to break dormancy, and GA3 promoted seed germination. We conclude that seeds of P. amurense var. wilsonii have physiological dormancy.</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>Phellodendron amurense var. wilsonii</keyword></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword>Imbibition</keyword></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword>Dormancy</keyword></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword>Seed germination</keyword></keywordSet><coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Taiping Mountain</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>121.29</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>121.3</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>24.3</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>24.3</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2004</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2006</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><contact scope="document"><references>1164360854796</references></contact><methods><methodStep><description><section><title>Seed collection and preparation</title><para>Mature black fruits of P. amurense var. wilsonii were harvested from Taiping Mountain (24&#194;&#176;30'N, 121&#194;&#176;29'E), Ilan County, northeastern Taiwan, at an elevation of 1600 m in September 2004. The fruits are very oily and aromatic. Fruits harvested from natural forests or plantations should be rapidly transported to the handling place to avoid decreases in viability of the seedlots due to high temperatures in the transport-containers (Chien personal observation). Each fruit contains 3~6 seeds (average 5), but some of them are empty. Fruits were macerated by hand in water, and the empty seeds were floated off and discarded. The clean sunken seeds were used for subsequent treatments. The black seed (4~6 mm long and 2~3 mm wide) consists of the seed coat and a large dicotyledonous embryo surrounded by a small amount endosperm (figure 1). The spatulate embryo (Martin, 1946) is fully developed with a mean (&#194;&#177; SE) embryo length : seed length ratio of 0.83 &#194;&#177; 0.02 (n = 15), and it does not grow within the seed before the radicle emerges. Seed moisture content was determined with three replicates of 20 seeds and calculated on a fresh-weight basis after oven drying for 17 hours at 103&#194;&#176;C (ISTA, 1999).</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><title>Imbibition</title><para>Each of 20 non-scarified and scarified (cut at the point away from embryonic axis) seeds were weighed individually to the nearest 0.1 mg at time 0 and after incubation at ambient laboratory temperature (~24&#194;&#176;C) for 24 hours on Whatman no. 1 filter paper in Petri dishes moistened with distilled water. Percentage water uptake was calculated as follows: %Ws = [(Wi -Wd)/Wd] X100, where Ws = increase in seed mass, Wi = seed mass after imbibition and Wd = initial seed mass (Hidayati et al., 2000). Embryos were excised from each of 30 imbibed seeds, and then three replications of 10 embryos were weighed to nearest 0.1 mg before and after drying them in an oven at 50&#194;&#176;C for 24 hours. Percentage embryo moisture content was calculated from these data as described above for seeds.</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><title>Effect of stratification on germination</title><para>For warm followed by cold stratification, freshly harvested seeds were placed in polyethylene bags (0.04 mm in thickness) with moist sphagnum and sealed, and then they were warm-stratified for 2, 4, 6 and 8 weeks at an alternating temperature regime of 30/20&#194;&#176;C with 12 hours of fluorescent light (80~100 Mole m-2 s-1; hereafter light) at the higher temperature. These warm-stratified seeds were then given 4, 8, 12, 16 or 20 weeks of cold moist stratification at 4&#194;&#176;C. A cold stratification treatment without a warm treatment was also carried out on fresh seeds in moist sphagnum for 4, 8, 12, 16 and 20 weeks prior to the seeds being subjected to germination tests. Each stratification treatment consisted of three replications of 100 seeds each. Moisture content (MC) of the sphagnum in both warm and cold stratification treatments was about 400% of its dry mass. Germination tests using fresh seeds were performed in germination chambers at constant 25&#194;&#176;C and at 35/10, 30/20 and 25/15&#194;&#176;C (12/12 hours) in light during the higher temperature. Germination tests of warm- followed by cold-stratified seeds or of cold-stratified seeds only were performed at 30/20&#194;&#176;C, i.e. same temperature as that for warm stratification. Sphagnum served as the germination medium. Germination, i.e. radicle at least 5 mm long, was recorded weekly. Results were expressed as percentage germination after 12 weeks and as the mean germination time (MGT) in days. MGT is a measure of the rate (speed) of germination and of the sharpness of the germination peak: MGT = (total niti)/Gt, where ni = number of seeds germinated in ti days from the beginning of the test and Gt = total number of germinated seeds at the end of the test (Kotowski, 1962).</para></section></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><section><title>Statistical analysis</title><para>Radical protrusion data were transformed to percentages based on number of treated seeds. Germination (mean &#194;&#177; SE) was calculated, and means were compared by two-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) and by least significant difference (LSD) at the 5% level of significance (SAS, 2004).</para></section></description></methodStep></methods><access authSystem="knb" order="denyFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission></allow></access><dataTable id="1164694781564" scope="document"><entityName>phellod 1.csv</entityName><physical id="1164694780423" scope="document"><objectName>phellod 1.csv</objectName><size unit="byte">306</size><dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>0</numHeaderLines><recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter><attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation><simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter></simpleDelimited></textFormat></dataFormat><distribution scope="document"><online><url function="download">ecogrid://knb/shunyingchen.24.1</url></online></distribution></physical><attributeList><attribute id="1164694781580" scope="document"><attributeName>Length of stratification at 30/20&#194;&#176;C</attributeName><attributeLabel>Time of stratification at 30/20&#194;&#176;C</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Time of stratification at 30/20&#194;&#176;C (wk)</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><interval><unit><standardUnit>nominalWeek</standardUnit></unit><precision>1</precision><numericDomain><numberType>natural</numberType></numericDomain></interval></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="1164694781595" scope="document"><attributeName>Germination percentage at 4&#194;&#176;C 0 weeks</attributeName><attributeLabel>Germination percentage at 4&#194;&#176;C 0 weeks</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Stratification at 4&#194;&#176;C for 0 weeks</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ordinal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>%</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></ordinal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="1164694781611" scope="document"><attributeName>Germination percentage for 4&#194;&#176;C 4 weeks</attributeName><attributeLabel>Germination percentage for 4&#194;&#176;C 4 weeks</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Stratification at 4&#194;&#176;C for 4 weeks</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ordinal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>%</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></ordinal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="1164694781626" scope="document"><attributeName>Germination percentage at 4&#194;&#176;C 8 weeks</attributeName><attributeLabel>Germination percentage at 4&#194;&#176;C 8 weeks</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Stratification at 4&#194;&#176;C for 8 weeks</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ordinal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>%</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></ordinal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="1164694781642" scope="document"><attributeName>Germination percentage at 4&#194;&#176;C 12 weeks</attributeName><attributeLabel>Germination percentage at 4&#194;&#176;C 12 weeks</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Stratification at 4&#194;&#176;C for 12 weeks</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ordinal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>%</definition></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></ordinal></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList><numberOfRecords>7</numberOfRecords></dataTable></dataset><additionalMetadata><unitList><unit id="month" name="month" parentSI="second" unitType="time"><description>month</description></unit></unitList></additionalMetadata></ns0:eml>