<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="IC.13.1" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"> <allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset> <title>Vegetation Line Point Intercept Data, Owens Valley, CA USA 1984-2013</title>
 <creator id="1395252146786"> <individualName><givenName>Zach</givenName>
 <surName>Nelson</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Inyo County Water Department</organizationName>
 <positionName>Vegetation Scientist</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>135 S. Jackson St.</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Independence</city>
 <administrativeArea>CA</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>93526</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">760-878-0008</phone>
 <phone phonetype="fax">7608782552</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>znelson@inyocounty.us</electronicMailAddress>
 <onlineUrl>http://www.inyowater.org/</onlineUrl>
 </creator>
 <abstract><para>Each year, the Inyo County Water Department monitors vegetation conditions on the floor of the Owens Valley.  The primary goal of this monitoring, according to the technical appendix to the Long-Term Water Agreement (Green Book) are to detect any &#8220;significant decreases and changes in Owens Valley vegetation from conditions documented in 1984 to 1987&#8221;.  Vegetation live cover and species composition documented during the 1984-87 mapping effort were adopted as the baseline for comparison with each annual reinventory according to the Agreement.  The reference measurements collected within individual areas mapped with similar vegetation (parcels) are referred to as baseline.

The Green Book details certain decreases and changes in vegetation community types that must be avoided under the Agreement.  Baseline vegetation communities in which evapotranspiration exceeds precipitation were classified as groundwater-dependent communities and are referred to as Types B, C, and D.  These phreatophytic communities are dependent on shallow groundwater to maintain plant populations, as precipitation alone is inadequate to meet the water demand of evaporation and transpiration (Sorensen et al. 1991, Steinwand et al. 2006).  For these parcels, according to the Green Book, &#8220;the goal is to manage groundwater pumping and surface water management practices so as to avoid causing significant decreases in live vegetation cover&#8221; and to prevent a significant amount of vegetation from changing to a &#8220;vegetation type that precedes it alphabetically (for example, Type D changing to either C, B, or A vegetation).&#8221;  The goal is to manage the effect of pumping on the depth to groundwater to maintain baseline plant communities.

To determine whether significant decreases and/or changes in vegetation have occurred, three criteria need to be met that are described in the Green Book: (1) measurability of vegetation change, (2) attributability of vegetation change to LADWP groundwater pumping or surface water management and (3) degree of significance defined by the magnitude, extent, duration and permanency of the change along with other factors including air quality, human health, impact to species of concern, etc. To avoid confusion, it is noteworthy to highlight that the standard dictionary definition of &#8220;measurability&#8221; is the degree to which something can be measured.  Vegetation of course can be measured and thus the first criteria for determining significant decreases or changes in vegetation may seem to the reader unfamiliar with the Green Book, unnecessary.  However, the Green Book assigns a different definition to the term &#8220;measurability&#8221;&#8212;defined in part as a change that is statistically significant.  Thus the first criteria, measurability, can be used interchangeably with statistical significance in the context of the technical appendix (Green Book) to the Agreement.  A main objective of the vegetation annual report is to evaluate the statistical significance (measurability) of vegetation change compared to baseline.  The second criterion, evaluating whether a statistically significant change in vegetation is caused by water management (attributability), is beyond the scope of this report owing to the need for a comprehensive analysis on a case by case basis for each vegetation parcel.  Another source of confusion may arise with the third criterion which is the &#8220;degree or significance&#8221; of environmental change.  For this criterion to be met, statistical significance is necessary but not sufficient.  As described above, there are several other factors in addition to statistical significance that must be demonstrated to evaluate the degree of significance for the third criterion.  For an example of a comprehensive evaluation of all three criteria for an individual parcel, see the report &#8220;Analysis of Conditions in Vegetation Parcel Blackrock 94&#8221; (available at www.inyowater.org).

A large proportion of groundwater-dependent parcels were mapped during baseline as Type C alkali meadows (61%), and the Agreement seeks to prevent these meadows from changing to shrub-dominated communities (Type B), a state change that is associated with increased depth to groundwater.  Alkali meadows are of special concern because small increases in depth to groundwater can decouple the groundwater from the root zone of grass species (Naumberg et al. 1996, Elmore et al. 2006).  Alkali meadow comprises 0.1% of the vegetation community types in California and 80% of alkali meadow communities are located within the Owens Valley (Davis et al. 1998).  Local management of this community type will determine the likelihood these ecosystems persist in a changing environment.  

Vegetation change across the Owens Valley was evaluated at both the valley scale and for each of 111 individual parcels sampled in 2013.  First, at the valley-wide scale we evaluated plant community cover and composition in parcels affected by groundwater pumping and for parcels that were relatively unaffected by groundwater pumping during the period of maximum pumping rate (1987-1993).  Second, we assessed whether transpiring vegetative cover differed over time for locations influenced by pumping compared to locations not influenced by groundwater pumping.  Third, we quantitatively assessed the divergence of these groups of parcels from the baseline cover values recorded from 1984 to 1987.  Fourth, we assessed whether vegetation composition in wellfield or control groups had changed from baseline values.  Lastly, since determination of significant impacts attributed to water management by LADWP is made on a case by case basis at the individual parcel scale, we (a) quantified the magnitude of change in perennial vegetation cover over the twenty-three year reinventory period, (b) assessed whether the relative proportion of woody vegetation (hereafter shrub), gramminoid vegetation (hereafter grass) and non-gramminoid herbaceous vegetation (hereafter herb) has changed compared to baseline and (c), quantified the temporal trends of vegetation composition for each parcel and evaluated what environmental factors explained the observed patterns in vegetation change.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>phreatophyte</keyword>
 <keyword>ecohydrology</keyword>
 <keyword>vegetation change</keyword>
 <keyword>1984-2013</keyword>
 <keyword>water resources</keyword>
 <keyword>line-point-intercept technique</keyword>
 <keyword>alkali meadow</keyword>
 <keyword>groundwater pumping</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <intellectualRights><para>These data are within the public domain.</para>
 </intellectualRights>
 <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Owens Valley, CA, USA</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-118.25</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>-118.0409</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>37.449</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>36.625</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1985</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate><calendarDate>2013</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact><references>1395252146786</references>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><title>Line point intercept transects</title>
 <para>Random location, random bearing, tape suspended taught, first contact recorded to species every 0.5 m for a total of 100 possible hits.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <sampling><studyExtent><description><para>Vegetation parcels that have been reinventoried since 1991 cover the entire spatial extent defined. The years 1988, 1989 and 1990 were not monitored using line point data. The reinventory of baseline started in 1991.</para>
 </description>
 </studyExtent>
 <samplingDescription><para>Each year random locations are generated in ArcGIS to conduct line point intercept transects. Hits are recorded as the first hit from every 0.5 m increment along a 50 m transect. Therefore 100 hits are possible and the number of hits translates to percent vegetation cover, which can further be subsetted by percent species or functional groups (i.e. shrub or grass).</para>
 </samplingDescription>
 </sampling>
 </methods>
 <dataTable id="1395265773281"><entityName>Transects.csv</entityName>
 <entityDescription>Line point transect data 1985-2013</entityDescription>
 <physical id="1395262596874"><objectName>Transects.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">1992109</size>
 <dataFormat><textFormat><numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
 <recordDelimiter>#x0A</recordDelimiter>
 <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
 <simpleDelimited><fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
 </simpleDelimited>
 </textFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/IC.3.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <attributeList><attribute id="1395265773282"><attributeName>Parcel</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Parcel refers to the 'vegetation parcel' used for baseline (1985-1987) vegetation mapping. Parcels were delineated by aerial photographs and interpretation or looked to be homogenous vegetation mapping units.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>BGP=Big Pine, thus BGP013 is the 13th named parcel in the Big Pine wellfield</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1395265773283"><attributeName>Year</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>The year of the reinventory</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>nominalYear</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1395265773284"><attributeName>Transect</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>The id of the transect. Transects conducted for each parcel-year varied as a function of area of the parcel. In 2013, between 14 and 36 transects were conducted in each of 111 parcels.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Just an id for the transects.</definition>
 </textDomain>
 </nonNumericDomain>
 </nominal>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1395265773285"><attributeName>Cover</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Perennial cover, # hits out of 100 possible. Here annuals have been excluded because the interest was in depth to water and vegetation cover. Annuals are predomiantly precipitation dependent.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1395265773286"><attributeName>Shrub</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition># shrub hits out of 100 possible</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1395265773287"><attributeName>Herb</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition># herbaceous hits out of 100 possible</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1395265773288"><attributeName>Grass</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>Grass hits out of 100 possible</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1395265773289"><attributeName>Herb_Shrub</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>sub-shrub and other hits out of 100 possible that didn't fit into shrub or grass. Note a very small proportion of total hits falls into this category.</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>whole</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1395265773290"><attributeName>pShrub</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>proportion of shrub= shrub hits /total hits</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1395265773291"><attributeName>pGrass</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>proportion of grass= grass hits /total hits</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 <attribute id="1395265773292"><attributeName>pHerb</attributeName>
 <attributeDefinition>proportion of herb= herb hits /total hits</attributeDefinition>
 <measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
 </unit>
 <numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
 </numericDomain>
 </ratio>
 </measurementScale>
 </attribute>
 </attributeList>
 <numberOfRecords>34441</numberOfRecords>
 </dataTable>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>