<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="paullheinrich.15.5" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"> <allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset> <title>Position-specific metabolic tracer probing of soil metabolic networks (4 of 4) - Soils Age Gradient</title>
 <creator id="1377812532960"> <individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation>
 <givenName>Paul</givenName>
 <surName>Dijkstra</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Northern Arizona University</organizationName>
 <positionName>Assistant Research Professor</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>Northern Arizona University</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>Biology Department, Building 21, Room 245</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Flagstaff</city>
 <administrativeArea>Arizona</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>86011</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">928-523-0432</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>Paul.Dijkstra@nau.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 </creator>
 <associatedParty id="1377812564660"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation>
 <givenName>Bruce</givenName>
 <surName>Hungate</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Northern Arizona University - Ecosystem Science and Society Center</organizationName>
 <positionName>Professor</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>Northern Arizona University</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>PO Box 5640, Building 21</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Flagstaff</city>
 <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>86011</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">928-523-0925</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>Bruce.Hungate@nau.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <onlineUrl>http://nau.edu/CEFNS/NatSci/Biology/Faculty-Staff/Faculty-Pages/Hungate/</onlineUrl>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty id="1377812581836"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation>
 <givenName>Joseph</givenName>
 <surName>Blankinship</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>US Santa Barbara</organizationName>
 <positionName>Postdoctoral Researcher</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>Department of Ecology, Evolution and Marine Biology</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>1108 Noble Hall</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Santa Barbara</city>
 <administrativeArea>CA</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>93106</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">(805) 893-8633</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>joseph.blankinship@lifesci.ucsb.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty id="1377812585642"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation>
 <givenName>Paul</givenName>
 <surName>Selmants</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Northern Arizona University</organizationName>
 <positionName>Professor</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>Northern Arizona University</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>School of Forestry, Box 15018</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Flagstaff</city>
 <administrativeArea>Arizona</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>86011</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">(928) 523-6600</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>paul.selmants@nau.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty id="1377812778257"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation>
 <givenName>Steven</givenName>
 <surName>Hart</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>University of California - Merced</organizationName>
 <positionName>Professor</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>University of California, Merced</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>5200 North Lake Road</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Merced</city>
 <administrativeArea>California</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>95343</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <electronicMailAddress>shart4@ucmerced.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty id="1377812962503"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation>
 <givenName>Egbert</givenName>
 <surName>Schwartz</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Northern Arizona  University</organizationName>
 <positionName>Professor</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>Northern Arizona University</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>Biology department, Room 250</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Flagstaff</city>
 <administrativeArea>Arizona</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>86011</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">(928) 523-6168</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>egbert.schwartz</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <associatedParty id="1377812973345"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation>
 <givenName>George</givenName>
 <surName>Koch</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Northern Arizona University</organizationName>
 <positionName>Professor</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>Northern Arizona University - Department of Biology</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>Biology Department, Room 243</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Flagstaff</city>
 <administrativeArea>Arizona</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>86011</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">(928) 523-7150</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>George.Koch@nau.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Content Provider</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <abstract><para>In order to study controls on metabolic processes in soils, we determined the dynamics of 13CO2 production from two position-specific 13C-labeled pyruvate isotopologues in the presence and absence of glucose, succinate, pine, and legume leaf litter, and under anaerobic conditions. We observed that the C from the carboxyl group (C1) of pyruvate was lost as CO2 much faster than its other C atoms (C2,3). Addition of glucose, pine and legume leaf litter reduced the ratio between 13CO2 production from 1-13C pyruvate and 2,3-13C pyruvate (C1/C2,3 ratio), whereas anaerobic conditions increased this ratio. We interpret a low C1/C2,3 ratio as an indication of increased Krebs cycle activity in response to carbon inputs, while a higher ratio implies a reduced Krebs cycle activity in response to anaerobic conditions. Succinate, a gluconeogenic substrate, reduced 13CO2 production from pyruvate to near zero, likely reflecting increased carbohydrate biosynthesis from
Krebs cycle intermediates. The difference in 13CO2 production rate from pyruvate isotopologues disappeared 4-5 days after pyruvate addition, indicating that C positions were scrambled by ongoing soil microbial transformations. This work demonstrates that metabolic tracers such as pyruvate can be used to determine qualitative aspects of C flux patterns through metabolic pathways of soil microbial communities.
This is 1 of 4 related datasets for this study.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>Stable isotopes; Carbon; C and N availability; Soil microbial biomass; C metabolism</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet><keyword>age gradient</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <intellectualRights><para>Merriam-Powell Center for Environmental Research Data Access Policy, Data Access Requirements, and General Data Use Agreement
This data policy document is based on the Long Term Environmental Research (LTER) Network data policy approved by the LTER Coordinating Committee April 6, 2005 
Merriam-Powell Center for Environmental Research (MPCER) Data Access Policy 
The MPCER data policy includes three specific sections designed to express shared network policies regarding the release of MPCER data products, user registration for accessing data, and the licensing agreements specifying the conditions for data use. 
MPCER Data Release Policy 
Data and information derived from publicly funded research, totally or partially from MPCER funds from NSF, Institutional Cost-Share, or Partner Agency or Institution where a formal memorandum of understanding with MPCER has been established, are made available online with as few restrictions as possible, on a nondiscriminatory basis. MPCER scientists should make every effort to release data in a timely fashion and with attention to accurate and complete metadata. 
Data 
There are two data types: 
Type I &#226;&#128;&#147; data are to be released to the general public according to the terms of the general data use agreement (see Section 3 below) within 2 years from collection and no later than the publication of the main findings from the dataset and, 
Type II - data are to be released to restricted audiences according to terms specified by the owners of the data. Type II data are considered to be exceptional and should be rare in occurrence. The justification for exceptions must be well documented and approved by the lead PI and MPCER Data Manager (Paul Heinrich). Some examples of Type II data restrictions may include: locations of rare or endangered species, data that are covered under prior licensing or copyright (e.g., SPOT satellite data), or covered by the Human Subjects Act. Researchers that make use of Type II Data may be subject to additional restrictions to protect any applicable commercial or confidentiality interests. 
While the spirit of this document is to promote maximum availability for ecological data in either Type I or II status, there are criteria by which priority for data release may be determined. Primary observations collected for core research activities directly supported by MPCER research must receive the highest priority for data release. Data collected by other sources to which MPCER supported research has added value is also a high priority Other types of data including non-MPCER data that was acquired for MPCER research, student thesis data, schoolyard MPCER data, or legacy data that already suffer from inadequate documentation or format obsolescence may be ranked a lower priority by a site with justifications provided in their data management policy. Finally, some data may be determined of lowest priority for archiving on the grounds that they are interim data that led to final products that carry the scientific value. These might include data files created during stages within an analytic workflow, raw or replicate data values that were subsequently aggregated or processed for release, or individual outputs from stochastic models. 
Metadata 
1.	Metadata documenting archived/online data sets of all types listed above will be made available when, or before, the dataset itself is released according to the terms above.
2.	All metadata will be publicly available regardless of any restrictions on access to the data.
3.	All metadata will follow MPCER recommended standards and will minimally contain adequate information on proper citation, access, contact information, and discovery. Complete information including methods, structure, semantics, and quality control/assurance is expected for most datasets and is strongly encouraged. Whenever possible Federal Geographic Data Committee standard metadata will be used. 
MPCER Network Data Access Requirements
The access to all MPCER data is subject to requirements set forth by this policy document to enable data providers to track usage, evaluate its impact in the community, and confirm users' acceptance of the terms of acceptable use. These requirements are standardized within MPCER to provide contractual exchange of data between Data Providers and Data Users that can be encoded into electronic form and exchanged between computers. This will allow direct access to data via a common portal once these requirements have been fulfilled. The following information may be required directly or by proxy prior to the transference of any data object:
Registration
1. Name
2. Affiliation
3. Email Address
4. Full Contact Information
&#226;&#128;&#162;	Acceptance of the General Public Use Agreement or Restricted Data Use Agreement, as applicable.
&#226;&#128;&#162;	A Statement of Intended Use that is compliant with the above agreements. Such statements may be made submitted explicitly or made implicitly via the data access portal interface. 

Data providers wishing to impose further requirements beyond these are encouraged to include them in their Restricted Data Use Agreements accompanying the datasets.
Data Use Agreements
Datasets released by MPCER will be accompanied with a use agreement that specifies the conditions for data use. For Type I data, this shall be the General Data Use Agreement (see appendix I). This document specifies general roles and the obligations and rights enjoyed by each regarding the use of most dataset released for general public use. For Type II datasets, a Restricted Data Use Agreement must be provided with the dataset that identifies the specific restrictions on the use of the data and their justification. Because these are expected to be unique to the dataset, no template is provided although in most cases the General Data Use Agreement can be modified to serve. Grounds for restricting data may include the need to restrict access to species, habitats or cultural resources protected by legislation; rights of privacy granted by human subjects legislation; or protection of intellectual, financial or legal rights over the data held by a third party. 
This policy becomes effective when approved by the MPCER Executive Committee. It may be revised by, or at the request of, the same body. 

&#226;&#128;&#131;
Appendix I:

General Data Use Agreement
Definitions
&#226;&#128;&#156;Data Set&#226;&#128;&#157; &#226;&#128;&#147; Digital data and its metadata derived from any research activity such as field observations, collections, laboratory analysis, experiments, or the post-processing of existing data and identified by a unique identifier issued by a recognized cataloging authority such as a site, university, agency, or other organization.
&#226;&#128;&#156;Data User&#226;&#128;&#157; - individual to whom access has been granted to this Data Set, including his or her immediate collaboration sphere, defined here as the institutions, partners, students and staff with whom the Data User collaborates, and with whom access must be granted, in order to fulfill the Data User's intended use of the Data Set
&#226;&#128;&#156;Data Set Creator&#226;&#128;&#157; - individual or institution that produced the Data Set
&#226;&#128;&#156;Data Set Owner&#226;&#128;&#157; &#226;&#128;&#147; individual or institution that holds intellectual property rights to the dataset. Note that this may or may not be defined as a legal copyright. If no other party is designated in the metadata as Data Set Owner, it may be presumed that these rights are held by the Data Set Creator.
&#226;&#128;&#156;Data Set Distributor&#226;&#128;&#157; - individual or institution providing access to the Data Sets.
&#226;&#128;&#156;Data Set Contact&#226;&#128;&#157; - party designated in the accompanying metadata of the Data Set as the primary contact for the Data Set.
Conditions of Use
The re-use of scientific data has the potential to greatly increase communication, collaboration and synthesis within and among disciplines, and thus is fostered, supported and encouraged. Permission to use this dataset is granted to the Data User free of charge subject to the following terms:
1) Acceptable use. Use of the dataset will be restricted to academic, research, educational, government, recreational, or other not-for-profit professional purposes. The Data User is permitted to produce and distribute derived works from this dataset provided that they are released under the same license terms as those accompanying this Data Set. Any other uses for the Data Set or its derived products will require explicit permission from the dataset owner. 
2 ) Redistribution. The data are provided for use by the Data User. The metadata and this license must accompany all copies made and be available to all users of this Data Set. The Data User will not redistribute the original Data Set beyond this collaboration sphere.
3 ) Citation. It is considered a matter of professional ethics to acknowledge the work of other scientists. Thus, the Data User will properly cite the Data Set in any publications or in the metadata of any derived data products that were produced using the Data Set. Citation should take the following general form: Creator, Year of Data Publication, Title of Dataset, Publisher, Dataset identifier. For example:
McKee, W. 2001. Vascular plant list on the Andrews Experimental Forest and nearby Research Natural Areas: Long-Term Ecological Research. Corvallis, OR: Forest Science Data Bank: SA002. [Database]. http://www.fsl.orst.edu/MPCER/data/abstract.cfm?dbcode=SA002. (21 October 2004)
4 ) Acknowledgement. The Data User should acknowledge any institutional support or specific funding awards referenced in the metadata accompanying this dataset in any publications where the Data Set contributed significantly to its content. Acknowledgements should identify the supporting party, the party that received the support, and any identifying information such as grant numbers. For example:
Data sets were provided by the Forest Science Data Bank, a partnership between the Department of Forest Science, Oregon State University, and the U.S. Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station, Corvallis, Oregon. Significant funding for collection of these data was provided by the National Science Foundation Long-Term Ecological Research program (NSF Grant numbers BSR-90-11663 and DEB-96-32921). 
5 ) Notification. The Data User will notify the Data Set Contact when any derivative work or publication based on or derived from the Data Set is distributed. The Data User will provide the data contact with two reprints of any publications resulting from use of the Data Set and will provide copies, or on-line access to, any derived digital products. Notification will include an explanation of how the Data Set was used to produce the derived work.
6 ) Collaboration. The Data Set has been released in the spirit of open scientific collaboration. Data Users are thus strongly encouraged to consider consultation, collaboration and/or co-authorship with the Data Set Creator.
By accepting this Data Set, the Data User agrees to abide by the terms of this agreement. The Data Owner shall have the right to terminate this agreement immediately by written notice upon the Data User's breach of, or non-compliance with, any of its terms. The Data User may be held responsible for any misuse that is caused or encouraged by the Data User's failure to abide by the terms of this agreement. 
Disclaimer
While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and documentation contained in this Data Set, complete accuracy of data and metadata cannot be guaranteed. All data and metadata are made available "as is". The Data User holds all parties involved in the production or distribution of the Data Set harmless for damages resulting from its use or interpretation. 

Forward comments to:
Paul Heinrich
Merriam-Powell Center for Environmental Research
Northern Arizona University
Peterson Hall, Room 310
Flagstaff, Arizona, 86011</para>
 </intellectualRights>
 <coverage> <temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2009-09-01</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate><calendarDate>2010-09-01</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 <geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>The C. Hart Merriam Elevation gradient is a series of five perminat research sites arrayed along a 1556 to 2620m elevation gradinet in the San Francisco Peaks of Northern Arizona.</geographicDescription>
<boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-111.73061</westBoundingCoordinate>
<eastBoundingCoordinate>-111.42651</eastBoundingCoordinate>
<northBoundingCoordinate>35.6927</northBoundingCoordinate>
<southBoundingCoordinate>35.35393</southBoundingCoordinate>
</boundingCoordinates>
</geographicCoverage>
<geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Sunset Crater - 35 21 56.08542(N) 111 30 02.34726(W)  Sunset Crater is a volcanic cinder cone located north of Flagstaff in U.S. State of Arizona. The crater is within the Sunset Crater Volcano National Monument.  The date of the eruptions that formed the 340-meter-high cone (1,120 ft) was initially derived from tree-ring dates, suggesting the eruption began between the growing seasons of A.D. 1064&#226;&#128;&#147;1065.[4] However, more recent geologic and archaeological evidence places the eruption around A.D. 1085.[5] The largest vent of the eruption, Sunset Crater itself, was the source of the Bonito and Kana-a lava flows that extended about 2.5 kilometers (1.6 mi) NW and 9.6 kilometers (6 mi) NE, respectively. Additional vents along a 10-kilometer-long fissure (6.2 mi) extending SE produced small spatter ramparts and a 6.4-kilometer-long lava flow (4 mi) to the east. The Sunset Crater eruption produced a blanket of ash and lapilli covering an area of more than 2,100 square kilometers (810 sq mi) and forced the temporary abandonment of settlements of the local Sinagua people.[2] The volcano has partially revegetated, with pines and wildflowers. The crater is the namesake for the Sunset Crater Beardtongue (Penstemon clutei).</geographicDescription>
<boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-111.50065</westBoundingCoordinate>
<eastBoundingCoordinate>-111.50065</eastBoundingCoordinate>
<northBoundingCoordinate>35.365579</northBoundingCoordinate>
<southBoundingCoordinate>35.365579</southBoundingCoordinate>
</boundingCoordinates>
</geographicCoverage>
<geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Red Mountain -  (35.52305 N -111.87555 W) is a volcanic cinder cone located in the Coconino National Forest of northern Arizona, USA. 25 miles northwest of Flagstaff. It rises 1,000 ft. above surroundings. It has a shape of the letter "U", with its opening towards the west. Geological Survey (USGS) and Northern Arizona University scientists suggest that Red Mountain was formed in eruptions nearly 740,000 years ago.[1]</geographicDescription>
<boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-111.87555</westBoundingCoordinate>
<eastBoundingCoordinate>-111.87555</eastBoundingCoordinate>
<northBoundingCoordinate>35.52305</northBoundingCoordinate>
<southBoundingCoordinate>35.52305</southBoundingCoordinate>
</boundingCoordinates>
</geographicCoverage>
<geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Cedar Mountain -  is a mountain summit in Coconino County in the state of Arizona (AZ). Cedar Mountain climbs to 5,883 feet (1,793.14 meters) above sea level. Cedar Mountain is located at latitude - longitude coordinates (also called lat - long coordinates or GPS coordinates) of N 37.006652 and W -111.696.</geographicDescription>
<boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-111.696</westBoundingCoordinate>
<eastBoundingCoordinate>-111.696</eastBoundingCoordinate>
<northBoundingCoordinate>37.006652</northBoundingCoordinate>
<southBoundingCoordinate>37.006652</southBoundingCoordinate>
</boundingCoordinates>
</geographicCoverage>
<geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>O'Neil (O'Neill) Crater - ()   O'Neill Crater (cinder cone) is part of the San Francisco Volcanic Field which covers roughly 4700 square kilometers of Northern Arizona and contains many, many volcanic features including mountains, domes and cinder cones. Famous points of interest in the field include Sunset Crater, Mt. Elden and of course, the San Francisco Peaks.</geographicDescription>
<boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-111.46238</westBoundingCoordinate>
<eastBoundingCoordinate>-111.46238</eastBoundingCoordinate>
<northBoundingCoordinate>35.25501</northBoundingCoordinate>
<southBoundingCoordinate>35.25501</southBoundingCoordinate>
</boundingCoordinates>
</geographicCoverage>
</coverage>
 <contact id="1377812549918"><individualName><salutation>Mr.</salutation>
 <givenName>Paul</givenName>
 <surName>Heinrich</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Merriam-Powell Center for Environmental Research</organizationName>
 <positionName>IT Manager</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>Northern Arizona University</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>800 South Beaver Street, Peterson Hall Room 330</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Flagstaff</city>
 <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>86011</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">928-523-1939</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>paul.heinrich@nau.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <onlineUrl>http://http://www.nau.edu/Merriam-Powell/</onlineUrl>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><title>Main Methods</title>
 <para>Soil was sieved (2 mm mesh), air-dried and kept in the dark until used. Soil moisture content was increased to field capacity. The soil was placed inside airtight Mason jars and kept overnight in the dark. Eighteen hours after incubation started, 10 ml of pure CO2 was added to the headspace and isotope composition of CO2 in each jar was determined after 30 min. The production of 13CO2 from pyruvate was calculated from the 13C content of CO2 in the 13C-labeled incubation corrected for 13C content of CO2 from control soil. Metabolic tracers were added 60 min later, as follows: two ml of a 3.2 mmol L-1 position-specific 13C-enriched sodium pyruvate solution was added to the surface of the soil. Isotope composition and concentration of CO2 were determined before and 10, 20, 40, 60, 120 and 240 min after pyruvate addition. At each time, 10 ml of headspace air was injected into a Tedlar air sample bag and diluted by CO2-free air. The isotope composition of CO2 was measured on a Picarro G1101-i CO2 cavity ring-down isotope spectroscope. Soil respiration rates were determined over 24 h on parallel incubations. CO2 concentration in the headspace was determined with a LICOR 6262.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 <instrumentation>Picarro G1101-i CO2 cavity ring-down isotope spectroscope</instrumentation>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 <project><title>C. Hart Merriam Elevation Gradient</title>
 <personnel id="1377813172981"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation>
 <givenName>Neil</givenName>
 <surName>Cobb</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Northern Arizona University - Merriam Powell Center for Environmental Research</organizationName>
 <positionName>Director</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>800 South Beaver Stree, Room 330</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>POB 6077</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Flagstaff</city>
 <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>86011</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">928-523-6221</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>neil.cobb@nau.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </personnel>
 <personnel id="1377813183652"><individualName><salutation>Dr.</salutation>
 <givenName>Amy</givenName>
 <surName>Whipple</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Northern Arizona University - Merriam-Powell Center for Environmental Research</organizationName>
 <positionName>Director - Merriam-Powell Research Station</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>800 South Beaver Street, Room 330</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>POB 6077</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Flagstaff</city>
 <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>86011</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">928-523-8727</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>amy.whipple@nau.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <onlineUrl>http://nau.edu/Merriam-Powell/Staff-and-Affiliates/</onlineUrl>
 <role>Principal Investigator</role>
 </personnel>
 <personnel id="1377813194104"><individualName><salutation>Mr.</salutation>
 <givenName>Paul</givenName>
 <surName>Heinrich</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Merriam-Powell Center for Environmental Research</organizationName>
 <positionName>IT Manager</positionName>
 <address><deliveryPoint>Northern Arizona University</deliveryPoint>
 <deliveryPoint>800 South Beaver Street, Peterson Hall Room 330</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Flagstaff</city>
 <administrativeArea>AZ</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>86011</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">928-523-1939</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>paul.heinrich@nau.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <onlineUrl>http://http://www.nau.edu/Merriam-Powell/</onlineUrl>
 <role>Custodian/Steward</role>
 </personnel>
 <funding><para>National Science Foundation and Northern Arizona University</para>
 </funding>
 </project>
 <dataTable id="1378405802140"><entityName>Metabolic Probing (4 of 4) - age gradinet</entityName>
<entityDescription>In order to study controls on metabolic processes in soils, we determined the dynamics of 13CO2 production from two position-specific 13C-labeled pyruvate isotopologues in the presence and absence of glucose, succinate, pine, and legume leaf litter, and under anaerobic conditions. We observed that the C from the carboxyl group (C1) of pyruvate was lost as CO2 much faster than its other C atoms (C2,3). Addition of glucose, pine and legume leaf litter reduced the ratio between 13CO2 production from 1-13C pyruvate and 2,3-13C pyruvate (C1/C2,3 ratio), whereas anaerobic conditions increased this ratio. We interpret a low C1/C2,3 ratio as an indication of increased Krebs cycle activity in response to carbon inputs, while a higher ratio implies a reduced Krebs cycle activity in response to anaerobic conditions. Succinate, a gluconeogenic substrate, reduced 13CO2 production from pyruvate to near zero, likely reflecting increased carbohydrate biosynthesis from
Krebs cycle intermediates. The difference in 13CO2 production rate from pyruvate isotopologues disappeared 4-5 days after pyruvate addition, indicating that C positions were scrambled by ongoing soil microbial transformations. This work demonstrates that metabolic tracers such as pyruvate can be used to determine qualitative aspects of C flux patterns through metabolic pathways of soil microbial communities.</entityDescription>
<physical><objectName>metabolic_probing_4of4_age_gradient.xlsx</objectName>
<dataFormat> <externallyDefinedFormat><formatName>application/vnd.ms-excel</formatName>
</externallyDefinedFormat>
</dataFormat>
<distribution><online><url>ecogrid://knb/paullheinrich.25.1</url>
</online>
</distribution>
</physical>
<attributeList><attribute id="1378405802156"><attributeName>Soil Origin</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>Soil Origin</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>Site of soil origin, see metadata location section for coordinates of sites</attributeDefinition>
<measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>Sunset Crater</code>
<definition>Sunset Crater</definition>
</codeDefinition>
<codeDefinition><code>Red Mountain</code>
<definition>Red Mountain</definition>
</codeDefinition>
<codeDefinition><code>O'Neil Crater</code>
<definition>O'Neil Crater</definition>
</codeDefinition>
<codeDefinition><code>Cedar Mountain</code>
<definition>Cedar Mountain</definition>
</codeDefinition>
</enumeratedDomain>
</nonNumericDomain>
</nominal>
</measurementScale>
</attribute>
<attribute id="1378405802171"><attributeName>Location</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>Location</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>whether soil was sampled from inter-canopy space or under canopy</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>text</storageType>
<measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>interspace</code>
<definition>soil form inter-canopy space</definition>
</codeDefinition>
<codeDefinition><code>under juniper tree</code>
<definition>soil form under juniper tree canopy</definition>
</codeDefinition>
</enumeratedDomain>
</nonNumericDomain>
</nominal>
</measurementScale>
</attribute>
<attribute id="1378405802187"><attributeName>replicate</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>replicate</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>replicate number</attributeDefinition>
<measurementScale><ordinal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>1</code>
<definition>replicate 1</definition>
</codeDefinition>
<codeDefinition><code>2</code>
<definition>replicate 2</definition>
</codeDefinition>
<codeDefinition><code>3</code>
<definition>replicate 3</definition>
</codeDefinition>
<codeDefinition><code>4</code>
<definition>replicate 4</definition>
</codeDefinition>
</enumeratedDomain>
</nonNumericDomain>
</ordinal>
</measurementScale>
</attribute>
<attribute id="1378405802202"><attributeName>Pyruvate addition - position labled</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>Pyruvate addition - position labled</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>whether pyruvate was added and if so whether the C1 or C2 &amp; C3 positions were labled with 13C</attributeDefinition>
<measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><enumeratedDomain><codeDefinition><code>C</code>
<definition>control - no pyruvate added</definition>
</codeDefinition>
<codeDefinition><code>1</code>
<definition>C1 labled with 13C pyruvate added</definition>
</codeDefinition>
<codeDefinition><code>23</code>
<definition>C2 and C2 labled with c13 pyruvate added</definition>
</codeDefinition>
</enumeratedDomain>
</nonNumericDomain>
</nominal>
</measurementScale>
</attribute>
<attribute id="1378405802218"><attributeName>d13C of CO2 in headspace after (min)</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>d13C of CO2 in headspace after (min)</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>&#226;&#128;&#162;	The stable isotopic compositions of low-mass (light) elements such as oxygen, hydrogen, carbon, nitrogen, and sulfur are normally reported as "delta" (&#239;&#129;&#164;) values in parts per thousand (denoted as &#226;&#128;&#176;) enrichments or depletions relative to a standard of known composition. The symbol &#226;&#128;&#176; is spelled out in several different ways: permil, per mil, per mill, or per mille. The term "per mill" is the ISO term, but is not yet widely used. &#239;&#129;&#164; values are calculated by: 
	(in &#226;&#128;&#176;) = (Rsample/Rstandard - 1)1000
where "R" is the ratio of the heavy to light isotope in the sample or standard. For the elements sulfur, carbon, nitrogen, and oxygen, the average terrestrial abundance ratio of the heavy to the light isotope ranges from 1:22 (sulfur) to 1:500 (oxygen); the ratio 2H:1H is 1:6410. A positive &#239;&#129;&#164; value means that the sample contains more of the heavy isotope than the standard; a negative &#239;&#129;&#164; value means that the sample contains less of the heavy isotope than the standard. A &#239;&#129;&#164;15N value of +30&#226;&#128;&#176; means that there are 30 parts-per-thousand or 3% more 15N in the sample relative to the standard. 
five columns for 0, 20, 60, 120 and 240 minutes after start of experiment</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>integer</storageType>
<measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
</unit>
<precision>1</precision>
<numericDomain><numberType>integer</numberType>
</numericDomain>
</ratio>
</measurementScale>
</attribute>
<attribute id="1378405802234"><attributeName>at% of CO2 in headspace after (min)</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>at% of CO2 in headspace after (min)</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>At% is 100 * fraction of the heavy isotope divided by the sum of all isotopes in a sample

five columns for 0, 20, 60, 120 and 240 minutes after start of experiment</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>float</storageType>
<measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
</unit>
<precision>.01</precision>
<numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
</numericDomain>
</ratio>
</measurementScale>
</attribute>
<attribute id="1378405802249"><attributeName>atom percent excess after (min)</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>atom percent excess after (min)</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>atom percent excess after (min)

five columns for 0, 20, 60, 120 and 240 minutes after start of experiment</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>float</storageType>
<measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
</unit>
<precision>.001</precision>
<numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
</numericDomain>
</ratio>
</measurementScale>
</attribute>
<attribute id="1378405802265"><attributeName>umol 13CO2 after (min)</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>umol 13CO2 after (min)</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>micromol of 13C CO2 present after x minutes
five columns for 0, 20, 60, 120 and 240 minutes after start of experiment</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>float</storageType>
<measurementScale><ratio><unit><customUnit>micromol</customUnit>
</unit>
<precision>.01</precision>
<numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
</numericDomain>
</ratio>
</measurementScale>
</attribute>
<attribute id="1378405802280"><attributeName>slope (over 60 min)</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>slope (over 60 min)</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>slope of regression of &#194;&#181;mol 13CO2 against time (over 60min)</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>float</storageType>
<measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
</unit>
<precision>.01</precision>
<numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
</numericDomain>
</ratio>
</measurementScale>
</attribute>
<attribute id="1378405802296"><attributeName>R2</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>R2</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>r-squared of regression of micromol of 13C CO2 against time (60 min)</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>float</storageType>
<measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
</unit>
<precision>.01</precision>
<numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
</numericDomain>
</ratio>
</measurementScale>
</attribute>
<attribute id="1378405802312"><attributeName>pyruvate C1 /C23 ratio</attributeName>
<attributeLabel>pyruvate C1 /C23 ratio</attributeLabel>
<attributeDefinition>ratio of slopes of C1-13C pyruvate against C2,3-13C pyruvate</attributeDefinition>
<storageType>float</storageType>
<measurementScale><ratio><unit><standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
</unit>
<precision>.01</precision>
<numericDomain><numberType>real</numberType>
</numericDomain>
</ratio>
</measurementScale>
</attribute>
</attributeList>
</dataTable>
</dataset>
 <additionalMetadata><metadata><unitList><unit id="micromol" multiplierToSI=".001" name="micromol" parentSI="mole" unitType="amount"><description>micromol = mol/1000</description>
</unit>
</unitList>
</metadata>
</additionalMetadata>
</ns0:eml>