<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" packageId="knb.257.3" scope="system" system="knb"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document"> <allow> <principal>uid=knbadmin,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>all</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow> <principal>cn=knb-prod,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>all</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow> <principal>cn=esa-moderators,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>all</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow> <principal>uid=KellyV,o=unaffiliated,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 <permission>write</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow> <principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset scope="document"> <alternateIdentifier system="Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies">Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies, Environmental Monitoring Program, Low-Volume Filter Pack Air Chemistry Data</alternateIdentifier>
 <title>Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies, Environmental Monitoring Program, Low-Volume Filter Pack Air Chemistry Data</title>
 <creator scope="document"> <organizationName>Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies</organizationName>
 </creator>
 <creator scope="document"> <individualName> <givenName>Vicky</givenName>
 <surName>Kelly</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies</organizationName>
 <address scope="document"> <city>Millbrook</city>
 <administrativeArea>New York</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>12545</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">845-677-7600 ext 174</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>kellyv@caryinstitute.org</electronicMailAddress>
 </creator>
 <metadataProvider scope="document"> <individualName> <givenName>Vicky</givenName>
 <surName>Kelly</surName>
 </individualName>
 </metadataProvider>
 <associatedParty scope="document"> <individualName> <givenName>Vicky</givenName>
 <surName>Kelly</surName>
 </individualName>
 <role>associatedParty</role>
 </associatedParty>
 <pubDate>2011-03-16</pubDate>
 <abstract> <para>The Cary Institute Environmental Monitoring Program is a long-term program to monitor environmental parameters that are important to natural ecosystems. The program includes monitoring of air, precipitation and stream chemistry as well as meteorological, solar radiation and physical stream parameters. The Cary Institute also hosts sites for two additional programs: The New York State Department of Environmental Conservation Ambient Air Monitoring Program, for ground level ozone and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA), U.S. Climate Reference Network (USCRN).  For an overview of the program, visit http://www.caryinstitute.org/science-program/research-projects/environmental-monitoring-program.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>Air Chemistry</keyword>
 <keyword>Aerosols</keyword>
 <keyword>Particulates</keyword>
 <keyword>Chemistry</keyword>
 <keyword>Atmosphere</keyword>
 <keyword>Atmospheric</keyword>
 <keyword>Acid Deposition</keyword>
 <keyword>Dry Deposition</keyword>
 <keyword>Calcium</keyword>
 <keyword>Chloride</keyword>
 <keyword>Potassium</keyword>
 <keyword>Magnesium</keyword>
 <keyword>Sodium</keyword>
 <keyword>Ammonium</keyword>
 <keyword>Nitrate</keyword>
 <keyword>Sulfate</keyword>
 <keyword>Sulfur</keyword>
 <keyword>Sulfur Dioxide</keyword>
 <keyword>Nitrogen</keyword>
 <keyword>Nitric Acid</keyword>
 <keywordThesaurus>GCMD</keywordThesaurus>
 </keywordSet>
 <additionalInfo> <para>The Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies / Environmental Monitoring Program furnishes data under the following conditions: The data presented on this web page have received quality assurance scrutiny by our program, and, although we are confident of the accuracy of these data, the Cary Institute will not be held liable for errors in these data. Data are subject to change resulting from updates in data screening or models used. Data citation: The following is a standard citation for referencing data from the Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies, Environmental Monitoring Program: Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies, Environmental Monitoring Program. 2008 (or current year). Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies, Box AB, Millbrook, NY 12545, www.caryinstitute.org. Those wishing to publish data from the Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies, Environmental Monitoring Program are encouraged to contact Data Manager Vicky Kelly, kellyv@caryinstitute.org.</para>
 </additionalInfo>
 <intellectualRights> <para>other</para>
 <para>see additional information</para>
 </intellectualRights>
 <distribution scope="document"> <online> <url function="download">http://www.caryarchive.org/emp_data.html</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 <distribution scope="document"> <offline> <mediumName>digital</mediumName>
 </offline>
 </distribution>
 <coverage scope="document"> <temporalCoverage scope="document"> <singleDateTime> <calendarDate>1987-12-29</calendarDate>
 </singleDateTime>
 </temporalCoverage>
 <geographicCoverage scope="document"> <geographicDescription>The Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies is located in the Hudson River Valley near Millbrook, New York, roughly 113 km north of New York City and 24 km east of Poughkeepsie.  The precipitation and air chemistry sampling equipment as well as the meteorological and solar radiation instruments are located in a flat, open field at an elevation of 128 m. GPS coordinates for the site are: N41.785823 W073.741447. Stream gauging equipment is located on the East Branch of Wappinger Creek in the Fern Glen on the Cary Institute property. Stream samples were collected from 4 locations on the East Branch of Wappinger Creek on the Cary Institute property from 1985 to 1995.  Sample collection was reduced to two locations in 1996. One site is located in the Fern Glen with the gauging equipment (GPS coordinates N 41.78707, W 73.73317) and one site is located in the Lowlands (GPS coordinates N 41.79235 W 73.74937).</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates> <westBoundingCoordinate>0.0000</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>0.0000</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>0.0000</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>0.0000</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact scope="document"> <individualName> <givenName>Vicky</givenName>
 <surName>Kelly</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies</organizationName>
 <address scope="document"> <city>Millbrook</city>
 <administrativeArea>New York</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>12545</postalCode>
 <country>USA</country>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">845-677-7600 ext 174</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>kellyv@caryinstitute.org</electronicMailAddress>
 </contact>
 <methods> <methodStep> <description> <section> <title>Low-Volume Filter Pack Air Chemistry Data</title>
 <para>Aerosol concentrations, HNO3 and SO2 were sampled using Teflon filter packs. Three 47- mm diameter filters were placed in each filter pack: a Teflon filter (1988-February 2004 Zefluor, 2 micron, Gelman Sciences, Inc.; February 2004-present Whatman, 1 micron) for collection of aerosols, a Nylasorb 1 micron nylon filter (Gelman Sciences, Inc.) for collection of HNO3 vapor and a potassium carbonate-coated cellulose filter for collection of SO2. The cellulose filters were Whatman 41, &gt;20-25 &#195;&#175;&#194;&#191;&#194;&#189;m particle retention, coarse porosity, ASTM, 12 sec, (Whatman number 1441-047). The cellulose filters were cleaned before coating by rinsing and soaking overnight in double-deionized water. The three filters were placed in line so that the Teflon filter was exposed to incoming ambient air first, the nylon filter second and the carbonate filter last. The filter packs were placed in an inverted stainless steel pot (from 1988 - July 1993 it was an inverted plastic funnel) on a tower approximately 10 m above a mowed grass surface. A continuous flow of air was drawn through the filter pack at 3.00 lpm using a Gast, Inc. oil-less vacuum pump (model 1031, upgraded to model 1531-107B-6288 in 1998), which was regulated by a mass flow controller (Tylan General Inc., model FC280V, upgraded to model FC2604S in 1998 and to Aalborg model GFC 17 in September 2002). When the mass flow controller was off line for any reason, either a needle valve or another mass flow controller regulated flow. During this time, flow was measured using a rotameter (Gilmont Instruments, Inc., or Scienceware&#195;&#175;&#194;&#191;&#194;&#189;), and the flow measurements were corrected for instantaneous temperature and atmospheric pressure. Clean filter packs were exchanged for exposed ones every Tuesday.  The Teflon filters were extracted in 50 ml of double deionized water for 24 hours in the dark at 2 degrees C after sonication for 15 minutes. The solution was then decanted into sample bottles and analyzed at the Cary Institute for pH, NO3-, SO4-2, NH4+, Cl-, Na+, Ca+2, Mg+2 and K+ for determination of aerosol chemistry. For analytical methods see http://www.caryarchive.org/empdata/metadata/Cary_Institute_Methods_of_Analysis_v2006.pdf. Nitric acid vapor was determined by extracting each nylon filter in 50 ml of a mixture of NaHCO3 (0.28 M) and Na2CO3 (0.22 M) diluted 1:100 with double deionized water. The filters were sonicated for 15 minutes and then refrigerated for 24 hours before decanting the solutions and analyzing them for NO3- and SO4-2. Sulfur dioxide was determined by extracting the carbonate-coated filters in 50 ml of double deionized water with 2 drops of hydrogen peroxide. The filters were sonicated and extracted as described above and the resulting solution was analyzed for SO4-2. Concentrations of SO4-2 from the nylon and carbonate filters were added to determine total SO2. After 1993 all sample extractions were preserved with 2 drops of chloroform. Using the total amount of time that each filter was exposed and the average flow rate for the week, weekly concentrations of each component were calculated. For samples that returned less than detection limit concentrations, one half the detection limit was used to calculate air concentrations. Deposition velocities were estimated using a multi-layer dry deposition model (Meyers, T.P., Finkelstein, P., Clarke, J., Ellestad, T.G., Sims, P.F. 1998. A multilayer model for inferring dry deposition using standard meteorological measurements. Journal of Geophysical Research 103: 22645-22661). Weekly average deposition velocities were combined with weekly concentrations to estimate weekly fluxes. Data sets include monthly mean air concentrations, monthly mean deposition velocities and monthly total deposition. For a descriptions of variables, see variable list with units below. For variable descriptions with units, instrument make, model, dates used, sensitivity, recommended significant figures, quality assurance and quality control parameters and methods, missing value codes, go to the Cary Institute Environmental Monitoring web page http://www.caryarchive.org/emp_data.html</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <sampling> <studyExtent> <description> <para>For complete metadata go to http://www.caryarchive.org/emp_data.html</para>
 </description>
 </studyExtent>
 <samplingDescription> <para>For complete list of instruments and other metadata go to http://www.caryarchive.org/emp_data.html</para>
 </samplingDescription>
 </sampling>
 </methods>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>