<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="peggym.1003.1" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"> <allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow><principal>uid=judithk,o=SANParks,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 <permission>write</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset> <title>Termites and Fire: The burning question. The effect of different fire regimes on termite activity.</title>
 <creator id="1251807652661"> <individualName><surName>Fahiema Daniels</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>SANParks, South Africa</organizationName>
 <positionName>Independent Project</positionName>
 </creator>
 <abstract><para>This experiment was carried out in the Shabeni and Kambeni experimental burn plots
in the Pretoriuskop region of the Kruger National Park, Mpumalanga Province, South
Africa. Sampling was conducted in the annually burned and control plot of each of
the sites. Four 50m transects and a 200mx 200m quadrat was set up in each site to
get an estimate of termite density and activity. The results show that there was a
greater density of termite activity on the annually burned plot than the control plots in
both sites ( Shabeni-df=1,P&lt;.01, Kambeni- df=1,P&lt;.01). The conclusion drawn from
the results is that termites do better in fire prone areas because fires promote habitat
heterogeneity.
Samevatting: Hierdie ekperiment was uitgedra in die Shabeni en Kambeni experimentale verbrande
komplotte in die Pretoriuskop gebied van die Kruger Nasionalle Park, Mpumalanga
Provinsie, Suid Afrika. Toetsing was uitgedra in die jaarliks verbrand en kontrol
komplot van die Shabeni en Kambeni eksperimentalle komplotte. In elke kompolt
was vier 50m lyne en &#329; 200m by 200m kwadrant gestuig om &#329; idea van witmier
digtheid te kry. Die uitslae duig aan dat die digtheid van witmiere in die jaarlikse
verbrande komplotte ho&#1105;r is dan die digtheid in die controle komplotte vir die
Shabeni en Kambeni komplotte ( Shabeni-df=1,P&lt;.01, Kambeni- df=1,P&lt;.01. Die
gevolgtrekking wat van die utslae geskep was, is dat witmiere beter vorder in die
jaarliks verbrande komplotte omdat vier woonplaas heterogeneteit bevorder.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>SANParks, South Africa</keyword>
 <keyword>fire treatments, termite activity, Shabeni and Kambeni experimental burn plots</keyword>
 <keyword>Kruger National Park, South Africa</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Kruger National Park</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-90.0</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>90.0</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>45.0</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>-45.0</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2004-01-01</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate><calendarDate>2004-05-01</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact><references>1251807652661</references>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><para>The experiment was carried out in the Shabeni and Kambeni burn plots in the Kruger National</para>
 <para>Park, Mpumalanga Province, South Africa (Figure 1). The Kambeni site was sampled on the 22nd -</para>
 <para>23rd February 2004 and Shabeni site was sampled on the 24th of February 2004. The sampling times</para>
 <para>were between 0700 hrs and 1300 hrs each day.</para>
 <para>A frequently burned plot (burned annually in August) and a less frequently burned plot (</para>
 <para>where fire is excluded as much as possible). In each of the plots a direct and indirect measure was</para>
 <para>used to determine termite activity . As an indirect method, a series of four transects of 50m each was</para>
 <para>sampled in each plot and below ground activity was recorded at every meter along the transect. The</para>
 <para>termite activity for a 1m x 1m plot from the transect was assessed by estimating the percentage of</para>
 <para>termite activity. A 200m x 200m plot was set out in each plot and the amount of termite mounds in the</para>
 <para>plot was counted as a direct measure of above ground termite activity. The number of trees with termite</para>
 <para>activity was also counted in the 200m x 200m plot.</para>
 <para>A chi squared contingency test was used to determine if there was a difference in the</para>
 <para>proportion of activity in the annually burned plots relative to the control plots.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>