<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="peggym.1000.1" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"> <allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow><principal>uid=judithk,o=SANParks,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 <permission>write</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset> <title>Navigation of nocturnal flying Insects</title>
 <creator id="1251801168442"> <individualName><surName>Michael Chazan</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>SANParks, South Africa</organizationName>
 <positionName>Independent Project</positionName>
 </creator>
 <abstract><para>Nocturnal flying insects fly in a straight line by maintaining a constant angle with the
brightest light in the sky, usually the moon. The moon is always above the horizon
and therefore moonlight always strikes insects from the top and never from below.
When observing whether insects would fly to a light source shining from below them
in comparison to a light source shining from above, no insects flew to the light
shining from below, while several flew to the lights source shining from above.
Samevatting: Nagtelike vli&#235;nde insekte vlieg in &#329; reguit lyn deur &#329; konstante hoek te bly hou met
die helderste lig in die h&#7879;mel, wat gewoontlik die maan is. Die maan is altyd bo die
horison en daarvoor raak dit altyd die insekte van bo af en nooit van onder af nie.
Terwyl my ondersoek om uit te vind of insekte verkies om na &#329; lig vanaf onder of bo
te kom het ek gevind dat daar min was wat na die lig vanaf onder gekom het. Die
insekte het dikwels na die lig van bo gekom.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>SANParks, South Africa</keyword>
 <keyword>Michael Chazan</keyword>
 <keyword>Kruger National Park, South Africa</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Kruger National Park</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-90.0</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>90.0</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>45.0</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>-45.0</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2004-01-01</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate><calendarDate>2004-05-01</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact><references>1251801168442</references>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><para>My study sites were the Skukuza and Shingwetzi camps in the Kruger National Park. I</para>
 <para>conducted two trials in Skukuza and one trial in Shingwetzi. I cut out a piece of cardboard one meter</para>
 <para>in length and .4 meters in width. In the middle of the rectangle two holes 1.5 cm in diameter were cut</para>
 <para>out. In each hole I placed a flashlight pointing in opposite directs. I then taped the barrier to a wall</para>
 <para>with equal amount of wall area above and below the barrier. For each trial I observed and tallied the</para>
 <para>insects that flew towards the light from above and below. An event would only be considered if the</para>
 <para>insects flew towards the light and either touched the light source or the barrier. Each trial was one hour</para>
 <para>long and began at 20h00. The trials were completed 23 February, 24 February, and 2 March</para>
 <para>respectively. The statistics performed was a &#967;2 &#8211; test.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>