<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="peggym.992.1" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"> <allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow><principal>uid=judithk,o=SANParks,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 <permission>write</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset> <title>The habitat- based relationship between peak frequency and wing morphology in Microchiropterans of the southern Kruger National Park</title>
 <creator id="1251721049936"> <individualName><surName>aspect ratio, habitat, peak frequency, microchiroptera, wing loading, wing morphology</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>SANParks, South Africa</organizationName>
 <positionName>Faculty Field Project</positionName>
 </creator>
 <abstract><para>Our study is an analysis of the aspect ratio, wing loading and call peak frequency of five
species of microchiropterans in Skukuza, Kruger National Park. Bats were caught on
four consecutive nights in February using mist nets erected over and around water
sources. Species of bats with higher peak frequencies grouped together in our analysis
and were also characterized by low wingloadings and aspect ratios as compared with
those bats with lower peak frequencies. These characteristics are indicative of already
observed foraging strategies. Our results therefore supported the notion that bats flying
in open areas tend to have high aspect ratios and wingloadings but low peak frequencies
of calls and that bats which forage in clutter have low aspect ratios and wingloadings but
high peak frequencies of calls.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>SANParks, South Africa</keyword>
 <keyword>aspect ratio, habitat, peak frequency, microchiroptera, wing loading, wing morphology</keyword>
 <keyword>Kruger National Park</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Kruger National Park</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-90.0</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>90.0</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>45.0</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>-45.0</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2004-01-31</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate><calendarDate>2004-05-31</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact><references>1251721049936</references>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><para>Our study period consisted of four nights in February, 2004. Mist nets of 6 and 12 meters in</para>
 <para>length were erected at three sites in Skukuza camp in the southern part of Kruger National Park. At all</para>
 <para>three sites the nets were erected over water. An artificial waterhole, a pond and a public swimming pool</para>
 <para>proved to be good sites. Bats drink about twice nightly from known water sources, usually permanent</para>
 <para>ones, and therefore one would expect a better catch rate at places where they converge to drink (Taylor</para>
 <para>2000). Between four and six nets were put up each night. Bats were kept overnight. Whilst in hand the</para>
 <para>following measurements were taken from each bat; left and right forearm, head length, tail length, and body</para>
 <para>mass. The right wing was stretched out over graph paper and was photographed with a digital camera. The</para>
 <para>image was calibrated to actual size and analysed using SigmaScan Pro 5. Wing span and wing area were</para>
 <para>measured using this software. Bats were hand-released the night following that of their capture and</para>
 <para>echolocation calls were recorded using an Anabat 2 recorder and analysed in BatSound Pro 3.3 to obtain</para>
 <para>the peak frequency of each call.</para>
 <para>Aspect ratio and wingloading were calculated from the acquired measurements. These two indices</para>
 <para>of wing morphology were graphed against peak frequency using Microsoft Excel 2000.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>