<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="peggym.1021.1" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"> <allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow><principal>uid=judithk,o=SANParks,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 <permission>write</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset> <title>Influences of Three Geology Types on Herpetofauna Biodiversity in Shingwedzi Region Kruger National Park</title>
 <creator id="1252927892792"> <individualName><surName>Dax MacKay and Mary Sparks (editors) Graeme Alexander (resource person)</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>SANParks, South Africa</organizationName>
 <positionName>Faculty Field Problem</positionName>
 </creator>
 <abstract><para>Surface geology structures are the foundation upon which many biotic
community assemblages are based, supplying fine scale micro-habitats for floral and
faunal species. Herpetofauna are one of the groups which make direct use of
rupicolous habitat for various life stages such as; reproduction, food resources and
shelter. The aim of this study was to determine if the geology type of the rock habitat
is as important a factor for herpetofaunal biodiversity as is its functional structure.
Our study was conducted in the Shingwedzi region of the Kruger National Park were
we sampled rock outcrops on intrusive igneous (granite), extrusive igneous (basalt)
from and sedimentary (mudstone and sandstone) geology types. The three rock type
sites were compared for species richness, species abundance and species diversity. A
total of 20 species were recorded from a total of 139 observations of which lizard
8
diversity was highest (10 species) and accounted for the majority of captures (n =
124). No significant differences were found for richness, abundance and diversity
comparisons. Our study suggests that herpetofaunal biodiversity is not determined by
geology type and that the rock type of any particular habitat does not affect the
species expected to be found within that habitat.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>SANParks, South Africa</keyword>
 <keyword>Geology type, reptile diversity, Herpetofauna, richness.</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Kruger National Park</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-90.0</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>90.0</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>45.0</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>-45.0</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><singleDateTime><calendarDate>2006</calendarDate>
 </singleDateTime>
 </temporalCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact><references>1252927892792</references>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><para>Our study was conducted in the Shingwedzi region of the Kruger National</para>
 <para>Park from September 16-18, 2006. Herpetofauna were sampled from 10 rock outcrop</para>
 <para>sites occurring on three different geology types; intrusive igneous (granite) from here</para>
 <para>on referred to as intrusive, extrusive igneous (basalt) from here on referred to as</para>
 <para>extrusive and sedimentary (mudstone and sandstone). Four intrusive sites and three</para>
 <para>extrusive and sedimentary sites were selected and surveyed for herpetofauna, by a</para>
 <para>team of 21 individuals. Species for each site were recorded in three ways: 1) active</para>
 <para>collection which involved rock turning, and leaf and woody debris searching; 2)</para>
 <para>observations of species and 3) observations of remnant remains (shedding) over a 30</para>
 <para>minute interval. Site surveys were randomly performed at different times of the day</para>
 <para>for the three geology types. Post-sampling, sites were returned to as near to pristine</para>
 <para>condition as possible.</para>
 <para>Species richness, species abundance and species diversity were compared</para>
 <para>across the three rock types. Data were input into Primer v5 to ascertain the normality</para>
 <para>distribution and run through multi-dimensional scaling at 40 ordinations to generate</para>
 <para>an output for richness (the number of different species), abundance (the number of</para>
 <para>individuals) and diversity. We used the Shannon-Weiner diversity index which</para>
 <para>describes the evenness of abundance in proportion to the species richness. Statistical</para>
 <para>analyses were computed; using Statistica 6.0, for species richness and abundance with</para>
 <para>a one-way ANOVA test and for species diversity with a Mann-Whitney U test.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>