<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="peggym.1039.1" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"> <allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow><principal>uid=judithk,o=SANParks,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 <permission>write</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset> <title>Measuring biodiversity using habitat as a surrogate indicator: an analysis of the GRADSEC methodology</title>
 <creator id="1251713247880"> <individualName><surName>Laura Buckley (co-editor), Fahiema Daniels (co-editor), Andrew Deacon (resource person), Rina Grant (resource person</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>SANParks</organizationName>
 <positionName>Faculty Field Problem</positionName>
 </creator>
 <abstract><para>The aim of this study is to determine the effectiveness of using habitats as a
surrogate for species diversity of small vertebrates in the Kruger National Park.
Vegetation structure and abundance of various habitats were assessed in five
different catenal units. A scoring system was used to predict which reptile
species would be found in these areas and a list of species found in each area and
their relative abundances was generated. The next phase of this study will be to
ground-truth the results and thereby determine the effectiveness of using this
surrogate. We concluded by suggesting modifications to the methodology</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>SANParks, South Africa</keyword>
 <keyword>biodiversity, biodiversity indicators, surrogate, small vertebrates, reptiles</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Skukuza National Park</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-90.0</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>90.0</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>45.0</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>-45.0</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2004-01-31</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate><calendarDate>2004-05-31</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact><references>1251713247880</references>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><para>The data for this experiment were collected along a catenal sequence in the Skukuza area</para>
 <para>of the Kruger National Park, Mpumalanga Province South Africa on the ninth and tenth of</para>
 <para>February 2004. Five different catena units were sampled for this experiment, i.e. the valley</para>
 <para>bottom, sodic site (this unit was sampled twice), seep-zone, mid-slope and the crest.</para>
 <para>The data collection in each of the catenal units was the same. A 100m transect was laid</para>
 <para>down to assess the general structure and the number of different habitats along the transect. The</para>
 <para>general structure includes recording the aspect, slope, soil, animal activity, signs of small</para>
 <para>vertebrates, mammal dung and termite activity. A habitat survey was done within a five meter</para>
 <para>band on both sides of the 100m transect line. Holes, rocks, standing logs, prostrate logs, live</para>
 <para>stems, brush habitats, and litter habitats were counted as potential habitats in the survey. A point</para>
 <para>survey was done at the end of the transect where the percentage grass, forbs and tree cover was</para>
 <para>recorded, number of small trees in a 15m radius (trees with a stem diameter of less than 15m are</para>
 <para>classified as small) and number of large trees in a 40m radius was counted. The height classes of</para>
 <para>the woody vegetation and the five most common tree species were recorded for each catenal unit.</para>
 <para>Another 100m transect was laid down and the process was replicated. After the 200m transect</para>
 <para>was completed we walked for another 100m to look for specialized habitats and sample them, if</para>
 <para>there were any.</para>
 <para>A scoring system designed by Andrew Deacon was used to determine the likelihood of</para>
 <para>finding a certain species in the sampled area. The scoring system works by assigning a score for</para>
 <para>each type of habitat which is determined by the frequency of the habitat along the transect. The</para>
 <para>scoring system then gives probability scores for species that are likely to be found in each of the</para>
 <para>habitats. The habitat score is then multiplied by the species probability score. The final score for</para>
 <para>species probability was compiled and a cut off score of five was chosen, we chose this number</para>
 <para>because we wanted to be conservative and prevent an underestimation of species richness.</para>
 <para>Therefore in each catenal unit, a list of species with a score higher than five was counted as</para>
 <para>present in the habitat. The species list will be used to investigate differences between the various</para>
 <para>catenal units sampled.</para>
 <para>Primer 5 was used to get the Shannon-Weiner diversity indices for each catenal unit.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>