<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="peggym.1035.1" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"> <allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow><principal>uid=judithk,o=SANParks,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 <permission>write</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset> <title>Diets and defenses: an examination of elephant foraging selection in Mapungubwe National Park, South Africa</title>
 <creator id="1253185289214"> <individualName><surName>Nick Cuneo, Colin Donihue, Laurence Kruger (resource person), Cassandra Nu&#241;ez</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>SANParks, South Africa</organizationName>
 <positionName>Independent Project #2</positionName>
 </creator>
 <abstract><para>Elephant populations in southern Africa have dramatically increased
recently, impacting vegetation structure and reducing tree diversity. We observed
and analyzed elephant foraging behavior to determine patterns in browsing
preference for male and female elephants in three age classes in relation to forage
characteristics. Elephants selectively browsed, generally preferring mechanically
defended tree species to those with chemical defenses. Elephants targeted trees
between 4 and 8 m tall significantly proportionally more frequently than any other
size tree, lending more evidence that elephants are fundamentally changing
vegetation structure. Females tended to have more selective diets due, we
speculate, to their physiology than did males, and adults had a much greater
impact on their environment than did juveniles or infants. Elephants have a
significant effect on the vegetation structure in their environment, and the
increasing populations are cause for concern. Patterns in environmental impact
according to sex and age are necessary to inform decisions on elephant
management, while patterns regard plant susceptibility are helpful in predicting
changes in vegetation structure and composition.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>SANParks, South Africa</keyword>
 <keyword>African elephant, behavior, browsing, defenses, impact</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Mapungubwe National Park, Lim popo Province, South Africa</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-90.0</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>90.0</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>45.0</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>-45.0</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><singleDateTime><calendarDate>2006</calendarDate>
 </singleDateTime>
 </temporalCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact><references>1253185289214</references>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><para>This study was conducted in Mapungubwe National Park, part of</para>
 <para>South Africa&#8217;s National Park system (SANParks). Mapungubwe is located in northern</para>
 <para>South Africa and borders Botswana and Zimbabwe. Most of Mapungubwe is arid</para>
 <para>mopane and acacia savanna with several riparian zones around seasonal waterways. The</para>
 <para>study was conducted November 15th-17th. A table of all study sites along with their</para>
 <para>respective start times, habitats, and GPS locations is included as Appendix A.</para>
 <para>Study species. The African elephant, Loxodonta africana, is the largest mammal</para>
 <para>in Africa with adults frequently standing three meters at the shoulder and weighing over a</para>
 <para>161</para>
 <para>ton. Females and juveniles typically form matriarchal pods containing 8 to 12 individuals</para>
 <para>while males tend to be solitary and highly territorial, only visiting their pod for mating.</para>
 <para>Twenty elephants were reintroduced in Mapungubwe in 2005 after being excluded for</para>
 <para>approximately 50 years. A year later that population had risen to over 400 (L. Kruger</para>
 <para>pers. comm.). Park management has never culled the elephant population, so their</para>
 <para>demographics are not artificially skewed and the animals are relatively tolerant of</para>
 <para>observation. The majority of the elephants migrate seasonally and sometimes daily</para>
 <para>through holes in the fences to Botswana. It is clear from personal observation that the</para>
 <para>border fences do not hinder the flow of elephants. While they are fairly well protected</para>
 <para>from poachers in South Africa, their vulnerability to poaching across the border is</para>
 <para>unknown. There are several impoverished settlements in the area which might hunt</para>
 <para>elephants for food or to protect crops.</para>
 <para>Plot design. We defined a vegetation-sampling plot as the circle of 25 m</para>
 <para>diameter radiating around a feeding elephant. The plot incorporated all of the vegetation</para>
 <para>choices that the focus elephant had within eyesight, so a comparison could be made</para>
 <para>between vegetation available and vegetation browsed which would reflect the elephant&#8217;s</para>
 <para>foraging preferences. We defined trees as single-stem vegetation as opposed to bushes,</para>
 <para>which were multi-stemmed. We collected data from 25 plots.</para>
 <para>Classification of elephants and browsing intensity. Infant elephants were those</para>
 <para>lacking tusks and noticeably smallest in the herd. Juveniles were those elephants with</para>
 <para>small tusks and body sizes less than 50 percent the size of the largest (adult) elephant in</para>
 <para>the group. Adult elephants were those with developed tusks and massive bodies. All</para>
 <para>solitary males were considered adults.</para>
 <para>We observed two general types of browsing by elephants. The first was &#8220;mobile</para>
 <para>browsing&#8221; while the elephant was walking purposefully forward. No data were taken to</para>
 <para>quantify this. When an elephant stopped or significantly slowed its movement to browse</para>
 <para>in a limited area&#8212;hereafter referred to as &#8220;stationary browsing&#8221;&#8212;a plot was declared and</para>
 <para>data were collected on browsing impact. Low impact browsing events were defined as</para>
 <para>leaf stripping. Medium impact browsing events were defined as branch breaking, and</para>
 <para>high impact events were any that reduced the canopy of that tree by more than 25</para>
 <para>percent.</para>
 <para>Data collection. We located elephants, either by vehicle or on foot, and then</para>
 <para>followed them on foot. We recorded GPS coordinates and time of arrival at every plot.</para>
 <para>We also conducted a vegetation survey of the plot, recording the species and height of all</para>
 <para>of trees present. The elephant or elephants were observed for the entire time they stayed</para>
 <para>within the plot, and the age class, sex, targeted tree species, individual height, and</para>
 <para>browsing event intensity were recorded. We followed elephants until they left the</para>
 <para>confines of the park, became aware of our presence (and so altered their behavior), or</para>
 <para>dusk fell.</para>
 <para>Data analyses. Data analyses were performed using the StatView&#174; statistical</para>
 <para>package, with significance set at &#945; = 0.05. To determine elephant preference and plant</para>
 <para>susceptibility we used &#967; 2 contingency tables to compare data on what species and height</para>
 <para>classes were browsed to what was available. When comparing preference among</para>
 <para>elephant age and sex groups, we were careful to exclude species not present in similar</para>
 <para>abundances during observations of all groups so as not to bias our results.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>