<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="peggym.1031.1" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"> <allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow><principal>uid=judithk,o=SANParks,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 <permission>write</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset> <title>The Effect of Vegetation and Habitat Type on Rodent Biodiversity in Mapungubwe National Park</title>
 <creator id="1253184196519"> <individualName><surName>William Boysen and Eliza Chamblin</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>SANParks, South Africa</organizationName>
 <positionName>Independent Project 2</positionName>
 </creator>
 <abstract><para>The status of small mammal populations reflects ecosystem integrity.
This study focused on rodent populations in two different habitats of the
Mapungubwe National Park, the mopane savanna and riverine forest. Live
trapping and vegetation surveys were performed in an effort to determine a
relationship between rodent population presence and habitat structure. We found
that there was a greater rodent abundance in the mopane savanna, but that there
were no significant differences in diversity and richness between the two habitats.
The higher abundance corresponded to areas with a greater understory height,
lower soil penetrability, and closer proximity to major rock outcroppings. These
findings establish that there is a relationship between habitat characteristics and
rodent species abundance. This information can be used by conservationists as a
baseline measure to develop conservation goals and plans that reflect the
interconnected nature of ecosystems.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>SANParks, South Africa</keyword>
 <keyword>abundance, biodiversity, mopane savanna, riverine forest, rodents, vegetation structure</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Kruger National Park</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-90.0</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>90.0</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>45.0</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>-45.0</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><singleDateTime><calendarDate>2006</calendarDate>
 </singleDateTime>
 </temporalCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact><references>1253184196519</references>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><para>We conducted our study in the Mapungubwe National Park in the Limpopo</para>
 <para>Province of South Africa. We utilized ten study sites: five in the riverine forest along the</para>
 <para>Shashi River and five in the mopane savanna (Appendix 1). We set out ten Sherman</para>
 <para>traps at each of our ten sites, putting out one hundred traps in total. Within each site, we</para>
 <para>placed five traps under cover and five in the open. A trap placed under cover, or a closed</para>
 <para>trap, was placed under tight vegetation, usually a shrub, whereas a trap placed in the open</para>
 <para>might have been placed along a log or at the bottom of a tree (never totally in the open).</para>
 <para>In addition, half of the traps were standard size (8 x 9 x 23 cm) and half were long traps</para>
 <para>(8 x 9.5 x 30 cm). Slade et al. (1993) demonstrated that long traps had a consistently</para>
 <para>greater capture rate than short traps, and thus are more effective. Due to resource</para>
 <para>limitations, we were unable to use long traps exclusively. Instead, we used an equal</para>
 <para>number of long and short traps at each site to ensure that there was an equivalent chance</para>
 <para>of catching rodents at all sites.</para>
 <para>For the safety of the animals that we caught, we made sure that all traps were</para>
 <para>well-shaded by covering them with debris. We baited each trap with a mixture of peanut</para>
 <para>butter, oats, and honey. We rebaited the traps after each catch and every afternoon, so as</para>
 <para>to ensure bait freshness. We checked the traps once in the early morning (between</para>
 <para>5:30am and 10:30am) and once in the late afternoon (between 3:30pm and 6:30pm) for</para>
 <para>four consecutive days (Tuesday, 14 November, 2006-Friday, 18 November, 2006) in the</para>
 <para>beginning of the summer rainy season. If we did find a specimen in one of our traps, we</para>
 <para>adhered to a uniform catch procedure: We uniquely marked and then released the</para>
 <para>specimen. We also recorded species weight and sex. We analyzed our collected data</para>
 <para>using Excel, Statistica and Primer.</para>
 <para>Vegetation/Habitat Survey</para>
 <para>To see if there was any relationship between the specific rodent species present</para>
 <para>and habitat conditions, we conducted habitat/vegetation surveys at each of our ten sites.</para>
 <para>We walked two 50 meter transects at each site from North to South. The transects were</para>
 <para>approximately ten meters apart. For each transect, we evaluated and recorded the habitat</para>
 <para>86</para>
 <para>type at one meter intervals: grass, sand, dirt, woody debris, dung, tree, rock, or shrub.</para>
 <para>Every five meters, we also estimated the proximity to a major rock outcropping and</para>
 <para>estimated the visibility at twenty centimeters, alternating to the East and to the West. In</para>
 <para>order to measure the visibility, one researcher held their head twenty centimeters above</para>
 <para>ground, while the other moved a notebook in a straight line away from the transect, also</para>
 <para>twenty centimeters above ground. When the individual at twenty centimeters could only</para>
 <para>see half of the notebook, we recorded the distance between the two individuals. These</para>
 <para>measurements were taken with the purpose of determining the level of habitat appeal and</para>
 <para>availability of protection from predators. Finally, every ten meters within each 50 meter</para>
 <para>transect, we took a penetrometer measurement of the soil to get a sense of the level of</para>
 <para>ease with which a rodent could burrow. Additionally, we noted the presence of dung,</para>
 <para>woody debris, rocks, or live trees within one meter of each transect. We analyzed all data</para>
 <para>with Excel, Statistica, and Primer.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>