<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="peggym.1024.1" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"> <allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow><principal>uid=judithk,o=SANParks,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 <permission>write</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset> <title>Aquatic Invertebrate Diversity in Calcareous and Sandstone Wetlands of the Cape Floristic Region, South Africa</title>
 <creator id="1253181851255"> <individualName><surName>Eliza Chamblin and Anna Chu (editors) Jenny Day (resource person)</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>SANParks, South Africa</organizationName>
 <positionName>Faculty Field Problem</positionName>
 </creator>
 <abstract><para>The wetlands of the Cape Floristic Region, South Africa are a hotspot of
species diversity. The aquatic invertebrates of this region are so diverse mainly
because of the varying geomorphology and hydrology of the realm, which affect
water chemistry. We hypothesized that there would be a significant difference
between the suite of invertebrate species of a closed, permanent and sandstone-based
wetland (Potberg Vlei) and a relatively open, temporary, calcareous wetland (De
Hoop Vlei). The water chemistry of each area is vastly different, but there is no
significant difference in species richness of the wetlands, though there has been an
increase in species richness since the fall. However, there does seem to be a difference
in the species diversity of the two vleis. These differences could be quite important in
determining conservation areas.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>SANParks, South Africa</keyword>
 <keyword>aquatic invertebrates, geology, wetland, Cape Floristic Region, inundation frequency</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Kruger National Park</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-90.0</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>90.0</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>45.0</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>-45.0</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><singleDateTime><calendarDate>2006</calendarDate>
 </singleDateTime>
 </temporalCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact><references>1253181851255</references>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><para>We collected data from two sites in the De Hoop Nature Reserve of the Cape</para>
 <para>Floristic Region on 24-25 October 2006. One of these sites has a calcareous parent</para>
 <para>rock (De Hoop Vlei) and the other has a sandstone parent rock (Potberg Vlei). The</para>
 <para>De Hoop Vlei is a relatively open vlei that experiences flooding every several years.</para>
 <para>In contrast, the Potberg Vlei is a closed vlei that has perennial flooding.</para>
 <para>To sample from the De Hoop Vlei, we divided the waters into three distinct</para>
 <para>biotopes based on vegetation. The first area, the Cladophora region, was closest to</para>
 <para>the shore. This section was largely characterized by a cover of the green algae,</para>
 <para>Cladophora. The second sampling region was the area of water containing the</para>
 <para>Potamogeton pectinatous plant. The third sampling site was the open water farthest</para>
 <para>from the shore. The Potberg Vlei contained only two of our designated divisions: the</para>
 <para>Potamogeton and open water areas. In these sections, we used the same sampling</para>
 <para>methods as in the De Hoop Vlei.</para>
 <para>We took three water samples from each of the regions in each of the biotopes</para>
 <para>in the De Hoop and Potberg Vleis. We then identified and classified (on a log scale)</para>
 <para>the number of invertebrates found within each sample. We also measured the pH and</para>
 <para>conductivity levels in all biotopes in each vlei.</para>
 <para>Using the program, Primer, we were able to create an ordination chart to</para>
 <para>spatially represent the diversity differences among our sampling sites. We then made</para>
 <para>another ordination chart to compare the differences in our sites to those of the same</para>
 <para>sites seven months ago. We used a one-way ANOVA to determine if there was a</para>
 <para>statistical difference between the species richness values of the biotopes of the De</para>
 <para>Hoop Vlei and the Potberg Vlei and t-tests and an ANOVA to find any statistical</para>
 <para>differences in the pH and conductivity levels within and between each vlei.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>