<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="peggym.990.1" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"> <allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow><principal>uid=judithk,o=SANParks,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 <permission>write</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset> <title>The effects of fire on vegetation structure and habitat in broadleaf savannas</title>
 <creator id="1251719850802"> <individualName><surName>Carla Staver and Taryn Morris</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>SANParks, South Africa</organizationName>
 <positionName>Faculty Field Problem</positionName>
 </creator>
 <abstract><para>Fire in savannas is instrumental in creating heterogeneous vegetation
structures and a patchwork landscape in savannas. The frequency and
season of fire have a direct effect on plant community composition and
vegetation structure. In turn this has implications for faunal composition
and diversity, since vegetation provides both habitat and food for
herbivores. This study found that burn regime has a marked effect on both
the structure and composition of the floral components. Infrequently burnt
sites have a higher proportion of larger trees and denser tree and grass
cover. These sites were dominated by climax, decreaser and mostly
palatable grasses. More frequently burned sites have fewer large trees and
more small trees. Frequent fires continually knock back woody vegetation
to small sizes. This fire trap results in a high proportion of seedlings and
gullivers. Grass communities mainly comprise pioneer increasers of
moderate to low palatability. Ant species richness increased with
increasing canopy cover, possibly because more canopy results in a greater
diversity of thermal niches. Bird communities closely followed variation
in vegetation due to differing burn regiments. Bird communities in more
frequently burned sites were more closely related to each other than less
frequently burned sites. These findings support the policy of managers of
Kruger National Park with respect to promoting patch heterogeneity.
Heterogeneity of ecosystems does indeed promote biodiversity of fauna in
all its natural facets and fluxes. Fire is a powerful tool for managers
hoping to drive this heterogeneity.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>SANParks, South Africa</keyword>
 <keyword>Skukuza, Kruger National Park, Mpumalanga Province, South Africa</keyword>
 <keyword>fire, herbivory, heterogeneity</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Kruger National Park</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-90.0</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>90.0</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>45.0</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>-45.0</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2004-01-31</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate><calendarDate>2004-05-31</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact><references>1251719850802</references>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><para>Kruger National Park management established a series of experimental burn plots</para>
 <para>(EBPs) in 1954. These burn plots are found in four areas of the park and within each of</para>
 <para>the four areas includes four burn strings. Each string consists of twelve burn treatments</para>
 <para>of various burn frequency and season (Van Wilgen et al. 2003). Our study was</para>
 <para>conducted in three of the four strings in the Pretoriuskop EBPs. Where possible we</para>
 <para>sampled the same burn season and frequency treatments across the three strings but due</para>
 <para>to herbivore exclusion experiments, access to some of the plots was restricted (Table 1).</para>
 <para>In each plot we ran one transect of 150 m, collecting a variety of vegetation</para>
 <para>structure and animal presence data. Within two meters of the transect, we the height and</para>
 <para>species of each tree. Every two meters along the transect, we noted the closest species of</para>
 <para>grass to the transect, with species, from which we calculated relative species abundance.</para>
 <para>Every fifteen meters along the transect, we calculated canopy cover and determined</para>
 <para>foliage profiles using boards 2m high and 10cm wide, divided into height classes of</para>
 <para>25cm. We measured the distance from the point at which 50% of each height class (25</para>
 <para>cm, 50 cm, 75 cm, 1 m, 1.5 m, and 2 m) on the board was obscured. The reciprocal of</para>
 <para>this distance is directly proportional to foliage density and is thus an approximation of the</para>
 <para>vertical distribution of biomass. Evidence of large herbivores (dung) was also assessed</para>
 <para>within 2m2 of the transect line. To determine butterfly species richness, all butterfly</para>
 <para>species within sight of the transect line were counted to yield a count of butterfly species</para>
 <para>richness. Bird species richness and ant diversity were determined independent of the</para>
 <para>transect. Bird species seen or heard were recorded for each site visited over a period of</para>
 <para>1.5 hrs. Only the data from the first three samples were used, as activity of birds</para>
 <para>decreased in the warmer periods later in the morning. Ant diversity was determined</para>
 <para>using pitfall traps set out overnight in each of four burn plots (Numbi and Shabeni no</para>
 <para>burn and August annual burn plots). We set out two pitfall traps every 10 m along a 40 m</para>
 <para>transect, giving 8 replicates for each site.</para>
 <para>Data analysis</para>
 <para>Foliage profiles, size class distributions and grass characteristics were graphed</para>
 <para>using Microsoft Excel 2002. Multi-dimensional scaling community analyses were</para>
 <para>generated using Primer 5. Primer 5 was also used to determine the Shannon wiener</para>
 <para>indices. The relationship between time of day and bird diversity was generated in</para>
 <para>Statistica 6.1.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>