<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="peggym.1029.1" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"> <allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow><principal>uid=judithk,o=SANParks,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 <permission>write</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset> <title>Is the reduction of the water provisioning program accomplishing desired goals?: The influence of waterhole closure near Shingwedzi on small mammal diversity</title>
 <creator id="1253183229904"> <individualName><surName>Jennifer Mizen and Bryan Barnhill</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>SANParks, South Africa</organizationName>
 <positionName>Independent Project I</positionName>
 </creator>
 <abstract><para>Given the detrimental effects of the artificial watering program in the Kruger
National Park, a number of artificial watering points have been closed. This study
examined the effect of waterhole closures in the Shingwedzi area on rodent populations
through live trapping methods, with particular attention paid to abundance, richness, and
diversity. In contrast to similar studies conducted near Punda Maria, we did not find a
significant difference between the populations around closed versus open waterholes. As
rodents can be used as environmental indicators, this suggests that closure of waterholes
alone is not enough to improve the biodiversity of these disturbed sites. Further studies
should consider seasonality, as this was a winter assessment.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>SANParks, South Africa</keyword>
 <keyword>artificial waterholes, biodiversity, rodents, Sherman traps</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Kruger National Park</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-90.0</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>90.0</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>45.0</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>-45.0</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><singleDateTime><calendarDate>2006</calendarDate>
 </singleDateTime>
 </temporalCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact><references>1253183229904</references>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><para>The study sites consisted of two open and two closed artificial watering holes.</para>
 <para>The sites were chosen by soil type, absence of recent burning from wildfire, and</para>
 <para>operational status. The soil type at all of the sites was basalt, in order to control for</para>
 <para>differences in resource availability due to vegetation. Thirty Sherman traps were used at</para>
 <para>each site, arranged in two 3 x 5 arrays with traps set 10 meters apart. Approximately</para>
 <para>equal numbers of short and long Sherman traps were used in each array. The arrays were</para>
 <para>positioned on opposite sides of the watering troughs at sites 1, 2, and 3, and on adjacent</para>
 <para>69</para>
 <para>sides of the trough at site 4. At sites 1, 2 and 3 the arrays began 20 meters from watering</para>
 <para>trough, as measured from the short sides of the trough at the first two sites and the long</para>
 <para>sides of the trough at the third site. The arrays at site 4 began 50 meters from the water</para>
 <para>trough. The traps were placed under bushes and/or in long grass and covered with grass</para>
 <para>or leaves for camouflage as well as protection from the heat of the sun.</para>
 <para>The traps were positioned and baited on the morning of September 21, and</para>
 <para>checked for the next three mornings. A mixture of peanut butter, honey, and oats was</para>
 <para>used as bait. The bait was then changed to a mixture of peanut butter with oats and</para>
 <para>honey for the remainder of the trapping time. Individuals captured were uniquely marked</para>
 <para>with hair dye or permanent marker, in order to note recapture. Each rodent&#8217;s weight, sex</para>
 <para>and species were recorded before release in the proximity of the trap.</para>
 <para>Data were compiled and analyzed using Microsoft Excel and Primer 5. The</para>
 <para>capture rate was calculated by dividing the number of successful captures by the total</para>
 <para>trapping effort (&#8220;trap days&#8221;), taking into account the loss of several traps during the</para>
 <para>course of the study due to trampling. G-tests were preformed to determine the</para>
 <para>significance of the open versus closed sites in terms of trap success and on short versus</para>
 <para>long trap use on trap success. Richness and abundance were also calculated for each site</para>
 <para>as measures of number of species found and numbers of individuals captured,</para>
 <para>respectively. Data from the 2004 and 2005 studies were rendered comparable to this</para>
 <para>study, then all three studies were analyzed in reference to each other. Shannon-Weiner</para>
 <para>tests were used to determine diversity indices for all eight sites studied between 2004 and</para>
 <para>2006. Data were log-transformed before multidimensional scaling (MDS) ordination.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>