<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="peggym.1018.1" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"> <allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow><principal>uid=judithk,o=SANParks,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 <permission>write</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset> <title>The impact of vegetation disturbance around water holes on rodent abundance and diversity in the north of Kruger National Park, South Africa.</title>
 <creator id="1252482547608"> <individualName><surName>Tammy Baudains, Taryn Morris and Govan Pahad</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>SANParks, South Africa</organizationName>
 <positionName>Independent Project</positionName>
 </creator>
 <abstract><para>Many studies have demonstrated a causal relationship between disturbance and species diversity
and furthermore between losses in diversity and declines in ecosystem function, resilience and
resistance. Our study supports this and additionally the notion that monitoring of small mammal
diversity can be used as a quick and inexpensive indicator of ecosystem integrity. The movement
of herbivores to and from waterholes results in an increasing gradient in their grazing, browsing and
trampling impacts towards waterholes, creating circular zones of impact known as piospheres. An
increase in artificial waterholes in the past has resulted in an overlap in these impacted areas,
creating a homogenised, disturbed habitat. The aim of our study was to determine if the vegetation
structure and composition is indeed impacted in the piosphere and whether this affects rodent
diversity and abundance. We tested an open waterhole and one which had been closed for about
two years. We found similar number of rodents at both waterholes. However the open waterhole
had a lower diversity of rodents than the closed waterhole and was dominated by the multimammate
mouse, Mastomys natalensis, which in other studies has been associated with disturbed areas.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>SANParks, South Africa</keyword>
 <keyword>Disturbance, diversity, Kruger Park, monitoring, piospheres, rodents, Sherman traps</keyword>
 <keyword>Kruger National Park, South Africa</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Kruger National Park</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-90.0</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>90.0</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>45.0</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>-45.0</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2004-01-09</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate><calendarDate>2004-05-09</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact><references>1252482547608</references>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><para>Sampling was undertaken on four consecutive nights from 21 to 24 March 2004. March is considered near</para>
 <para>the end of the breeding season of small mammals (Monadjem and Perrin 1997). Two waterholes were sampled in the</para>
 <para>Punda Maria region of the Kruger National Park (Figure 1). One waterhole, which we named Elephant waterhole,</para>
 <para>had been closed approximately two years prior to our study. The other, Elandskuil waterhole, had remained open</para>
 <para>since construction.</para>
 <para>The vegetation was sampled along two transects of 50m in each of the two grids at each waterhole to</para>
 <para>investigate correlations with rodent diversity. Percentage grass cover was assessed every 10m along the transect by</para>
 <para>randomly placing a 0.5x0.5m quadrate on the ground and estimating the percentage grass cover within. Vegetation</para>
 <para>composition was determined by recording the species present at points every 2m along each transect. Structure was</para>
 <para>sampled by determining foliage profiles using boards 1.5m high and 10cm wide, divided into height classes of 25cm.</para>
 <para>At five points (every 10m) along each transect, we measured the distance from the point at which 50% of each height</para>
 <para>class on the board was obscured. The reciprocal of this distance is directly proportional to foliage density and is thus</para>
 <para>an approximation of the vertical distribution of biomass. From these values, a foliage profile of each site was</para>
 <para>constructed.</para>
 <para>Sherman traps were set in two 5 by 6 grids of 30 traps spaced ten metres apart on opposite sides of each</para>
 <para>waterhole. At the open waterhole, grids were laid approximately 20m away from the waterhole so that the absence of</para>
 <para>vegetative cover due to excessive over grazing and trampling would not affect our results. Traps were left open day</para>
 <para>and night and were checked and rebaited in the early mornings and late afternoons. Traps were baited using a mixture</para>
 <para>of peanut butter, rolled oats, and whole seeds including corn and sorghum. Rodents trapped were identified to species</para>
 <para>level, sexed, weighed and were marked on the third day by cutting a patch of fur off the belly), before being released</para>
 <para>in the same area. Reproductive status was assessed by males either being scrotal or not scrotal and females being</para>
 <para>nulliperous or sexually active. This was checked by feeling whether or not the pubic symphasis was open or closed</para>
 <para>(many females were pregnant or suckling and so were easily identified as sexually active).</para>
 <para>Data were analyzed using Microsoft Excel 2000, Primer 5, JMP IN 5.1 and Statistica 6. The mean</para>
 <para>percentage vegetation cover was derived for the open and closed waterhole and graphed. Additionally a student&#8217;s ttest</para>
 <para>for independent samples was performed in Statistica 6 to determine whether the difference in percentage cover</para>
 <para>was significant or not. The vegetation species composition at the four open waterhole transects and four closed</para>
 <para>waterhole transects were compared by producing a cluster analysis in Primer 5. A foliage density graph was created</para>
 <para>to illustrate the vertical distribution of biomass at each waterhole. Additionally student t-tests for independent</para>
 <para>samples were performed on 0.25m, 0.5m and 0.75m height classes to determine if there was significant difference in</para>
 <para>the amount of foliage at those heights.</para>
 <para>The rodent captures were summed and divided by the number of trap days to determine percentage trap success at</para>
 <para>231</para>
 <para>each waterhole. All calculations took into account the loss of two traps at the open waterhole due to damage by an</para>
 <para>elephant, and the disappearance of one trap. Species data were graphed using Microsoft Excel so that graphical</para>
 <para>comparisons could be made i.e. what were the most common species at each of the two sites</para>
 <para>A Shannon-Wiener diversity test was performed in Primer 5 on the species data to see whether either site</para>
 <para>was more diverse in rodent species than the other. It is a measure of both the number of species and the equality of</para>
 <para>representation of the individuals of all the species i.e. evenness. The Peterson method was used to obtain an</para>
 <para>estimation of the population size using the unbiased estimator equation: N = (((M+1)(C+1))/(R+1)) -1, where M=</para>
 <para>number of individuals marked in the first sample, C = Total number of individuals captured in the second sample and</para>
 <para>R = Number of individuals in second sample that are marked (Krebs 1999). G-tests were performed to compare male</para>
 <para>versus female ratios, perimeter versus interior trap success and trap success in long model Sherman traps versus short</para>
 <para>model ones, in JMP IN 5.1. Lastly mean weights per species were determined.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>