<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="peggym.1012.1" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"> <allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow><principal>uid=judithk,o=SANParks,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 <permission>write</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset> <title>An investigation into the fine-scaled variation in tree diversity and the varied architecture of Colophospermum mopane in the Mopaniveld</title>
 <creator id="1251812575539"> <individualName><surName>Benjamin Wigley and Jasper Slingsby (secretaries), Laurence Kruger (editor)</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>SANParks, South Africa</organizationName>
 <positionName>Independent Project</positionName>
 </creator>
 <abstract><para>In this study we investigate the drivers behind variation in species richness and diversity at a fine
scale in the Mopaniveld (i.e. what causes monospecific vs. multispecies stands?) and the drivers
behind variations in stand and individual C. mopane architectures (height, basal area,
multistemmedness). We hypothesize that the basic compositional structure of the plant
communities is determined by physical and edaphic soil characteristics. In the absence of
disturbance, competition should determine densities and stand architectures of C. mopane given the
abiotic template. In highly disturbed savanna environments the effects of competition are most
likely less obvious, and densities and stand architectures of C. mopane would be determined by its
response to the disturbance regime. Our data indicated the presence of catenal sequences.
Plots with sandy soils were located at higher elevations and had lower conductivity, calcium and
carbon concentrations than plots with clay soils (U=57, P=.022; U=45, P=.01; U = 56, P = .02;
U=35, P&lt;.005). Variation in species richness and diversity at a fine scale in this part of the
Mopaniveld appears to be determined by catenal sequences as species richness and diversity was
higher in plots with sandier soils (U=52.5, P&lt;.05 and U=62, P=.05 respectively). C. mopane
appears to grow in higher densities on clay soils (U=66, P&lt;.055), but grows larger on sandy soils
(Beta=0.652, P&lt;.05 and Beta =0.553, P&lt;.01 respectively) with high calcium concentrations
(Beta=0.487, P&lt;.05 and Beta =0.463, P&lt;.05 respectively). Variations in disturbance regimes and
competition at the catenal scale could be important in determining stand and individual C. mopane
architecture.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>SANParks, South Africa</keyword>
 <keyword>abiotic factors, competition, Colophospermum mopane, disturbance, Mopaniveld, species richness, diversity</keyword>
 <keyword>Kruger National Park, South Africa</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Kruger National Park</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-90.0</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>90.0</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>45.0</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>-45.0</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2004-01-01</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate><calendarDate>2004-05-01</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact><references>1251812575539</references>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><para>The study site we selected occurs in the Bulweni land system near Punda Maria rest camp in the northern</para>
 <para>Kruger National Park, South Africa. It occurs on soils derived from the Karoo sediments, Ecca shale and mudstone.</para>
 <para>The area receives a mean annual rainfall of 450-500mm, making it one of the driest areas in the park (Venter et al.</para>
 <para>2003).</para>
 <para>Data collection</para>
 <para>We sampled thirty 400m2 plots, one every c. 250m along a 7.25km transect (latitudes and longitudes given in</para>
 <para>Appendix 1). All trees were identified, their height and diameter at 50cm measured (D50cm), and the total number of</para>
 <para>stems counted. The number of stems with branches damaged by mechanical damage were counted (this was assumed</para>
 <para>to be as a result of elephants), and the presence of dead, charred stems was noted, as an indication of fire disturbance.</para>
 <para>In each plot a 50cm deep hole was dug in order to determine if a calcrete layer was present and at what</para>
 <para>depth. A soil sample was taken from the centre of each plot. This was used to determine pH, conductivity and the</para>
 <para>concentrations of available phosphorous, calcium, nitrogen and carbon for each site. Soil texture was established</para>
 <para>using the field assessment method described in Tongway and Hindley (1995). Soil pH was determined using calcium</para>
 <para>chloride and a 1:2.5 ratio of soil to salt solution according to the method outlined by Rowell (1994). Conductivity</para>
 <para>was determined by using a 1:5 ratio of soil to distilled water. The solution was shaken for 15 minutes using a soil</para>
 <para>shaker before conductivity was measured using a conductivity meter.</para>
 <para>Data analysis</para>
 <para>The plots were divided into two categories for soil texture and Shannon Weiner diversity. Soil texture was</para>
 <para>divided into sandy and clay soils. Clay to sandy clay loam (Tongway and Hindley 1995) were classified as clay soils.</para>
 <para>Sandy loam, loamy sand and sand (Tongway and Hindley 1995) were classified as sandy soils. Shannon Weiner</para>
 <para>diversity categories were set as those plots with indices less than one versus those plots with indices greater than one.</para>
 <para>These categories were used to compare various biotic and abiotic properties using Mann-Whitney U tests.</para>
 <para>We performed a number of correlation and multiple regression analyses testing for significant relationships</para>
 <para>between the main vegetation components and physical and chemical components.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>