<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="peggym.1019.1" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"> <allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow><principal>uid=judithk,o=SANParks,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 <permission>write</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset> <title>Reduced kin recognition in the success of a widespread ant: Lepisiota capensis</title>
 <creator id="1252482889965"> <individualName><surName>Eric Caldera</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>SANParks, South Africa</organizationName>
 <positionName>Independent Project</positionName>
 </creator>
 <abstract><para>Intraspecific competition for resources is often the factor limiting worker population size in ants.
Energy expended on competition would otherwise go toward colony growth and reproduction. A
loss of intraspecific aggression has been key to the success of many invasive ants, including the
Argentine ant. The Black Sugar Ant (Lepisiota capensis) may be capable of displacing the
Argentine ant. Here I tests whether L. capensis has also experienced a similar reduction in
intraspecific aggression by conducting aggression assays within and among four sites in Kruger
National Park, South Africa. My results show that the L. capensis does have reduced intraspecific
aggression. This reduction in intraspcific aggression may help L. capensis escape energetic costs
associated with intraspecific competition, making this species a better competitor. Because of this
reduced intraspecific aggression, L. capensis may pose a threat as a potentially invasive species and
consequently a threat to biodiversity in South Africa.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>SANParks, South Africa</keyword>
 <keyword>Argentine ant, kin recognition, Lepisiota capensis, intraspecific aggression</keyword>
 <keyword>Kruger National Park</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Kruger National Park</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-90.0</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>90.0</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>45.0</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>-45.0</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2004-01-09</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate><calendarDate>2004-05-09</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact><references>1252482889965</references>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><para>Collection sites. I collected ants from four sites in the Kruger National Park (KNP), South Africa: Punda Maria camp</para>
 <para>(PM), Letaba camp (LB), Skukuza camp (SK), and the Luvuvhu River west of the Pafuri camp (LR). At each site, I</para>
 <para>collected from two nests that were a minimum of 100m apart to reduce the risk of sampling from the same nest more</para>
 <para>than once. To further ensure that individuals from each sample belonged to different nests, I only collected ants</para>
 <para>where queens and brood were present. I maintained ant colonies in plastic containers and fed them 20% sugar water</para>
 <para>once a week.</para>
 <para>Behavioral assays and analysis. I used aggression assays that have been previously used to investigate levels of</para>
 <para>intraspecific aggression in Argentine ants to quantify kin recognition in L. capensis (Holway et al. 1998; Tsutsui et al.</para>
 <para>2000; Caldera and Holway, 2004). Pairwise aggression assays were performed between ants from the two nests</para>
 <para>collected at each site and among ants collected from nests from the four sites (Figure 1). For each aggression assay</para>
 <para>two workers, one from each of two nests, were placed into a vial, after which a smaller plastic container was inserted</para>
 <para>into the vial so that the space for the ants to move was minimized, thus increasing the probability for the ants to</para>
 <para>interact.</para>
 <para>Interactions between the ants were observed for 5min and scored using a 4 point scale of escalating</para>
 <para>aggression: touch = 1 (contacts that included prolonged antenation), avoid = 2 (contacts that resulted in one or both</para>
 <para>ants quickly retreating in opposite directions), aggression = 3 (lunging, biting, and pulling legs or antennae), or fight =</para>
 <para>4 (prolonged aggression between individuals including spraying of formic acid).</para>
 <para>Each aggression assay was repeated 10 times, using different ants each time, and the average was compared</para>
 <para>to the average level of aggression between nestmates using a Kruskal-Wallis non parametric test. The average level</para>
 <para>of aggression between nestmates (1.1&#177;0.447) was determined by conducting 10 aggression assays between workers</para>
 <para>from the same nest, repeating the assays using a different nest, and averaging them together. For the sites where</para>
 <para>aggression between the two nests sampled was not significantly different from the average level of aggression</para>
 <para>between nestmates only one of the nests was used to conduct aggression assays between the different sites. However,</para>
 <para>where aggression between two nests collected was high, both nests were used in aggression assays between sites.</para>
 <para>To ensure that aggression seen in L. capensis was not due to aspects of being housed in lab colonies</para>
 <para>interfering with recognition sensory mechanisms, I separated one nest into two lab colonies and conducted aggression</para>
 <para>assays after 2 weeks.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>