<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="peggym.1013.1" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"> <allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow><principal>uid=judithk,o=SANParks,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 <permission>write</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset> <title>Biotic determinants of soil characteristics in the Northern Plains of Kruger National Park</title>
 <creator id="1251812864545"> <individualName><surName>Carla Staver</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>SANParks, South Africa</organizationName>
 <positionName>Independent Project</positionName>
 </creator>
 <abstract><para>The study investigates the effects that changing herbivory patterns in the Northern Plains of Kruger
National Park have had on vegetation structure and composition and on soil characteristics, both
chemical and physical. Type I herbivores such as zebra and buffalo have encroached into the area,
which has been historically inhabited by type II herbivores such as roan and sable. The study found
that the more intense and less selective grazing associated with type I herbivores has had a marked
effect on vegetation and soil chemical characteristics. Overall grass and tree cover has decreased,
and the size of the remaining trees is reduced. Colophospermum mopane seems to thrive especially
under disturbance conditions. Calcium, available phosphorus, salinity, and pH have homogenized
under the influence of type I grazers, while organic carbon and total nitrogen have diversified.
Differential land use patterns and grazing habits of type I and type II herbivores may drive these
changes. However, until these patterns are better understood, their role in determining vegetation
and soil properties will remain unclear.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>SANParks, South Africa</keyword>
 <keyword>herbivory, Northern Plains, soil nutrients, vegetation</keyword>
 <keyword>Kruger National Park, South Africa</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Kruger National Park</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-90.0</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>90.0</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>45.0</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>-45.0</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2004-01-01</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate><calendarDate>2004-05-01</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact><references>1251812864545</references>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><para>The roan enclosure directly north of Shingwedzi provides an ideal location in which to examine the effects</para>
 <para>of herbivory and vegetation structure on soil characteristics in the Northern Plains. The enclosure lies on olivine-rich</para>
 <para>basalt in the Karoo geologic sequence and receives between 350 and 450 mm of rainfall per year. The enclosure was</para>
 <para>established in 1968 in an area upslope from a river; riparian and fluvial zones were added to the enclosure in 1985.</para>
 <para>This study examined upslope areas, where vegetation structure and soils have had more time to adjust to the exclusion</para>
 <para>of herbivory.</para>
 <para>The roan enclosure is divided into four quarters. One lies on black soil, which is dominated by marula</para>
 <para>(Sclerocarya birrea) and knobthorn (Acacia nigrescens), and was burnt 4-5 years ago. Fifteen sites were sampled in</para>
 <para>this quarter of the roan enclosure. The remainder of the enclosure lies on mopane-veld (dominated by</para>
 <para>Colophospermum mopane), characterized by red soils, which extends beyond the fence of the enclosure. Fifteen plots</para>
 <para>were sampled in the south-west corner of the enclosure, an area dominated by C. mopane, which was burned 4-5</para>
 <para>years ago. Corresponding plots were sampled outside the enclosure on each soil type (see Figure 1 for a map of the</para>
 <para>enclosure with sampling layout). The fifteen plots in each site lie every 30 meters along three transects. These</para>
 <para>transects run parallel to the slope of the hill in order to minimize bias from effects of down-slope water, nutrient, and</para>
 <para>small particle flow on soil properties.</para>
 <para>The following parameters were sampled in each plot:</para>
 <para>&#8226; Trees within 400m2 circle (r=11.3): species, height, DBH</para>
 <para>&#8226; Grasses within circle of 2m radius: species, abundance, total cover</para>
 <para>&#8226; Soil samples at the center of these circles</para>
 <para>Soil nutrients (total N, available P, Ca) were analyzed at a soil lab according to the standard method. Soil</para>
 <para>pH was determined using the method outlined by Rowell (1994), using a 1:2.5 ratio of soil to 0.01 M CaCl2 solution.</para>
 <para>Conductivity was determined with a 1:5 ratio of soil to water and converted to standard-scale conductivity (ECe)</para>
 <para>using the method outlined by Landon (1991). Volumetric soil moisture content was determined by weighing soil</para>
 <para>moisture samples and then drying them at 105oC for 24 hours. Porosity was determined in the field using a surrogate</para>
 <para>measure; I measured the absorption time of 100 mL of water over an area of ~20 cm2. I used a field method for</para>
 <para>determining soil texture outlined by Tongway and Hindley (1995).</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>