<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="peggym.1026.1" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 eml.xsd"> <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"> <allow><principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 <allow><principal>uid=judithk,o=SANParks,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 <permission>write</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 <dataset> <title>The effects of time of day, gender, and age on time budgets in African Elephants in Kruger National Park</title>
 <creator id="1253182405289"> <individualName><surName>Billy Boysen, Wren Larson, Jodie Reed</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>SANParks, South Africa</organizationName>
 <positionName>Independent Field Project 1</positionName>
 </creator>
 <abstract><para>The African elephant, Loxodonta africana, is a species of great importance in
Kruger National Park because of the extensive impact it has on ecological processes. In
this study, we focused on the effects of time of day, gender and age on time budgets in
elephants. We sought to determine whether there were any activities that were performed
more frequently at different times of the day or by elephants of a certain age or gender.
Using focal observation, we determined the proportion of total time spent performing
various activities. We found that the time budgets did not vary statistically with gender
or age, but that there were significant differences in time spent standing still between the
morning and afternoon (p=0.0143). More time was spent eating in the afternoon than the
morning (p=0.002183), but overall time spent eating was less than previous studies have
found. Despite the fact that elephant populations in Kruger are growing, the destruction
of trees was not observed in any of our focal studies, indicating elephants in our study did
not appear to impact the ecosystem as much as reported in previous literature.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>SANParks, South Africa</keyword>
 <keyword>activity budgets, African elephant (Loxodonta africana), age differences, behavior, gender differences, Kruger National Park</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Kruger National Park</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-90.0</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>90.0</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>45.0</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>-45.0</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage><singleDateTime><calendarDate>2006-09-17</calendarDate>
 </singleDateTime>
 </temporalCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact><references>1253182405289</references>
 </contact>
 <methods><methodStep><description><section><para>The study focused on the African Elephant, Loxodonta africana, the largest of all</para>
 <para>land mammals. Adult males can weigh over 6000 kg, with 200 kg contributing to the</para>
 <para>ivory tusks. When protected, an elephant can live to be over 70 years, constrained only by</para>
 <para>the irreplaceable six molar pairs that wear down over time (Frandsen 1998). For this</para>
 <para>behavioral study, we actively searched for elephants twice a day in Open Air Game</para>
 <para>Viewing Vehicles from September 21-24, 2006. Weather conditions were dry and hot,</para>
 <para>with temperatures around 30&#176; C. Searching was held in the morning, 7:00 AM-12:00</para>
 <para>PM, and afternoon, 12:00 PM-6:00 PM. All searching and observations were conducted</para>
 <para>along the Shingwedzi River within 30 km of the Shingwedzi Research Camp in Kruger</para>
 <para>National Park, South Africa (S 23.05682; E 031.34634). The majority of elephants were</para>
 <para>studied along the riverbank, with observation occurring from the opposite bank. Some</para>
 <para>individuals were encountered along the road and were observed there.</para>
 <para>When an elephant was observed, a GPS locator was used to pinpoint the location</para>
 <para>of the animal. The time of observation was noted and the elephant was classified in</para>
 <para>terms of age and gender. Three distinct age classes were used to categorize elephants:</para>
 <para>infant, juvenile, and adult. An infant was defined as any small elephant that had not yet</para>
 <para>51</para>
 <para>developed tusks. A juvenile was any tusked individual in the herd not yet fully grown,</para>
 <para>generally 75% or less of the size of the largest animals (adults). Ambiguity in the sexes</para>
 <para>prevented the identification of genders in the infants and juveniles. As a result, only the</para>
 <para>adult elephants were classified as male or female.</para>
 <para>After gender and age classification, activity budgets were determined through</para>
 <para>observation in focal studies (Altmann 1974). During the ten-minute focal observation, the</para>
 <para>activity of one elephant was carefully described and timed. One person observed the</para>
 <para>elephant through binoculars while a second recorded all of the reported observation.</para>
 <para>These descriptions were used to later classify the behavior into seven categories: eating,</para>
 <para>standing, drinking, traveling (walking or running), vigilance (looking around, head</para>
 <para>shaking, ears out), playing (trunk wrestling, shoving, butting, splashing, etc.), and other</para>
 <para>(mating, scratching, rolling around in the mud, nursing) (Estes 1999). Data were</para>
 <para>collected from 64 elephants. Because the elephants were observed from a distance, we</para>
 <para>assumed that our presence did not have an effect on their behavior.</para>
 <para>We calculated our statistics using Statistica 7.0 (StatSoft, Inc. &#169; 1984-2004). The</para>
 <para>data were tested for normality using the Lilliefors test and found to be non-normally</para>
 <para>distributed; therefore we used nonparametric statistical tests in the analysis of our data.</para>
 <para>To analyze the effect of gender and age on time budgets we used a Kruskal-Wallis oneway</para>
 <para>ANOVA. If significant differences were detected, a Mann-Whitney U test was</para>
 <para>performed between adult males and adult females. If no significant differences were</para>
 <para>detected, these two groups were combined and reclassified as adults. The Kruskal-Wallis</para>
 <para>test was then performed on the three age groups and if significant differences were</para>
 <para>detected, this was followed by Mann-Whitney U tests of pairs of age groups per activity,</para>
 <para>along with a Bonforoni correction. The variability in the activity budgets due to the</para>
 <para>effect of time of day was analyzed using Mann-Whitney U tests.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>