<ns0:DryadDataPackage xmlns:ns0="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1" xmlns:ns2="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:ns3="http://rs.tdwg.org/dwc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1 http://datadryad.org/profile/v3.1/dryad.xsd">
  <ns2:type>package</ns2:type>
  <ns2:creator>Brandley, Matthew C.</ns2:creator>
  <ns2:creator>Kuriyama, Takeo</ns2:creator>
  <ns2:creator>Hasegawa, Masami</ns2:creator>
  <ns2:dateSubmitted>2014-05-02T16:12:32Z</ns2:dateSubmitted>
  <ns2:available>2014-05-02T16:12:32Z</ns2:available>
  <ns2:title>Data from: Snake and bird predation drive the repeated convergent evolution of correlated life history traits and phenotype in the Izu Island scincid lizard (Plestiodon latiscutatus)</ns2:title>
  <ns2:identifier>http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.v47s1</ns2:identifier>
  <ns2:description>Predation may create strong natural selection pressure on the phenotype and life history characteristics of prey species. The Izu scincid lizards (Plestiodon latiscutatus) that inhabit the four Japanese Izu Islands with only bird predators are drab brown, mature later, lay small clutches of large eggs, and hatch large neonates. In contrast, skinks on seven islands with both snake and bird predators are conspicuously colored, mature early, lay large clutches of small eggs, and hatch small neonates. We test the hypothesis that these suites of traits have evolved independently on each island via natural selection pressures from one of two predator regimes &#8211; birds-only and birds + snakes. Using two mtDNA genes and a nuclear locus, we infer a time-calibrated phylogeny of P. latiscutatus that reveals a basal split between Mikura and all islands south, and Miyake, all islands north, and the Izu Peninsula. Populations inhabiting Miyake, Niijima, Shikine, and Toshima are not monophyletic, suggesting either multiple colonizations or an artifact of incomplete lineage sorting (ILS). We therefore developed novel phylogenetic comparative analyses that assume either a multiple colonization or more restrictive single colonization ILS scenario and found 1) statistically significant support for the of different suites of phenotypic and life history characteristics with the presence of bird-only or bird + snake predator assemblages, and 2) strong phylogenetic support for at least two independent derivations of either the &#8220;bird-only&#8221; or &#8220;snakes + birds&#8221; phenotypes regardless of colonization scenario. Finally, our time-calibrated phylogeographic analysis supports the conclusion that the ancestor to modern Izu Island P. latiscutatus dispersed from the mainland to the Izu proto-islands between 3&#8211;7.6 million years ago (Ma). These lineages remained present in the area during successive formation of the islands, with one lineage re-colonizing the mainland 0.24-0.7 Ma.</ns2:description>
  <ns2:subject>Bayesian</ns2:subject>
  <ns2:subject>comparative analysis</ns2:subject>
  <ns2:subject>phylogeography</ns2:subject>
  <ns2:subject>phylogenetic ANOVA</ns2:subject>
  <ns2:subject>independent contrasts</ns2:subject>
  <ns2:subject>island biogeography</ns2:subject>
  <ns2:subject>skink</ns2:subject>
  <ns2:subject>Squamata</ns2:subject>
  <ns3:scientificName>Plestiodon latiscutatus</ns3:scientificName>
  <ns3:scientificName>Plestiodon japonicus</ns3:scientificName>
  <ns2:spatial>Japan</ns2:spatial>
  <ns2:temporal>Pleistocene</ns2:temporal>
  <ns2:references>http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0092233</ns2:references>
  <ns2:hasPart>http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.v47s1/1</ns2:hasPart>
</ns0:DryadDataPackage>