<metadata xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.fgdc.gov/metadata/fgdc-std-001-1998.xsd">
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>New Mexico Tech</origin>
            <pubdate>20140124</pubdate>
            <title>NMT Rio Hondo Geochemistry, General Chemistry (November 16th-17th, 2012)</title>
            <geoform>document</geoform>
            <onlink>http://nmepscor.org/dataportal</onlink>
            <onlink>https://gstore.unm.edu/dataone/v1/object/165c5000-d8e3-48e4-90ca-b1a249b372a4</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>With growing concerns about declining snowpack, warmer temperatures, and land use changes, it is becoming increasingly 
                important to determine the sources that contribute to surface water. In western states, such as New Mexico, most of the surface 
                water is derived from mountainous watersheds. However, the interaction between the groundwater and the surface water within these 
                mountain systems is poorly understood. Geochemical data collected from a mesoscale (~200 km2) watershed in northern New Mexico 
                indicate there may be significant groundwater contributions to the surface water that have largely been ignored in previous studies. 
                Stable isotopic analysis of &#948;18O and &#948;2H and Piper diagrams for surface water, groundwater, and spring water are not geochemically 
                distinct. Surface water solute concentrations for most constituents increase as a function of the drainage area while the stable 
                isotopic signature remains constant, suggesting that the water is sourced from similar areas but has undergone differing degrees 
                of geochemical evolution along different flow paths. Plots of SiO2 vs Ca2+, Na+, Mg2+, and K+ show evidence of spatial evolution 
                of groundwater with solute concentrations from the headwaters to the watershed outlet. We hypothesize that the increasing solute 
                concentrations in the surface water are controlled by inputs from deep, more geochemically evolved groundwater. This is similar 
                to what Frisbee et al. (2011) saw in the Saguache Watershed, though our watershed is significantly smaller and has a different 
                geological setting. Due to the chemical kinetics involved, this more geochemically evolved groundwater would require longer residence 
                time along a given flow path to achieve the observed chemical compositions. Significant contributions of old groundwater to surface 
                water could result in the surface water system having increased buffering capacity against climate change. This deep groundwater 
                component in watersheds has largely been unexplored. Our research provides support for our hypothesis and indicates that deep 
                groundwater contributions to surface water may occur at even smaller scales than previously published.</abstract>
         <purpose>Characterizing the geochemical and isotopic composition of waters within the Rio Hondo Watershed</purpose>
         <supplinf>
                General chemistry results may include original lab results (PDF), Excel spreadsheets and duplicate lab work for the set of files included.
                
                This document is made available through New Mexico's
                Experimental Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (NM EPSCoR) data portal. The
                portal provides access to data generated by and of use to the EPSCoR community
                including researchers, educators, and policy leaders, as well as the general
                public.</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>20121116</begdate>
               <begtime>000000</begtime>
               <enddate>20121117</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>Ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>In work</progress>
         <update>As needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-105.84993</westbc>
            <eastbc>-104.3995</eastbc>
            <northbc>33.64792</northbc>
            <southbc>33.16255</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
            <themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>NMT</themekt>
            <themekey>EPSCoR 3</themekey>
            <themekey>Gus Tolley</themekey>
            <themekey>Geochemistry</themekey>
            <themekey>Groundwater</themekey>
            <themekey>Water quality</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>GNIS</placekt>
            <placekey>Rio Hondo</placekey>
            <placekey>New Mexico</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None</accconst>
      <useconst>None</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>New Mexico Tech</cntorg>
               <cntper>John Wilson</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>801 Leroy Place</address>
               <address>Department of Earth and Environmental Science</address>
               <city>Socorro</city>
               <state>NM</state>
               <postal>87801</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>575.835.5634</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>jwilson@nmt.edu</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
   </idinfo>
   <spdoinfo>
      <indspref>Rio Hondo</indspref>
   </spdoinfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>Earth Data Analysis Center</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Clearinghouse Manager</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>MSC01 1110</address>
               <address>1 University of New Mexico</address>
               <city>Albuquerque</city>
               <state>NM</state>
               <postal>87131-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>505-277-3622 ext. 230</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>505-277-3614</cntfax>
            <cntemail>clearinghouse@edac.unm.edu</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1700 MT, M-F -7 hours GMT</hours>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
      <distliab>The material on this site is made available as a public service. Maps and data are to be used for reference purposes only and the Earth Data Analysis Center (EDAC), DataONE and The University of New Mexico are not responsible for any inaccuracies herein contained. No responsibility is assumed for damages or other liabilities due to the accuracy, availability, use or misuse of the information herein provided. Unless otherwise indicated in the documentation (metadata) for individual data sets, information on this site is public domain and may be copied without permission; citation of the source is appreciated.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ZIP</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>https://gstore.unm.edu/dataone/v1/object/165c5000-d8e3-48e4-90ca-b1a249b372a4</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
                  <accinstr>Download from DataONE at http://www.dataone.org.</accinstr>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None. The files are available to download from DataONE (http://www.dataone.org).</fees>
         <ordering>Contact Earth Data Analysis Center at clearinghouse@edac.unm.edu</ordering>
      </stdorder>
      <custom>Contact Earth Data Analysis Center at clearinghouse@edac.unm.edu</custom>
      <techpreq>Adequate computer capability is the only technical prerequisite for viewing data in digital form.</techpreq>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20140325</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>Earth Data Analysis Center</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Clearinghouse Manager</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>MSC01 1110</address>
               <address>1 University of New Mexico</address>
               <city>Albuquerque</city>
               <state>NM</state>
               <postal>87131-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>505-277-3622 ext. 230</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>505-277-3614</cntfax>
            <cntemail>clearinghouse@edac.unm.edu</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1700 MT, M-F -7 hours GMT</hours>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <mettc>local time</mettc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>