<metadata xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.fgdc.gov/metadata/fgdc-std-001-1998.xsd">
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Edward Martinez</origin>
            <pubdate>20140114</pubdate>
            <title>NMHU Valles Caldera Water Quality 2010-2012</title>
            <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
            <onlink>http://nmepscor.org/dataportal</onlink>
            <onlink>https://gstore.unm.edu/dataone/v1/object/56c88ff3-dda1-443d-8102-d249e212337c</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>High elevation areas, such as the Valles Caldera National Preserve (VCNP)
                located in the Jemez Mountains of Northern New Mexico, have been described as
                exceptionally vulnerable to changes in climate and thus offer an ideal window to
                monitor temperature changes and their possible implications. In the present study,
                we examined the effects diurnal and seasonal temperature changes and discharge have
                on water quality. Two water sampling regimes (diurnal and grab samples) were
                employed over a one-year time frame (May 2010-May 2011) at four sites along two
                potentially vulnerable headwater streams located within the VCNP. Concentrations of
                primary nutrients (nitrate, nitrite, and phosphate) and other solutes (bromide,
                chloride, fluoride, and sulfate), along with discharge and physicochemical
                parameters (conductivity, dissolved oxygen, pH, and turbidity) served as indices of
                water quality. The results of this study indicated that primary nutrients and other
                solutes were largely sensitive to seasonal temperature changes, but that their
                sensitivity was modulated by the unique characteristics of sample sites. It was
                concluded that the examination of the effects of seasonal water temperature
                fluctuations on primary nutrient and other solute concentrations can offer a deeper
                understanding of challenges headwater streams may face as result of anticipated
                climate changes.</abstract>
         <purpose>The objective of this research was to monitor the effects of water temperature
                on two Valles Caldera National Preserve (VCNP) headwater streams in an attempt to
                gain a better understanding of nutrient and other solute dynamics in association
                with discharge and physiochemical parameters. First, we wanted to determine the
                extent to which water temperature changes were related to alterations in solute
                concentrations, discharge, and physiochemical parameters. Second, we set to
                determine the influence of seasonal water temperature changes on water quality, as
                defined by solute concentrations, discharge, and physiochemical
                parameters.</purpose>
         <supplinf>Funding Source is NM EPSCOR. Principal Investigator is Edward Martinez at New
                Mexico Highlands University. The main researcher for this project is Sebastian
                Medina, Ernesto Sandoval, Daryl Williams, and Julie Trujillo at New Mexico Highlands
                University. This file is made available through New Mexico's Experimental Program to
                Stimulate Competitive Research (NM EPSCoR) data portal. The portal provides access
                to data generated by and of use to the EPSCoR community including researchers,
                educators, and policy leaders, as well as the general public. Research results based
                on this file have been published. Trujillo, J.A., Medina, S., Williams, D., and
                Pilotti, M. (2012). Impact of Micro-Temperature Changes on Dissolved Organic Carbon
                in High Mountain Streams. New Mexico Journal of Science, 46:203-216. With the
                exception of DOC, blank cells in columns containing nutrient and solute
                concentrations (fluoride, chloride, nitrite, bromide, nitrate, phosphate, sulfate)
                signify that the sample was below the detection limit of the Dionex ICS-1000 (0.01
                mg/L).</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>20100515</begdate>
               <begtime>000000</begtime>
               <enddate>20120618</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>Publication date</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>In work</progress>
         <update>As needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-106.51295</westbc>
            <eastbc>-106.342417</eastbc>
            <northbc>35.891617</northbc>
            <southbc>35.840617</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
            <themekey>inlandWaters</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>Edward Martinez</themekt>
            <themekey>EPSCoR 3</themekey>
            <themekey>Water Quality</themekey>
            <themekey>Head Water Streams</themekey>
            <themekey>Water Temperature</themekey>
            <themekey>Nutrient Concentration</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>Spatial Reference System Identifiers</placekt>
            <placekey>EPSG:4269</placekey>
            <placekey>EPSG:7019</placekey>
         </place>
         <place>
            <placekt>GNIS</placekt>
            <placekey>New Mexico</placekey>
            <placekey>Valles Caldera</placekey>
            <placekey>Northern New Mexico</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None</accconst>
      <useconst>None</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>Department of Natural Resources Management, New Mexico Highlands
                        University</cntorg>
               <cntper>Edward Martinez</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>P.O. Box 9000</address>
               <city>Las Vegas</city>
               <state>NM</state>
               <postal>87701</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>505-425-7511</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>eamartinez@nmhu.edu</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <logic>Not provided</logic>
      <complete>Not provided</complete>
      <lineage>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Field Methods: Two sampling regimes were implemented from May 2010 to May
                    2011. Diurnal sampling was performed largely during the 2010 field collection
                    season using model 3700 portable ISCO samplers (Teledyne Technologies, Lincoln,
                    Nebraska, USA). Samplers were programmed to simultaneously collect water samples
                    every hour, over a 24-hour period at the four sites, once a month for nine
                    months. In addition, bi-monthly water samples were collected manually (grab
                    samples) from each site. Following the 2010 field collection season, water
                    samples were collected exclusively using the grab sample method. Water samples
                    were analyzed for biodegradable organic carbon (BDOC), dissolved organic carbon
                    (DOC), anionic nutrients (nitrate, nitrite, and phosphate) and other anionic
                    solute concentrations (fluoride, chloride, bromide). All water samples for
                    nutrient analysis were stored on ice for transportation to the lab (~3 hrs.).
                    Prior to analysis all samples were stored frozen (~&#8804;1 week) prior to analysis.
                    Prior to carbon sampling, all glassware was pre-sterilized. This process
                    included: washing glassware (borosilicate vials) with detergent and rinsing it
                    in cold water, rinsing it in 0.1N HCl followed by deionized water then wrapping
                    glassware in aluminum and heating it in a kiln for six hours at 500&#176;C. The
                    0.45-&#956;m pore size Whatman GF/F filters used for data collection were wrapped in
                    foil and heated in the kiln following the same procedure used for glassware.
                    During grab sample collections, two 40 mL-grab water samples at each site were
                    taken, a sample for measuring DOC and a sample for measuring BDOC. In the field,
                    the DOC and BDOC samples were filtered into pre-sterilized borosilicate vials
                    using Whatman GF/F filters with a 0.45-&#956;m pore size. DOC samples were collected
                    and preserved with sodium azide and stored at 4&#186;C prior to analysis. BDOC
                    samples were immediately wrapped in aluminum foil and stored in the dark at
                    20&#177;5&#186;C for 28 days following collection. Discharge in m3/s for each stream was
                    recorded at the time of grab sample collection and during diurnal sample
                    collection utilizing a model 201D Marsh-McBirney portable water current meter
                    (Marsh-McBirney, Gaithersburg, Maryland, USA) and a Rickly wading rod (Rickly
                    Hydrological, Columbus, Ohio, USA ), following standard U.S. Geological Survey
                    methods. Additionally, physicochemical data (Dissolved Oxygen, pH, Turbidity,
                    Specific Conductivity, and Water Temperature) at each sample collection were
                    obtained with an YSI model 6920 V2-2 sonde (YSI, Yellow Springs, Ohio, USA).
                    HOBO Pendant Data loggers (Onset Computer, Cape Cod, Massachusetts, USA) were
                    also placed at each site on the stream bed, below water level, to continuously
                    record hourly water temperature.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntorgp>
                     <cntorg>New Mexico Highlands University</cntorg>
                     <cntper>Sebastian Medina</cntper>
                  </cntorgp>
                  <cntpos>Graduate Research Assistant</cntpos>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
                     <address>P.O. Box 9000</address>
                     <city>Las Vegas</city>
                     <state>NM</state>
                     <postal>87701</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>505-310-2422</cntvoice>
                  <cntemail>smedin13@live.nmhu.edu</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>Laboratory Analysis: Anion concentrations (Br-, Cl-, F-, NO3-, NO2-, PO43-
                    and SO42- ) were determined by a Dionex Ion Chromatography System (ICS)-1000,
                    AS40 automated sampler (Dionex, Sunnyvale, California, USA), utilizing an AS9-HC
                    anion column and a ASRS self-regulating suppressor. Retention times and ionic
                    signatures were determined according to the Dionex Quality Assurance Report
                    serial number 18487. Carbon concentrations (DOC, BDOC) were determined using an
                    OI Analytical Aurora 1030/ Autosampler Model 1088 TOC analyzer (OI Analytical,
                    College Station, Texas, USA). All internal calibration verifications (ICV) and
                    continuous calibration verifications (CCV) were prepared using multi element or
                    total organic carbon standards. Both ICV&#8217;s and CCV&#8217;s encompassing the
                    concentration range of samples (0.1-10 mg/L) were included in each method of
                    analysis. The latter were performed on every 15 samples to ensure reliability of
                    the instrument. All standards, reagents, and field blanks were prepared with 18
                    mega-ohm water from a Barnstead Easy Pure II UV/UF water purification system
                    (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, Massachusetts, USA). The detection limits of
                    the Dionex ICS-1000 and OI Analytical TOC analyzer were approximately 0.01
                    mg/L.</procdesc>
            <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
            <proccont>
               <cntinfo>
                  <cntorgp>
                     <cntorg>New Mexico Highlands University</cntorg>
                     <cntper>Sebastian Medina</cntper>
                  </cntorgp>
                  <cntpos>Graduate Research Assistant</cntpos>
                  <cntaddr>
                     <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
                     <address>P.O. Box 9000</address>
                     <city>Las Vegas</city>
                     <state>NM</state>
                     <postal>87701</postal>
                     <country>USA</country>
                  </cntaddr>
                  <cntvoice>505-310-2422</cntvoice>
                  <cntemail>smedin13@live.nmhu.edu</cntemail>
               </cntinfo>
            </proccont>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <indspref>Valles Caldera</indspref>
      <direct>Vector</direct>
      <ptvctinf>
         <sdtsterm>
            <sdtstype>Point</sdtstype>
            <ptvctcnt>519</ptvctcnt>
         </sdtsterm>
      </ptvctinf>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <geograph>
            <latres>0.00000001</latres>
            <longres>0.00000001</longres>
            <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
         </geograph>
         <geodetic>
                <horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
                <ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
                <semiaxis>6378137.000000</semiaxis>
                <denflat>298.257222</denflat>
            </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>Valles Caldera Water Temperature 2010-2012, NMHU</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Water Quality 2010-2012</enttypd>
            <enttypds>EDAC</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Site</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Study site number</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Sebastian Medina</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Site number</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Season</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Valles Caldera season breakdown</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Sebastian Medina</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>1</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Spring(April to May)</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Sebastian Medina</edomvds>
               </edom>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>2</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Summer(June to August)</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Sebastian Medina</edomvds>
               </edom>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>3</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Fall(September to October)</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Sebastian Medina</edomvds>
               </edom>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>4</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Winter(November to March)</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>Sebastian Medina</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Date</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Sample collection date</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Sebastian Medina</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Sample collection date</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>DOC</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Dissolved organic carbon concentrations in mg/L</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Sebastian Medina</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>100</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>milligrams per liter (mg/L)</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Fluoride</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Fluoride concentrations in mg/L</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Sebastian Medina</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>30</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>milligrams per liter (mg/L)</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Chloride</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Chloride concentrations in mg/L</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Sebastian Medina</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>30</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>milligrams per liter (mg/L)</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Nitrite</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Nitrite concentrations in mg/L</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Sebastian Medina</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>30</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>milligrams per liter (mg/L)</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Bromide</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Bromide concentrations in mg/L</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Sebastian Medina</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>30</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>milligrams per liter (mg/L)</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Nitrate</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Nitrate concentrations in mg/L</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Sebastian Medina</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>30</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>milligrams per liter (mg/L)</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Phosphate</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Phosphate concentrations in mg/L</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Sebastian Medina</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>30</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>milligrams per liter (mg/L)</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Sulfate</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Sulfate concentrations in mg/L</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Sebastian Medina</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>30</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>milligrams per liter (mg/L)</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>WaterTemp</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Water temperature in degrees Celsius</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Sebastian Medina</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>-5</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>50</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>Degree Celsius</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Discharge</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Discharge recorded for study sites in cubic meters per second according to
                    USGS methods</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Sebastian Medina</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>Unknown</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>Unknown</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>Cubic meters per second</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>pH</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>pH measurements recorded in standard units</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Sebastian Medina</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>14</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>standard pH units</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>DO</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Dissolved oxygen concentrations recorded in mg/L</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Sebastian Medina</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>20</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>milligrams per liter (mg/L)</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Turbidity</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Turbidity measurements recorded</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Sebastian Medina</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>3000</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>NTU</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>Conductivity</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Conductivity measurements recorded</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Sebastian Medina</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <rdom>
                  <rdommin>0</rdommin>
                  <rdommax>100</rdommax>
                  <attrunit>millisiemens per cm^c-1</attrunit>
               </rdom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>Earth Data Analysis Center</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Clearinghouse Manager</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>MSC01 1110</address>
               <address>1 University of New Mexico</address>
               <city>Albuquerque</city>
               <state>NM</state>
               <postal>87131-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>505-277-3622 ext. 230</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>505-277-3614</cntfax>
            <cntemail>clearinghouse@edac.unm.edu</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1700 MT, M-F -7 hours GMT</hours>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
      <distliab>The material on this site is made available as a public service. Maps and data are to be used for reference purposes only and the Earth Data Analysis Center (EDAC), DataONE and The University of New Mexico are not responsible for any inaccuracies herein contained. No responsibility is assumed for damages or other liabilities due to the accuracy, availability, use or misuse of the information herein provided. Unless otherwise indicated in the documentation (metadata) for individual data sets, information on this site is public domain and may be copied without permission; citation of the source is appreciated.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ZIP</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>https://gstore.unm.edu/dataone/v1/object/56c88ff3-dda1-443d-8102-d249e212337c</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
                  <accinstr>Download from DataONE at http://www.dataone.org.</accinstr>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None. The files are available to download from DataONE (http://www.dataone.org).</fees>
         <ordering>Contact Earth Data Analysis Center at clearinghouse@edac.unm.edu</ordering>
      </stdorder>
      <custom>Contact Earth Data Analysis Center at clearinghouse@edac.unm.edu</custom>
      <techpreq>Adequate computer capability is the only technical prerequisite for viewing data in digital form.</techpreq>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20140325</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>Earth Data Analysis Center</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Clearinghouse Manager</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>MSC01 1110</address>
               <address>1 University of New Mexico</address>
               <city>Albuquerque</city>
               <state>NM</state>
               <postal>87131-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>505-277-3622 ext. 230</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>505-277-3614</cntfax>
            <cntemail>clearinghouse@edac.unm.edu</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1700 MT, M-F -7 hours GMT</hours>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <mettc>local time</mettc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>