<metadata xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.fgdc.gov/metadata/fgdc-std-001-1998.xsd">
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>Edward Martinez</origin>
            <pubdate>20140121</pubdate>
            <title>NMHU Valles Caldera and Jemez Springs Las Conchas Macroinvertebrates, 2011 - 2012</title>
            <geoform>document</geoform>
            <onlink>http://nmepscor.org/dataportal</onlink>
            <onlink>https://gstore.unm.edu/dataone/v1/object/790aa75d-6690-4dbd-bbdd-d378e1e7b5d8</onlink>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>The Valles Caldera, located in Northern New Mexico is
                being affected by climate change. The most pronounced effects on the region are the
                increasing temperatures and decreasing snowpack. Climate change is expected to
                increase wildfire severity. Following large wildfires, the potential for soil
                erosion during precipitation events is also increased, therefore potentially
                degrading the aquatic system. The purpose of this study is to determine the impact
                of the Las Conchas wildfire had on diversity and populations of aquatic macro
                invertebrates. Samples were collected from various parts of the steam pre and post
                fire. The macro invertebrates will be sorted, counted, and identified to family.
                This is preformed to determine the effects of large wildfire on the aquatic macro
                invertebrate ecosystem. Future research will be conducted to determine the length of
                time needed for aquatic macro invertebrates to increase in numbers.</abstract>
         <purpose>This study was conducted in the Valles Caldera, in northern New Mexico by the
                water quality group at NMHU under New Mexico EPSCoR.</purpose>
         <supplinf>Funding source is NM EPSCoR. Principal Investigator is Edward Martinez at New
                Mexico Highlands University. The main researcher for this project is Lorraine Garcia at
                New Mexico Highlands University. This document is made available through New Mexico's
                Experimental Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (NM EPSCoR) data portal. The
                portal provides access to data generated by and of use to the EPSCoR community
                including researchers, educators, and policy leaders, as well as the general
                public.</supplinf>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
               <begdate>20110601</begdate>
               <begtime>000000</begtime>
               <enddate>20120630</enddate>
            </rngdates>
         </timeinfo>
         <current>Ground condition</current>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>In work</progress>
         <update>As needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>-106.6927</westbc>
            <eastbc>-106.44755</eastbc>
            <northbc>35.97168</northbc>
            <southbc>35.77062</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
            <themekey>biota</themekey>
         </theme>
         <theme>
            <themekt>Edward Martinez</themekt>
            <themekey>EPSCoR 3</themekey>
            <themekey>Lorraine Garcia</themekey>
            <themekey>Macrophytes</themekey>
            <themekey>Las Conchas Fire</themekey>
            <themekey>Water quality</themekey>
         </theme>
         <place>
            <placekt>GNIS</placekt>
            <placekey>Valles Caldera</placekey>
            <placekey>Jemez Moutains</placekey>
            <placekey>New Mexico</placekey>
         </place>
      </keywords>
      <accconst>None</accconst>
      <useconst>None</useconst>
      <ptcontac>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>Department of Natural Resources Management, New Mexico Highlands
                        University</cntorg>
               <cntper>Edward Martinez</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
               <address>P.O.Box 9000</address>
               <city>Las Vegas</city>
               <state>NM</state>
               <postal>87701</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>505-425-7511</cntvoice>
            <cntemail>eamartinez@nmhu.edu</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </ptcontac>
   </idinfo>
   <spdoinfo>
      <indspref>Valles Caldera</indspref>
   </spdoinfo>
   <eainfo>
      <overview>
         <eaover>Invertebrates were collected at the Valles Caldera National Preserve and surrounding Jemez Mountains, during the summer of 
                2011 (June), fall of 2011 (October), spring of 2012 (April), and summer of 2012 (June). Invertebrate collection at each site was 
                divided into three sections, a collection at and/or right below the spring, a collection at above the confluence of the spring 
                and river, and a collection below the confluence below the spring and river. Collection at each site spanned approximately 20 meters 
                of the river, and quantitative sample were collected. In the lab invertebrates were identified into taxonomic family, as well as 
                into functional feeding guilds (shredder, filtering collector, gathering collector, scrapper, and predators). </eaover>
         <eadetcit>Edward Martinez and Lorraine Garcia, New Mexico Highlands University</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>Earth Data Analysis Center</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Clearinghouse Manager</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>MSC01 1110</address>
               <address>1 University of New Mexico</address>
               <city>Albuquerque</city>
               <state>NM</state>
               <postal>87131-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>505-277-3622 ext. 230</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>505-277-3614</cntfax>
            <cntemail>clearinghouse@edac.unm.edu</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1700 MT, M-F -7 hours GMT</hours>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
      <distliab>The material on this site is made available as a public service. Maps and data are to be used for reference purposes only and the Earth Data Analysis Center (EDAC), DataONE and The University of New Mexico are not responsible for any inaccuracies herein contained. No responsibility is assumed for damages or other liabilities due to the accuracy, availability, use or misuse of the information herein provided. Unless otherwise indicated in the documentation (metadata) for individual data sets, information on this site is public domain and may be copied without permission; citation of the source is appreciated.</distliab>
      <stdorder>
         <digform>
            <digtinfo>
               <formname>ZIP</formname>
            </digtinfo>
            <digtopt>
               <onlinopt>
                  <computer>
                     <networka>
                        <networkr>https://gstore.unm.edu/dataone/v1/object/790aa75d-6690-4dbd-bbdd-d378e1e7b5d8</networkr>
                     </networka>
                  </computer>
                  <accinstr>Download from DataONE at http://www.dataone.org.</accinstr>
               </onlinopt>
            </digtopt>
         </digform>
         <fees>None. The files are available to download from DataONE (http://www.dataone.org).</fees>
         <ordering>Contact Earth Data Analysis Center at clearinghouse@edac.unm.edu</ordering>
      </stdorder>
      <custom>Contact Earth Data Analysis Center at clearinghouse@edac.unm.edu</custom>
      <techpreq>Adequate computer capability is the only technical prerequisite for viewing data in digital form.</techpreq>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20140325</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>Earth Data Analysis Center</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Clearinghouse Manager</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
               <address>MSC01 1110</address>
               <address>1 University of New Mexico</address>
               <city>Albuquerque</city>
               <state>NM</state>
               <postal>87131-0001</postal>
               <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>505-277-3622 ext. 230</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>505-277-3614</cntfax>
            <cntemail>clearinghouse@edac.unm.edu</cntemail>
            <hours>0800 - 1700 MT, M-F -7 hours GMT</hours>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
      <metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
      <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
      <mettc>local time</mettc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>