<metadata xmlns:ns0="http://purl.org/ornl/schema/mercury/terms/v1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://purl.org/ornl/schema/mercury/terms/v1.0 mercury-ornl-v1.xsd">
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Portmann, Felix T.</origin>
        <origin>Siebert, Stefan</origin>
        <origin>Doll, Petra</origin>
        <title>Global Data Set of Monthly Irrigated and Rainfed Crop Areas around the Year 2000 (MIRCA2000)</title>
        <onlink>http://daac.ornl.gov/metadata/bluangel_harvest/RGED/QC/basic/vegetation/irrigated_rainfed_crops.xml</onlink>
        <alt_onlink>http://daac.ornl.gov/metadata/bluangel_harvest/RGED/QC/basic/vegetation/irrigated_rainfed_crops.xml</alt_onlink>
        <onlink />
        <onlink />
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>A global data set of monthly irrigated and rainfed crop growing areas around the year 2000 (MIRCA2000) was developed to support global and continental-scale studies on food security and water use. MIRCA2000 provides both irrigated and rainfed crop areas of 26 crop classes for each month of the year for 402 spatial units. The data set covers all major food crops (including regionally important ones such as wheat, rice, maize, barley, rye, millet, sorghum, soybeans, sunflower, potatoes, cassava, sugar cane, sugar beet, oil palm, rape seed/canola, roundnuts/peanuts, pulses, citrus, date palm, grapes/vine, cocoa, coffee), major water-consuming crops (cotton), and unspecified other crops (other perennial crops, other annual crops, fodder grasses). The data set refers to the period 1998-2002 and has a spatial resolution of 5 arc-minutes by 5 arc-minutes (about 9.2 km by 9.2 km at the equator).

The data set is consistent with irrigated area statistics of the AQUASTAT program of the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO) and with version 4.0.1 of the Global Map of Irrigation Areas (GMIA). At the cell-level, there is also consistency with total cropland extent and harvested crop areas provided by the Center for Sustainability and the Global Environment (SAGE) of the University of Wisconsin at Madison. In the future, the data set will be improved, e.g. with a better spatial resolution of crop calendars and an improved crop distribution algorithm.

Data available for download:

Monthly Growing Area Grids (MGAG) for 26 Irrigated and Rainfed Crops. For each of the 26 irrigated and 26 rainfed crop classes there is one file containing the 4320 x 2160 grid cells, 12 values indicating the monthly growing areas in hectares.

Cell Specific List of Growing Periods (Cropping Periods List, CPL). ASCII text files indicating for each grid cell, each irrigated crop and each related sub-crop the growing area in hectares and additionally the month in which the growing period starts and the month in which the growing period ends.

Condensed Crop Calendars (CCC) for 26 Irrigated and Rainfed Crops. ASCII text files providing each of the 402 spatial units (or entities) for each crop and sub-crop, growing area, start and end month of the cropping periods. Crops are listed separately for irrigated and rainfed crops.

Calendar Units (spatial units). The 402 used spatial units (or entities) are presented as a ASCII list with codes and names (about 10 KB), and a ASCII-grid of unit codes with 5 arc-minute resolution.

Related MIRCA2000 products can be found through the download page
http://www.geo.uni-frankfurt.de/ipg/ag/dl/forschung/MIRCA/data_download/index.html, e.g.:

Annual Harvested Area Grids for 26 Irrigated and Rainfed Crops [Besides for grids for each crops (irrigated and rainfed), also sums for all irrigated crops (AHI), rainfed crops (AHR), and irrigated and rainfed crops alltogether (total AHI+AHR) are provided].

Maximum Monthly Growing Area Grids (MMGAG) for 26 Irrigated and Rainfed Crops [Maximum monthly area within the year of the given crop. This product is designed for people who want to run their own crop model].

Maximum Monthly Cropped Area Grids (MMCAG) for either All Irrigated or All Rainfed Crops [Maximum monthly area within the year of all irrigated or rainfed crops. Please note, that the sum of both is not the overall maximum monthly area, as the month of the maximum can be different in either case.].

Cell Area Grid.

Oak Ridge National Laboratory (ORNL) also provides the Global Data Set of Monthly Irrigated and Rainfed Crop Areas around the Year 2000 (MIRCA2000), but in GeoTiff format. ORNL used Matlab to convert data from binary format to ESRI ASCII Grid format, and then used ArcGIS to convert data from ESRI ASCII Grid format to GeoTIFF format. ORNL georectified the data by setting coordinate reference system to be EPSG:4326, spatial extent to be global (-180, -90, 180, 90), and spatial resolution to be 0.0833333333. The processed GeoTIFF data was fed into ORNL DAAC Web Map Service v1.1.1  (WMS), Web Coverage Service v1.0.0 (WCS), and Spatial Data Access Tool (SDAT) to provide data visualization and distribution capabilities.

According to MIRCA2000, 25% of the global harvested areas are irrigated, with a cropping intensity (including fallow land) of 1.12, as compared to 0.84 for the sum of rainfed and irrigated harvested crops. For the dominant crops [rice (1.7 million km2 harvested area), wheat (2.1 million km2), and maize (1.5 million km2)], roughly 60%, 30%, and 20% of the harvested areas are irrigated, respectively, as are half of citrus, sugar cane, and cotton areas. While wheat and maize are the crops with the largest rainfed harvested areas (1.5 million km2 and 1.2 million km2, respectively), rice is clearly the crop with the largest irrigated harvested area (1.0 million km2), followed by wheat (0.7 million km2) and maize (0.3 million km2). Using MIRCA2000, 33% of global crop production and 44% of total cereal production were determined to come from irrigated agriculture.

Source: Portmann, F.T., S. Siebert, and P. D&#195;&#131;&#194;&#182;ll. 2010. MIRCA2000 Global monthly irrigated and rainfed crop areas around the year 2000: A new high-resolution data set for agricultural and hydrological modeling. GLOBAL BIOGEOCHEMICAL CYCLES, VOL. 24, GB1011, 24 PP., 2010 doi:10.1029/2008GB003435</abstract>
      <supplinf />
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>19980101</begdate>
          <enddate>20021231</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Final</progress>
      <update>As appropriate</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-180</westbc>
        <eastbc>180</eastbc>
        <northbc>90</northbc>
        <southbc>-90</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Parameter_Sensor_Source</themekt>
        <themekey>LAND COVER|ANALYSIS|COMPUTER MODEL</themekey>
        <themekey>LAND USE CLASSES|ANALYSIS|COMPUTER MODEL</themekey>
        <themekey>AGRICULTURAL LANDS|ANALYSIS|COMPUTER MODEL</themekey>
        <themekey>LAND MANAGEMENT|ANALYSIS|COMPUTER MODEL</themekey>
        <themekey>AGRICULTURAL EQUIPMENT|ANALYSIS|COMPUTER MODEL</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Parameter</themekt>
        <themekey>LAND COVER</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Source</themekt>
        <themekey>COMPUTER MODEL</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Sensor</themekt>
        <themekey>ANALYSIS</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Place Keywords</placekt>
        <placekey>Global (gridded)</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Portmann, Felix T.</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntfax>6.1.10.8 Contact Electronic Mail: INTERNET &amp;gt; Portmann@em.uni-frankfurt.de</cntfax>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Institute of Physical Geography, University of Frankfurt, Frankfurt, Germany</cntorg>
          <cntper>Portmann, F.T.</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntvoice>+49 69 798 40218</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>6.1.10.8 Contact Electronic Mail: INTERNET &amp;gt; Portmann@em.uni-frankfurt.de</cntfax>
        <cntemail>hydrology@em.uni-frankfurt.de</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>http://www.geo.uni-frankfurt.de/</computer>
            <accinstr>Public</accinstr>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
    </stdorder>
    <resdesc>Portmann, F.T., S. Siebert, and P. D&amp;#195;&amp;#182;ll. 2010. Global Data Set of Monthly Irrigated and Rainfed Crop Areas Around the Year 2000 (MIRCA2000). Available online at [http://www.geo.uni-frankfurt.de/ipg/ag/dl/forschung/MIRCA/index.html] from the Institute of Physical Geography, University of Frankfurt, Frankfurt, Germany.</resdesc>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20110322 165401</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntper>ORNL DAAC Staff</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>ORNL DAAC Staff</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntvoice>+1(865)241-3952</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>ornldaac@ornl.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
  </metainfo>
  <mercury>
    <begdate>19980101</begdate>
    <enddate>20021231</enddate>
    <Site_Information>
      <Site>Global (gridded)</Site>
      <Westernmost_Longitude>-180</Westernmost_Longitude>
      <Easternmost_Longitude>180</Easternmost_Longitude>
      <Northernmost_Latitude>90</Northernmost_Latitude>
      <Southernmost_Latitude>-90</Southernmost_Latitude>
    </Site_Information>
    <Keywords>Agricultural lands</Keywords>
    <Keywords>Annual crops</Keywords>
    <Keywords>Cropland</Keywords>
    <Keywords>Crops</Keywords>
    <Keywords>EOSDIS</Keywords>
    <Keywords>Food crops</Keywords>
    <Keywords>Food security</Keywords>
    <Keywords>Irrigated area</Keywords>
    <Keywords>Irrigated crops</Keywords>
    <Keywords>Irrigation</Keywords>
    <Keywords>Perennial crops</Keywords>
    <Keywords>Rainfed cropland</Keywords>
    <Keywords>Rainfed crops</Keywords>
    <Keywords>Terrestrial ecosystems</Keywords>
    <Keywords>Vegetation Collections</Keywords>
    <Keywords>Water-consuming crops</Keywords>
    <Keywords>Water use</Keywords>
    <Parameter_Description>
      <Parameter>LAND COVER</Parameter>
      <Sensor>ANALYSIS</Sensor>
      <Source>COMPUTER MODEL</Source>
      <Term>LAND USE/LAND COVER</Term>
      <Topic>LAND SURFACE</Topic>
    </Parameter_Description>
    <Parameter_Description>
      <Parameter>LAND USE CLASSES</Parameter>
      <Sensor>ANALYSIS</Sensor>
      <Source>COMPUTER MODEL</Source>
      <Term>LAND USE/LAND COVER</Term>
      <Topic>LAND SURFACE</Topic>
    </Parameter_Description>
    <Parameter_Description>
      <Parameter>AGRICULTURAL LANDS</Parameter>
      <Sensor>ANALYSIS</Sensor>
      <Source>COMPUTER MODEL</Source>
      <Term>TERRESTRIAL ECOSYSTEMS</Term>
      <Topic>BIOSPHERE</Topic>
    </Parameter_Description>
    <Parameter_Description>
      <Parameter>LAND MANAGEMENT</Parameter>
      <Sensor>ANALYSIS</Sensor>
      <Source>COMPUTER MODEL</Source>
      <Term>LAND USE/LAND COVER</Term>
      <Topic>HUMAN DIMENSIONS</Topic>
    </Parameter_Description>
    <Parameter_Description>
      <Parameter>AGRICULTURAL EQUIPMENT</Parameter>
      <Sensor>ANALYSIS</Sensor>
      <Source>COMPUTER MODEL</Source>
      <Term>AGRICULTURAL ENGINEERING</Term>
      <Topic>AGRICULTURE</Topic>
    </Parameter_Description>
    <Project />
    <Navpath>COMPUTER MODEL|ANALYSIS|LAND COVER</Navpath>
    <Navpath>COMPUTER MODEL|ANALYSIS|LAND USE CLASSES</Navpath>
    <Navpath>COMPUTER MODEL|ANALYSIS|AGRICULTURAL LANDS</Navpath>
    <Navpath>COMPUTER MODEL|ANALYSIS|LAND MANAGEMENT</Navpath>
    <Navpath>COMPUTER MODEL|ANALYSIS|AGRICULTURAL EQUIPMENT</Navpath>
    <Principal_Investigator>
      <Name>Portmann, Felix T.</Name>
      <Email>Portmann@em.uni-frankfurt.de</Email>
    </Principal_Investigator>
    <Principal_Investigator>
      <Name>Siebert, Stefan</Name>
      <Email>s.siebert@uni-bonn.de</Email>
    </Principal_Investigator>
    <Principal_Investigator>
      <Name>Doll, Petra</Name>
      <Email>P.Doell@em.uni-frankfurt.de</Email>
    </Principal_Investigator>
    <Data_Set_Link>
      <URL>https://anmeldung.uni-frankfurt.de/_fb11/mirca/index.php</URL>
      <Label>Global Data Set of Monthly Irrigated and Rainfed Crop Areas around the Year 2000 (MIRCA2000)</Label>
      <Link_Note>Please register to access this data set by filling out the form on this page. Then go to http://www.geo.uni-frankfurt.de/ipg/ag/dl/forschung/MIRCA/data_download/index.html. Readme files are located inside the download folders. Data users should check whether a new version or bigfixes are available, which is easily done via linking at e.g. http://www.geo.uni-frankfurt.de/ipg/ag/dl/forschung/MIRCA/index.html or at http://www.geo.uni-frankfurt.de/ipg/ag/dl/forschung/MIRCA/data_download/index.html.</Link_Note>
    </Data_Set_Link>
    <Documentation_Link>
      <URL />
      <Label />
      <Text />
    </Documentation_Link>
    <Documentation_Link>
      <URL />
      <Label />
    </Documentation_Link>
    <Alternate_Data_Access>
      <Data_Set_Status>Final</Data_Set_Status>
      <Data_Set_Restrictions>Public</Data_Set_Restrictions>
      <Data_Set_Location>The Oak Ridge National Laboratory (ORNL) Distributed Active Archive Center (DAAC)</Data_Set_Location>
      <Data_Contact_Person>
        <Email>ornldaac@ornl.gov</Email>
        <Name>ORNL DAAC User Services Office Oak Ridge National Laboratory Oak Ridge, Tennessee 37831 USA FAX: +1(865)574-4665</Name>
        <Phone>+1(865)241-3952</Phone>
        <Data_Center_URL>http://daac.ornl.gov/</Data_Center_URL>
      </Data_Contact_Person>
      <Data_Center_URL>http://daac.ornl.gov/</Data_Center_URL>
      <Data_Set_Citation>Oak Ridge National Laboratory (ORNL) Distributed Active Archive Center (DAAC). 2010. Global Data Set of Monthly Irrigated and Rainfed Crop Areas around the Year 2000 (MIRCA2000). Available online at [http://webmap.ornl.gov/wcsdown/dataset.jsp?ds_id=10015] from the Oak Ridge National Laboratory (ORNL) Distributed Active Archive Center (DAAC), Oak Ridge, Tennessee 37831 U.S.A.</Data_Set_Citation>
      <Data_Set_Link>
        <URL>http://webmap.ornl.gov/wcsdown/dataset.jsp?ds_id=10015</URL>
        <Label>Global Data Set of Monthly Irrigated and Rainfed Crop Areas around the Year 2000 (MIRCA2000)</Label>
        <Link_Note>This data set contains 26 data granules in GeoTIFF format. Use the links in the table on this web page to view and download data using WCS.</Link_Note>
        <Data_Center_URL>http://daac.ornl.gov/</Data_Center_URL>
      </Data_Set_Link>
    </Alternate_Data_Access>
    <OME_Software_Version>Version 4.7.5, Revision Date: 04 Apr 2006</OME_Software_Version>
    <OME_DTD_Version>basic02.dtd</OME_DTD_Version>
    <Contact_Person>
      <Email>hydrology@em.uni-frankfurt.de</Email>
      <Name>Portmann, F.T.</Name>
      <Phone>+49 69 798 40218</Phone>
    </Contact_Person>
    <Temporal_Resolution />
    <enddate_blank />
    <File_ID>Created 20101005 133555 by 69.19.14.37</File_ID>
    <Spatial_Reference_Method>Raster</Spatial_Reference_Method>
    <Spatial_Extent>64800</Spatial_Extent>
    <Search_Text_Link>
      <URL />
      <Label />
    </Search_Text_Link>
    <Other_Link>
      <URL />
      <Label />
    </Other_Link>
    <Granule_Details />
    <OGC_URL />
  </mercury>
  <sourceData>database</sourceData>
</metadata>