<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="corridor_SRS.4.2" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 eml.xsd"> <dataset scope="document"> <title>Corridor Project Data, Bird Dispersed Seed Movement in Corridors, Savannah River Site, SC USA, 2000-2001</title>
 <creator id="1246293904492" scope="document"> <individualName> <salutation>Dr.</salutation>
 <givenName>Douglas</givenName>
 <surName>Levey</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>University of Florida</organizationName>
 <positionName>Professor</positionName>
 <address scope="document"> <deliveryPoint>621 Carr, Box 118525</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Gainesville</city>
 <administrativeArea>FL</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>32611-8525</postalCode>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">(352) 392-9169</phone>
 <phone phonetype="fax">(352) 392-3704</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>dlevey@zoology.ufl.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <onlineUrl>http://www.zoology.ufl.edu/faculty/levey.html</onlineUrl>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1246023660349" scope="document"> <individualName> <salutation>Dr.</salutation>
 <givenName>Joshua</givenName>
 <surName>Tewksbury</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>University of Washington</organizationName>
 <positionName>Assistant Professor</positionName>
 <address scope="document"> <deliveryPoint>University of Washington, 528 Kincaid Hall, Box 351800</deliveryPoint>
 <city>Seattle</city>
 <administrativeArea>WA</administrativeArea>
 <postalCode>98115</postalCode>
 </address>
 <phone phonetype="voice">(206) 616-2129</phone>
 <phone phonetype="fax">(206) 616-2011</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>tewksjj@u.washington.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 <onlineUrl>http://faculty.washington.edu/tewksjj/</onlineUrl>
 </creator>
 <abstract> <para>The objective of this experiment was to look at bird dispersed seed movement in fragmented habitats and those connected by corridors.   It was conducted in experimental landscapes that consist of five open habitat patches surrounded by a mature pine plantation matrix.  There is one central patch surrounded by four peripheral patches.  One peripheral patch is connected to the central patch by a corridor; the unconnected peripheral patches have either a rectangular or winged shape.  Transplants and cuttings from bird dispersed species, Ilex vomitoria and Myrica cerifera, were placed in the central patches.  Sixteen artificial perches with seed traps were placed in each peripheral patch.  Fecal samples were collected from the traps weekly and analyzed for the presence of seeds from the central patch.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>Habitat Fragmentation</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>Connectivity</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>Corridor</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>Seed Dispersal</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>Bird</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <keywordSet> <keyword>Ornithochory</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <additionalInfo> <para>Article Citations: (1)Haddad, N.M., B. Hudgens, E.I. Damschen, D.J. Levey, J.L. Orrock, J.J. Tewksbury, and A.J. Weldon.  In press.  Assessing positive and negative ecological effects of corridors.  In J. Liu, V. Hull, A. Morzillo, and J. Wiens, Sources, sinks, and sustainability across landscapes, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK  (2)Levey, D. J., B. M. Bolker, J. J. Tewksbury, S. Sargent, N. M. Haddad. 2005. Effects of Landscape Corridors on Seed Dispersal by Birds.  Science 309:146-148  (3)Levey, D. J., J. J. Tewksbury, B. M. Bolker. In press. Modeling long-distance seed dispersal in heterogeneous landscapes. Journal of Ecology  (4)Tewksbury, J. J., D. J. Levey, N. M. Haddad, S. Sargent, J. L. Orrock, A. Weldon, B. J. Danielson, J. Brinkerhoff, E. I. Damschen, P. Townsend. 2002. Corridors affect plants, animals, and their interactions in fragmented landscapes. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 99:12923-12926</para>
 </additionalInfo>
 <intellectualRights> <para>Permission to use this data may be granted upon request to the designated contact person.</para>
 </intellectualRights>
 <coverage scope="document"> <geographicCoverage scope="document"> <geographicDescription>Data were collected at the Savannah River Site (SRS) in South Carolina.  SRS is located in Aiken, Barnwell, and Allendale counties, approximately 10 miles south of Aiken, SC.  The uplands are primarily longleaf pine (Pinus elliotii) plantations, loblolly pine (Pinus taeda) plantations, and longleaf pine savannah.</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates> <westBoundingCoordinate>-81.75708055555556</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>-81.50800833333334</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>33.372280555555555</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>33.185566666666666</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 <temporalCoverage scope="document"> <rangeOfDates> <beginDate> <calendarDate>2000-12-01</calendarDate>
 </beginDate>
 <endDate> <calendarDate>2001-02-15</calendarDate>
 </endDate>
 </rangeOfDates>
 </temporalCoverage>
 <taxonomicCoverage scope="document"> <taxonomicClassification> <taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Ilex</taxonRankValue>
 <taxonomicClassification> <taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>vomitoria</taxonRankValue>
 <commonName>yaupon holly</commonName>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 <taxonomicClassification> <taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>Myrica</taxonRankValue>
 <taxonomicClassification> <taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
 <taxonRankValue>cerifera</taxonRankValue>
 <commonName>wax myrtle</commonName>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicClassification>
 </taxonomicCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact id="1246023751788" scope="document"> <organizationName>The Corridor Project</organizationName>
 <electronicMailAddress>corridorproject@gmail.com</electronicMailAddress>
 </contact>
 <methods> <methodStep> <description> <para>Experimental Landscape Design</para>
 <section> <para>The data was collected in 50-ha experimental landscape blocks.  Each landscape includes five open habitats (patches) within mature longleaf and loblolly plantation forest.   The patches were created by harvesting the overstory and are being managed for longleaf pine savanna.  These patches include a central 100 X 100-m patch surrounded by four peripheral patches.  One peripheral patch is 100 X 100-m and connected to the center patch by a 25 X 150-m corridor (referred to as the"connected patch").  The other peripheral patches are either a 100 X 137.5-m rectangular patch or a 100 X 100-m patch with two 25 X 75-m projections on opposite sides (referred to as a"winged patch").  All peripheral patch types are 150-m from the center patch.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep> <description> <para>Seed Provision Methods</para>
 <section> <para>In the central patch, cuttings of yaupon holly (Ilex Vomitoria; Aquifoliaceae) were wired to four rebar stations and arranged to look like real trees.  Each of the cuttings was 2-3 meters tall with 1,500-5,000 fruits.  Every two weeks during the period of 1 December 2000 to 15 February 2001, the cuttings were replaced with fresh ones.  Additionally, three mature wax myrtle (Myrica cerifera; Myricaceae) bushes were placed in the central patch.  The M. cerifera bushes were all female and were supplemented by wiring four to eight cuttings into the bush.  These cuttings were replaced weekly.  Since M. cerifera is abundant in the area, the M. cerifera fruits in the central patch were sprayed with a solution of fluorescent powder and Wilt-Pruf (Wilt-Pruf Products Essex, CT).  A Nikon Optiphot 2 epifluorescent microscope with a FITC filter block and X20 objective lens was used to determine if the fecal samples contained florescent powder.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep> <description> <para>Seed Collection Methods</para>
 <section> <para>The seeds were collected from bird fecal samples that had fallen in seed traps located beneath artificial perches.  The perches were 3-m tall PVC poles with a horizontal dowel 1.2-m from the ground.  Each connected patch had 16 perches arranged on a four by four grid with six additional perches in a straight line down the center of the corridor.  The winged patches had 16 poles on a four by four grid in the center of the patch; additionally, each winged projection had three perches spaced out along the center of the projection.  The rectangle patches had perches arranged based on a four by six grid; perches were at every position on that grid except for the row of four farthest from the central patch, which only had perches in the center two columns.  All poles were 25-m from all other poles and at least 12.5-m from the edge.  Basket traps were positioned just below the top of the PVC.  Seed traps (27 X 51 cm) with a 1-cm grid hardware cloth covering were positioned below the dowel elevated about 1-inch from the ground.  Fecal samples were collected weekly from 1 December 2000 to 15 February 2001.  A total of 3,805 fecal samples were collected.</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 <methodStep> <description> <para>Labeling Descriptions</para>
 <section> <para>The eight experimental blocks used are labeled as 8, 10, 53N, 53S, 54N, 54S, 75W and 75E.  Within each of the experimental blocks, the patches are labeled with letters A to E.  The central patch is labeled as A and the connected patch is labeled as B.  Moving clockwise from patch B, the other peripheral patches are labeled as C, D, and E.  Patches C, D, and E are randomly assigned to either winged or rectangular patch types.  The winged patches are 8-C, 8-E, 10-D, 53N-C, 53N-E, 53S-C, 53S-E, 54N-D, 54S-D, 75E-D, 75E-E and 75W-D.  The rectangular patches are 8-D, 10-C, 10-E, 53N-D, 53S-D, 54N-C, 54N-E, 54S-C, 54S-E, 75E-C, 75W-C and 75W-E.</para>
 <para>Coordinate locations associated with the experimental blocks:  Block-8, 33&#176;22'11.67"N 81&#176;42'09.33"W; Block-10, 33&#176;17'57.88"N 81&#176;44'57.55"W; Block-53N, 33&#176;19'31.49"N 81&#176;35'09.23"W; Block-53S, 33&#176;18'39.15"N 81&#176;34'23.65"W; Block-54N, 33&#176;19'22.64"N 81&#176;32'07.71"W; Block-54S, 33&#176;17'37.95"N 81&#176;31'45.30"W; Block-75W, 33&#176;11'30.84"N 81&#176;31'10.30"W; Block-75E, 33&#176;11'54.97"N 81&#176;33'10.99"W</para>
 </section>
 </description>
 </methodStep>
 </methods>
 <project scope="document"> <title>The Corridor Project</title>
 <personnel scope="document"> <references>1246023751788</references>
 <role>Project</role>
 </personnel>
 <funding> <para>National Science Foundation Grants DEB-9815834, DEB-9907365; and by funds provided to the Department of Agriculture, Forest Service, Savannah River, under Interagency Agreement DE-AI09-00SR22188 with the Department of Energy, Aiken, SC</para>
 </funding>
 </project>
 <access authSystem="knb" order="denyFirst" scope="document"> <allow> <principal>public</principal>
 <permission>read</permission>
 </allow>
 </access>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>