<metadata xmlns:ns0="http://purl.org/ornl/schema/mercury/terms/v1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://purl.org/ornl/schema/mercury/terms/v1.0 mercury-ornl-v1.xsd">
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Environmental Protection Agency</origin>
        <origin>United States Geologic Survey (USGS)</origin>
        <title>Map ORR Land Cover LandsatTM NLCD 30m 1992</title>
        <onlink>http://daac.ornl.gov/data/bluangel_harvest/WBW/gibbs/metadata/Map_ORR_Land_Cover_LandsatTM_NLCD_30m_1992.xml</onlink>
        <onlink>ftp://ftp.esd.ornl.gov/pub/orr/Maps/Land_Cover/ORR/based_on_Landsat/1992_nlcd/Browse%20ORR%20Land%20Cover%201992%20NLCD.html</onlink>
        <onlink>http://www.epa.gov/mrlc/</onlink>
        <onlink>http://landcover.usgs.gov/nationallandcover.asp</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This land cover map is a subset of the National Land Cover Dataset (NLCD) produced by the Multi-Resolution Land Characteristics (MRLC) Consortium (USGS, EPA, NOAA, and USFS) 1/6/1999. The NLCD was produced in order to provide a consistent, land cover data layer for the conterminous U.S. utilizing early 1990s Landsat Thematic Mapper data.  The raster map depicts the land cover of the Oak Ridge Reservation at a 30m spatial resolution.
     Yang et al. (2001) found the thematic accuracy for the MRLC land cover map for the eastern U.S. to be 59.7% at Anderson Level II thematic detail and 80.5% at Anderson Level I.  
     
The NLCD classification scheme (based on Anderson et al. 1976)  is as follows - 

Water - All areas of open water or permanent ice/snow cover.
     11. Open Water - all areas of open water, generally with less than 25% cover of   vegetation/land cover. 
     12. Perennial Ice/Snow - all areas characterized by year-long surface cover of ice and/or snow.

Developed Areas characterized by a high percentage (30 percent or greater) of constructed materials (e.g. asphalt, concrete, buildings, etc).
      21. Low Intensity Residential - Includes areas with a mixture of constructed materials and vegetation. Constructed materials account for 30-80 percent of the cover. Vegetation may account for 20 to 70 percent of the cover. These areas most commonly include single-family housing units. Population densities will be lower than in high intensity residential areas.
      22. High Intensity Residential - Includes highly developed areas where people reside in high numbers. Examples include apartment complexes and row houses. Vegetation accounts for less than 20 percent of the cover. Constructed materials account for 80 to100 percent of the cover.
      23. Commercial/Industrial/Transportation - Includes infrastructure (e.g. roads, railroads, etc.) and all highly developed areas not classified as High Intensity Residential.

Barren - Areas characterized by bare rock, gravel, sand, silt, clay, or other earthen material, with little or no green vegetation present regardless of its inherent ability to support life. Vegetation, if present, is more widely spaced and scrubby than that in the green vegetated categories; lichen cover may be extensive. 
      31. Bare Rock/Sand/Clay - Perennially barren areas of bedrock, desert pavement, scarps, talus, slides, volcanic material, glacial debris, beaches, and other accumulations of earthen material.
      32. Quarries/Strip Mines/Gravel Pits - Areas of extractive mining activities with significant surface expression.
      33. Transitional - Areas of sparse vegetative cover (less than 25 percent of cover) that are dynamically changing from one land cover to another, often because of land use activities. Examples include forest clearcuts, a transition phase between forest and agricultural land, the temporary clearing of vegetation, and changes due to natural causes (e.g. fire, flood, etc.).

Forested Upland - Areas characterized by tree cover (natural or semi-natural woody vegetation, generally greater than 6 meters tall); tree canopy accounts for 25-100 percent of the cover.
      41. Deciduous Forest - Areas dominated by trees where 75 percent or more of the tree species shed foliage simultaneously in response to seasonal change.
      42. Evergreen Forest - Areas dominated by trees where 75 percent or more of the tree species maintain their leaves all year. Canopy is never without green foliage.
      43. Mixed Forest - Areas dominated by trees where neither deciduous nor evergreen species represent more than 75 percent of the cover present. 

Shrubland - Areas characterized by natural or semi-natural woody vegetation with aerial stems, generally less than 6 meters tall, with individuals or clumps not touching to interlocking. Both evergreen and deciduous species of true shrubs, young trees, and trees or shrubs that are small or stunted because of environmental conditions are included.
      51. Shrubland - Areas dominated by shrubs; shrub canopy accounts for 25-100 percent of the cover. Shrub cover is generally greater than 25 percent when tree cover is less than 25 percent. Shrub cover may be less than 25 percent in cases when the cover of other life forms (e.g. herbaceous or tree) is less than 25 percent and shrubs cover exceeds the cover of the other life forms.

Non-Natural Woody - Areas dominated by non-natural woody vegetation; non-natural woody vegetative canopy accounts for 25-100 percent of the cover. The non-natural woody classification is subject to the availability of sufficient ancillary data to differentiate non-natural woody vegetation from natural woody vegetation. 
      61. Orchards/Vineyards/Other - Orchards, vineyards, and other areas planted or maintained for the production of fruits, nuts, berries, or ornamentals. 

Herbaceous Upland - Upland areas characterized by natural or semi-natural herbaceous vegetation; herbaceous vegetation accounts for 75-100 percent of the cover.
      71. Grasslands/Herbaceous - Areas dominated by upland grasses and forbs. In rare cases, herbaceous cover is less than 25 percent, but exceeds the combined cover of the woody species present. These areas are not subject to intensive management, but they are often utilized for grazing.

Planted/Cultivated - Areas characterized by herbaceous vegetation that has been planted or is intensively managed for the production of food, feed, or fiber; or is maintained in developed settings for specific purposes. Herbaceous vegetation accounts for 75-100 percent of the cover. 
      81. Pasture/Hay - Areas of grasses, legumes, or grass-legume mixtures planted for livestock grazing or the production of seed or hay crops.
      82. Row Crops - Areas used for the production of crops, such as corn, soybeans, vegetables, tobacco, and cotton. 
      83. Small Grains - Areas used for the production of graminoid crops such as wheat, barley, oats, and rice.
      84. Fallow - Areas used for the production of crops that do not exhibit visable vegetation as a result of being tilled in a management practice that incorporates prescribed alternation between cropping and tillage.
      85. Urban/Recreational Grasses - Vegetation (primarily grasses) planted in developed settings for recreation, erosion control, or aesthetic purposes. Examples include parks, lawns, golf courses, airport grasses, and industrial site grasses. 

Wetlands - Areas where the soil or substrate is periodically saturated with or covered with water.
      91. Woody Wetlands - Areas where forest or shrubland vegetation accounts for 25-100 percent of the cover and the  soil or substrate is periodically saturated with or covered with water.
      92. Emergent Herbaceous Wetlands - Areas where perennial herbaceous vegetation accounts for 75-100 percent of the cover and the soil or substrate is periodically saturated with or covered with water.


Citations
Anderson, J. F., E. E. Hardy, J. T. Roach, and R. E. Witmer. 1976. A land use and land cover classification system for use with remote sensor data. In: U.S. Geological Survy Professional Paper. 964 (pp.28). Washingont, DC: U.S. Geological Survey.

Yang, L., S. V. Stehman, J. H. Smith, and J. D. Wichham. 2001. Thematic accuracy of MRLC land cover for the eastern United States. Remote Sensing of Environment, 76:418-422.</abstract>
      <supplinf />
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>19900101</begdate>
          <enddate>19930101</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Final</progress>
      <update>As appropriate</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-84.44</westbc>
        <eastbc>84.19</eastbc>
        <northbc>36</northbc>
        <southbc>-35.87</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>Parameter_Sensor_Source</themekt>
        <themekey>LAND CLASSES|LANDSAT TM(LANDSAT THEMATIC MAPPER)|LANDSAT-5</themekey>
        <themekt>Parameter</themekt>
        <themekey>LAND CLASSES</themekey>
        <themekt>Source</themekt>
        <themekey>LANDSAT-5</themekey>
        <themekt>Sensor</themekt>
        <themekey>LANDSAT TM(LANDSAT THEMATIC MAPPER)</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Place Keywords</placekt>
        <placekey>Oak Ridge Reservation, TN, USA</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Environmental Protection Agency</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntfax>6.1.10.8 Contact Electronic Mail: INTERNET &amp;gt; N/A</cntfax>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Environmental Sciences Division, Oak Ridge National Laboratory</cntorg>
          <cntper>Gibbs, Holly K.</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntvoice>(865) 574-7356</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>6.1.10.8 Contact Electronic Mail: INTERNET &amp;gt; N/A</cntfax>
        <cntemail>gibbshk@ornl.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>ftp://ftp.esd.ornl.gov/pub/orr/</computer>
            <accinstr>Public</accinstr>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
    </stdorder>
    <resdesc>Vogelmann, J.E., Howard, S.M., Yang, L., Larson, C.R., Wylie, B.K., Van
Driel, N.,  Completion of the 1990s National Land Cover Dataset for the
Coterminous United States from Landsat Thematic Mapper Data and Ancillary
Data Sources. Photogrammetric Engineering and Remote Sensing, v. 67, no. 6,
p. 650 - 661.</resdesc>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20040323 151543</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntper>Gibbs, Holly K.</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Gibbs, Holly K.</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntvoice>(865) 574-7356</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>gibbshk@ornl.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
  </metainfo>
  <mercury>
    <begdate>19900101</begdate>
    <enddate>19930101</enddate>
    <Site_Information>
      <Site>Oak Ridge Reservation, TN, USA</Site>
      <Westernmost_Longitude>-84.44</Westernmost_Longitude>
      <Easternmost_Longitude>84.19</Easternmost_Longitude>
      <Northernmost_Latitude>36</Northernmost_Latitude>
      <Southernmost_Latitude>-35.87</Southernmost_Latitude>
    </Site_Information>
    <Keywords>Oak Ridge Reservation</Keywords>
    <Keywords>Landsat</Keywords>
    <Keywords>Land cover</Keywords>
    <Keywords>Land use</Keywords>
    <Keywords>MRLC</Keywords>
    <Keywords>NLCD</Keywords>
    <Keywords>Naitonal Land Characterization Database</Keywords>
    <Parameter_Description>
      <Parameter>LAND CLASSES</Parameter>
      <Sensor>LANDSAT TM(LANDSAT THEMATIC MAPPER)</Sensor>
      <Source>LANDSAT-5</Source>
      <Term>LAND USE/LAND COVER</Term>
      <Topic>LAND SURFACE</Topic>
    </Parameter_Description>
    <Project>The Oak Ridge Reservation Bioenergy and Carbon Sequestration Initiative; managed by Robin L. Graham</Project>
    <Navpath>LANDSAT-5|LANDSAT TM(LANDSAT THEMATIC MAPPER)|LAND CLASSES</Navpath>
    <Principal_Investigator>
      <Name>Environmental Protection Agency</Name>
      <Email>N/A</Email>
    </Principal_Investigator>
    <Principal_Investigator>
      <Name>United States Geologic Survey (USGS)</Name>
      <Email>custserv@edcmail.cr.usgs.gov</Email>
    </Principal_Investigator>
    <Data_Set_Link>
      <URL>ftp://ftp.esd.ornl.gov/pub/orr/Maps/Land_Cover/ORR/based_on_Landsat/1992_nlcd/</URL>
      <Label>Download 1992 Land Cover Map</Label>
      <Link_Note />
    </Data_Set_Link>
    <Documentation_Link>
      <URL>ftp://ftp.esd.ornl.gov/pub/orr/Maps/Land_Cover/ORR/based_on_Landsat/1992_nlcd/Browse%20ORR%20Land%20Cover%201992%20NLCD.html</URL>
      <Label>Browse image and metadata</Label>
      <Text />
    </Documentation_Link>
    <Documentation_Link>
      <URL>http://www.epa.gov/mrlc/</URL>
      <Label>EPA link to National Land Cover Data set</Label>
    </Documentation_Link>
    <Documentation_Link>
      <URL>http://landcover.usgs.gov/nationallandcover.asp</URL>
      <Label>USGS link to National Land Cover Data set</Label>
    </Documentation_Link>
    <Alternate_Data_Access>
      <Data_Set_Status />
      <Data_Set_Restrictions />
      <Data_Set_Location />
      <Data_Contact_Person>
        <Email />
        <Name />
        <Phone />
        <Data_Center_URL />
      </Data_Contact_Person>
      <Data_Center_URL />
      <Data_Set_Citation />
      <Data_Set_Link>
        <URL />
        <Label />
        <Link_Note />
        <Data_Center_URL />
      </Data_Set_Link>
    </Alternate_Data_Access>
    <OME_Software_Version>Version 4.3.03, Revision Date: 21 October 2003</OME_Software_Version>
    <OME_DTD_Version>metadata23.dtd</OME_DTD_Version>
    <Contact_Person>
      <Email>gibbshk@ornl.gov</Email>
      <Name>Gibbs, Holly K.</Name>
      <Phone>(865) 574-7356</Phone>
    </Contact_Person>
    <Temporal_Resolution>N/A</Temporal_Resolution>
    <enddate_blank />
    <Harvest_Date>20140923</Harvest_Date>
    <File_ID>Created 20020413 174012 by 160.91.16.106</File_ID>
    <Spatial_Reference_Method>Raster</Spatial_Reference_Method>
    <Spatial_Extent>12119.4381</Spatial_Extent>
    <Search_Text_Link>
      <URL>ftp://ftp.esd.ornl.gov/pub/orr/Maps/Land_Cover/ORR/based_on_Landsat/1992_nlcd/Browse%20ORR%20Land%20Cover%201992%20NLCD.html</URL>
      <Label>Browse image and metadata</Label>
    </Search_Text_Link>
    <Other_Link>
      <URL>http://www.epa.gov/mrlc/</URL>
      <Label>EPA link to National Land Cover Data set</Label>
    </Other_Link>
    <Other_Link>
      <URL>http://landcover.usgs.gov/nationallandcover.asp</URL>
      <Label>USGS link to National Land Cover Data set</Label>
    </Other_Link>
  </mercury>
</metadata>