<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="MontanaIOE.120.2" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 eml.xsd">  <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst"><allow><principal>public</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
</allow>
<allow><principal>cn=viglesias,ou=people,dc=rcg,dc=montana,dc=edu</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
<permission>write</permission>
</allow>
<allow><principal>cn=cwhitlock,ou=people,dc=rcg,dc=montana,dc=edu</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
<permission>write</permission>
</allow>
</access>
<dataset> <title>Changes in forest structure of a mixed conifer forest, southwestern Colorado, USA.</title>
 <creator id="1404011909993"> <individualName><givenName>P.Z.</givenName>
 <surName>Fule</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>School of Forestry and Ecological Restoration Institute, Northern Arizona University</organizationName>
 <phone phonetype="voice">+1 928 523 1463</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>Pete.Fule@nau.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1404011988600"><individualName><givenName>J.E.</givenName>
 <surName>Korb</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Department of Biology, Fort Lewis College</organizationName>
 </creator>
 <creator id="1404012015449"><individualName><givenName>R.</givenName>
 <surName>Wu</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>USDA Forest Service, San Juan National Forest</organizationName>
 </creator>
 <abstract><para>We selected a warm/dry mixed conifer forest (ponderosa pine, white fir, Douglas-fir, and aspen) in southwestern Colorado to reconstruct historical conditions of fire regime and forest structure in preparation for an experiment in ecological restoration. Although mixed conifer forests are of high ecological and social value in the Southwest, they have been less studied than ponderosa pine forests. Fire-scar analysis on a 150-ha area showed recurring fires at mean intervals of 24 years (all fires with minimum of 2 sample trees scarred) to 32 years (fire scarring 25% or more of sample trees) from the 16th century until the abrupt cessation of fire after 1868, concurrent with European settlement. There was no evidence in age or species-specific data of severe burning at the scale of the study blocks (approximately 200&#160;ha). The forest remained unharvested throughout most of the 20th century, until a cut in the early 1990s removed approximately equal basal areas of ponderosa pine and white fir. Forest structure had already changed substantially, however. Total basal area increased from an average of 11&#160;m2&#160;ha&#8722;1 in 1870 to 27&#160;m2&#160;ha&#8722;1 in 2003, despite harvesting of at least 8.4&#160;m2&#160;ha&#8722;1. Ponderosa pine declined from representing nearly two-thirds of basal area in 1870 to one-third in 2003. The other species increased dramatically, especially white fir, which went from 12% to 35% of basal area and dominated stand density with an average of 392&#160;trees&#160;ha&#8722;1. Total tree density increased from 142&#160;trees&#160;ha&#8722;1 in 1870 to 677&#160;trees&#160;ha&#8722;1 in 2003. The ecological changes that occurred here since the 19th century have been in exactly the opposite direction considering the warm, fire-favoring climate expected in the 21st century. If warm/dry mixed conifer forests of southern Colorado are to have a reasonable chance for persistence under the future climate regime, restoring conditions more similar to the frequently burned, open forests of the past is likely to be a useful starting point.

Ful&#233; P.Z., J.E. Korb and R. Wu. 2009. Changes in forest structure of a mixed conifer forest, southwestern Colorado, USA. Forest Ecology and Management 258, 1200.1210. DOI, 10.1016/j.foreco.2009.06.015.</para>
 </abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>ecological restoration</keyword>
 <keyword>San Juan mountains</keyword>
 <keyword>fire history</keyword>
 <keyword>dendrochronology</keyword>
 <keyword>fuel</keyword>
 </keywordSet>
 <intellectualRights><para>The broad spectrum of possible applications of paleoenvironmental data suggests an array of potential users of the database, ranging from the original collectors of the data, their collaborators, interested scientists, reviewers, meta-analysts, resource managers and educators. We would like published data in the database to be available without restrictions and free of cost. For end users to get the most value from the records, it is important that data be archived in a format that can be interpreted by non-specialists both now and in the future. Our central goal has been to ensure that users can easily access the raw data and correctly interpret the records.</para>
 </intellectualRights>
 <coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Lower Middle Mountain_CO_Fire scar</geographicDescription>
 <boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-107.228</westBoundingCoordinate>
 <eastBoundingCoordinate>-107.228</eastBoundingCoordinate>
 <northBoundingCoordinate>37.296</northBoundingCoordinate>
 <southBoundingCoordinate>37.296</southBoundingCoordinate>
 </boundingCoordinates>
 </geographicCoverage>
 </coverage>
 <contact id="1404012047778"><individualName><givenName>Cathy</givenName>
 <surName>Whitlock</surName>
 </individualName>
 <organizationName>Montana State University</organizationName>
 <positionName>Director, Montana Institute on Ecosystems</positionName>
 <phone phonetype="voice">(406) 994-6910</phone>
 <electronicMailAddress>whitlock@montana.edu</electronicMailAddress>
 </contact>
 <otherEntity><entityName>Data_and_metadata</entityName>
 <physical><objectName>Firescar_Set7.csv</objectName>
 <size unit="byte">1058</size>
 <dataFormat><externallyDefinedFormat><formatName>text/plain</formatName>
 </externallyDefinedFormat>
 </dataFormat>
 <distribution id="1404012125990"><online><url function="download">ecogrid://knb/MontanaIOE.119.1</url>
 </online>
 </distribution>
 </physical>
 <entityType>Other</entityType>
 </otherEntity>
 </dataset>
 </ns0:eml>