<ns0:eml xmlns:ns0="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="judithk.723.6" scope="system" system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.0.1 eml.xsd"> <dataset scope="document">  <title>Patch Dynamics and Clonal Expansion of Reeds in the Letaba River, Kruger National Park</title>
<creator id="1160116891007" scope="document"><individualName><surName>Kotschy</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>University of the Witwatesrand</organizationName>
<address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>School of Animal Plant and Environmental Sciences</deliveryPoint>
<deliveryPoint>University of the Witwatesrand</deliveryPoint>
</address>
</creator>
<abstract><para>A multiscale approach was used to study the dynamics of reed patches in a section of the
Letaba River flowing through the Kruger National Park (KNP), South Africa's largest conservation
area. The valley floor consists of a mosaic of patches of reeds, water, sand and
rock. Reed vegetation change in space and time is closely linked to geomorphic change in
the rivers of the KNP, because of reciprocal interactions between reeds, flow and sediment.
Reeds are thus considered a potentially important species around which to formulate management
goals for these rivers.
A study of clonal growth characteristics at the scale of individual reedbeds was combined
with a study of reed patch dynamics at the river reach scale. Mechanisms affecting clonal
expansion across reedbed boundaries were combined with short-term patterns of reed
persistence, loss and gain at the reach scale, and longer-term trends in reed cover, to
produce a conceptual model of proposed relationships between flow conditions and reed
cover in the Letaba River.
Reed areal cover increased between 1988 and 1999. Despite this, reed persistence was
low, and reeds were a dynamic element of the river landscape in the short term. Turnover
of water and reed patches was high, within a matrix of sand. Complex patterns of reed
gain and loss occurred at the boundaries of reed patches, with gain exceeding loss throughout
the period of study.
During a drier period (1988-1996), clonal expansion of patches and establishment of new
patches contributed equally (50% each) to the increase in reed cover. During a wetter
period (1996-1999), the relative contribution of clonal expansion increased to 90%. Reed
persistence was higher in the wetter period due to less reed loss, and reed cover increased
more rapidly.
The relative proportions of reed, water and sand patches did not remain constant over 3
years or over 8 years in the alluvial section of the river studied. At the time and space scales
of this study, therefore, the Letaba River did not display the kind of compositional stability
described in other river systems. This points to the difficulty of applying equilibrium
concepts of either geomorphology or vegetation dynamics to semi-arid rivers.
A clear spatial patchiness was present in the distribution of sediment and nutrient resources
on the macro-channel floor. Reed patches were associated with `current shadow'
features, the characteristic raised elevation of the central, denser parts of reedbeds suggesting accumulation of sediment within reedbeds. Silt and clay particles accumulated
preferentially within reedbeds. The results suggest that this accumulation was achieved
primarily by selective retention of nes within reedbeds, and to a lesser extent by selective
deposition of stones within reedbeds.
Total carbon, nitrogen and phosphorus were all higher beneath reedbeds than in uncolonised
sediment. The distributions of total N and total P were not correlated with
that of total C, suggesting that nutrient accumulation does not simply reflect breakdown
of reed organic matter. It was proposed that the nutrient accumulation recorded in this
study was due primarily to interactions between reedbeds and flow, and to a lesser extent
to the input of reed organic matter. The fact that surface resource distribution patterns did
not always correspond to subsurface patterns illustrates the importance of viewing reed
patches as three-dimensional entities.
A high stem density and limited plasticity in spacer characteristics of Phragmites mauritianus
in the Letaba River were consistent with a consolidation strategy of clonal growth.
Physiological integration within within the clone was, however, limited&#151;a notable departure
from the consolidation strategy.
While Phragmites mauritianus showed little evidence of plasticity in the horizontal spacer
characteristics traditionally measured in studies of clonal growth patterns (internode length,
branching pattern and bud activity), it was proposed that plasticity in rhizome characteristics
related to regenerative capacity is important for reed persistence and clonal expansion
in this habitat. The added vertical dimension of the rhizome system in species such as
P. mauritianus limits the usefulness of horizontal spacer characteristics in explaining patterns
of clonal expansion. Progressive accumulation of sediment above the rhizomes and
upgrowth of reeds to the surface was proposed as a mechanism whereby the depth of the
rhizome layer is increased, thus increasing the density of reed stems and enhancing the
persistence of the reedbed.
Rhizomes at reedbed boundaries did not show particular adaptations for rapid expansion
into available space. Clonal expansion and consolidation of the space aroud established
reedbeds was limited both by features of the rhizomes themselves (high proportion of
dormant buds, low branching probability and shallow depth), and by external factors
(flow disturbance).
Management concerns over reed `encroachment' in the Letaba River appear unfounded.
While rapid reed expansion may occur during favourable periods, conditions suitable for
large increases in reed cover occur relatively infrequently and persist for short periods of
time. It was proposed that wet periods with a high frequency of medium flows and no
large floods are most likely to be associated with large increases in reed cover.</para>
</abstract>
 <keywordSet><keyword>Reeds, clonal expansion, Letaba River, Kruger National Park</keyword>
</keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword>SANParks, South Africa</keyword><keyword>Kruger National Park, South Africa</keyword></keywordSet>
<intellectualRights><para>Digital and non-digital data and metadata belonging to the Kruger National Park Scientific Services are provided on an "as-is" basis with no guarantee as to data quality. Neither the staff nor South African National Parks (SANParks) may be held liable for any loss of any sort resulting from use of data and/metadata provided by Scientific Services</para>
</intellectualRights>
<coverage scope="document"><geographicCoverage scope="document"><geographicDescription>Letaba River</geographicDescription>
<boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>31.144636</westBoundingCoordinate>
<eastBoundingCoordinate>31.826395</eastBoundingCoordinate>
<northBoundingCoordinate>-23.648514</northBoundingCoordinate>
<southBoundingCoordinate>-23.989389</southBoundingCoordinate>
</boundingCoordinates>
</geographicCoverage>
<temporalCoverage scope="document"><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>1988</calendarDate>
</beginDate>
<endDate><calendarDate>1999</calendarDate>
</endDate>
</rangeOfDates>
</temporalCoverage>
<taxonomicCoverage scope="document"><taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
<taxonRankValue>Phragmites</taxonRankValue>
<taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
<taxonRankValue>mauritianus</taxonRankValue>
</taxonomicClassification>
</taxonomicClassification>
</taxonomicCoverage>
</coverage>
<contact id="1086295214645" scope="document"><individualName><surName>Kruger</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>SANParks</organizationName>
<address scope="document"><deliveryPoint>Private Bag x402</deliveryPoint>
<city>Skukuza</city>
<postalCode>1350</postalCode>
<country>South Africa</country>
</address>
</contact>
<methods><methodStep><description><section><title>Methods</title>
<para>Carter and Rogers (1995) analysed changes in reed cover up until 1988. Aerial photographs</para>
<para>from 1988, 1996 and 1999 were used to extend their work. A Geographical</para>
<para>Information System (GIS), PCI-ILWIS, was used to analyse the aerial photographs. The</para>
<para>GIS software made it possible to calculate not only changes in reed cover, but also changes</para>
<para>in the distribution of reeds within the macro-channel. It was thus possible to determine</para>
<para>the persistence of reedbeds and to assess the relative contributions of clonal expansion and</para>
<para>establishment of new patches to changes in reed cover. Spatial and temporal relationships</para>
<para>between reed patches, and water and sand patches, could also be investigated.</para>
<para>Since the focus of this thesis is on the dynamics of reed patches, an alluvial section of the</para>
<para>river was chosen for study. Alluvial channel types have a smaller diversity of patches on</para>
<para>the macro&#150;channel oor than other channel types, because of the absence of bedrock and</para>
<para>woody vegetation. Reed patches could also be distinguished relatively easily on the aerial</para>
<para>photographs. The 25 km llong study section lay between Mingerhout and Engelhard dams</para>
<para>(Figure 2.1). The work of Carter and Rogers (1995) showed that landscape state changes</para>
<para>taking place in this section reflect the changes taking place in the river as a whole, both in</para>
<para>overall pattern and in relative magnitude.</para>
<para>Eight subsections were selected from the study section, each approximately 300 m in</para>
<para>length. These were chosen subjectively in order to cover both the length of the study</para>
<para>section and the range of histories of reed change (increasing reed cover, decreasing reed</para>
<para>cover, and no change). Four of the subsections included the study sites at which fieldwork</para>
<para>was done (Chapter 5).</para>
<para>The aerial photographs were digitized using a scanner, at a resolution of 300 dots per</para>
<para>inch (dpi), giving a pixel size of approximately 0.8 m</para>
<para>0.8 m on the ground. The three photographs from each site were then cross-georeferenced using features recognisable on all three photos (mainly trees). Pixels were classified as either reeds, water or sand using</para>
<para>unsupervised classification based on grayscale ranges. Woody vegetation could not be</para>
<para>uniquely identified on the basis of its grayscale range, and was omitted from the analysis.</para>
<para>This was not considered a problem as woody vegetation in this section of the Letaba occurs</para>
<para>almost exclusively as a riparian fringe on the macro&#150;channel banks and does not form</para>
<para>part of the mosaic of patches on the macro-channel oor. Occasional `problem' patches</para>
<para>of woody vegetation were masked using the GIS software and thus ommitted from the</para>
<para>analysis. The accuracy of each classification was assessed visually from the photographs</para>
<para>and by comparing the maps produced by the GIS with reed distribution at the study sites.</para>
<para>The resulting maps of reed distribution for each year were then combined to produce</para>
<para>raster maps showing the location of patches (pixels) which had undergone one of nine</para>
<para>categories of change, as follows:</para>
<para>1) reeds-&gt; reeds 4) sand-&gt; reeds 7) water-&gt; reeds</para>
<para>2) reeds-&gt; sand 5) sand-&gt; sand 8) water-&gt; sand</para>
<para>3) reeds-&gt; water 6) sand-&gt; water 9) water-&gt; water</para>
<para>Two sets of these combined maps were produced, one for each of the two time periods</para>
<para>(1988 to 1996, and 1996 to 1999). This made it possible to compare changes taking place</para>
<para>over a longer and a shorter period (8 years and 3 years).</para>
<para>3.2.1 Short-term reed dynamics: changes in cover, persistence,</para>
</section>
</description>
</methodStep>
<methodStep><description><section><title>Short term reed dynamics: changes in cover, persistence, gain and loss</title>
<para>The GIS software was used to calculate the proportion of the macro-channel covered by</para>
<para>each of the nine categories of change for each period. Reed cover present at the beginning</para>
<para>of a period could then be calculated by combining categories 1, 2 and 3, and that present</para>
<para>at the end of a period by combining categories 1, 4 and 7. Changes in the proportion of</para>
<para>the macro-channel covered by water and sand were calculated in a similar way.</para>
<para>Pattterns of reed persistence, appearance and disappearance were investigated by calculating</para>
<para>the frequencies of each type of change involving reeds (categories 1, 2, 3, 4 and 7)</para>
<para>as a percentage of the total changes involving reeds. These were compared between the</para>
<para>two time periods using two-sample t tests.</para>
<para>Reed persistence is a measure of what proportion of reed patches were able to maintain</para>
<para>their position on the macro-channel floor, and thus, possibly, undergo clonal expansion. It</para>
<para>was calculated as the proportion of reeds which were not lost or gained during a period,</para>
<para>in other words, those that maintained their position in space (category 1). Reed turnover</para>
<para>was therefore defined as the reciprocal of persistence: the proportion of reed patches</para>
<para>which did not maintain their position in space. Reeds which were lost are given by the</para>
<para>relative frequencies of categories 2 and 3, while reeds which became established are given</para>
<para>by the frequencies of categories 4 and 7.</para>
<para>Although this approach differs slightly from that of Arscott et al. (2002), where patch</para>
<para>turnover was calculated as the proportional area of new patches present at the end of</para>
<para>each time period, it allows patterns of reed loss and reed gain to be distinguished, and</para>
<para>therefore allows for a more detailed analysis of reed dynamics. The term turnover, as</para>
<para>used by Arscott et al. (2002), is misleading in the sense that it suggests complete removal</para>
<para>and re-establishment of patches, whereas in fact it simply indicates the extent of new</para>
<para>reed area, which may have arisen either by establishment of new patches or by clonal</para>
<para>expansion of existing patches. Patch turnover was, however, also calculated as described</para>
<para>above, to allow the results of this study to be compared with those of Arscott et al. (2002),</para>
<para>the only other known study of patch turnover in a disturbance-driven river system.</para>
<para>It was hypothesised that high reed persistence increases the potential for clonal expansion,</para>
<para>and thus produces a greater increase in cover. This hypothesis was tested by relating</para>
<para>percentage change in reed cover in each subsection to reed persistence using regression</para>
<para>models.</para>
<para>The response variable for regression models was always plotted against the fitted values</para>
<para>to allow visual inspection of the fit of the model. The model fit was assessed further using</para>
<para>the following diagnostic plots:</para>
<para>Residuals vs fitted values, useful for identifying outliers and visualising structure in</para>
<para>the residuals</para>
<para>Normal quantile plot of residuals, to test the assumption that the model's errors are</para>
<para>normally distributed</para>
<para>Scale-location plot, for measuring spread and identifying pattern in the residuals</para>
<para>Cook's distance plot, a measure of the inuence of individual observations on the</para>
<para>regression coefficients</para>
<para>To determine whether the fate of reed patches depends on their association with other</para>
<para>patch types, the probabilities of association between reeds and all the other categories of</para>
<para>change were calculated for each river section. This was done by calculating, for each type</para>
<para>of reed pixel, the number of neighbouring pixels of each of the 9 categories of change.</para>
<para>Reed pixels included reeds which remained (cagegory 1); reeds which were lost (categories</para>
<para>2 and 3); and new reeds which became established (categories 4 and 7). While</para>
<para>pixels of a particular type are most likely to be surrounded by pixels of the same type, it is</para>
<para>the relationships with neighbouring pixels of different types that can provide insight into</para>
<para>the spatial associations between changes involving reeds, and those involving water and</para>
<para>sand.</para>
<para>Spatial associations between persistent reed patches and areas of reed loss were further</para>
<para>quantified by estimating from the maps the proportion of patches of loss which lay within</para>
<para>a 5 m radius of persistent reed patches. This made it possible to estimate what proportion</para>
<para>of patches were removed completely, and what proportion merely became smaller.</para>
</section>
</description>
</methodStep>
<methodStep><description><section><title>Clonal expansion vs establishment of new reed patches</title>
<para>Patches of new reeds which are close to persistent reed patches are most probably a result</para>
<para>of clonal expansion of the persistent patches, whereas those which are far from persistent</para>
<para>patches must have established from seed or clonal progagules. The relative contribution</para>
<para>of these two types of reed gain was determined by estimating the proportion of new reed</para>
<para>patches found within a 5m radius of persistent patches, as described above for reed loss.</para>
<para>Edge:area ratios were also calculated for all types of patches and compared between time</para>
<para>periods using two-sample t tests. A decrease in this ratio indicates that patches have</para>
<para>become more consolidated, suggesting clonal expansion in the case of reed patches. An</para>
<para>increase in edge:area ratio indicates that patches have become smaller and more fragmented.</para>
<para>Thus it was possible to determine whether a particular type of change occurred</para>
<para>in large contiguous areas or rather in small discontinuous patches.</para>
<para>Due to computational constraints, it was not possible to convert the raster maps of whole</para>
<para>river subsections into vector format, necessary for calculating edge:area ratios. Instead,</para>
<para>two randomly selected smaller areas (approximately 100 m in length) from each subsection</para>
<para>map were converted into vector format and used to calculate edge:area ratios.</para>
<para>The submaps converted into vector format for the calculation of edge:area ratios were also</para>
<para>used to calculate the relative lengths of vegetated and unvegetated channel edge. The fact</para>
<para>that new areas of water could be distinguished from older, more persistent ones made it</para>
<para>possible to estimate the time required for channel edges to become colonised by reeds.</para>
</section>
</description>
</methodStep>
<methodStep><description><section><title>Relationships between reed dynamics and geomorphic change</title>
<para>Given the highly dynamic nature of the patch mosaic in semi-arid rivers generally, reed</para>
<para>patch dynamics is likely to be related to geomorphic change, which may be quantified by</para>
<para>the dynamics of water and sand patches. Relationships between reed patch dynamics and</para>
<para>geomorphic change were explored by:</para>
<para>Determining probabilities of association between reed patches, and water and sand</para>
<para>patches with different histories (neighbour analysis)</para>
<para>Comparing the persistence and turnover of reed and water patches in each period</para>
<para>Relating reed cover and persistence to water cover and persistence using regression</para>
<para>models</para>
</section>
</description>
</methodStep>
</methods>
<access authSystem="knb" order="denyFirst" scope="document"><allow><principal>public</principal>
<permission>read</permission>
</allow>
</access>
</dataset>
 </ns0:eml>